Chapter 6

1. In my search for answers to the question of life I felt just like a man who is lost in a wood.

2. I came to a clearing, climbed a tree and saw clearly into the never-ending distance. But there was no house there, nor could there be. I walked into the thicket, into the gloom and saw the darkness, but there was no house there either.

3. In the same way I wandered in the forest of human knowledge, both amidst the bright rays of mathematical knowledge and experimental knowledge, where wide horizons were opened up to me, but in a direction where I could find no house, and amidst the darkness of speculative knowledge where I was immersed in ever deeper gloom the further I progressed. And I became quite convinced that there was not, and could not be, a way out.

4. When I inclined to the bright side of knowledge I realized that I was only avoiding facing the question. However bright and attractive those horizons spreading out before me were, and however tempting it was to immerse myself in the infinity of all this knowledge, I already knew that the clearer the knowledge was, the less I needed it, and the less it answered my question. 'Well,' I said to myself, 'I know everything that science so urgently wants to know and along that path there is no answer to the question of the meaning of my life.' 'In the speculative realm I knew that despite the fact, or rather precisely because of the fact, that the primary purpose of this knowledge is to answer my question, the answer given was none other than the one I had already given myself: what is the meaning of my life? It has none. Or: what will come of my life? Nothing. Or: why does everything there is exist, and why do I exist? Because it does.

5. When I put my questions to one branch of human knowledge I received a countless number of precise answers to things I had not asked: the chemical composition of the stars, the movement of the sun towards the constellation Hercules, the origin of the species and of man, the forms of infinitely tiny atoms, the fluctuations of infinitely small and imponderable particles of ether. But the only answer this branch of knowledge provided to my question concerning the meaning of life was this: you are that which you call your life; you are a temporary, incidental accumulation of particles. The mutual interaction and alteration of these particles produces in you something you refer to as your life. This accumulation can only survive for a limited length of time; when the interaction of these particles ceases, that which you call life will cease, bringing an end to all your questions. You are a randomly united lump of something. This lump decomposes and the fermentation is called your life. The lump will disintegrate and the fermentation will end, together with all your questions. This is the answer given by the exact side of knowledge, and if it adheres strictly to its principles, it cannot answer otherwise.

6. However, the truth is that this answer does not reply to the question. I need to know the meaning of my life, and the fact that it is a particle of infinity not only fails to give it any meaning, but eliminates any possible meaning.

7. The experimental side of knowledge vaguely compromises with the speculative side in saying that the meaning of life lies in development and in the encouragement of this development. But owing to the inaccuracies and obscurities these cannot be regarded as answers.

8. Whenever the other side of knowledge, the speculative realm, sticks firmly to its principles and gives direct answers to the question, it has always, throughout the ages, given the same answer: the universe is something infinite and incomprehensible. Man's life is an inscrutable part of this inscrutable 'whole'. Again I exclude all the compromises made between the speculative and experimental sciences, which support a whole array of semi-sciences: the so-called judicial, political and historical sciences. In these sciences there is the same mistaken approach to the understanding of development and perfection, with the only difference that in one instance we have the development of everything, and in the other the development of people's lives. The mistake is identical: development and perfection can have no purpose or direction in infinity, and as far as my question is concerned, no answer.

9. When speculative knowledge is exact, namely in true philosophy, and not that which Schopenhauer calls professorial philosophy (which serves only to divide all existing phenomena into new philosophical categories, with new names), here when philosophy does not lose sight of the essential question, the answer is always the same as the one given by Socrates, Schopenhauer, Solomon and Buddha.

10. 'We grow closer to the truth only to the extent that we grow further away from life,' says Socrates when preparing himself for death. 'What do we, who love the truth, strive for in life? In order to be free of the body and of all the evil that arises from the life of the body. If this is so then how can we fail to rejoice when death approaches?'

11. 'The wise man seeks death throughout his life, and therefore death is not frightening to him.'

12. 'If we understand the inner essence of the universe as will,' says Schopenhauer, 'and if we understand all phenomena, from the dark forces of nature to the full conscious activity of man, as no more than the objectivity of the will, we cannot escape the conclusion that it is in the free denial and self-renunciation of the will that all phenomena disappear; the constant striving and the aimless and untiring allurement towards all the levels of subjectivity in which, and through which, the universe exists will disappear, as will all the various subsequent forms. When form disappears so too will all phenomena of form, including both space and time, until eventually even the last basis of form will disappear, i.e. subject and object. There is no idea without will, and no universe. Before us, of course, there remains only nothingness. But that which opposes this transition into nothingness, our nature, is but our own will to exist (Will zum Leben), of which both we and our universe are made up. That we are afraid of nothingness, or that we wish to live, only indicates that we ourselves are nothing other than this desire to live and we know nothing other than this. Therefore what remains to us, who are so full of will after the annihilation of the will, is of course nothingness; on the other hand, in those in whom the will has been reversed and renounced, this universe of ours that is so real with all its suns and galaxies is nothingness.'

13. 'Vanity of vanities,' says Solomon, 'all is vanity. What profit hath a man of all his labour which he taketh under the sun? One generation passeth away, and another generation cometh, but the earth abideth forever... The thing that hath been, it is that which shall be; and that which is done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun. Is there any thing whereof it may be said, See this is new? It hath been already of old time, which was before us. There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with those that shall come after. I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem. And I gave my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all things that are done under the heaven: this sore travail hath God given to the sons of man to be exercised therewith. I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and vexation of spirit... I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I am come to great estate, and have gotten more wisdom than all they that have been before me in Jerusalem: yea, my heart had great experience of wisdom and knowledge. And I gave my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also is vexation of spirit. For in much wisdom is much grief: and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow. I said in mine heart, Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also is vanity. I said of laughter, it is mad: and of mirth, what doeth it? I sought in mine heart to give myself unto wine, yet acquainting mine heart with wisdom; and to lay hold on folly, till I might see what was that good for the sons of men, which they should do under the heaven all the days of their life. I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards; I made me gardens and orchards, and planted trees in them of all kind of fruits: I made me pools of water to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees: I got me servants and maidens, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of great and small cattle above all that were in Jerusalem before me: I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces: I gat me men singers and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, as musical instruments, and that of all sorts. So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me. And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them, I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in all my labour: and this was my portion of all my labour. Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and, behold, all was vanity and vexation of the spirit, and there was no profit, from them under the sun. And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king? Even that which hath been already done. Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness. The wise man's eyes are in his head; but the fool walketh in darkness: and I myself perceived also that one event happeneth to them all. Then I said in my heart, as it happeneth to the fool, so it happeneth even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then I said in my heart, that this also is vanity. For there is no remembrance of the wise more than of the fool for ever; seeing that which now is in the days to come shall all be forgotten. And how dieth the wise man? As the fool. Therefore I hated life; because the work that is wrought under the sun is grievous unto me: for all is vanity and vexation of spirit. Yea, I hated all my labour which I had taken under the sun: because I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me... For what hath man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath laboured under the sun? For all his days are sorrows, and his travail is grief, yea his heart taketh not rest in the night. This is also vanity. There is nothing better for a man than that he should eat and drink, and that he should make his soul enjoy good in his labour...

14. All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth and to him that sacrificeth not: as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath. There is an evil among all things that are done under the sun, that there is one event unto all; yea, also the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead. For him that is joined to all the living there is hope: for a living dog is better than a dead lion. For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten. Also their love, and their hatred, and their envy, is now perished; neither have they any more a portion for ever of any thing that is done under the sun.'

15. Thus speaks Solomon, or the person who wrote these words.

16. This is what an Indian sage says: 'Saki-Muni, a young and happy Prince, from whom illness, old age and death had been kept secret, went out for a drive one day and saw a frightful, toothless, drivelling old man. The Prince, who until now knew nothing of old age, was aghast and asked the driver what it was and what had brought the man to such a pitiful, repulsive and ugly state. When he learnt that it is a fate common to all men and that he, a young Prince, inevitably faced the same thing, he could go no further and gave orders to return home so that he could think it over. He shut himself up alone and reflected on it. Presumably his thoughts consoled him because he went out again, happy and cheerful, for another drive. But this time he met a sick man. He saw an emaciated bluish, trembling man, with dim eyes. The Prince, from whom sickness had been hidden, stopped the driver and asked what this was. When he discovered that it was sickness, to which all people are susceptible and that he, a healthy and happy Prince, might become sick tomorrow, he again lost the spirit to be cheerful and demanded to be taken home, where he again sought solace. He probably found it for he set out again, for the third time. But on this occasion he saw yet another new thing: he saw some people carrying something. 'What is it?' 'A dead man.' 'What does dead mean?' asked the Prince. He was told that to be dead was to be what this man was. The Prince went up to the dead body, uncovered it and looked at it. 'What will become of him now?' he asked. The Prince was told that the man would be buried in the ground. 'Why?' 'Because he will never live again and all that will come of him is stench and worms.' 'And is this the fate of all men? Will it happen to me too? Will I be buried and give off a stench and be consumed by worms?' 'Yes.' 'Go back! I do not wish to go for a drive. I will never go for a drive again!'

17. Saki-Muni could find no consolation in life and resolved that life is a great evil, and he devoted all the strength of his soul to freeing himself, and others, from life. He wanted to free them in such a way that after death life would not be renewed anywhere, but would be completely annihilated, at the roots. This is what all Indian sages say.

18. These then are the straightforward answers given by human wisdom in reply to the questions of life:

19. 'The life of the body is evil and a lie. And since the annihilation of the life of the body is a blessing we must long for it,' says Socrates.

20. 'Life is that which it should not be: evil. The transition into nothingness is the only thing sacred in life,' says Schopenhauer.

21. Everything in the world, both folly and wisdom, richness and poverty, happiness and grief, all is vanity and emptiness. A man dies and nothing remains. This is absurd,' says Solomon.

22. 'It is impossible to live in the consciousness that suffering, weakening, old age and death are inevitable; we must free ourselves from life, from all possibility of life,' says Buddha.

23. And the very same thing said by these powerful minds has been said and thought by millions of people similar to them. And I too have thought and felt it.

24. And thus my perusals in the realms of knowledge not only failed to lead me out of my despair, but simply increased it. One branch of knowledge did not answer the question of life; the other gave an answer but the reply only confirmed my despair and showed me that the conclusion I had reached was not the result of my erring ways, or of a morbid state of mind. On the contrary it convinced me that what I had thought was correct, and in accord with the conclusions reached by the most penetrating human minds.

25. To deceive oneself is pointless. All is vanity. Happy is he who was never born. Death is better than life; one must free oneself from it.

Chapter 7

1. Failing to find an explanation in knowledge I began to search for it in life, hoping to find it among the people around me. I began to observe how these people like myself lived, and how they dealt with the question that had led me to despair.

2. And this is what I discovered among people whose position in life, as regards education and lifestyle, was similar to my own.

3. I found that these people of my circle had four methods of escape from the dreadful situation in which we all find ourselves.

4. The first method of escape is that of ignorance. It consists of failing to recognize, or understand, that life is evil and absurd. The majority of the people of this kind are either women, or very young, or very stupid and have not yet understood the problem of life that presented itself to Schopenhauer, Solomon and Buddha. They see neither the dragon that is waiting for them, nor the mice that are gnawing away at the bush from which they are clinging, and they lick the drops of honey. But they only lick them for a while: something will turn their attention to the dragon and the mice and their licking will come to an end. There was nothing I could learn from them, for we can never cease knowing what we know.　　5. The second method of escape is that of epicureanism. It consists, while knowing the hopelessness of life, of enjoying the blessings we have without looking at the dragon or the mice, and of licking the honey in the best possible way, especially if a lot of it has fallen on the bush. Solomon describes this method thus:

6. 'Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun than to eat, to drink, and to be merry: for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his life, which God giveth him under the sun...

7. Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart... Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity: for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takest under the sun... Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is not work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave, whither thou goest' (Ecclesiastes, Ⅷ.15, Ⅸ.7, 9-10).

8. This second method of escape sustains the majority of people of our circle. The conditions in which they find themselves dictate that they have a greater share of the good things in life than the bad; their moral torpor allows them to forget that all the privileges of their position are accidental and that not everyone can have a thousand wives and palaces as Solomon did; that for every man with a thousand wives there are a thousand men without wives, and that for every palace there are a thousand men who built it by the sweat of their brow, and that the same chance that has made you Solomon today might make you Solomon's slave tomorrow. The inertia of these people's imagination enables them to forget why it was Buddha was granted no peace: the inevitability of illness, old age and death, which can, if not today then tomorrow, destroy all these pleasures. The fact that a number of these people affirm that the dullness of their thought and imagination is something called 'positive philosophy' fails, in my opinion, to make them any different from the ranks of those who, failing to see the question, lick the honey. I could not imitate these people, for not sharing their dullness of imagination I could not create it artificially in myself. Like any man who sincerely lives I could not turn my eyes away from the mice and the dragon once I had seen them.

9. The third method of escape is through strength and energy. It consists of realizing that life is evil and senseless, and of destroying it. This is what a few strong and consistent people do. Having understood the utter stupidity of the joke that is being played on them, and realizing that the blessings of the dead are far greater than the blessings of the living, and that the best thing of all is not to live, they act accordingly and instantly bring an end to this stupid joke, using any available means: a noose around the neck, water, a stab in the heart, a train on a railway line. There are increasing numbers of people belonging to our circle who act in this way. On the whole those who behave like this do so during the prime of their life, when the strength of the soul is in full force and few of the habits that undermine human reason have yet been acquired. I saw that this was the most worthy mode of escape and wanted to follow it through.

10. The fourth road of escape is that of weakness. It consists of clinging to a life that is evil and futile, knowing in advance that nothing can come of it. People belonging to this category know that death is preferable to life but, lacking the strength to act rationally and bring a quick end to the deception by killing themselves, they seem to wait for something. This is the escape of weakness, for if I know of something better and it is within my reach, then why not yield to it? I myself belonged to this category.

11. Thus, people of my kind have four ways of saving themselves from a terrible contradiction. However hard I strained my mental faculties I could find no other than these four modes of escape. In the first method there is a failure to understand that life is meaningless, vain and evil and that it is better not to live. I could not help knowing this, and once I had realized it I could not close my eyes to it. The second method is to make use of life, such as it is, without thinking about the future. Neither could I do this. Like Saki-Muni, I could not ride out hunting when I knew that suffering, old age and death exist. My imagination was too fertile. Moreover I could not take pleasure in those fleeting occasions which momentarily threw pleasure on my existence. The third method is to have realized that life is evil and absurd and to bring it to an end by killing oneself. The fourth method of escape is to live like Solomon and Schopenhauer, knowing that life is a stupid joke being played on us, but nevertheless continuing to live, to wash, to dress, to eat, to talk, and even to write books. Although I found it offensive and painful I remained in this position.

12. I can now see that if I did not kill myself it was because of some vague awareness that my ideas were mistaken. No matter how convincing and irrefutable I felt my train of thoughts to be, as well as that of the wise ideas that had led us all to the conclusion that life is meaningless I still had some obscure doubts as to the validity of the final outcome of my deliberations.

13. It was expressed as follows: I, that is my reason, have acknowledged that life is irrational. If there is nothing higher than reason (and there is not, and nothing can prove that there is), then reason is the creator of life for me. Without reason I can have no life. How then can reason deny life when it is the creator of it? Or looking at it another way: if there were no life my reason would not exist, which must mean that reason is the offspring of life. Life is everything. Reason is the fruit of life and yet this reason rejects life itself. I felt that something was not quite right here.

14. Life is a senseless evil, that is certain, I said to myself. Yet I have lived and still live, and so too humanity has lived and still lives. How can this be? Why do men live when it is possible not to live? Can it be that only Schopenhauer and I have been intelligent enough to understand the senselessness and evil of life?

15. The argument about the vanity of life is not particularly subtle and all simple folk have known it for a long time; yet they have lived and still live. How is it they all live and never think of doubting the logic of life?

16. My knowledge, confirmed by the wisdom of the sages, had revealed to me that everything in the world, organic and inorganic, is arranged with the most unusual intelligence, and it is only my position that is absurd. But these fools, the vast masses of simple folk, while knowing nothing about the organic and inorganic arrangement of the world, continue to live and feel that life is very sensibly organized!

17. And it occurred to me that there might be something I did not yet know. After all, that is exactly how ignorance behaves. Ignorance always says what I am saying. When it does not know something it says that the thing it does not know is stupid. In any event it appears that there is a whole section of mankind that has lived and still lives, as if it knew the meaning of life, for without knowing this meaning it could not live. Yet I am saying that all life is meaningless and that I cannot live.

18. No one prevents Schopenhauer and me from denying life. Go ahead then, kill yourself and you won't have to think about it again. If you don't like life kill yourself. If you live and cannot understand the meaning of it, put an end to it, but don't turn around and start talking and writing about the fact that you don't understand life. You find yourself in cheerful company, where everyone is happy and know what they are doing, so if you find it boring and objectionable, leave!

19. For in the end what are we, who are convinced that suicide is obligatory and yet cannot resolve to commit it, other than the weakest, the most inconsistent and, speaking frankly, the most stupid of people, making such a song and dance with our banalities.

20. After all, our wisdom, however irrefutable it may be, has provided us with no understanding of the meaning of life. Yet all those millions who make up humanity manage to live without ever doubting its meaning.

21. Indeed, since those long ago days when life began and of which I know nothing, people who knew the argument about the vanity of life (which seems to me to prove its senselessness), have nevertheless lived and brought to life a meaning of their own. Ever since there has been some form of human life, people have had this understanding of life, and have pursued this life, and passed it down to me. Everything that is in me and around me is the fruit of their understanding of life. These very instruments of thought with which I judge life, and condemn it, were made by them and not by me. I myself was born, educated and grew up thanks to them. They dug up the iron, taught us how to fell wood, tamed the cattle and the horses, taught us how to sow the crops and how to live together; they created an order in life. They taught me how to think and speak. I am their offspring, provided by them with food and water, taught by them, able to think and speak using their thoughts and words, and now I have proved to them that it is all senseless! 'There is something wrong here,' I told myself, 'I have made a mistake somewhere.' But I could not discover where the mistake lay.

Chapter 8

1. None of these doubts, which I can now express more or less coherently, could I have formulated at the time. At the time I simply felt that despite the fact that my deductions about the vanity of life were logically unavoidable and were confirmed by the greatest thinkers, there was still something wrong with them. Whether it was in my reasoning, or whether it was in my formulation of the question, I did not know. I simply felt that the reasoning behind my conviction was complete, but that it was not enough. All these conclusions failed to persuade me to follow my argument to its end, that is to kill myself. I would not be speaking the truth if I said that it was through my reason that I arrived where I did and yet did not kill myself. My reason was working, but so too was something else that I can only call a consciousness of life. There was also another force at work which made me pay attention to the latter and not to the former. It was this force that led me out of my state of despair and guided my reason in an entirely different direction. It compelled me to pay attention to the fact that I, and the hundreds of others similar to myself, do not comprise the whole of humanity, and that I still did not know what this life of humanity was.

2. As I looked around at the narrow circle of my colleagues I saw nothing but people who had failed to understand the question, or who had understood it but drowned it in the intoxication of life, or who had understood it and had put an end to their lives, or who understood it but through weakness continued living in despair. And I saw no others. I thought that this narrow circle of scholars, and of rich and distinguished people, to which I belonged made up the whole of mankind and that the millions who had lived and still live were THEM, some sort of cattle, people.

3. It seems so strange to me now, so utterly incomprehensible, that in my reasoning of life I could have overlooked the life of humanity that surrounded me on all sides and that I could have been so ridiculously mistaken as to think that my life, and the life of Solomon and Schopenhauer, was the true, normal life, while the lives of millions was not worthy of attention. However strange it may seem now, I know it was so at the time. Amidst the wanderings of my conceited mind I felt certain that Solomon, Schopenhauer and myself had posed the question so honestly and exactly that there could be no two ways about it. I felt so certain that all these millions simply belonged to the category of those who had not yet penetrated the depths of the question, that as I searched for the meaning of my life it never once occurred to me to think: 'What sort of meaning do all the millions who have lived, and do live in the world give to their lives?'

4. I lived in this state of madness for a long time. It is a state which if not in deed then in words is very characteristic of more liberated and learned people. But whether it was thanks to my somewhat strange and instinctive love of the true working people that I was forced to understand them and to realize that they are not as stupid as we thought; or whether it was thanks to the sincerity of my conviction that I knew of nothing better to do than hang myself, I sensed anyway that if I wanted to live and to understand the meaning of life I must not seek it among those who have lost it and wish to kill themselves, but among the millions of people living and dead who have created life, and who carry the weight of our lives together with their own. And I looked around at the enormous masses of simple, uneducated people without wealth, who have lived and who still live, and I saw something quite different. I saw that with a few exceptions all those millions do not fit into my divisions, and that I could not categorize them as people who did not understand the question because they themselves posed, and answered, the question with unusual clarity. Neither could I categorize them as epicureans, since their lives rest more on deprivation and suffering than on pleasure. I could still less regard them as living out their meaningless lives irrationally, since they could explain every act of their lives, including death. They considered suicide the greatest evil. It appeared that mankind as a whole had some kind of comprehension of the meaning of life that I did not acknowledge and derided. It followed that rational knowledge does not provide the meaning of life, but excludes it; while the meaning given to life by the millions of people, by humanity as a whole, is founded on some sort of knowledge that is despised and considered false.

5. Rational knowledge, as presented by the learned and wise, negates the meaning of life, yet the vast masses－humanity as a whole－recognize that this meaning lies in irrational knowledge. And this irrational knowledge is faith, the very thing that I could not help rejecting. This God, one in three, the creation in six days, the devils and angels and all the rest that I could not accept without going mad.

6. My position was terrible. I knew that I could find nothing along the path of rational knowledge, other than negation of life. While in faith I found nothing other than a negation of reason, which was even more impossible than denial of life. According to rational knowledge life is an evil and people know it. They have the choice of ending their lives and yet they have always carried on living, just as I myself have done, despite having known for a long time that life is meaningless and evil. According to faith it follows that in order to comprehend the meaning of life I must renounce my reason, the very thing for which meaning was necessary.

Chapter 9

1. A contradiction arose from which there were only two ways out: either that which I called reasonable was not as reasonable as I thought, or that which I felt to be irrational was not as irrational as I thought. And I started to check the line of argument that stemmed from my rational knowledge.

2. As I checked this line of argument I found it to be entirely correct. The conclusion that life is nothing was inevitable, but I spotted a mistake. The mistake was that my thinking did not correspond to the question I had posed. The question was: why do I live? Or: is there anything that will remain and not be annihilated of my illusory and transitory life? Or: what meaning has my finite existence in an infinite universe? In order to answer this question I studied life.

3. Clearly the solution to all the possible questions of life could not satisfy me because my question, however simple it may seem at first, involves a demand for an explanation of the finite by means of the infinite and vice versa.

4. I had asked: what meaning has life beyond time, beyond space and beyond cause? And I was answering the question: 'What is the meaning of my life within time, space and cause?' The result was that after long and laboured thought I could only answer: none.

5. In my deliberations I was continually drawing comparisons between the finite and the finite, and the infinite and the infinite, and I could not have done otherwise. Thus I reached the only conclusion I could reach: force is force, matter is matter, will is will, the infinite is the infinite, nothing is nothing; and I could go no further than that.

6. It was somewhat similar to what happens in mathematics when, trying to resolve an equation, we get an identity. The method of deduction is correct, but the only answer obtained is that a equals a, and x equals x, or o equals o. Precisely the same thing was happening with my reasoning concerning the meaning of life. The only answers the sciences give to this question are identities.

7. And really, strictly rational knowledge, such as that of Descartes, begins with complete doubt in everything and throws aside any knowledge founded on faith, reconstructing everything along laws of reason and experiment. And it can provide no answer other than the one I reached: an indefinite one. It was only at first that I thought knowledge had given an affirmative answer, Schopenhauer's answer that life has no meaning and is evil. But when I went into the matter I realized that this answer is not affirmative and that it was only my senses that had taken it to be so. Strictly expressed, as it is by the Brahmins, Solomon, and Schopenhauer, the answer is but a vague one, an identity: o equals o, life presented to me as nothing is nothing. Thus, philosophical knowledge denies nothing but simply replies that it cannot solve the question, and that as far as it is concerned any resolution remains indefinite.

8. Having understood this, I realized that it was impossible to search for an answer to my questions in rational knowledge; that the answer given by rational knowledge simply suggests that the answer can only be obtained by stating the question in another way, by introducing the question of the relation of the finite to the infinite. I realized that no matter how irrational and distorted the answers given by faith might be, they had the advantage of introducing to every answer a relationship between the finite and the infinite, without which there can be no solution. Whichever way I put the question: how am I to live? the answer is always: according to God's law. Or to the question: is there anything real that will come of my life? the answer is: eternal torment or eternal bliss. Or, to the question: what meaning is there that is not destroyed by death? the answer is: unity with the infinite, God, heaven.

9. Thus in addition to rational knowledge, which I had hitherto thought to be the only knowledge, I was inevitably led to acknowledge that there does exist another kind of knowledge - an irrational one - possessed by humanity as a whole: faith, which affords the possibility of living. Faith remained as irrational to me as before, but I could not fail to recognize that it alone provides mankind with the answers to the question of life, and consequently with the possibility of life.

10. Rational knowledge had led me to recognize that life is meaningless. My life came to a halt and I wanted to kill myself. As I looked around at people, at humanity as a whole, I saw that they lived and affirmed that they knew the meaning of life. I looked at myself. I had lived as long as I knew the meaning of life. For me, as for others, faith provided the meaning of life and the possibility of living.

11. Having looked around further at people in other countries and at my contemporaries and predecessors, I saw the same thing. Where there is life there is faith. Since the day of creation faith has made it possible for mankind to live, and the essential aspects of that faith are always and everywhere the same.

12. Whatever answers faith gives, regardless of which faith, or to whom the answers are given, such answers always give an infinite meaning to the finite existence of man; a meaning that is not destroyed by suffering, deprivation or death. This means that only in faith can we find the meaning and possibility of life. I realized that the essential meaning of faith lies not only in the 'manifestations of things unseen', and so on, or in revelation (this is only a description of one of the signs of faith); nor is it simply the relationship between man and God (it is necessary to define faith, then God, and not God through faith); nor is it an agreement with what one has been told, although this is what faith is commonly understood to be. Faith is a knowledge of the meaning of human life, the consequence of which is that man does not kill himself but lives. Faith is the force of life. If a man lives, then he must believe in something. If he did not believe that there was something he must live for he would not live. If he does not see and comprehend the illusion of the finite he will believe in the finite. If he does understand the illusion of the finite, he is bound to believe in the infinite. Without faith it is impossible to live.

13. I recalled the whole course of my inner thinking and was horrified. It was now clear to me that in order for man to live he must either be unaware of the infinite, or he must have some explanation of the meaning of life by which the finite can be equated with the infinite. I had this explanation but it was no use to me while I believed in the finite; and I began to test it against my reason. And in the light of reason my former explanation vanished into thin air. But the time came when I no longer believed in the finite. And then I began, on a rational basis, to construct out of what I knew an explanation which might give a meaning to life; but nothing came of it. Together with the finest human intellects I reached the conclusion that o equals o and was most astonished at reaching this conclusion and that there could be no other.

14. What did I do when I searched for an answer in the experimental sciences? I wanted to find out why I lived and I therefore studied everything that exists outside myself. It became clear that I could discover a great deal, but nothing of what I needed.

15. What happened when I searched for the answer in the realms of philosophy? I studied the thoughts of those who found themselves in the same predicament as myself and who had no answer to the question of why we live. It was apparent that I could discover nothing here that I did not already know: namely that it is impossible to know anything.

16. What am I? A part of the infinite. It is indeed in these words that the whole problem lies. Can it be that this question has only occurred to man so recently? Can it be that no one before me has posed this question to himself, such a simple question, one that might spring to the lips of any intelligent child?

17. Surely this question has been raised ever since man has existed. Since the beginning it has been evident that solving the question by equating the finite with the finite is just as unsatisfactory as equating the infinite with the infinite. Since time immemorial man has striven to express the relationship between the finite and the infinite.

18. All the concepts we use to compare the finite to the infinite, and to arrive at an understanding of life, of the concepts of God, freedom and goodness, are put to the test of logic. But they fail to stand up to the critique of reason.

19. If it were not so frightening it would be amusing to observe the pride and complacency with which we, like children, take apart the watch, pull out the spring and make a toy of it, and are then surprised when the watch stops working.

20. It is both valuable and necessary to have a solution to the contradiction between the finite and the infinite, an answer to the question of life that makes it possible to live. The one solution we always find everywhere, among all peoples, is the solution that has been passed down to us from times we have lost all record of. It is such a difficult solution that we would be unable to devise anything like it. And it is a solution which we casually destroy so that we may yet again pose the question that confronts us all, and for which we do not have an answer.

21. The concepts of an infinite God, the sanctity of the soul, the relationship between God and the affairs of man, of moral good and evil, are all concepts that have been worked out in history, through the life of a humanity that is hidden to us. Without the existence of these concepts there would be neither life nor myself, and yet I, rejecting all the efforts of humanity, wanted to do it all over again, alone, in my own way.

22. I did not think so at the time but the germs of these thoughts were already within me. I realized that: (1) Despite our intelligence the contentions of Schopenhauer, Solomon and myself were foolish: we considered life to be evil and nevertheless continued to live. This was apparent stupidity because, if life is meaningless and I am so fond of reason, then I must destroy life so that no one can deny it. (2) All our arguments went round in a vicious circle, like a wheel that is not attached to the carriage. However much, and however well, we deliberated, we could find no answer to the question because o will always equal o, and therefore, our method must be mistaken. (3) I began to realize that the most profound wisdom of man is preserved in the answers given by faith, and that I did not have the right to negate them on grounds of reason and, above all, that it is these answers alone that can reply to the question of life.

Chapter 10

1. I could see this but it did not make matters any easier for me.

2. I was now prepared to accept any faith so long as it did not demand a direct denial of reason, which would have been a deceit. So I studied books on Buddhism and Mohammedanism and above all I studied Christianity, both through its writings and through people living around me.

3. Naturally I first turned to believers from my own circle, to learned people, Orthodox theologians, elder monks, theologians of the newest types of Orthodoxy, and even to the so-called New Christians who taught salvation through faith in redemption. I seized on these believers and questioned them on how they believed and what they understood to be the meaning of life.

4. Despite making all possible allowances and avoiding all arguments I could not accept the faith of these people. I saw that what they took to be faith gave no explanation to the meaning of life but obscured it, and that they themselves did not profess their faith in response to the question of life, that had led me to faith, but for some other reasons which were alien to me.

5. I recall the tormenting feeling of fear should I return to my former despair, after the hope I had experienced so many times in my relations with these people. The more precisely they expounded their teachings to me, the more clearly I saw their errors, until I lost all hope of finding an explanation to the meaning of life in their faith.

6. I was not so much alienated by the fact that in expounding their religious beliefs they confused Christian truths that had always been close to me with much that was unnecessary and irrational. It was more the fact that the lives of these people were just like my own, with the only difference that they did not live according to the principles expounded in their teachings. I felt strongly that they were deceiving themselves and that, like myself, they had no other concept of life than of living while they lived and of grabbing hold of everything they could. I saw this from the fact that if they had possessed a meaning that annihilated the fear of deprivation, suffering and death, they would not have been afraid of these things. But these believers of our class lived, just as I did, in excess, striving to maintain and increase it and fearing deprivation, suffering and death. Like myself and all non-believers, they lived only to satisfy their desires and they lived just as badly as, if not worse than, non-believers.

7. No arguments could convince me of the truth of their faith. Only actions showing me that they had an understanding of life that did not make them afraid, as I was, of poverty, sickness and death might have convinced me. But I witnessed no such behaviour among the believers of my circle. So that, while I witnessed this sort of behaviour among those of my circle who did not believe, I never witnessed it among the so-called believers.

8. I realized that the belief these men had was not the faith I was seeking and that their faith is not really faith but only one of the epicurean consolations in life. I understood that while this faith might perhaps serve, if not for consolation, then as some kind of distraction for a repentant Solomon on his deathbed, it is entirely unsuitable for the vast majority of mankind who do not seek amusement at the expense of other men's labour, but to make something of life. In order for mankind to live and to perpetuate life, instilling it with meaning, these millions must all have some different, more genuine concept of faith. Indeed it was not that neither I nor Solomon, nor Schopenhauer, had killed ourselves that convinced me of the existence of faith, but the fact that these millions have lived and still live, bearing those like Solomon and myself on the crest of their lives.

9. And I began to grow close to the believers among the poor, simple, uneducated folk: pilgrims, monks, sectarians and peasants. The belief held by these people was the same Christianity as that of the pseudo-believers of my circle. They too had mixed a great deal of superstition alongside Christian truths, but the difference was that while superstition was quite unnecessary to the believers of my circle, had nothing to do with their lives and simply provided some kind of epicurean distraction, the superstitions of the believers belonging to the labouring section of the population were so interconnected with their lives that they could not have conceived of life without them; they were a necessary condition of their lives. The whole way of life of the believers of my own circle stood in contradiction to their faith, whereas the whole way of life of the believers from the working population reaffirmed the meaning their faith gave to life. And I started to look more closely at the life and faith of these people, and the further I looked the more convinced I became that theirs was the true faith, that their faith was essential to them, and that it alone provides a sense of the meaning and possibility of life. In contrast to what I saw among the people of my class where it is possible to live without faith and where among the thousands there is barely one who can admit to being a believer, among them there is hardly one in a thousand who does not believe. In contrast to what I saw happening in my own circle, where the whole of life is spent in idleness, amusement and dissatisfaction with life, I saw that these people who laboured hard throughout their entire lives were less dissatisfied with life than the rich. In contrast to the people of our class who resist and curse the privations and sufferings of their lot, these people accept sickness and grief without question or protest, and with a calm and firm conviction that this is how it must be, that it cannot be otherwise and that it is all for the good. Contrary to us, who the more intelligent we are the less we understand the meaning of life and see some kind of malicious joke in the fact that we suffer and die, these people live, suffer and approach death peacefully and, more often than not, joyfully. In contrast to the fact that a peaceful death, a death without horror and despair, is a most rare exception in our circle, a tormented, rebellious and unhappy death is a most rare exception amongst these people. And there are millions and millions of these people who are deprived of all those things, which for the Solomons and I are the only blessings in life, and who nevertheless find tremendous happiness in life. I looked more widely around me. I looked at the lives of the multitudes who have lived in the past and who live today. And of those who understood the meaning of life I saw not two, or three, or ten, but hundreds, thousands and millions. And all of them, endlessly varied in their customs, minds, educations and positions, and in complete contrast to my ignorance, knew the meaning of life and death, endured suffering and hardship, lived and died and saw this not as vanity but good.

10. And I came to love these people. The further I penetrated into the lives of those living and dead about whom I had read and heard, the more I loved them and the easier it became for me to live. I lived like this for about two years and a great change took place within me, for which I had been preparing for a long time and the roots of which had always been in me. What happened was that the life of our class, the rich and learned, became not only distasteful to me, but lost all meaning. All our activities, our discussions, our science and our art struck me as sheer indulgence. I realized that there was no meaning to be found here. It was the activities of the labouring people, those who produce life, that presented itself to me as the only true way. I realized that the meaning provided by this life was truth and I accepted it.

Chapter 11

1. I remembered how these very beliefs repelled me and seemed devoid of any meaning when they were professed by people who lived in contradiction to them, and I remembered how these same beliefs attracted me and seemed sensible when I saw people living in accord with them; and I realized why I had rejected them and found them meaningless and why I now accepted them and found them full of meaning. I realized that I had been lost, and how I had become lost. I had strayed not so much because my ideas had been incorrect as because I had lived foolishly. I realized that I had been blinded from the truth not so much through my mistaken thoughts as through my life itself, which had been spent in satisfying desire and in exclusive conditions of epicureanism. I realized that my question as to what my life is, and the answer that it is an evil, was quite correct. The only mistake was that I had extended an answer that related only to myself to life as a whole. I had asked myself what my life was and had received the answer that it is evil and meaningless. And this was quite true, for my life of indulgent pursuits was meaningless and evil, but that answer applied only to my life and not to human life in general. I understood a truism that I subsequently found in the gospels: that people often preferred darkness to light because their deeds were evil. For he who acts maliciously hates light and avoids it so as not to throw light on his deeds. I understood that in order to understand life it is first of all necessary that life is not evil and meaningless, and then one may use reason in order to elucidate it. I realized why I had for so long been treading so close to such an obvious truth without seeing it, and that in order to think and speak about human life one must think and speak about human life and not about the lives of a few parasites. The truth has always been the truth, just as 2×2＝4, but I had not admitted it, because in acknowledging that 2×2＝4 I would have had to admit that I was a bad man. And it was more important and necessary for me to feel that I was good than to admit that 2×2＝4. I came to love good people and to loathe myself, and I acknowledged the truth. And then it all became clear to me.

2. Imagine an executioner who has spent all his life torturing people and chopping off heads, or a hopeless drunkard, or a madman who has spent his entire life in a dark room which he detests but imagines that he would die if he left it - imagine if they should ask themselves, 'What is life?' Obviously the only answer they could come up with is that life is the greatest of evils. The madman's answer would be absolutely correct, but only with respect to himself. Suppose I am such a madman? Suppose all of us who are wealthy and learned are such madmen?

3. And I realized that we really are such madmen. I, at any rate, was one. Indeed, a bird is made in such a way that it can fly, gather food and build a nest, and when I see a bird doing these things I rejoice. Goats, hares and wolves are made in order to eat, multiply and feed their families, and when they do this I feel quite sure that they are happy and that their lives are meaningful. What should a man do? He too must work for his existence, just as the animals do, but with the difference that he will perish if he does it alone, for he must work for an existence, not just for himself, but for everyone. And when he does this I feel quite sure that he is happy and that his life has meaning. And what had I been doing for all those thirty years of conscious life? Far from working for an existence for everyone, I had not even done so for myself. I had lived as a parasite and when I asked myself why I lived, I received the answer: for nothing. If the meaning of human existence lies in working to procure it I had spent thirty years attempting, not to procure it, but to destroy it for myself and for others. How then could I get any answer other than that my life is evil and meaningless? Indeed it was evil and meaningless.

4. The life of the world runs according to someone's will; our lives and the lives of everything in existence are in someone else's hands. In order to have any chance of comprehending this will we must first fulfil it by doing what is asked of us. If I do not do what is asked of me I will never understand what it is that is asked of me, and still less what is asked of us all, of the whole world.

5. If a naked, hungry beggar were taken at a crossroads and led to an enclosed part of a splendid establishment where he is given food and drink, and then forced to move some kind of handle up and down, it is obvious that before deciding why it was he had been brought there to move the handle, and whether or not the establishment was reasonably arranged, the beggar must first move the handle. If he moves the handle he will see that it operates a pump, that the pump draws water and the water flows into the garden. Then he will be taken away from the enclosed place and given another job, and he will gather fruits and will enter into the joy of his Lord. As he progresses from lower to higher tasks he will continue to understand more and more about the structure of the establishment and participate in it, and he will never stop to ask why he is there, and he will never come to reproach his master.

6. Likewise the simple uneducated working people, whom we refer to as the herd, fulfil the will of their master without ever reproaching him. But we, the wise, eat the master's food without doing what he asks of us; instead of doing it we sit around in circles debating whether we should do something as stupid as moving a handle up and down. And then we think it over and decide that either the master is stupid, or that he does not exist and that we are the only intelligent ones. The only thing is, we feel that we are no good for anything and that we must somehow escape from ourselves.

Chapter 12

1. Having realized the errors in rational knowledge I found it easier to free myself from the temptation of futile theorizing. The conviction that knowledge of the truth can only be found in life stirred me to doubt the worth of my own way of life. The thing that saved me was that I managed to tear myself away from my exclusive existence and see the true life of the simple working people, and realize that this alone is genuine life. I realized that if I wanted to understand life and its meaning I had to live a genuine life and not that of a parasite; and having accepted the meaning that is given to life by that real section of humanity who have become part of that genuine life, I had to try it out.

2. At this time the following happened to me: over the course of a whole year, almost every minute I asked myself whether I had not better kill myself with a rope or a bullet. And at the same time as I was experiencing the thoughts and observations I have described, my heart was agonized by a tormenting feeling. I can only describe this feeling as a quest for God.

3. I say that this quest for God was not a debate but an emotion because it did not arise from my stream of thoughts - it was in fact quite contrary to them - but from my heart. It was a feeling of fear, abandonment, loneliness, amid all that was strange to me, and a sense of hope that someone would help me.

4. Despite the fact that I was utterly convinced of the impossibility of proving the existence of a God (Kant had shown me this and I had fully understood that it cannot be proven), I nevertheless searched for God in the hope that I might find Him, and reverting to an old habit of prayer, I prayed to Him whom I sought but could not find. In my mind I went over the arguments of Kant and Schopenhauer on the impossibility of proving the existence of God, and I began to refute them. Cause, I told myself, does not belong to the same category of thought as space and time. If I exist then there must be a cause, and a cause of the cause. And the cause of everything is that which we call God. I dwelled on this thought and tried with my whole being to recognize the presence of this cause. And as soon as I recognized that there is a force with power over me I immediately felt the possibility of life. But I asked myself: 'What is this cause, this force? How should I think about it? How should I relate to this thing I call God?' But only the familiar answers came into my head: 'He is the creator, He is omniscient.' The answers did not satisfy me and I felt that I still lacked something inside me that is necessary in order to live. I fell into a state of panic and started to pray to the one whom I sought, in order that He might help me. And the more I prayed the more apparent it became that He did not hear me and that there was really no one to whom I could turn. And with my heart full of grief that there was no one, no God, I cried: 'Lord have mercy on me. Save me! O Lord show me the way!' But no one had mercy on me and I felt that my life had come to an end.

5. Yet time and again, from different approaches, I kept coming to the same conclusion, that I could not have come into the world without any cause, reason, or meaning; that I could not be the fledgeling fallen from the nest that I felt myself to be. If I lie on my back crying in the tall grass, like a fledgeling, it is because I know that my mother brought me into the world, kept me warm, fed me and loved me. But where is she, that mother? If I am abandoned, then who has abandoned me? I cannot hide myself from the fact that someone who loved me gave birth to me. Who is this someone? Again, God.

6. 'He knows and He sees my search, my struggle and my grief. He does exist,' I told myself. And I had only to recognize this for an instant and life would rise up within me and I would feel the possibility and joy of living. But again, from the recognition of the existence of God, I moved on to search for my relationship to Him, and again I was presented with that God, our Creator, in three persons, who sent us His son, our Saviour. And again, that God, separated from me and the world, would melt like ice before my eyes, and once more there was nothing left and my flicker of life was extinguished. I fell into despair and felt that there was nothing else I could do except kill myself. And worst of all was that I did not even feel I could do that.

7. Not two or three, but tens of hundreds of times, my mood suddenly changed from joy and animation to despair and a consciousness of the impossibility of living.

8. I can remember once in early spring I found myself alone in the woods. I was listening and concentrating my thoughts on the one thing I had been continuously thinking about over the last three years. Again I was searching for God.

9. 'Fine then,' I said to myself, 'so there is no God, other than something I imagine and the only reality is my own life. There is no God and no miracle can prove that there is because it would only be part of my imagination, and would be irrational.'

10. 'But what about my concept of God, of He whom I seek?' I asked myself, 'Where does this concept come from?' Once again, confronted with these thoughts, joyous waves of life surged up within me. Everything around me came to life and took on meaning. But my joy did not last long. My mind continued its work. 'A concept of God is not God,' I told myself. 'A concept of God is something within me that I can either evoke or not evoke. It is not this that I am seeking. I am seeking that, without which there cannot be life.' Once again everything within and around me began to die, and again I wanted to kill myself.

11. But then I stopped and looked at myself and at what was going on inside me. I recalled the hundreds of occasions when life had died within me only to be reborn. I remembered that I only lived during those times when I believed in God. Then, as now, I said to myself: I have only to believe in God in order to live. I have only to disbelieve in Him, or to forget Him, in order to die. What are these deaths and rebirths? It is clear that I do not live when I lose belief in God's existence, and I should have killed myself long ago, were it not for a dim hope of finding Him. I live truly only when I am conscious of Him and seek Him. What then is it you are seeking? a voice exclaimed inside me. There He is! He, without whom it is impossible to live. To know God and to live are one and the same thing. God is life.

12. 'Live in search of God and there will be no life without God!' And more powerfully than ever before everything within and around me came to light, and the light has not deserted me since.

13. And I was saved from suicide. When and how this change occurred in me I could not say. Just as the life force within me was extinguished gradually and imperceptibly, and I came upon the impossibility of life, the cessation of life and the need for suicide, so too did this life force return to me, gradually and imperceptibly. And, strangely, the life force that returned to me was not a new one but the same old one that had attracted me during the early period of my life. I returned to all those things that had been part of my childhood and youth. I returned to a belief in that will that had given birth to me and which asked something of me. I returned to the idea that the single most important aim of my life is to improve myself, that is, to live according to this will. I returned to the conviction that I could find the manifestation of this will in something that had been hidden from me for a long time, in what humanity had worked out long ago for its own guidance. In other words I returned to a belief in God, in moral perfection, and to that tradition which had given life a meaning. Only the difference now was that whereas before I had accepted all this unconsciously, I now knew that I could not live without it.

14. Something like this happened to me: without remembering when I had been put into it, I found myself in a boat that had set off from some unknown shore. The direction to the opposite shore was shown to me, oars were put into my inexperienced hands, and I was left alone. I rowed as best I could and moved forwards, but the further I rowed towards the centre of the stream, the faster the current became that was carrying me directly away from my object, and I kept meeting more oarsmen like myself, who were being carried away by the current. There were lone oarsmen who continued to row; there were some who had discarded their oars; there were large rowing boats and enormous ships full of people, some struggling with the current, others abandoning themselves to it. And as I looked at the flow of those drifting downstream, I found that the more I rowed, the more I forgot the directions that had been given to me. In the very middle of the current, amid the crowd of boats and ships being pulled downstream, I lost my directions and abandoned my oars. From all directions people were being carried downstream by sail and oar, shouting for joy and assuring me and themselves that there could be no other direction. And I believed them and flowed with them. And I was carried a long way, so far that I could hear the noise of the rapids which were bound to shatter me, and I caught sight of boats that were already being smashed against them. Then I came to my senses. For a long time I could not understand what had happened to me. I saw nothing ahead of me except the destruction towards which I was rushing, but which I feared, and I could see no salvation anywhere, and I did not know what to do. But looking behind me I saw countless boats that could not stop but were defiantly pushing against the current, and I remembered the oars and the direction of the shore, and I began to struggle back against the current, towards the shore.

15. The shore was God, the direction was tradition, and the oars were the freedom given to me to row towards the shore and unite with God. In this way the force of life rose up within me and I started to live once again.

Chapter 13

1. I renounced the life of our class, having recognized that it is not life but only a semblance of life, and that the conditions of luxury in which we live deprive us of the possibility of understanding life. I knew that in order to comprehend life I must understand the life not of the minority of those of us who are parasites, but of the simple working people, and of the meaning they give to life. The ordinary working people around me were the Russian people and it was to them that I turned, and to the meaning they give to life. This meaning, if it is possible to describe, is as follows. Every person comes into the world through the will of God. And God created man in such a way that each of us can either destroy his soul or save it. Man's purpose in life is to save his soul; in order to save his soul he must live according to God.

2. In order to live according to God one must renounce all the comforts of life, work, be humble, suffer and be merciful. This is the meaning the people have derived from all the religious teaching that has been handed down and communicated to them by the pastors, and by the traditions that form part of their lives and are expressed in their legends, sayings and tales, and it was clear to me and close to my heart. But, together with this meaning rooted in the faith of the people, there was much that was inextricably bound to the non-sectarian people among whom I lived, which revolted me and which I found incomprehensible: the sacraments, the church services, the fasts, the bowing before relics and icons. The people could not separate one thing from another, and neither could I. However strange I found much of what went on in the people's faith, I accepted all of it, attended services, prayed morning and evening, fasted, received communion, and for the first time my reason did not oppose anything. The very thing I had formerly found impossible now provoked no opposition.

3. My attitude to faith was now quite different from what it had been before. Formerly life had seemed full of meaning, and belief seemed to comprise an arbitrary confirmation of various completely unnecessary and irrational propositions that had nothing to do with life. At that time I asked myself what meaning these propositions could have and, convinced that they had none, I threw them aside. Now, on the contrary, I knew very well that my life has, and could have, no meaning. And not only did the tenets of faith cease to appear unnecessary to me, but I was led by indisputable experience to the conviction that it was only these tenets that can give meaning to life. I had formerly looked upon them as completely irrelevant double Dutch but now, even if I knew that I did not understand them, I knew there was meaning in them, and I told myself that I must learn to understand them. I made the following calculation. I told myself that, as with man and his faculty of reason, knowledge of faith arises from a mysterious source. This source is God, the origin of the human mind and body. Just as my body has succeeded to me from God, so too has my reason and my comprehension of life; therefore the stages in the development of this comprehension cannot be false. Those things in which people sincerely believe must be the truth. It may be expressed in various ways but it cannot be a lie. Therefore if I think it is a lie, it can only mean that I do not understand it. And I also said to myself: the essence of any faith consists in giving a meaning to life that will not perish with death. Faith must provide answers to the questions of a Tsar dying in the midst of luxury, an old serf worn out by work, an ignorant child, a wise old man, a half-witted old lady, a happy young woman, and a youth racked with passion. And so, if it is to answer to people living in the most differing circumstances of life and of different education, and if there is only one answer to the eternal questions of life－why do I live? what is the purpose of my life?－this answer, although essentially always the same, must be endlessly varied in its manifestation. The more unique, sincere and profound the answer, the more strange and peculiar it will appear in attempts to give it expression, depending on the education and circumstances of each individual. But these debates, while justifying much that was strange to me about the ritualistic aspects of religion, were nevertheless insufficient to enable me to perform acts I felt dubious about, particularly when it came to the faith that had become the sole concern of my life. With all the powers of my being I wished to be in a position whereby I could merge with the people in fulfilling the ritual aspects of their faith; but I could not do it. I felt that I would be lying to myself, and mocking what I considered sacred, if I were to do so. But at this point I was helped by some new Russian theological works.

4. According to the explanations of these theologians, the basic dogma of faith is the infallibility of the Church. The truth of everything the Church professes follows from this dogma as a necessary conclusion. The Church, as an assembly of believers, united in love and therefore possessing the truth, became the basis of my faith. I told myself that religious truth cannot be attained by one man alone, but only reveals itself to a union of all people, united through love. In order for the truth to be attained there must be no separation; and for there to be no separation we must love and make peace with those who are not in agreement with us. Truth manifests itself as love, and therefore if you do not respect the rituals of the Church you destroy love. And in destroying love you deprive yourself of the possibility of knowing the truth. At the time I did not see the sophistry of this argument. I did not see that unity in love can reveal the greatest love but never the divine truth as expressed in the definitive words of the Nicene Creed. I failed to see that love can never make a given expression of the truth a compulsory condition of unity. At the time I did not see the flaws in the argument, and thanks to it I was able to accept and fulfil all the rites of the Orthodox Church without understanding the majority of them. At the time I tried with my whole soul to avoid any arguments or contradictions, and attempted to explain those doctrines of the Church with which I was in conflict as reasonably as possible.

5. In fulfilling the church rituals I subdued my reason and submitted myself to a tradition shared by all mankind. I united myself with my ancestors and loved ones, with my father and mother, and grandfather and grandmother. They and all who came before them had believed and lived, and they had brought me into the world. And I joined those millions whom I so admired. Nor was there anything wrong in these acts in themselves (by wrong I mean the indulgence of desire). As I rose early in the morning to go to church I knew that I was doing something good, if only in that I was sacrificing my bodily comforts in order to subdue my proud mind, for the sake of unity with my ancestors and contemporaries, and of finding the meaning of life. It was the same when I prepared for communion and said my daily prayers, making the sign of the cross and genuflecting, as too when I fasted. However insignificant these sacrifices were, they were made for the sake of something good. I prepared for communion, I fasted and I observed the hours of prayer both at home and in church. While listening to the church services I paused at each word and whenever I could I gave it meaning. In the liturgy the most significant words for me were: 'Love one another in unity.' But further on I ignored the words: 'We believe in the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost', because I could not understand them.

Chapter 14

1. At the time it was so essential for me to believe in order to live that I subconsciously hid from myself the contradictions and obscurities in the religious dogma. But there was a limit to the amount of meaning that could be read into the rituals. If the most important words of the Ectene became increasingly clear to me, and even if I somehow managed to interpret the words: 'And remembering Our Sovereign Lady, Holy Mother of God, and all the saints, ourselves and one another, let us all devote our entire life to Christ, Our Lord'; and even if I interpreted the frequent repetition of prayers for the Tsar and his family by the fact that they are more exposed to temptation than others, and therefore in greater need of prayer, and the prayers for the subjugation of our enemies and adversaries by saying that they are evil, nevertheless these prayers and others, such as the Hymn of the Cherubim, the Chosen Warriors, as well as the whole sacrament of the Eucharist, in fact nearly two thirds of the service, if not all of it, had no meaning or made me feel that in giving it meaning I was lying and thereby destroying my relation to God and losing all possibility of faith.

2. I experienced the same thing over the celebration of the major feasts. I could understand the law of observing the Sabbath, in other words devoting one day to God. But the most important feast was in memory of the Resurrection, the reality of which I could neither imagine nor understand. And the name 'Resurrection' was also given to the weekly feast day. On this day the sacrament of the Eucharist was performed, which I found quite incomprehensible. All the other twelve feast days, except for Christmas, were in memory of miracles - things which I endeavoured not to think about, in order not to deny them: the Ascension, Pentecost, the Epiphany, the Intercession of the Virgin, and so on. At the celebration of these festivals, feeling that an importance had been ascribed to things I considered to be of little importance, I either invented something that would suffice as an explanation, or closed my eyes so that I would not see the things that tempted me.

3. This happened to me more powerfully than ever when I participated in what are the most usual, and regarded as the most important, sacraments: Baptism and Communion. Here I did not come into conflict with something incomprehensible but with fully comprehensible acts; it seemed to me that these acts were seductive and I found myself in a dilemma - either I rejected them, or I lied about them.

4. I shall never forget the tormenting feeling that I experienced on the day I received communion for the first time in many years. The service, the priest, the rules of prayer, were all something I could understand, and created in me a joyful realization that the meaning of life was being revealed. The communion itself I interpreted as an act performed in memory of Christ, signifying the purification of sin and the full acceptance of Christ's teachings. If this explanation was artificial I failed to notice its falsity. As I bowed down and humbled myself before the confessor, a simple, timid priest, I felt so happy to be shaking loose all the dirt in my soul, repenting all my sins, so happy to be united in thought with the aspirations of the Fathers who had written the prayers of the office, so happy to be united with all those who have and who do believe, that I failed to notice the artificiality of my interpretations. But when I approached the Royal Doors and the priest asked me to repeat what I believe, and that what I was about to receive was actually the body and blood, my heart contracted; it was more than a false note, it was a cruel demand made by someone who evidently had never known what faith is.

5. I can now permit myself to say that it was a cruel demand, but at the time I did not think so; it was just horribly painful to me. I was no longer in the position I had been in during my youth, when I thought that everything in life was lucid. I had come to faith because apart from it I had found nothing, absolutely nothing, other than destruction; it was therefore impossible to give up the faith, and so I submitted. I discovered in my soul a feeling that helped me to endure it. It was a sense of self-abasement and humility. I humbled myself and swallowed the body and blood without feeling any sense of blasphemy, and with the desire to believe; but the blow had already struck. Knowing in advance what awaited me I could not do it a second time.

6. I nevertheless continued to perform the church rituals, and I still believed that the truth lay in the dogma I was following. Then something happened to me which is clear to me now, but which struck me as strange at the time.

7. I was listening to the conversation of an illiterate peasant, a pilgrim, speaking about God, religion, life and salvation when a knowledge of faith was opened up to me. I drew closer to the people and, as I listened to their debates on life and religion, I found myself coming closer and closer to an understanding of the truth. The same thing happened to me when I read the Lives of the Martyrs and the Prologues, which became my favourite reading. Disregarding the miracles and thinking of them as fables expressing ideas, this reading revealed to me the meaning of life. There were the lives of Macarius the Great, Joseph the Prince (the story of Buddha), the writings of John Chrysostom, the story of the traveller in the well, of the monk who found gold, of Peter the Publican and the histories of the martyrs, all of whom proclaimed that death does not obliterate life; and there were the tales of illiterate and stupid men who found salvation, although they knew nothing about the teachings of the Church.

8. But I had only to mix in the company of learned believers, or to borrow their books, and vague feelings of doubt, dissatisfaction and exasperation with their arguments would rise up within me, and I felt that the further I penetrated their discourses, the further I distanced myself from the truth and headed for despair.

Chapter 15

1. I so often envied the peasants their illiteracy and lack of learning. They found nothing false in those doctrinal statements which seemed apparent rubbish to me. They could accept them and believe in the truth, in the same truth that I believed in. Only for me, wretched fellow, it was obvious that the truth was interwoven with fine threads of falsehood, and that I could not accept it as such.

2. Thus I lived for about three years and in the early days when, like one possessed, I was gradually acquiring the truth, scenting out the direction that seemed the clearest, these details struck me less. When I failed to understand something I told myself: 'I am guilty, I am a fool.' But the more I became infused with the truths I was studying, the more they became the basis of my life, the more burdensome and irritating these obstacles became, and the sharper the division between what I did not understand and what I could never understand except by lying to myself.

3. Despite the doubts and sufferings I still clung to the Orthodox Church. But questions of life that had to be resolved kept rising to the surface, and the Church's ruling on these issues - contrary to the very foundations of faith by which I lived - finally obliged me to renounce the possibility of communion with Orthodoxy. First and foremost these issues concerned the attitude of the Orthodox Church to other Churches, to the Catholics and the so-called Raskolniks. At the time, as a result of my interest in religion, I had come into contact with believers of various denominations: Catholics, Protestants, Old Believers, Molokans, and others. Among them I met many deeply moral men with sincere belief. I wished to be a brother to these people. And what happened? The teaching which had promised me unity of all through one faith and through love, that very teaching, speaking through its highest representatives, told me that all these people were living a lie, that the thing which gave them strength of life was a temptation of the devil, and that it is we alone who are in possession of the only possible truth. And I saw that the Orthodox Church regarded as heretics all those who did not profess an identical faith to theirs, just as the Catholics and the others consider the Orthodox followers to be heretics. And I saw that the Orthodox, although they may try to hide it, regard with hostility all those who do not practise their faith by using the same external symbols and words as themselves. And this could not be otherwise, first of all because the assertion that you live in falsehood and I in truth is the most cruel thing that one man can say to another and secondly, because a man who loves his children and his brothers cannot help feeling hostile towards those who want to convert his children and his brothers to a false belief. And this hostility increases in proportion to one's knowledge of theology. And assuming that truth lies in union by love, I was struck by the fact that theology was destroying the thing it should be advancing.

4. The temptation is obvious to educated men like ourselves who live in countries where a variety of different faiths are practised and who have seen the contemptuous, self-righteous, invincible manner of rejection with which the Catholics behave towards the Orthodox and the Protestants, and the Orthodox towards the Catholics and Protestants, and the Protestants towards them both. And there is such a similar attitude between the Old Believers, Russian Evangelists, Shakers and all the other religions, that the very obviousness of the temptation initially perplexed me. I told myself: no, it cannot be so simple. Surely if men fail to see that if their two convictions contradict each other, then neither of them possesses the sole truth that constitutes faith. There is something else here, there must be an explanation. I felt sure there was and I searched for the explanation, reading everything I could on the subject and consulting everyone I could. But I received no explanation other than the one according to which the Sumsky Hussars consider themselves to be the finest regiment in the world, while the Yellow Uhlans consider that they are the best regiment in the world. The ecclesiastics of all the different religious denominations, through their finest representatives, could tell me nothing except that they believed themselves to be in possession of the truth whilst others had strayed from it and that all they could do was to pray for them. I visited archimandrites, bishops, elder monks and monks of the strictest orders, yet none of them made any attempt to elucidate the matter for me. Only one explained it to me, but in such a way that I never asked anyone again.

5. I have already said that for every non-believer who returns to the faith (and this could include all of our younger generation), the question that first presents itself is: why is the truth not to be found in Lutheranism, or Catholicism, but only in the Orthodox faith? Someone who has been educated at secondary school cannot help knowing what the peasant does not know - namely, that the Protestants and Catholics are equally convinced of the singular truth of their faiths. Historical evidence, twisted by each religion to suit its own purpose, is insufficient. Is it not possible, as I have suggested, to understand the teachings in a superior way, so that from an elevated level the differences might disappear, as they do for people who genuinely believe? Is it not possible to go further along that path which we are following with the Old Believers? They stress the fact that their cross, their allelujahs, and their way of processing around the altar differ from ours. We say: you believe in the Nicene Creed and in the seven sacraments, and so do we. Let us keep to that and for the rest you may do as you please. Thus we have united with them by placing the essential aspects of faith above the non-essential. Is it not possible to say to the Catholics: you believe in such and such and so and so, which are the important things, as for the issue of the filoque and the Pope, you may do as you please. And can we not say the same to the Protestants and unite with them in the more important issues? My interlocutor agreed with my ideas, but told me that such concessions would provoke criticism from the spiritual authorities in that it suggests a departure from the faith of our ancestors and would lead to a schism, and that the vocation of the clergy is to safeguard, in all its purity, the Greek Orthodox faith that has been handed down by our forefathers.

6. Then I understood it all. While I am seeking faith, the force of life, they are seeking the best way of fulfilling, in the eyes of men, certain human obligations. And in fulfilling these human affairs they perform them in a human fashion. However much they might speak about their compassion for their lost brethren, or of their prayers for those who stand before the throne of the Almighty, it has always been necessary to use force in carrying out human duties. Just as it has always been applied, so it is now, and always will be. If two religions each consider that they hold the truth and the other a lie, then in order to convert their brothers to the truth they will each preach their own doctrines. And if a false doctrine is taught to the inexperienced sons of the Church which holds the truth, then that Church will have no choice other than to burn the books and banish the person who is leading his sons into temptation. What can be done with a sectarian who, in the eyes of the Orthodox Church, is ablaze with the fire of false doctrine, and who is misleading the sons of the Church in the most important matter of life, in faith? What can be done with him other than chop off his head or imprison him? Under the Tsar, Alexis Mikhailovitch, they were burned at the stake; in other words, the severest method of punishment of the time was enforced. In our day too the severest method of punishment is enforced: imprisonment in solitary confinement. As I turned my attention to what is done in the name of religion I was horrified and very nearly repudiated Orthodoxy. A further thing was the Church's attitude to life with regard to war and executions.

7. At the time Russia was at war. And, in the name of Christian love, Russians were killing their fellow men. It was impossible not to think about this. It was impossible to avoid the fact that killing is evil and contrary to the most basic principles of any faith. And yet prayers were said in the churches for the success of our armies, and our religious teachers acknowledged this killing as an outcome of faith. And this was not only applied to murder in time of war, but, during the troubled times that followed the war, I witnessed members of the Church, her teachers, monks, and ascetics condoning the killing of helpless, lost youths. As I turned my attention to all that is done by people who profess Christianity, I was horrified.

Chapter 16

1. I no longer had any doubts and was fully convinced that not all the teachings of the faith I had joined were true. Whereas before I used to say that all religious teaching is a lie, I no longer found it possible to say this. There could be no doubt that the people as a whole had a knowledge of the truth, otherwise they would not be here. Moreover, this knowledge of the truth was now accessible to me; I had already lived by it and felt its validity. But there was falsehood in it as well, of this I had no doubt. All that had hitherto repelled me now stood vividly before me. Although I could see that the mixture of lies I so loathed was less apparent among the peasants than among the representatives of the Church, I could nevertheless see that even in the people's faith there was falsehood mixed with the truth.

2. But where did the falsehood come from, and where did the truth come from? Both had been passed down by what is called the Church. But falsehood and truth are contained in tradition, in the so-called holy tradition and in the Scriptures.

3. Whether I liked it or not, I was led to study and examine these writings and traditions - an examination that until now I had been very fearful of.

4. I turned to a study of that very theology I had once so contemptuously rejected as unnecessary. It had previously struck me as a collection of useless nonsense, this at a time when I had been surrounded by manifestations of life that I thought clear and full of meaning. Now I would have been glad to discard all those things that did not enhance health of mind, but I did not know what to do with myself. The one meaning of life that had been revealed to me rests on this religious doctrine, or is at least inseparably connected. However far-fetched it might seem to my old, infirm mind, it was the only hope of salvation. It must be carefully and attentively examined in order to be understood, even if it is not understood in the way I understand the propositions of science. I do not seek that, nor can I, since I know the unusual nature of religious knowledge. I shall not seek the explanation of everything. I know that the explanation of all things, like the origin of all things, must remain a secret of eternity. But I want to understand in such a way as to be brought to the inevitably inexplicable. I want to realize that all that is inexplicable is so, not because the demands of my intellect are at fault (they are correct and apart from them I can understand nothing), but because I can recognize the limits of my intellect. I want to understand in such a way that everything inexplicable presents itself to me as being necessarily inexplicable and not as being something that I am under an obligation to believe.

5. I have no doubt that there is truth in the teachings, but I also have no doubt that there is falsehood in them too, and that I must discover what is true and what is false and separate one from the other. This is what I have set out to do. That which I found false in the teachings, and that which I found true, and the conclusions I came to comprise the following section of this essay, which, if someone should consider it worthwhile and useful to people, will probably be published some day, somewhere.

6. I wrote the above three years ago.

7. The other day, while I was re-reading this printed section and returning to the train of thoughts and feelings that were inside me when I was experiencing all this, I had a dream. This dream expressed for me, in condensed form, all that I had lived through and described, therefore I think that for those who have understood me a description of the dream will refresh, clarify and unify all that has been related at such length in these pages. Here is the dream: I see that I am lying on a bed. I am neither comfortable, nor uncomfortable. I am lying on my back. But I start to think about whether or not I am comfortable and it seems to me that my legs are a bit awkward; I do not know whether it is that they are too short or that they are uneven. I shift my legs and at the same time I begin to think about the way I am lying and what I am lying on, things which had not entered my head until now. And looking at my bed I see that I am lying on some plaited rope supports that are attached to the sides of the bed. My feet are resting on one of the supports, my calves on another and my legs are uncomfortable. I somehow know that these supports can be moved. Moving one of my legs I push away the furthest support beneath my feet. I presume that this will be better. But I have pushed it too far and want to rescue it with my legs, and this movement causes yet another support, beneath my calves, to fall off and my calves are left dangling. I move my whole body in order to adjust my position and am quite certain that this will settle the matter. But with this movement still more of the supports slip and move away beneath me and I can see that things are getting worse: the whole lower part of my body is slipping and hanging down, and my feet do not reach the ground. I am only supported on the upper half of my back and I start to feel not just uncomfortable but terrified of something. Only at this point do I ask myself the thing that has not yet entered my head. I ask myself: where am I and what am I lying on? I begin looking around and before anywhere else I look beneath me, where my body is dangling and in the direction where I feel I am bound to fall very soon. I look below, and I cannot believe my eyes. I am at a height not just of, say, an extremely tall tower or mountain, but I am at a height such as I could never have imagined.

8. I cannot even discern whether I can see anything there below, in the bottomless abyss over which I am hanging and into which I am being drawn. My heart contracts and I feel terrified. It is dreadful to look down there. I feel that if I look down I will immediately slip from the last support and perish. I do not look, but not looking is still worse because I am thinking about what is going to happen to me when I slip from the last support. And I feel that I am losing my last bit of strength through terror, and that my back is slowly slipping lower and lower. Another moment and I will fall off. And then I have a thought: perhaps it is not real. It is a dream. I will wake up. I try to wake up and cannot. 'What can I do, what can I do?' I ask myself, looking upwards. Above there is also an abyss. I look into this abyss of sky and try to forget about the abyss below, and I do in fact forget it. The infinity below repels and frightens me; the infinity above attracts and reassures me. Thus I am hanging over the abyss, held up by the last of the supports that has not yet slipped out from under me; I know that I am dangling but I only look upwards and my fear passes away. As happens in a dream, a voice says: 'Take note of this, this is it!' I look further and further into the infinity above me and feel myself growing calmer. I remember everything that has happened and how it happened: how I shifted the position of my legs, how I was dangling there, how terrified I felt, and how I was saved from my terror by looking upwards. And I asked myself: 'Am I not still dangling there?' And I do not look around so much as feel with my whole body the edge of the support by which I am held up. I see that I am no longer dangling or falling but am firmly supported. I ask myself how I am being supported: I grope about, look around and see that beneath me, under the middle of my body, there is a single support and when I look up I am lying on it in a position of secure balance, and that it alone gave me support before. And then, as happens in dreams, the mechanism by which I am supported seems to me to be a very natural, comprehensible and sure thing, although when awake it makes no sense at all. I am even surprised, in my sleep, that I had not understood this before. It appears that there is a pillar at my head and the solidity of this slender pillar is beyond doubt, although there is nothing for it to stand on. A rope is hanging very ingeniously, yet simply, from the pillar, and if one lies with the middle of one's body on the rope and looks up there can be no question of falling. This was all clear to me and I was glad and tranquil. It was as if someone were saying to me: 'See that you remember.' And I woke up.

译者导读

尼可罗·马基雅维利（Niccolò Machiavelli，1469—1527），意大利政治哲学家、音乐家、诗人和浪漫喜剧剧作家，意大利文艺复兴时期的重要人物。马基雅维利出生在一个没落的贵族家庭，家境贫寒，没有接受过多少正规教育，通过自学，使自己博古通今、多才多艺。他于1498年出任佛罗伦萨共和国第二国务厅的长官，兼任共和国执政委员会秘书，1505年担任国民军九人指挥委员会秘书。1511年教皇的军队攻陷佛罗伦萨，废黜执政官，马基雅维利丧失了一切职务。1527年，美第奇家族倒台，马基雅维利被逐，郁悒成疾，五十八岁即去世。

《阴谋论》是马基雅维利关于阴谋论和军队、战争、战略等领域思想认识的一个合集，该合集用意大利语写成，1513年首次出版。马基雅维利曾于1498年进入十人执政团服务，随后奉命出国担任外交官员，期间积累的工作经验为其政治军事著作提供了丰富的经验基础。整个合集大量引用罗马时期的事例，来论述其政治军事领域的思想。

《阴谋论》合集共分七个部分。第一部分主要是其关于阴谋论的认识，通过对阴谋的成因、实施、失败因素以及防范措施的论述，旨在提醒统治者如何阻止阴谋。第二部分主要介绍了其关于军队、军纪和各兵种方面的认识，通过对比引证，强调了步兵在战争中的重要性，论述了炮兵如何在战争中发挥作用。第三部分主要驳斥了关于城堡利弊、利用城市内讧夺取城市等一些与战争有关的错误认识。第四部分引用罗马共和国在平时与战时和相邻国家城市关系的经验教训，旨在唤起统治者的注意。第五部分通过引用罗马共和国的战争事例，阐述其对战争、策略、新装备和纪律等方面的一些评论。第六部分主要在大战前的小规模战斗、如何取得军队信任、熟悉地形等方面，为征战中的统帅们提出一些建议。第七部分通过对于战争欺诈、誓死卫国、城下之盟的论述，印证其人民利益至高无上的思想。整个合集作于其著名论著《君主论》之后，是在美第奇家族重新掌权后马基雅维利失意之时所作，作为政治军事领域的重要图书，被列入企鹅口袋书“伟大的思想”系列。

阴谋论

引言

既然阴谋会导致对君主和个人同样危险的后果，那么我也就无法略去不谈其性质，毕竟有更多君主由于阴谋而非公开战争丧失了性命和政权，因为能对一个君主宣战的不过寥寥几个人，但是策划谋反的却可能是任何人。另一方面，在任何一项事业里，没有比个人参与阴谋更危险或者更轻率鲁莽的事情了，因为整个过程都充满困难和危险。因此，尽管人们已有许多阴谋尝试，但达到目的的却寥寥无几。为了使君主们了解如何防范此类危险，为了使个人三思而行并学会安于天命、臣服君主，我将对阴谋进行细致的探讨，不会遗漏任何与君王或个人相关的重要事项。事实上，克奈里乌斯·塔西佗曾经说过这样一句金玉良言：“人应尊重过去，更应着眼当下，即使内心渴求明主，也必须接受自己的君王——不论他们是怎样的人。”毋庸置疑，那些反其道而行之的人常常给他们自己和他们的国家带来灾难。

在开始讨论此话题之前，第一个需要思考的问题是：这些阴谋的产生是针对谁？事实证明，阴谋的产生要么是针对其祖国，要么是针对君主。此文中，我会对这两种类型的阴谋分别进行探讨，因为以将城池移送给围城的敌人手里为目的而制造的阴谋，或者因某种理由制造的与此相似的阴谋，其他地方已言之足矣。

成因

在此论述第一部分，我们先谈谈针对君主的阴谋。首先，我们对其众多成因提出疑问。但其实有一个成因比其他所有成因都更为重要，那就是君主所激起的普遍仇恨，因为当其激起了这种普遍仇恨之时，我们就能预料到，那些曾被他大大冒犯的人将会寻求报复。而当这些人发现君主已经激起了人们的普遍憎恶，他们的报复欲望就更强烈了。因此，君主应当避免招致此类个人恩怨，鉴于别处已经论及如何避免个人恩怨，此处不再赘述。之所以提及，是因为若君主真有意提防，那么仅仅对于个人施以惩罚将会招致较少的敌意。原因如下：首先，我们很少遇到这样的人，对某种不公正行为无比愤慨，从而身犯险境去实施报复；其次，如果他们确实想这么做且已具备必需的能力，那么他们也会因为君主受人民拥戴而行动受限。

伤害可能波及人的财产、生命或荣誉。杀戮的威胁要比杀戮本身更危险。的确，威胁要进行杀戮是极其危险的，然而杀戮却毫无危险，因为死人不可能思量着复仇，而那些幸存者却通常促使你作复仇的思虑。但是，那些已受到威胁并意识到不得不做些什么或者投身其中的人，对君主而言已构成真正的威胁，我们将引用实例说明。

除去那些由求生本能驱使的行动实例，对人的财产或者荣誉的伤害是最容易激怒人的，对此君主应当警惕，因为不论他如何掠夺一个人的财产，也无法确保那人丧失复仇的能力；不论他如何剥夺一个人的荣誉，也无法让那人打消报复的念头。在人们被剥夺的众多荣誉中，最重要的是女人的荣誉，其次是对男人人品的蔑视。正因如此，帕萨尼亚斯才揭竿而起反对马其顿国王菲利普；也正因如此，才有许多人拿起武器反对其君主。在我们的时代，如果卢西奥·柏兰提没有把他女儿嫁给西恩纳暴君潘多佛为妻，然后又把她带走，那么他就不会被迫密谋反对潘多佛了，这点我们会在适当时候详述。导致帕西对美第奇谋反的主要原因在于美第奇下令夺走了乔瓦尼·邦热美的继承权。

导致人们密谋反对君主的另外一个原因，也是非常有力的一个原因，就是他们收复已被君主攫为己有的国土的欲求。正因如此，布鲁特斯和卡修斯才转而反对恺撒，也正因如此，有那么多人密谋反对法拉里斯、狄奥尼修斯和其他国家权力的篡夺者。没有一个暴君可以超越此种意志，除非放弃其暴政。然而，没有暴君愿意放弃暴政，所以几乎所有暴君皆以悲剧收场。因此尤维纳尔的诗歌这样写道：“几乎没有君主可以毫发未伤地陨落于冥界，暴君也屡屡难逃悲惨下场。”

单人阴谋

如前所述，阴谋带来的危险是相当多的，并且持续不断，因为一个阴谋中会有多种危险突然出现，这些危险充斥于阴谋形成、实施的整个过程，以及阴谋产生的后果中。阴谋的形成可由单人而为，亦可由多人而为。若仅由单人而为，并不能理所当然地称之为阴谋。准确地说，它是某个个体要杀掉君主的坚定决心。在阴谋所蕴含的三种危险之中，单人之谋仅包含后两种危险。因为在行动之前是不可能有危险产生的，既然没有其他人知晓，也就不存在对君主实施该阴谋的危险。而是否有实施阴谋的决心取决于这个人的能力——无论他伟大或渺小，高贵或卑微，与君主关系密切或疏远。因为任何被准许在某个时间同君主交谈的人，以及任何有机会同君主交谈的人，其情绪皆有可能得以舒缓。我们已经屡次提到的帕萨尼亚斯，在马其顿国王菲利普与一帮武装人员前去庙宇的路上杀害了他，当时走在国王两边的分别是他的儿子和女婿。但是，帕萨尼亚斯是贵族，且与君主相识（但也有其他人）。一个贫穷可怜的西班牙人将匕首刺入了西班牙国王斐迪南的脖子，尽管伤口并不致命，但是它却表明了此种类型的人也可能具备做这种事的意图和机会。一个托钵僧或土耳其牧师，在巴雅泽用弯刀袭击了当时的土耳其君主。他并没有杀死他，但是他必然具有这样做的意图和机会。我认为，我们周围有很多想要做这种事的人，但仅仅心怀这种意图，既不需要受到惩罚，也不会产生任何的危险。但是真正去做的人却寥寥无几，且在这些人中，也只有非常少的人在其行动中幸存。因此，你会发现没有人甘于赴死。但让我们撇开这些单人阴谋，来谈谈多人阴谋。

弱者的阴谋

在我看来，历史上所有的阴谋要么是有名望之人所为，要么是君主近侍或亲信所为，其他人除非是十足的疯子，否则不可能阴谋陷害君主，毕竟无权之人以及无法接触君主之人没有成功实施阴谋的任何希望和机会。首先，无权之人笼络不到可以忠于他们的人，毕竟在有可能冒大风险的情况下，没有人会答应去为他们做事，因为阴谋一旦传达至两三人，告密者就会出现，他们的计划便会暴露。其次，即使他们足够幸运，没有告密者出现，他们在阴谋的实施中也一样会由于无法轻易接近君主而困难重重，而在得以行事之时根本无法逃离险境。既然有名望之人和能够轻易接近君主的人都得屈服于这些困难，更不要说其他人了，他们面临的困难将被无限放大。所以，只要他们的生命和财产并未受到威胁，只要他们不会丢掉脑袋，那么当其认识到自己的劣势，就会变得小心谨慎，即使对君主心怀不满，也只会私下咒骂发泄，等待着那些拥有更高地位声望之人可以替他们报仇雪恨。这样一来，一旦遇见这种人欲行谋害君主之事，人们应对其意图动机而非审慎态度加以赞赏。

强者的阴谋

阴谋者似乎一直都是有名望之人或者与君主关系密切之人，其中因赐予太多利益而导致的谋反与因施予太多惩罚所引发的谋反案例一样众多，例如，卜兰尼斯密谋反对康茂德，普劳提阿努斯密谋反对西弗勒斯，塞扬努斯密谋反对泰比里厄斯。对于这些人而言，君主赐予的财富、荣誉和头衔已经很多，似乎什么都不缺，除了君主的头衔，他们对此不愿意忍受，因此密谋反对君主，而最终总会得到其忘恩负义之行应得的结果。

而近代发生的相似阴谋中，有一个却取得了成功，即雅各布·阿皮亚诺密谋反对比萨君主梅瑟·皮耶罗·干姆巴科尔提，因为雅各布正是由后者抚养长大，且名誉加身，而他却夺了后者的权。在我们的时代也有科波拉阴谋反对亚拉贡国王费迪南。因为对于已经拥有巨大财富的科波拉来说，唯一缺少的就是一个王国，而他也因为决心得到它而丧命。然而，如果有名望之人谋反成功，则情况一定如此：阴谋必定是由有名的另一位君主所为。但是那种易于使人盲目的支配欲，又一次使他们在着手做事时失去理智。只要他们知道怎样谨慎实施恶行，那么就不可能不成功。

对君主们的忠告

因此，想要提防阴谋的君主，相对于那些已被其过多伤害的人，更应当害怕那些被其授予过多恩惠的人。因为前者缺乏机会，而后者却机会多多，尽管二者所欲相同；统治国家的欲望与复仇的欲望一样大，甚至更大。所以，君主授予其朋友的权力应当保持一个度，即在此权力和君主权力之间应当保持一个特定的间距，且在此间距之中还有别的东西可所欲求。否则，如果我们刚谈论的事情未发生在他们身上，那倒是一件怪事了。下面，言归正传。

告密引发的危险

前面已经提及，谋反者一定是有名望之人和容易接近君主之人，这里我们就谈谈他们的成功和事例，以及为什么有些人成功了而其他人却失败了。如前所述，阴谋的危险常常发生在三个阶段：开始之时，实施之时和结束之后。我们发现，阴谋很少成功，因为成功通过这三个阶段是不可能或者几乎不可能的。首先，我们来谈谈开始阶段的危险。鉴于在制订计划过程中要使阴谋不被发现需要敏锐的判断力和足够的运气，对此阶段危险的探讨显得更加重要。阴谋暴露有两种方式，要么走漏了消息，要么出自推断。信息泄露要么是合谋之人变节，要么是其不够谨慎所致。变节之事时有发生，因为你只能将阴谋传达给你认为会誓死效忠于你的人，或对君主不满的人。也许其中有一两个人是你可以信任的，但是如果你将计划透露给多人，那么要找到这样的人是不可能的，因为他们必须对你非常信任，他们对危险和惩罚的估计不会影响对你的信任。人常常错估别人对自己的情分，而除非你有前车之鉴，否则无法确定这份情谊。然而，这种前车之鉴的获得也要冒很大风险。甚至于即使在其他危险事件中，他们忠诚于你，你也不能保证他们会在种种危险远远超出之前的事件中保持同等忠诚。如果你判断一个人的忠诚度是依据他对君主的不满程度，那么你很容易犯错；因为你接受了这种不满，即是为他提供了获得满足的各种条件，这样一来，如果要他保持对你的忠诚，要么他确实苦大仇深，要么你对他的影响一定巨大。

所以，阴谋就屡遭暴露，在开始就被挫败。的确，若是一个传达给多人的阴谋很长时间内一直仍是秘密，那可真让人啧啧称奇，就像历史上庇索密谋反对尼罗，以及我们这个时代帕西密谋反对洛伦佐和朱利亚诺·美第奇一样，当时五十多人对此保守秘密，直到采取行动的那一刻阴谋才暴露。

轻率导致的危险

由于轻率而使阴谋暴露的情况发生在密谋时不够谨慎而使佣人或者第三者听到之时，例如，布鲁特斯之子就因其与塔奎因报信者的阴谋谈话被佣人听到而被告发。或者，阴谋的暴露是因为你无意中将其告诉了女友或者男友或者别的轻佻之人，以蒂姆努斯为例，他和菲洛塔斯以及其他人一起谋反亚历山大大帝，曾向一个他很喜欢的名叫尼克马库斯的男孩谈到了他们的计划，不料那个男孩立刻就把此事告诉了他的哥哥赛巴利努斯，而赛巴利努斯又把这个阴谋告诉了国王亚历山大。

推断引发的暴露

由于推断而引起的阴谋暴露，庇索尼安阴谋反对尼罗即是一例。其中一个名叫斯伽维努斯的阴谋者在计划杀掉尼罗的前一天立下遗嘱，并命令他的自由民米里库斯把他那把老旧而锈迹斑斑的匕首磨光，释放所有的奴隶并分给他们钱财，准备好用于包扎伤口的绷带，从这些事情中米里库斯推断出了有阴谋存在并告诉了尼罗。于是，斯伽维努斯，连同前一天被看到跟他一起长时间秘密谈话的共谋者纳塔莱斯，一起被捕了。由于他们解释不一致，最后被迫说出真相，这样一来阴谋就暴露了，所有与之相关的人都遭遇了灭顶之灾。

防止暴露的困难

无论是由于恶意，还是由于不够谨慎，或者是言行失检，或者是轻率的谈话，所有这些情况下如果知道阴谋的人超过三个或者四个，那么要防止上述这些原因造成的阴谋暴露就是不可能的。因为一旦有一个以上的阴谋者被捕，那么要想阻止阴谋泄露就不可能，原因在于两个人不可能在他们给出解释的每一个细节上都能保持一致。如果只有一个人被捕而他恰好是一个果毅之人，那么他或许不会供出他的同谋者。但是，极为重要的是，其他同谋者也必须有不逊于被捕者的胆量坚守其立场不逃跑，因为无论是被捕之人还是在逃之人，均可能由于缺乏勇气而泄露阴谋。

的确存在这样一个稀少的案例，由泰特斯·李维提出，即反对锡拉库扎国王希罗尼穆斯的阴谋。在这场阴谋中，其中一个叫狄奥多士的同谋者被捕后，他仗义保护其他同谋者，栽赃给了国王的朋友；而他的同伴也非常信得过狄奥多士的为人，他们之中没有一个人离开锡拉库扎或者表现出一丝的害怕。

预防暴露的措施

以上这些都是在阴谋实施之前暴露所面临的危险；避免泄露的补救措施如下。首要的、最安全的，实话讲也是唯一的补救方法就是不给共谋者泄露对你不利信息的时间，且仅在你准备行动之时而非提前将你的计划告知他们。这样做，至少可以避开因谋划阴谋而招致的危险，其他人通常也可以逃离危险。事实上，他们都会成功，任何谨慎之人都会发现这样做事是可行的。后面我会引用两个实例，暂且讨论至此。

奈勒迈特斯由于无法忍受伊庇鲁斯君主亚里士提摩斯的暴政，集结了家中众多亲戚和朋友，劝说他们一起解放祖国。有人提出需要时间考虑，先把家里的事情安排好。奈勒迈特斯让随从锁上家门，对这些人说道：“要么你们现在就跟我一起行动，要么我把你们统统作为囚犯交给亚里士提摩斯。”这些话让他们下了决心，他们发了誓并立即行动，成功地执行了奈勒迈特斯的命令。当通过诡计获得波斯王冠后，王国的一个领袖马吉中的一人和奥塔尼斯听说了此消息并发现了这个诡计，于是他就与其他六位领袖协商，告诉他们是时候推翻这个占星师的暴政了。当有人问何时行动时，六位领袖中一个名叫达赖厄斯的人站起来说道：“要么我们现在立刻行动解决此事，要么我去指控你们。”于是他们整齐划一地行动，在敌人未来及作任何准备之时成功实施了计划。与这两个实例相似的还有埃托利亚人为了杀掉斯巴达暴君纳比斯所采用的方法。他们命令同胞亚历科萨麦尼斯带领三十匹马和两百步兵假意援助纳比斯，并只将计划告知亚历科萨麦尼斯，命令其他人必须严格服从于他，违者处以流放之惩罚。因此，亚历科萨麦尼斯去到斯巴达，绝口不提其受委托的任务，直到准备好行动的那一刻。结果，他成功地杀掉了纳比斯。这些人通过采用这些手段，避免了策划阴谋阶段隐藏的危险，效仿他们做法的人也同样总是能避免危险。

阴谋的实用性

他们的行为人人可以效仿，这一点可以从前文提到的庇索案例中得以证明。庇索是尼罗非常信任的人，和尼罗关系密切，有很高的地位和声望。尼罗经常在自己的花园中和庇索一起用餐，这样一来庇索就可以结交到无论心态、勇气还是爱好都非常适合执行此阴谋的朋友，这对于有身份地位的人是非常容易的。当尼罗在花园里的时候，庇索可以用适当的言语指使这些人做一些他们没有时间拒绝的事，或者使本不可能成功的阴谋最后取得成功。因此，纵观诸多阴谋，没有几个不是按照这个方法成功的。但是，通常情况下人们很少关注世事，因而往往犯下重大错误，尤其是在那些超出常规的事情上，比如阴谋。

进一步的防范

不到迫不得已或时机成熟之时，阴谋绝不能泄露。如果必须要泄露，也只能泄露给一个人，并且是你知根知底或者与你动机相同的人。找一个这样的人要比找一群这样的人容易得多，因为知道的人越多意味着越危险。此外，在合谋者不多的情况下，如果你犯了错误，你还可能找到保护自己的机会。一位智者曾经说过，你可以把你所有的事情单独告诉一个人，因为别人无论肯定回答还是否定回答意义都差不多，除非他说服你将你的所作所为写下来。每个人都要特别提防写下任何东西，因为没有什么比自己的笔迹更容易证实自己的罪行。普劳提阿努斯决心杀掉君主西弗勒斯及其儿子安东尼纳斯，并把这个秘密告诉护民官撒图尔尼努斯。撒图尔尼努斯想去告发他，但又害怕控告普劳提阿努斯时别人相信他而不相信自己，于是他要求普劳提阿努斯提供书面凭证，以证明自己受普劳提阿努斯的委托和授权。被雄心壮志冲昏头脑的普劳提阿努斯真的写给了他，最终因被撒图尔尼努斯控告而获罪。如果没有这份书面材料和其他一些不利证据，普劳提阿努斯完全可以厚着脸皮死不承认以保全自己。可见，如果没有书面材料或其他证据，即便你被控告，照样有机会得以逃脱，因此对待提供书面材料之事要慎之又慎。

在针对尼罗的庇索尼安阴谋中，有一个名叫艾比开瑞斯的女人，曾是尼罗的情人。她认为让一个曾担任尼罗警卫的战船船长参与进来有助于阴谋的实施，因此她把阴谋告诉了这位船长，但是并未告知共谋者都是谁。后来，这个船长食言向尼罗控告她的时候，她严词否认了对她的控告，以至于尼罗无法定夺而让她离开。因此，将阴谋告知另外一人存在两种危险。一种危险是他可能会主动指控你；另一种危险是他受到怀疑或者不利证据而被捕，在被宣判有罪或受到严刑拷问之时将你供出。在这两种情况下，危险都是可以补救的。因为在第一种情况下，你可以否认对你的指控，宣称对方因为恨你而捏造事实；在第二种情况下，你也可以否认指控，宣称对方是因为被暴力威逼而撒谎。

无预谋的暗杀

因此，最明智的做法是不把自己的情况告诉任何人，而只按照上述案例行动；或者如果你不得不告诉某一个人，也不要告诉再多的人，这样尽管危险可能会更大，但是也不会比你告诉更多人的危险大。当情势逼迫你必须要对君主下手，就像你看到君主准备要对你下手一样时，情况也是一样的，因为此时此刻你的需要迫切至根本没有时间考虑如何防范。这种必要性几乎总能导向理想的结果，为了证明这一点，举两个例子。

在君主康茂德的几个主要朋友和亲信里，里图斯和埃克莱克图斯掌管着禁卫军，而马西娅是他主要情妇之一。这些人有时候会因他的行为有失体统而责备他，所以康茂德决定将他们处死，并把这三人和他决定在第二天夜里处死的其他几个人列了一个名单。他把名单放在了枕头下。在他去洗漱的时候，他最喜爱的小儿子在他床上玩耍嬉闹，无意中看到那个名单，就拿在手里跑了出去，在外面遇到了马西娅，马西娅从他手里拿过名单，读完之后记录下内容，并立即派人去叫里图斯和埃克莱克图斯。他们三人都意识到了自己处境的危险，于是决定先发制人。所以，他们没有浪费任何不必要的时间，在第二天夜里杀掉了康茂德。

第二个例子是，君主安东尼纳斯·卡拉卡拉带兵到美索不达米亚时，有一个地方行政长官叫马克里努斯，比起他的战士身份，他倒更像是一个平民百姓。与所有那些不好的君主一样，安东尼纳斯总是害怕别人不按照他所认为应该得到的礼遇对待他。他给在罗马的一个名叫马特尼安纳斯的朋友写信，托他向占星家询问是否有人觊觎他的王位，并给他一些相应的建议。马特尼安纳斯回信说，马克里努斯就是那个觊觎王位之人，但是这封信却在送给安东尼纳斯之前落入了马克里努斯之手。就这样，马克里努斯意识到，要么在下一封来自罗马的信到达之前杀掉安东尼纳斯，要么就会被他杀掉，只能二选一。于是他命令手下一个名叫马尔提亚里斯的百夫长将安东尼纳斯暗杀，马尔提亚里斯最终成功完成了任务。马尔提亚里斯效忠于马克里努斯，他的兄弟几天前刚刚被安东尼纳斯处死。

可以看到，当情势紧迫到没有时间可以耽搁的时候，结果就会与前面所说的伊庇鲁斯的奈勒迈特斯所用方法产生的结果相同。还可以看到，我在本文一开始所说的话仍然适用，即与实际造成的伤害相比，威胁对君主的伤害更大，更可能导致阴谋的产生。因此，君主必须防止这类威胁，要么他应该对那些人十分关怀，要么应该确保那些人不对他造成伤害，但是在任何情况下，他都绝不应该将那些人置于“不是你死就是我亡”的境地。

改变计划导致的危险

阴谋实施过程中发生的危险，要么是因为计划发生改变，要么是因为阴谋实施者缺乏勇气，要么是因为实施者粗心犯错，要么是因为未将目标全部消灭而没能完成任务。因此，在此我要指出，没有预先通知突然改变计划，放弃起初拟定的行动计划，是干扰计划实施的最大因素。如果计划的改变会滋生混乱，那么也是在军事行动和我们正谈及的事件之中。因为此类事件中，首先必须要做的是，让参与行动的人清晰地了解自己要做的事情；如果他们花了几天时间去设想一个详细的计划及其行动过程，而突然被告知行动有变，一切都会失调，整个计划就会被搞砸。所以，即使看到计划中存在不妥之处，执行原计划也比取消计划从而卷入诸多不便之中好得多。这个原则适用于没有时间制定新计划的情况，因为如果有时间的话，完全可以按其所愿进行计划安排。

帕西阴谋反对洛伦佐和朱利亚诺·美第奇的事为大家所熟知。根据拟定的计划，洛伦佐和朱利亚诺·美第奇会受邀与圣乔治教堂的红衣主教共进晚餐，在用餐时将其暗杀。计划还详细布置了哪些人负责暗杀、哪些人负责占领宫殿以及哪些人负责在城市周围散播讯息鼓动人们解放自己。当帕西、美第奇和红衣主教在佛罗伦萨天主教堂出席庄严肃穆的集会时，大家得知朱利亚诺那天不会去和他们共进晚餐，所以共谋者们聚集起来决定将原打算在美第奇家里完成的任务改在教堂完成。这个决定搅乱了整个计划，因为吉奥万巴提斯塔·蒙特塞克拒绝参与，他说他不会去教堂做这件事。因此，不得不寻找替补并重新分配任务，由于没有时间搞清楚行动的细节，他们在实施的时候就犯了许多致命错误，最终失败了。

由于优柔寡断造成的失败

负责完成阴谋任务的实施者优柔寡断，要么是因为尊重人性，要么是因为胆小怯懦。君主展现的威严和气场很容易动摇阴谋实施者的决心或者使他害怕。马里厄斯被民特纳人俘虏后，一个奴隶被派去杀他，但来到马里厄斯面前时，奴隶被他的强大气场所震慑，又想到他的名字代表的含义，顿时失去了杀他的勇气和力量。如果连一个被锁在监狱之中承受不幸的人都有如此魅力，那么未被俘虏且身穿君主长袍，威严无比地被壮丽浮华和朝臣包围时的他一定更有魅力。这样的排场足以威慑到你，他对你热情亲切的迎接可能会让你心软。有一伙人阴谋反对色雷斯国王西塔尔凯斯，他们于行动之日到达国王所在之地，但是竟然没有人敢向西塔尔凯斯动手，最后什么都没做就离开了，他们搞不清到底是什么原因阻止了行动，只好互相责怪。就这样，他们不止一次犯下同样的错误，最终导致阴谋暴露，他们也都因这一可能犯下但最终没有实施的罪行而受到了惩罚。菲拉拉的阿方索公爵有两个兄弟共谋反对他，他们选择了一个给公爵当差的人作为中间人，这个人既是牧师又是合唱指挥。应两兄弟的要求，此人多次成功引公爵与他们会面，让他们可以趁势杀掉阿方索，但兄弟二人均不敢动手，阴谋暴露后，他们不得不遭受邪恶与缺乏谨慎而招致的惩罚。只有在被君主的强大气场所震慑及因其仁慈的举止而失掉戾气的情况下，这种疏忽大意的过错才会出现。

由于心绪不宁而造成的失败

阴谋实施过程中的诸多不顺利，是由于缺乏谨慎或缺乏勇气酿成的错误所致，因为这两种情况都可能发生，使得你心绪混乱，说错话、做错事。提图斯·李维向我们讲述的一个叫亚历科萨麦尼斯的埃托利亚人的事例，最能贴切描述人们这样崩溃混乱的情形。亚历科萨麦尼斯决心杀掉前文所述的斯巴达人纳比斯，行动时机到来之时，他告知手下任务，并且，依照李维的叙述：“努力使自己集中力量，因为思索这样一件大事令他的思绪混乱。”的确，一个人的意志再坚强，对死亡或持弄刀剑再熟悉，也不太可能不混乱。因此，应当选择有做这种事情经验的人，不要把事情委托给任何其他人，即使人们认为他再勇敢也不行。做大事的时机到来之时，如果行动者之前没有任何经验，那么没人敢肯定会发生什么。例如，心绪混乱可能导致武器从手中滑落，或者偶然泄露某些信息并导致同样的后果。康茂德的姐姐卢西拉与昆提阿努斯一起计划杀掉他，昆提阿努斯在圆形剧场入口处等待着康茂德，拿着亮晃晃的匕首来到康茂德面前，说道：“元老院送你的礼物！”这些话让他没来得及放下武器袭击康茂德就被捕了。之前提到过，梅瑟·安东尼奥·沃尔泰拉受命杀掉洛伦佐·美第奇，在扑向美第奇那一刻，他喊道：“啊，叛徒！”这一惊叫挽救了洛伦佐的性命，摧毁了那个阴谋。

旨在推翻多位君主的阴谋

由于上述原因，成功密谋推翻一位君主已经相当不易，而成功密谋推翻两位君主更是难上加难。换句话说，推翻两位君主的密谋几乎不可能成功，因为你几乎不可能在同一时间不同地点实施相似的行动，而在不同的时间实施两次又很难确保二者不相互影响。因此，如果说密谋推翻一位君主是没有把握、危险、鲁莽任务，那么密谋推翻两位君主的行为则完全是愚蠢、轻佻。如果不是出于对历史学家的尊重，我是绝不会认为赫罗狄安关于普劳提阿努斯的记叙是可能的。依照他的说法，普劳提阿努斯委任同一个人——百夫长萨图尔尼努斯，去刺杀居住在不同地方的西弗勒斯和安东尼纳斯。这件事完全不合理，我相信它的唯一理由就是赫罗狄安的权威性。

几个雅典青年志士密谋推翻雅典暴君狄奥克莱斯和希庇亚斯，他们杀死了狄奥克莱斯，但希庇亚斯得以逃脱并为他报了仇。柏拉图的弟子，赫拉克勒亚的希翁和利奥尼兹密谋推翻暴君克利阿科斯和萨提洛斯，但他们只杀死了克利阿科斯，萨提洛斯得以存活并替他报了仇。我们前边多次提到的帕西，也仅仅成功杀死了朱利亚诺。因此，任何人都不应该参与密谋推翻多位统治者，因为这对他自己、对他的国家、对其他任何人都没有一点好处。相反，得以幸存的统治者会变本加厉地残暴，就像前文提到的佛罗伦萨、雅典、赫拉克勒亚后来的境况一样。的确，佩洛皮达斯解放他的祖国底比斯的密谋涉及了前文提到的重重困难，最后却得以成功；佩洛皮达斯推翻的君主不是两位而是十位，他不仅是个外人，难以接触到君主，而且他还是一个反叛者。尽管如此，他仍然能够进入底比斯，杀死统治者，解放祖国。但其实，他是因得到了君主参赞卡戎的帮助才得以轻松完成这项壮举的。任何人都不该模仿佩洛皮达斯的做法，因为这本身就是一个不可能的任务，最终能成功是个奇迹。所有提到这件事的作家也都一致认为这件事情是举世无双、空前绝后的事迹。

错误认知导致的失败

阴谋的实施可能被中途产生的错误认知或者不可预见的意外而摧毁。就在布鲁特斯和他的同伙准备刺杀恺撒的那个早晨，恺撒碰巧和共谋者之一的盖厄斯·庞庇利乌斯·雷那进行了一次长谈。其他同伙发现他们聊了那么久，于是就怀疑庞庇利乌斯向恺撒泄密，并且企图不等他进入元老院就将他当场杀死。实际上，他们确实会这样做，但他们的争论后来得到平息，在看到恺撒没有表露出任何异常的迹象后也消除了疑虑。谨慎的人会充分考虑到这种错误认知并给予充分的关注，但是关注越多越容易产生错觉。这是因为当一个人心里有鬼的时候，很容易认为别人都在谈论他，哪怕毫不相关的言论都可以扰乱他，使其认为肯定和他有关，这样就会导致其放弃密谋，或者过早行事，搅黄密谋。知情人越多，这样的情形越容易发生。

由不可预见的意外导致的失败

由于意外不可预见，我们唯一能做的就是举例说明该如何谨慎行事。前文提到过的西恩纳的卢西奥·柏兰提，因潘多佛带走了已经与他结婚的女儿而对他充满愤怒，于是决定选好时机杀掉潘多佛。潘多佛之前每天都去看望一位生病的亲戚，途中要路过卢西奥的房子。卢西奥发现后，安排同伙在他的家里，以备在潘多佛经过时将其杀害。这些同伙携带武器站在门口内侧，一个观察哨在窗口观察，一旦潘多佛经过门口，观察哨给出信号，门口的同伙就立马冲出去。潘多佛出现那天，信号发出后，他碰巧遇到一个老朋友停了下来，同行的另外几人继续往前走，看到发生了什么，听到武器的嘈杂声，发现了这场预谋。结果，潘多佛逃过一劫，卢西奥和他的同伙不得不逃离西恩纳。就这样，这次偶然的会面打乱了谋划中的事情，从而导致卢西奥计划的流产。由于这样的意外是偶发事件，因此也无法提前给出解决方法。我们能做的只能是尽量考虑所有可能发生的情况，并采取相应的举措。

阴谋实施后的危险

我们现在需要讨论阴谋成功实施后可能发生的危险。唯一的危险就是，幸免于难的人可能会为君主的死亡实施报复。例如，君主可能还有在世的兄弟、儿子或其他支持者，他们会继承王位。这些可能寻求报复的人之所以得以幸存，往往是由于你的疏忽或者上文提到的原因。因而，当乔瓦尼·安德烈和他的同伙杀死了米兰公爵后，米兰公爵幸存的一个儿子和两个弟弟及时赶到为他复仇。此情形之下共谋者们情有可原，因为对于这样的事情他们也无能为力；但是由于不谨慎或疏忽而导致留下活口，他们就没有任何借口了。弗利城堡的几个公民密谋杀害了他们的君主吉罗拉莫伯爵，俘虏了他的妻子和年幼的孩子。然而，在他们看来，只有获得城堡他们的性命才能保全，但掌控城堡的人拒绝交出城堡。于是，那位名叫凯瑟琳的伯爵夫人向密谋者承诺，如果他们放她回城堡，她就会安排把城堡交给他们。同时，他们把她的孩子作为人质。达成协议后，阴谋者们放她回到城堡，而她一进入城堡就斥责他们杀害了她的丈夫，并威胁会以各种形式报复。

为了使阴谋者相信她不在意那些孩子，她把自己的性器官展示给阴谋者们，并告诉他们她还可以生更多的孩子。阴谋者们目瞪口呆，意识到他们错了，但为时已晚，最终为不谨慎的错误受到了永久流放的惩罚。

但是，如果阴谋者杀害的是受人民爱戴的君主，那么阴谋实施后的危险将是最无法避免和令人畏惧的。这样的情形下阴谋者们无法补救和挽回，因此他们不可能安全。恺撒大帝就是典型例证，因为罗马人民爱戴他，替他复仇，因此阴谋者们在被驱逐出罗马之后，均在不同时间不同地点相继被杀。

旨在反对国家的阴谋

与旨在反对君主的阴谋相比，旨在反对国家的阴谋给参与者带来的危险会更小，因为后者在筹划中的危险更少，在实施过程中也同样，实施完毕后则根本不存在危险了。策划阴谋的过程中危险不多，因为公民在谋划攫取权力时，可以不向任何人透露自己的想法和计划。如果计划未受干扰，那么任务就能完成；但是如果受到某部法律或者其他因素的限制，那么就必须放弃此次尝试，寻找其他合适时机。这个原则适用于在一定程度上腐败的共和国，因为在一个并不腐败的国家，根本找不到踏入邪途的起步之地，也根本没有公民会有这种想法。对于生活在封邑的公民，他们有各种方法和手段使自己受益，同时不冒任何风险或卷入麻烦；在共和国中也类似，因为相比君主，共和国采取行动会更慢、更让人信服，也因此更不谨慎；还因为共和国对有权势的公民更加尊重，因此这些人更敢于也更倾向于违反国家利益行事。大家都读过撒路斯对于喀提林阴谋的叙述，知道喀提林在阴谋暴露后不仅仍在罗马，而且还加入了元老院，发表着对元老院和执政官的各种无礼申斥言论，由此可见这个城市对公民尊重的程度。如果雷恩图卢斯和其他人自己手中并未持有明明白白证明其阴谋的信件的话，那么在喀提林离开罗马并已经同军队取得联系之时，他们也不会被捕。

迦太基地位显赫的公民汉诺，希望建立一个暴力政权，他安排好要在女儿婚宴上毒死全体元老院成员并自立为王。听到此消息后，元老院仅做了一件事，便是通过了一项法律，限制婚礼和宴会的费用开销。人们对于地位显赫之人的尊重程度可见一斑。

另一方面，旨在反对国家的阴谋在实施过程中，也有可能遇到更多的困难和更大的危险，因为在针对如此多人的阴谋中，你几乎不可能拥有足够的兵力，而且也不是每个人都有任其指挥的军队，像恺撒、阿加托克利斯、克莱奥梅尼等人一样可以靠他们指挥的军队一举征服他们的国家。对于他们来说，此方法简单易行、安全可靠，但是对于没有军队可供指挥的人而言，要想成功实施计划，要么必须采用骗术和诡计，要么必须借助外国军队的力量。雅典人皮西斯特拉妥的故事就是使用骗术和诡计的好例子，他通过战胜麦加拉人而取得了人民的拥护。一天早上，他拖着受伤的身体出现在公众视野，声称是贵族们出于嫉妒袭击了他，并请求武装军队随行保护他本人。得到授权以后，他轻而易举地大权独揽，成为了雅典的独裁君主。在和其他流放者一起回到西恩纳之后，潘多佛·佩特鲁奇受命指挥露天广场的护卫队，这是一份常规性的差事，别人都不愿意接受。但是，这支武装军队却逐渐为他赢得了声望，不久后他就成了一名君主。除此之外，也有不少人采取过各种手段或方法，最终毫无危险地达到了目的。

一些人企图通过自己的军队或者借助外国军队以控制国家，他们能否取得成功，取决于命运对他们是否眷顾。前文提到的喀提林就丧命于自己的阴谋尝试中。上文提到的汉诺，先是使用毒药却失败了，后来拥有了几千武装支持者，但最终全军覆没，自己也因此丧命。底比斯的几个地位显赫的公民召集了一支斯巴达军队来援助他们，并在底比斯建立专制政权。仔细探究这些推翻国家的阴谋，我们会发现，当阴谋还在策划之中的时候，没有人或者只有寥寥几人受到镇压，但是阴谋付诸实施之时，所有人要么都成功了，要么都失败了。在取得成功之后，除了那些在根本上涉及君主统治权的阴谋，其他阴谋都不会引起任何后续的危险。这是因为，假如一个人变成了专制君主，他就会面临专制统治自然带来的各种危险，而为了避开这些危险，只能采取我们在上文讨论过的那些方法来进行补救。

毒药的使用

关于阴谋，我们要说的到此为止。我之所以重点讨论那些使用刀剑而非毒药的阴谋，是因为它们其实属于同一类型。的确，毒药的不确定性更大，因此它也更加危险，但由于不是每个人都有毒药这种东西，所以人们在使用时必须向那些有毒药的人请教，而请教这一举动对你本身就意味着危险。由于种种原因，一杯下毒的饮料可能并不致命。例如，要去杀康茂德的人发现康茂德将他们给的毒药扔掉之后，如果想要他死，则不得不去勒死他。

阻止阴谋所采取的策略

这样看来，最不利于君主的就是阴谋。若一场旨在推翻君主的阴谋已经形成，结果要么是君主被杀，要么是君主蒙受恶名：如果阴谋得逞，君主必死无疑；如果阴谋暴露，君主杀掉了共谋者，人们就会倾向于以为整件事是被君主冠以阴谋之名的工具，以掩盖他对被杀者的贪婪残忍。因此，我必须提醒那些知道有人策划谋反的君主或者共和国，要在采取惩罚性行动之前尽力挖掘精确的信息，并将阴谋者的实力和地位与自己认真对比，如果发现谋反者实力壮大，就要装作毫不知情，直到自己拥有足够兵力一举摧毁它。如若不然，只会招致灾祸。因此，他们应当尽力学会如何掩饰自己，以防共谋者发现自己已经暴露，从而不顾后果地立即采取行动。

罗马人给我们作了很好的例证。在其他地方已经提到过，两个军团的士兵被派去守卫加普亚，以防萨谟奈人的进攻，而军团的指挥者合谋要征服并统治加普亚。当这个消息传到罗马，一个名叫卢提鲁斯的执政官被委任彻查此事。为了不打草惊蛇，他将元老院批准的加普亚军团的住宿营地公之于众。密谋军队信以为真，认为有足够时间实施计划，于是并不急于行动。就这样，直到意识到执政官已将两个军团分离，共谋者们才起了疑心，采取行动并命令实施计划。没有比这更好的例子了，因为在这个事例中，我们可以看到，当人们认为有时间的时候其行动会十分迟缓，而当形势紧迫时其行动又会非常迅速。如果一位君主或共和国政权想让阴谋延迟起事，最好的做法就是巧妙地给共谋者提供在未来某天的时机，这样，当他们等待那天的来临，相信时间充裕之时，君主或共和国就可以趁机策划对阴谋者的惩罚。

没有这样做的人，只会加速自己的失败，雅典公爵和古格里尔莫·帕西就是例证。当公爵成为佛罗伦萨的独裁君主，并听说有人阴谋推翻他的时候，他把其中的一个共谋者抓了起来，但没有进一步调查此事，结果其他共谋者立刻揭竿而起，一举推翻了他的政权。1501年，当古格里尔莫担任瓦尔基亚纳行政官的时候，他发现了在阿雷佐有一个支持维海利的阴谋企图从佛罗伦萨人手中夺走城镇，于是立刻奔赴阿雷佐。他既没有考虑共谋者或者他自己的实力，也没有兵力准备就绪，就在主教即其儿子的建议之下抓获一位共谋者。不料，其他共谋者立刻拿起武器，一举从佛罗伦萨人的手中夺取了城镇，古格里尔莫也不再是行政官，而是变成了阶下囚。

但是，如果阴谋本身就脆弱不堪，上述二例就能也应该立刻受到镇压，以免夜长梦多。人们也不应采取下述两种策略——尽管二者的行事方向几乎完全相反。一种是上述的雅典公爵所用的，他为了证明自己相信佛罗伦萨人深深爱戴他，处死了一个向他告密的人。另一种是锡拉库扎人戴恩所用，为了揭露自己所怀疑之人的意图，允许他信任的卡利普斯假装正在酝酿一场阴谋。这两种策略无一例外导致了灾难：第一种阻挠了告密者，鼓励了阴谋者；第二种使杀死戴恩变得很容易，在这场阴谋中他自己其实就是实际的领导者，从他的经历来看，卡利普斯此时已经能够阴谋推翻戴恩——这一计划非常缜密，最终不仅让戴恩丢掉了政权，也丢掉了性命。

军队、军纪和兵种

军队军纪：当代与昔日之差

托夸图斯与德西乌斯领导下的拉丁人之战是罗马人与外族之间最重要的一战。种种迹象表明，如果拉丁人战败，其就会被罗马人统治，同样，如果罗马人战败，也会沦为拉丁人的臣民。泰特斯·李维认为，这两支军队在军纪、素质、战斗力和人数方面都势均力敌，唯一区别就在于：与拉丁军队将领相比，罗马军队统帅更工于战术。

在这场战争中，还有两件前所未有、闻所未闻的事引起了人们的注意，即为拢军心、正军规，一个执政官选择了自杀，另一个执政官则选择了杀子。在泰特斯·李维看来，这两支军队的共同之处是由于长期交战而形成的相同的语言、相同的军纪、相同的武器装备、相同的作战阵形，甚至相同的作战单位和军官称谓。因此，既然实力相当，一方则必然有某些非凡之处用于鼓舞士气提升战斗力。正如我们在他处提到过的，胜利取决于决心，因为只要战士胸中决心不灭，他们绝不会退缩。正因如此，为了使罗马战士的决心比拉丁人更持久，既出于巧合，也出于执政官的素质，托夸图斯不得不杀子，德西乌斯不得不自杀。

泰特斯·李维在指出双方势均力敌时，详细描述了罗马人如何组织和调遣军队作战。所以，此处不再赘述，但有几个值得关注的事我却无法避而不谈，当今所有统帅对它们的忽视，导致了组织调遣军队作战中严重缺乏纪律性。从李维那里，我们知道罗马军队分为三个主要作战单位，托斯卡纳语称为“三列阵法”。第一列为枪兵，第二列为主力兵，第三列为后备兵；每一列都有自己的骑兵。在战场上列阵时，枪兵置于最前沿，其后面紧接的是第二列主力兵，在第三列相同的空间上，部署后备兵。每个作战单位的骑兵都被部署在三个方阵的左右两翼。骑兵部分，因其队形和位置，被称为“翼”，因为他们看起来像鸟的一双翅膀。罗马人的第一列由枪兵组成密集队形，以向前冲杀并抵御敌军的攻击。第二列的主力兵，最初不参加战斗，而是当第一列被敌人击败或压制时，对其进行支援；他们不是排成密集队形，而是排成疏松的阵形，这样如果第一列被敌人击败而被迫后退，第二列能够和第一列整合且不破坏阵形。第三列的后备兵阵形比第二列更疏松，旨在与败退下来的前两列（即枪兵和主力兵）整合在一起。阵形布置完毕后，他们就投入战斗。如果第一列被迫后退或被打败，他们能直接退入主力兵阵列的间隙中，重新组成一个完整的阵形，继续战斗。如果这两个阵列都被击败或被迫后撤，他们可以退到后备兵更疏松的阵线中，三个阵列又组成一个阵形重新作战。如果这样也被击溃了，就真的失败了，因为没有机会重整阵形。因此，当后备兵阵列参战时，说明军队已身处险境，于是谚语有曰“一切取决于后备兵”，抑或如托斯卡纳习语所曰“我们已经孤注一掷了”。

正如当今将领们已抛弃了所有其他传统，且对古代军队纪律漠不关心一样，他们也已摒弃军事纪律举足轻重的意义。当军队排列成能在战斗中三次组成的阵形时，要击败它，进攻三次已属走运，进攻者的勇气必须要足够打击它三次。只能承受一次攻击的军队，通常指基督徒军队，更容易战败，因为无组织性或缺乏勇气的军队均会与胜利无缘。我们的军队无法三次组成阵形，是因为其丢失了将一个阵列吸纳到另一个阵列中的传统。究其原因，当代战斗阵形中存在两个问题：其一，将阵列一字并排展开，使阵形很宽，但很薄弱，面对进攻时，会因缺乏纵深而不堪一击。其二，为了加强阵线，他们会按罗马方式组织阵形，然而却没有组织好第二阵列如何吸纳第一阵列，所以当第一阵列败退下来时，所有阵列都会乱作一团，不战自败。因为前面的阵列一旦溃退，就会与第二阵列发生冲突，如果第二阵列想要前进，就会受第一阵列的阻碍。因此，当第一阵列冲垮第二阵列，第二阵列又冲垮第三阵列之时，混乱丛生，整个军队往往会遭受灭顶之灾。

率领法国军队的富瓦亲王战死的那场拉文那战斗，如今看来，也是一场鏖战。西班牙和法国均按照上述方式组织军队阵形，并排列队，因此双方都只有宽度要远大于纵深的单一阵线。在像拉文那这样宽阔的平原交战时，他们总是采用这样的战术。因为他们认为如果军队排成两列，撤退时容易产生混乱，为了避免混乱发生，故将阵线排得很长，如上所述。但是一旦可作战空间狭小不堪，他们就只能忍受上述糟糕的安排，毫无办法。无论是实战，还是军事演习，他们均以此糟糕阵形御敌。

同样，正如法国国王查尔斯穿越意大利之后，因为城市反叛而爆发佛罗伦萨人和比萨人之战，最终前者被后者击败的地方一样，在比萨领地内的圣莱戈洛，灾难完全是由于盟友骑兵团导致的，他们在阵前被敌人打败后，溃退至佛罗伦萨步兵阵列，引发混乱，结果所有战士均闻风而逃。曾经的佛罗伦萨步兵队长——梅瑟·西里亚科·达尔·博尔格，经常在我面前说，除了盟友骑兵外，他从未被打败过。瑞士人被誉为现代战争的大师，他们与法国并肩作战时，首先考虑的就是将其军队部署于两翼，这样即使盟友骑兵被迫撤退，也不会与其冲撞在一起。虽然此战术容易理解且十分可行，但当代将领们仍无人以此改进当代军队阵形。虽然同样有三重军队编制，即前卫、主力和后卫，但其唯一用处仅在于方便安排士兵扎营。如上所述，此法阵列，众人皆在劫难逃。

鉴于许多人为了掩饰其无知，声称火炮的毁灭力已使得古代战例战术不再适用于当代，下面的章节我将会对火炮是否使得往昔岁月英勇不再这个问题再作探讨。

炮兵在军队中应处于何种地位，大众持有的观点是否合情合理

除以上所述外，我在想，当代被法国人称为“日子”而意大利人称为“武器的功绩”的正面战斗，罗马人在不同时期共进行了多少次，于是我立刻想起大众持有的观点：如果那个时代里有了火炮，罗马人就不可能征服外族行省，也不可能轻易地变外族为其附庸国，也绝不可能进行如此大胆的掠夺占领。他们认为，毁灭性武器的应用已经扼杀了人们像古时那样运用展现其优势的能力。第三个观点还认为，现今比过去更难实现议和，保持古代惯例是不可能的。事实上，不久以后，战争将会变成火炮之间的单纯较量。

探究此观点是否可靠，或者查究火炮究竟会增强还是削弱军队的实力，及其究竟会剥夺还是赋予优秀将军展现“才能”的机会，我认为均值得关注。所以从第一个观点入手，即如果那个时代有火炮，古罗马人将无法取得当时的战绩。

为此，我要指出，战争既有进攻也有防守。那么，我们不禁要问火炮对哪一方更有用或更危险。虽然火炮对双方都有一定作用，但显然其对防守者的杀伤力要远大于进攻者。因为防守者往往身处有城墙的城镇或有栅栏的营地中。如果是有城墙保护的城镇，像大多数城堡一样，空间可能非常狭小，但也或者比较大。若是空间狭小，防守者就必败无疑，因为城墙根本无法抵挡火炮的威力，最厚的城墙也只能多撑几天而已。由于城中的防守者没有足够空间退守或挖掘壕沟或修筑壁垒，因此其失败无法避免。即使有火炮的帮助，他们也无法抵抗敌人从城墙上打开缺口涌入城中，因为有一条公认的真理：火炮无法抵挡猛烈的大规模进攻。所以，在对抗阿尔卑斯山外的异族凶猛进攻时，火炮根本不起作用，但是对抵挡意大利人的进攻却非常有效，因为后者不会大规模进攻，只是以分队形式袭击，这种袭击方式只能称作骚扰战。以这种脆弱阵形向有火炮防守的城墙突破口进军，无疑是自寻死路，对付这样的进攻，火炮非常有用。但是当进攻者以密集持续的阵形涌向突破口，除非有壕沟或壁垒阻挡，否则他们就会到处渗透。火炮即使歼灭一些敌军，也依然无法抵挡更多人冲杀进来夺取胜利。

意大利许多城镇均被阿尔卑斯山附近的外族攻陷就是明证，尤以布雷西亚为典型。其反抗法国统治时，法国人仍以其国王的名义据守卫城。为了防止来自卫城的法国人袭击，威尼斯人在通往卫城的街道上构造了防御工事，并将大炮置于卫城前方、两侧及其他妥当之处。但是，富瓦亲王却对此嗤之以鼻。与之相反，他带领骑兵中队下马作战，冲破火炮的封锁，占领了城市。无人听说过火炮让他损失惨重。因此，如上所述，当小城市防守者自知其城墙低矮且没有可以躲避的壁垒和壕沟，而不得不依赖火炮时，他们会很快溃败。

若是防守一座有回旋空间的大城市，包围者的火炮仍然比防守者的更有用。首先，要使火炮对包围者造成伤害，必须将其抬至高于地面的位置，因为在水平面上，敌人挖掘的壕沟和构筑的壁垒能够为其提供防御，致使你根本无法对其造成破坏。即使将火炮抬升并拖到城墙的凹处，或者用别的方法提升到高处，你仍然会遇到两个问题。第一，使用相同尺寸和威力的火炮时，你不可能像包围者那么有效率，因为你不可能在狭小空间内操作大型武器。第二，即使成功将其安置，你也无法建筑安全可靠的壁垒来掩护火炮，它会被外面的攻击轻易摧毁，而在地面上，任何人都能有想要的空间和便利。因此，包围者有威力足够大的火炮时，防守者不可能在高处设置火炮，如果被赶至低处，如上所述，火炮则很难发挥作用。所以，防守城市不得不像古代军队那样依靠肉搏战，用小口径的火炮作为支援。虽然小型火炮有一定作用，但是其劣势抵消了其优势。由于重炮，城墙被摧毁，壕沟被填平，当守军进行肉搏战时，其处境会因此更为不利。所以，如上所述，这些战争机器对包围者比对防守者更有用。

至于第三个观点，如果为了避免正面作战而用栅栏保护军营，除非情况对你有利并能发挥你方优势，否则我认为在这种情况下，同样是为了避免交战，你不会比古时情况更好，况且有火炮的时代，你可能会更处于劣势。因为如果敌人攻击你，并且地理优势不明显，只要其处于比你更高的地方，这种情况就会发生，或者如果在他们到来之前，你还没有挖好壕沟做好防护，那么敌人会在你采取补救措施之前，将你赶出来，你就不得不放弃防御工事与敌人作战。西班牙人和拉文那交战时就是如此。他们在龙果河岸建立防御阵地，但是其土木工事不够高，而法国人占有略微地理优势。最终其防御工事被火炮摧毁，被迫参战。但是假设你选择的营地高于敌人领地，且土木工事良好坚固，那么鉴于你的地形优势和其他准备充足，敌人就不敢发动进攻。通常情况下，敌人据守易守难攻之地时，必须依靠古代战术，即四处搜索，占领和包围你的友邦城市，切断你的供给，以迫使你离开营地进行决战，如上所述，火炮发挥不了作用。因此，从罗马人发动战争的原因中，可以看到其几乎所有的战争都是进攻模式，而非防守模式，由此可见，上述内容仍然适用，即如果那个时代有火炮，它将成为罗马人的优势，并加速他们的胜利。

对于第二个观点，其认为火炮的使用使得人们不能再像古代那样英勇，我不否认。当军队以小分队进行战斗时，如果必须攀爬城墙或者不以整体队形而是以个人形式，一个接一个发起攻击，则现在的危险要比过去更大。军队统帅会比以前面临更多危险，这是事实，因为无论在哪里，他们都会受到火炮的威胁。即使在最后一支骑兵中队或非常勇敢的士兵们的保护下也无济于事。我们发现，这两种危险情况仍然极少造成重大损失。毕竟人不可能攀登上防御严密的城墙，也不可能被小股部队攻击。如果想要占领一座城市，就必须像古时那样包围它。甚至在其被攻陷时，现在的危险也没有比过去更大，因为那个时代城里的守军不缺少发射弹丸的武器，即使不令人恐惧，仍然能有效杀伤敌人。至于军队统帅阵亡的例子，在意大利最近二十四年战争里阵亡的人数要比古代十年战争中阵亡的人数更少。除了几年之前在菲拉拉战死的卢多维科·黛拉·米兰多拉伯爵，和在切里尼奥拉战死的内穆尔公爵，没有其他人死于火炮的轰炸。富瓦亲王死于刀剑下，而不是被炮弹所杀。因此，如果作为个人无法展现英勇，原因一定不在火炮，而在于拙劣的战术和无能的（现代）军队，因为他们作为一个整体都缺乏勇气，个体就更不可能勇敢了。

第三个观点说，肉搏战不可能出现，战争将最终成为火炮之间的较量。这一观点完全错误，尤其对于希望军队在战斗中表现出古代素质的人们来说，更被视为绝对谬论。想要组建善战之师的人理应通过模拟战或实战，使士兵适应与敌人近距离战斗，刀锋相见。他们应该更多依靠步兵，而非骑兵，理由将在下文中详述。如果他们确实依靠步兵，并按照上述方式训练，那么火炮将变得一无是处。相对于躲避古代的战象或装有大镰刀的战车，或者其他罗马步兵遭遇的不熟悉的武器而言，当今步兵在交战中躲避炮弹更加容易。他们总能找出对付那些武器的对策，而找到对付火炮的方法则更容易，因为火炮造成伤亡的时间要比大象和镰刀战车更短。后者在战斗中会让你陷入混乱，而前者只是战斗开始前的小麻烦。步兵可以通过借助战场掩体或者在炮弹来袭时卧倒的方式轻松躲避这种小麻烦。但是，经验表明，这是没有必要的，尤其是遇到重炮需要防御时，因为调整重炮的射程很费劲。要么炮口太高，打不到你，要么太低，落在你的前面。

同样，当军队之间展开近战时，事实也清楚地表明，无论是重炮还是小炮都伤害不到你。如果敌人将火炮设在阵前，你可以缴获它；如果将它放在后面，它会在打到你之前打到他们自己人。如果在侧翼，火炮无法对你造成伤害，你反而可以冲过去夺取它，所以毋庸置疑，最终结果都是一样的。瑞士人的例子即是明证：1513年在诺瓦拉，瑞士人在没有火炮和骑兵的情况下，与法国军队交战，虽然法军在防御阵地上有火炮支援，但是瑞士人还是轻而易举地击败了他们。

除了上述原因外，还因为想要火炮发挥作用，就必须要将其置于城墙、壕沟或土木工事的保护下；缺少任何一种形式的保护，它都会被敌人夺取或不起作用，当人们必须在战场正面激战时，以上情况就会发生。除非像古代人使用抛射机那样，否则火炮无法在侧翼使用。这种发射装置被安置在主力部队外围，是为了使其在阵列之外发挥作用，当操作手被敌人骑兵或其他部队袭击时，他可以躲到正规军中。那些对火炮期望甚高的人并没有理解它的用处，因此仅仅寄希望于容易让其失望的武器上。土耳其人使用火炮战胜了古波斯王苏菲和苏丹，仅仅是由于火炮奇怪的轰鸣声惊吓骑兵的马匹而引发的混乱。

最后，我的结论是，只有在如古人所表现的勇气的支持下，火炮才能发挥作用，否则，它一样无法抵御无畏的军队。

罗马权威和古代军事实例表明步兵比骑兵更应该受到重视

许多原因和事例清楚地表明，在所有军事行动中，罗马人对步兵的重视程度要大于骑兵，并以此制订作战计划。例如，罗马人与拉丁人在里吉洛斯湖附近交战，为了支援开始动摇的罗马军队，一些骑兵被命令下马，徒步作战。这个方法的采用，使战斗得以延续，罗马人最终取得胜利。此例中，相对骑兵而言，罗马人明显对徒步作战的士兵更有信心。他们在其他诸多战斗中也使用了此战术，并发现在危急关头这是最好的补救措施。

即使是汉尼拔也不能反驳这一点，在坎尼战役中，他注意到罗马执政官让骑兵下马参加战斗，于是开玩笑说“Quam mallem vinctos mihi traderent equites”，意思是：“如果他们能把骑兵交由我指挥，我将不胜荣幸。”即使这话出自一位伟人，我们也还是更应该相信罗马共和国及其众多杰出将领的观点，而非汉尼拔一家之言。除了对权威的认同之外，我还可以列举其他合理的原因：步兵可以到达骑兵无法到达的地方；步兵可以被训练保持阵列，即便阵列被攻破，步兵也知道如何重新列阵，然而骑兵就很难保持阵列，当其阵列被打乱时，不可能重新组织。除此之外，马和人一样，有时胆小，有时勇敢，于是经常会发生这样的事情，即胆怯之人骑着英勇之马，以及英勇之人骑着胆怯之马，无论是哪一种组合，都会扰乱军队的秩序。

组织严密的步兵能轻松击败骑兵，但是骑兵却很难击溃步兵。这个观点不仅仅在古代和现代的诸多事例中得以证实，而且也得到了公民行为规范制定者的认同：在没有组建步兵之前，骑兵是战争中的主力军，后来有了步兵，人们随即确信其比骑兵更有用。但这并不是说骑兵对军队不重要，骑兵的作用是侦察敌情，袭击和掠夺乡村，追逐逃亡的敌人，以及与敌军的骑兵对抗。但是，步兵构成了军队的基础，军队的中坚力量应该是步兵，所以应该得到更多的重视。

使意大利陷于外国统治者奴役的意大利君主犯下的诸多罪行中危害最大的就是，不重视军队的规模，过分专注于骑兵。这种荒唐做法源自军官们的刚愎自用和统治者的无知。失去官方地位的意大利民兵在过去的二十五年里，逐渐沦为雇佣兵。这些民兵意识到，如果他们拥有统治者所没有的武装力量，他们就能获得应有的地位。由于他们没有财力维持一支大规模的步兵团，没有可利用的人力资源，而小规模军队不足以使他们声名鹊起，于是他们将目光转向骑兵。两三百人的雇佣骑兵队就能确保佣兵队长的名誉，而且这笔数目不大的金钱容易从国务大臣那里得到。因此，他们得遂所愿并取得了名誉，于是更加轻视步兵的作用，更多关注骑兵。这种做法的滥用导致即便在规模最大的军队中步兵也只占少数。此做法以及其他与之有关的诸多错误行为，让意大利的民兵组织变得软弱无能，从而使意大利沦为更容易被外族人欺凌的对象。

为了更明确地证实“应重视骑兵轻视步兵”这一观点的错误，另以罗马为例。罗马人在索拉城外扎营之时，从城中杀出一支骑兵袭击他们营地。罗马人组织骑兵进行反击。两军交锋时，意外出现了，第一回合交手中双方指挥官均阵亡。即便如此，战斗仍然继续，罗马士兵为了更容易战胜对手，从马上下来，使敌人骑兵也被迫下马徒步作战，凭这个战术罗马人取胜了。这个例子极好地说明了步兵比骑兵更有功效。在别的行动中，执政官让罗马骑兵下马的目的是协助处于被动、需要支援的步兵。但是在此处，他们下马不是为了帮助自己的步兵，也不是为了与敌人步兵交战，而是骑兵对骑兵的对决，因为罗马人意识到他们在马上无法战胜敌人，他们徒步战斗胜算会更大。所以，据此我推断，只有付出艰苦的努力，一支组织严密的步兵团才有可能被另外一支步兵团击败。

虽然帕提亚骑兵数目庞大，但罗马的克拉苏和马克·安东尼，依靠极少的骑兵和众多的步兵占领了帕提亚的领土很长时间。尽管克拉苏和他的军队被消灭了，但是马克·安东尼英勇作战，最终脱离险境。虽然罗马人遭受了不幸，但我们仍看出步兵比骑兵的价值更大，平原广阔，无险可依，河流稀少，远离大海，交通不便，但是帕提亚人自己也承认，马克·安东尼凭借他杰出的才智拯救了自己。虽然帕提亚拥有庞大的骑兵，却依旧不敢与他的军队决战。克拉苏被留在了战场上，仔细研究他当时的行为记录，人们发现他死于敌人的计谋而非武力。尽管克拉苏陷入被动，帕提亚人也没有趁机冒险进攻他。相反，他们总是在附近游击，拦截他的护卫，许下空头承诺，直到将他逼入绝境。

如果近期没有太多有说服力的事例证明步兵的“功效”要比骑兵更大的话，那么我将不得不花大力气以作证实，但事实证明这种担心完全多余。之前提到过九千瑞士士兵在诺瓦拉进攻一万骑兵和一万步兵，并打败了他们。因为一方面骑兵无法靠近他们，另一方面他们还不屑那些步兵，因为其大部分步兵是只会吹牛的加斯科涅人，组织混乱。后来有两万六千瑞士军队前往米兰，欲与法国国王弗朗西斯交战，后者有两万骑兵、四万步兵和一万门大炮。即使没有像诺瓦拉那样取得胜利，他们依然英勇战斗了两天，虽然被打败了，但仍然有半数的军队成功逃脱。马尔库斯·雷古鲁斯·阿蒂利乌斯不仅有勇气以步兵与敌人骑兵作战，他还与象兵作战。即使他没有获胜，也不是因为他的步兵缺乏勇气而使他不相信他们能战胜困难。再次强调，要想战胜纪律严明的步兵，必须要借助纪律更加严明的步兵，否则只有痛苦的绝望。

米兰公爵菲利普·维斯康蒂在位期间，伦巴第遭到一万六千瑞士人的进攻。于是公爵派遣卡尔米纽奥拉率领他的军队迎敌，共有一千骑兵和少数步兵。卡尔米纽奥拉不熟悉敌人的作战方式，用骑兵进攻敌军，以为能迅速击溃他们。但是瑞士人稳住了阵脚，他却损失惨重，于是撤退了。然而，作为勇士，他知道情况改变时如何抓住有利战机，所以当增援军队到达，实力增强时，他果断出击，命令骑兵下马，并将其置于步兵前面，于是这些骑兵无处可逃。由于卡尔米纽奥拉的骑兵下马作战，而且有厚重的盔甲保护，他们轻而易举地突破了瑞士人的阵列，而没有损伤，随着阵线的突破，最终战胜了瑞士人。结果仁慈的卡尔米纽奥拉选择宽恕他们，瑞士人得以保全性命。

我相信很多人都已意识到这两个兵种之间的特点差异，但是我们当今有些世人仍不接受这一点，无论是古代抑或现代的事例，或者正在发生的公认的错误，都不足以使现代统治者改变观点并意识到：一位君主或一个国家要想保持其军队的声誉，就必须恢复步兵的地位和信誉，信任他们，壮大他们，这样他们才能为统治者带来安全保障和显赫声望。但是，如果统治者就像忽视了上述的其他提醒一样忽视了这点，则不良后果将迅速降临，不仅不会为国家带来荣誉，反而会造成损害。

与战争相关的错误

建造城堡往往弊大于利

对于当代精明之士来说，罗马人似乎做了一件蠢事，即虽然希望取得拉丁姆和普里乌努姆民众的忠心支持，但也没有建造城堡去控制民众，迫使他们保持忠诚，尤其是在佛罗伦萨，这已是公认事实。于是，这些精明之士断言，比萨和其他城市均应该依靠城堡守卫。如果罗马人能力具备，他们也会毫无疑问地建造城堡，但是因其品德、判断力和权力与常人不同，所以他们没有这么做。只要罗马依然享受着自由，依然忠于其自身的制度和有效的体制，就决不会依靠城堡守卫罗马的城市与行省（原有的城堡除外）。古罗马人和当今统治者在此件事上看法不同，鉴于此，我认为，建造城堡是否有益及其对于建造者来说是利是弊，都值得思考。

须知城堡作为防御工事是用于抵御外敌或镇压臣民的。于前者，它不必要，于后者，其则有害。首先，我们要解释为什么于后者而言是有害的。我坚信，君王或共和国惧怕他的臣民，害怕他们会聚众叛乱。此恐惧根源于臣民对统治者的切肤之恨；此仇恨源自统治者的荒诞行为，而荒诞行为又来自于他们自以为能通过武力或愚蠢的统治方式控制民众的幻想。有城可据，是统治者们迷信武力的原因之一，因此，统治不当升级为仇恨也往往由坐拥城堡的君主或共和国所致。在此事例中，城堡的作用弊远大于利。正如前文所说，一开始，它会使你在对待臣民时更加鲁莽粗暴。然后，它无法满足你内心希望得到的安全感。在控制你的臣民时，除了下面两种情况之外，武力与暴力均无济于事：一是你拥有一支像罗马人一样能投入战斗的善战之师；二是你的臣民精疲力竭、一盘散沙、各自为战，无法联合起来反抗你。如果你使他们穷困潦倒，“虽然被盘剥殚尽，他们仍然能武装起来”，就算你解除了他们的武装，“他们的怒火将成为最锋利的武器”，如果你处决了他们的领袖，将暴动扼杀在萌芽中，其他领袖也会像九头蛇一样又重新出现。如果你建立了城堡，它们在和平时期有用，能为你虐待臣民的暴行壮胆，但是在战争时期，却会变得一无是处，因为它们将受到来自敌人和臣民的攻击，在这双重打击之下，没有城堡能幸免于难。而且，火炮的使用让城堡风光不再，根本无法对抗火炮的威力来守卫狭小的城堡，如上所述，没有人能够舒服地躲在高墙之后逃过一劫。

在这个问题上我意欲浓墨重彩。我的君主，你想用城堡牢牢掌控城中居民吗？作为一国之主或共和国，你想固守住你在战争中夺取的城市吗？我想告诉你，如果你成为君主，控制百姓最无用的办法就是修建城堡，理由我早已给出：它简单易行，无所顾忌，是严酷之法，只会使百姓希望你早日垮台，正因如此，他们的愤怒会让你失去城堡的庇护。因此，贤明的君主若希望永保圣明，同时不给子孙自甘堕落的理由，那么他永远也不会建造城堡，而是希望继任者能更多地倚重臣民的衷心拥护，而非高墙壁垒。

弗朗西斯科·斯福尔扎伯爵，虽然被誉英明之士，但却在成为米兰公爵之后建造了城堡，我坚信，他的做法极不明智，结果也证明这座城堡非但没有为其后人提供安全保护，反而招致祸害。他们自以为在城堡中就可以安全无虞，可以镇压市民臣民，肆无忌惮地对他们使用暴力；结果被人们极度憎恶，如此一来敌人可轻而易举地攻取他们的国家。城堡在战争时期，既不能提供保护，也不能为其所用，在和平时期又对他们产生损害；如果没有城堡，残酷对待公民亦非明智之举，他们本该早点意识到危险，本可不受其害。在此例中，与其拥有城堡和离心离德的臣民，不如没有城堡却能够和忠诚的臣民共同英勇抵抗法国的进攻。

无论如何，城堡都不会有助于你。守军的背叛，敌人猛烈的进攻，或饥饿围困都会让城堡失陷。在仅存一座城堡的情况下，如果你想利用它收复失地，则必须要有一支能反攻入侵者的军队。有了这样一支军队，即使没有城堡，你也能夺回领土。尤其当你没有因城堡而心生傲慢，没有欺凌友善的臣民，这将更容易做到。经验表明，当遇到灾祸时，米兰城堡无论对斯福尔扎家族，还是对法国人都毫无用处。它带来的灾难与毁灭，反而让其甚至无暇顾及这是否是维护其地位的最有效方法。

乌尔比诺公爵吉多贝多，即弗雷德里克之子，曾贵为军队统帅，却被恺撒·博尔吉亚（即教皇亚历山大六世之子）驱逐流放。后来，因偶然的原因，他又重返故土，将当地所有的城堡都夷为平地，因为在他看来城堡是祸害。他的臣民爱戴他，所以他不需要城堡；在敌人面前，他意识到自己无法保卫城堡，除非专门调派一支军队在战场上保护它们。所以他决心摆脱它们的束缚。

教皇尤利乌斯将本蒂沃利奥从博洛尼亚驱逐出境后，建造了一座城堡，随后他的总督残酷压迫居民，从而导致群众暴动，很快就失去了城堡。城堡非但没帮助他，反而害了他。如果当初不那么做，城堡本可以有益于他。

维特里之父尼科洛·达·卡斯特罗，当他从流亡地重新踏上国土时，立刻拆除了教皇西克斯特四世建造的两座城堡，因为他坚信，不是城堡而是人民对他的衷心爱戴为他守护了自己的国家。

但是，在所有事件中，最近也最值得注意的是不久前发生在热那亚的事件，它能从各个方面说明建造城堡的徒劳无用，以及拆除它们的种种好处。众所周知，1507年热那亚反抗法国国王路易十二，法国国王亲率所有军队重新征服了它，随后建立了当时所知的最坚固的城堡，由于地处海角山顶，因此称“热那亚之角”。因其地理位置险要及其他因素，该城堡易守难攻，可以控制港口和热那亚城的大片地区。1512年，情况有变，法国人被赶出意大利之后，尽管依然控制着城堡，但热那亚人还是起义了。奥塔维诺·弗雷哥索取得政权，使出浑身解数围困城堡达十六个月之久，最终城堡中的人在饥饿面前屈服。人们都希望而且许多人建议应将城堡作为紧急避难所保留下来，但是弗雷哥索是聪明之人，他拆除了城堡，因为他认识到将权力赋予统治者的不是城堡的威严，而是人民的意愿。所以，他没有依赖城堡，而是选择用美德和贤明来巩固地位，他做到了。过去想夺取热那亚政权，一千步兵足矣，但如今纵使它的敌人有上万之众，热那亚也岿然不动。从此，人们知道拆掉城堡不会对奥塔维诺产生威胁，建立城堡也不会有助于君主。一旦他能率领军队进入意大利，即便没有城堡，他也能收复热那亚；但假若他无法率军进入意大利，即使有城堡他也无法收复热那亚。由此可见，法国国王花费大笔金银修建城堡，却落得城破人亡、颜面尽失，反之，奥塔维诺征服城堡为他带来了无上荣耀，拆毁城堡又使他获益匪浅。

现在来谈一下共和国，他们在夺取的城镇中而非自己的国家里建立城堡。如果已列举的关于法国和热那亚的事例还不能说明问题，那么引用佛罗伦萨和比萨的事例应该足矣。佛罗伦萨人修建城堡以控制比萨城，却不知道比萨人对其统治充满了愤怒，渴望得到自由，将反抗作为重获自由的必经之途。佛罗伦萨人要想得到比萨，就要采用罗马人的方式，要么化敌为友，要么将其毁灭。查尔斯国王的到来，使得城堡的作用日益明显，比萨人向他投降了，既是因为对现有管理者的不信任，也是因为害怕招来更坏的统治者。但是如果一开始没有城堡，佛罗伦萨人不用城堡也能控制比萨，那么查尔斯国王也就无法因此从其手中夺取比萨，因为迄今他们所采用的方法或许能守住比萨，但利用城堡无疑是最具灾难性的方法。

由此可见，城堡不利于保卫自己的国家，也无法守住夺取的城镇。罗马人这一事例足以证明这一点。为了固守所得城镇，他们非但没有修建城墙，反而拆掉它们。若有人引用古代塔伦特姆和现代布雷西亚的例子驳斥我，我现对此作出回应。这两个地方在当地民众起义之后，都是因为城堡的协助得以收复。为了收复塔伦特姆，费边·马克西姆斯在其执政初期，就派遣了所有的军队，即使没有城堡，也足够收复之用。虽然费边利用了城堡，但即便没有城堡，他也能用其他方法取得同样的效果。也就是说，收复城市，只需要一支军队和一个像费边·马克西姆斯一样的指挥者足矣。从加普亚的例子来看，罗马人收复它是迟早的事，那里没有城堡，罗马人依靠的是军队的英勇。

现在谈谈布雷西亚。那场暴动中发生的事情绝对是极其罕见的。一个城市发动暴动，城堡仍在你的控制中，而且附近驻有你一支大军，这就是法国人当时的处境。国王的指挥官富瓦亲王，在博洛尼亚有一支军队，当他听到布雷西亚失守时，没有片刻犹豫，立即出兵平叛，三天内就抵达了布雷西亚，并凭借城堡的抵抗收复了失地。在这里，布雷西亚的城堡发挥了作用，但它依然需要富瓦亲王和行军三天后的法国军队来解救。因此布雷西亚的例子并不足以反驳与之相反的例子。在最近发生的战争中，许多城堡被反复争夺，拥有着和那些被反复争夺的不设防的国家相同的命运，不只是在伦巴第，也在罗马涅，在那不勒斯，在意大利的每个角落都是如此。

对于拥有强大军队的人民或国家来说，没有必要修建城堡抵御外敌；对于没有这样军队的国家来说，也没有此必要。无城可守的善战之师足以保卫国家，而有城可据的孱弱之师则无以御敌。这里有享誉青史的统治者的经验为证，以罗马人与斯巴达人为例。罗马人没有建造城堡，斯巴达人不仅没有这么做，甚至不允许修建城墙，他们选择依靠个人品德来抵御外敌，因此无须其他。当斯巴达人被雅典人问到雅典的城墙是否美观时，他们回答道：“非常好，专为女人们而建。”

对于拥有强大军队的统治者而言，在领土的海岸和边界上设立城堡，以阻挡敌人进攻使其有备而战，有时有用，但并非必要。但是，如果没有强大的军队，那么在其境内或边境上修建城堡，要么有害，要么无用。有害是因为他会很轻易地失去这些城堡，而且失守后会被敌人所用；如果城堡足够坚固，没有被敌人占领，那么也会被敌军丢在身后，毫无用武之地。因为强大的军队不会遭遇激烈抵抗，行进军不会理会城市和城堡，只会把它们甩在身后。古代史中弗朗西斯科·玛丽亚多次进攻乌尔比诺，但途中敌人的城市均秋毫无犯。

能召集强大军队的统治者，没有城堡也能成就大业，而没有强大军队的统治者最好不要修建城堡。最好的办法是，加固其所居住的城市，保证食物供给充足，妥善安置居民，这样才能抵挡敌人的进攻，直到达成协议或争取到外援解救。所有其他计谋在和平时期只会耗费财力，而在战时却毫无用处。如上所述，罗马人在其他管理制度方面同样明智而谨慎，正如他们决定用更善良、更明智的方法来获得拉丁人和普里奈特人的忠心那样。

利用内讧借机征服城市的策略不可取

罗马共和国时期，平民和贵族之间冲突不断，因此维恩特人和伊特鲁里亚人认为，只要他们联手利用这些矛盾就可以摧毁罗马政权。于是，他们组织军队，入侵罗马领土，元老院派遣盖厄斯·曼利厄斯和马库斯·费边去抵抗入侵。当罗马军队靠近维恩特人的军队时，后者不停地辱骂罗马人。他们的鲁莽与傲慢反倒让内讧的罗马人同仇敌忾，一致对外，战斗一开始，他们就被罗马人打得落花流水，大败而归。由此可见，依赖敌方内部的不和来制定策略多么愚蠢啊！历史在不断地重演，他们自以为唾手可得，却功败垂成。维恩特人自以为在罗马人不团结时，可以趁虚而入，结果入侵反而引火烧身，使罗马人重新团结起来。罗马共和国内部不和通常是因其正处太平盛世，而团结一致是因其恐惧和战争。如果维恩特人稍有头脑，发现罗马人内部不和时，就应该有意避免与之开战，而采用和平时期所用的计谋来智取。

首先，要取得内讧城市的信任。只要还没有开始互相攻击，他们就可继续在各派之间充当仲裁人的角色。已经武力冲突时，也不要急于支持较弱的一方，而应让其继续自相残杀，消耗彼此的实力。有效的策略不会给任何人留有余地去怀疑你是在谋划征服他们，成为他们的统治者。计谋进展顺利，你就能达到目的，取得你想要的结果。我曾在另一个论题中提及，佛罗伦萨共和国就是靠这种计谋征服了皮斯托亚城。皮斯托亚城正处在分裂中时，佛罗伦萨人时而支持这一方，时而又支持另一方，两面都不得罪，诱使他们上当，直到皮斯托亚城人厌倦其动乱的生活方式，最终自愿投入佛罗伦萨的怀抱。

西恩纳城从未因佛罗伦萨人的帮助而改变其政体，除非那种帮助微弱而少有，因为频繁而有力的帮助反而会使整个城市为保卫当权政府而团结起来。还有一个有力的实例，即米兰公爵菲利普·维斯康蒂，曾利用佛罗伦萨人的内讧对他们发动过几次战争，但结果都以失败告终，因此他为这些无果的进攻而悲叹，说佛罗伦萨人的愚蠢让他花费了两百万金币，却一无所获。

如上所述，维恩特人和托斯卡纳人在这点上均犯了大错，因此刀兵相见之时，反而被罗马人击败。如果其他人也打算借助此法妄想征服敌人，那么也会犯同样的错误。

蔑视和侮辱对施行的人非但无益，反而会招致仇恨

避免使用威胁和侮辱性言语是人们审慎的标志，因为这两个方法都不能夺敌之勇，反而会使其保持警惕，其次会加深对你的仇恨，使其更加处心积虑地想消灭你。上个章节中讨论的维恩特人一例就是证明。除了战争所带来的伤亡之外，他们还用言语侮辱罗马人，每个理智的统帅都应该禁止他的士兵这样做。因为这种言语只会激怒敌人，他们会为此复仇，或者如上所述，这只会影响他的进攻：事实上它们会变成对抗你的武器。

亚洲有一个很有名的事例即是证明。波斯统帅科巴第斯对阿米达城长时间包围，逐渐心生厌倦，于是决定撤军。正当他拔营撤退时，城里的人为其胜利忘乎所以，登上城墙，极尽各种羞辱之能事，嘲笑和辱骂波斯人的胆小和怯懦。这一行为终于惹怒了科巴第斯，他深感愤怒，于是改变主意，又重新包围此城，并在几天后将其攻陷。

同样的事情也发生在维恩特人身上，如上所述，他们不仅对罗马人开战，而且还轻视敌人，走近罗马军营防御栅栏，不停地辱骂他们。这比战争本身更让罗马军队恼怒，本来一开始他们不情愿打仗，但是现在反而逼迫执政官要求参战，结果正如前文中提到的，维恩特人为其行为得到了应有的惩罚。优秀的军队统帅和明智的共和国统治者应该采取一切必要措施来阻止粗言秽语和嘲讽横行，无论是在城中，还是在军队中，无论是对自己人，还是对敌人。除非谨慎之人采取预防措施，否则，如果对敌人使用，会导致上述麻烦产生，如果对自己人使用，后果更糟。

被留在加普亚的罗马军团密谋反抗加普亚人时，（与这次阴谋有关的）兵变发生了，后来瓦列利乌斯·科尔维努斯将其镇压下去，并在集会中制定了对那些责难他人参与兵变之人应处以的最严厉刑罚规定。

提比略·格拉古，在对汉尼拔的战争中，曾受命指挥因兵员短缺而被罗马人武装起来的奴隶们，对那些胆敢侮辱奴隶的人，他特意制定了一条死刑的特殊规定。

可见，罗马人认为诽谤或责难他人的过失非常有害，如上所述，没有比这个更能激怒人心，或引起更大愤怒，无论嘲笑是真的，还是在开玩笑，“智者说过，当他们接近真相时，要将苦涩的滋味丢掉”。

明智的君主和共和国应满足于胜利，否则胜利将弃之而去

轻视敌人通常是因胜利或者对胜利虚假的希望而骄傲，这种虚假的希望不仅让人在言语中，也会让人在行动中犯错误。人一旦有了这种希望，就不再小心行事，从而常常与希望中可成之事失之交臂，更别提可改进的确定之事。这值得思考，因为人们经常会犯这样的错误，以推罗城为例，被胜利冲昏了头脑的人们，不仅拒绝了使者的条件，还杀了这位前来谈判的使者。因此，亚历山大震怒了，全力攻城，最终占领并毁灭了推罗城，城里居民不是被杀，就是沦为奴隶。

1512年，西班牙军队入侵佛罗伦萨，旨在重振美第奇并对该城征税。佛罗伦萨的内奸使他们相信，只要他们越过边境，就会以其名义揭竿而起。但是当西班牙军队进入阿尔诺河平原后，却发现没有内应，由于缺少粮食补给，于是提出议和。但佛罗伦萨人太过骄傲没有接受，由此导致了普拉托的陷落和国家的灭亡。

因此，当统治者遭受攻击，而敌军比其自己的军队强大许多时，此时最愚蠢的决定就是拒绝和谈，尤其如果和谈是由敌方提出，因为条件不会太苛刻，接受条款的人总会得到一些利益，所以从某种程度上说，他们也分享了胜利。举例说明，亚历山大接受他起初拒绝的条件时，如果推罗城的人们能满足于此，那么他们获得的胜利将不止一点，因为凭借自己的军队，他们使一个伟人被迫屈尊于其意愿。同样地，当西班牙军队对佛罗伦萨人的条件作出让步而没有提出自己的条件时，如果佛罗伦萨人能够满足于此，这也将是伟大的胜利。因为西班牙军队想要的是佛罗伦萨改变政体，不再亲近法国，以及征收贡品。对于这三件事，如果西班牙人能得到后两个，佛罗伦萨人则能保留第一个，即保留他们的政体，双方都能获得一定的荣誉和满足。只要性命无忧，佛罗伦萨人也不会对另两件事太过计较。可惜结果并非如此。如果他们能将此看成一个不错的、几成定局的更伟大的胜利，那么也不会沦落到将自己完全交付命运的安排，并且拿最后的本钱冒险，除非万不得已，否则，冒险绝非明智之举。

曾在意大利尊享荣耀十六年的汉尼拔，当因被迦太基人召回帮助他自己的国家而离开意大利时，他发现哈斯德鲁巴和西法克斯已经被击溃，努米底亚王国灭亡了，迦太基人被困在自己的城市里，只有他和他的军队能为他们带来希望。当他意识到祖国已经危如累卵，于是就决定，在尝试过所有的补救措施之前，绝不去冒险，追求和平并非耻辱，因为他确信，如果他的国家还有一线希望，那就是和平，而不是战争。当和平没有出路时，既然自觉仍可能取得胜利，即使必然战败，他也没有拒绝战斗。但如果他的失败不可避免，他至少可以光荣地失败。虽然汉尼拔具备将领的大智大勇，也拥有一支强劲的军队，但考虑到战败后，人民将沦为奴隶，他便更倾向于和平，而非战争。因此，那些并不具备他的才智和经验的人，在决定开始战争前，是否应该三思呢？但是，人会犯错误，因为他们的希望太无边无际；他们会被摧毁，因为他们只依赖这样的希望而不考虑其他因素。

罗马在和平时与战时同相邻国家和城市的关系

共和国或君主如果不为公众或个人伸张正义、惩奸罚恶将是危险的

什么会使人产生愤怒？这可以从罗马人的经历中找到答案。罗马人派遣三个法比依家族的人出使高卢，当时高卢人正准备进攻托斯卡纳，尤其是克鲁修姆城。克鲁修姆人请求罗马帮助抵抗高卢人。因此罗马人向高卢派遣三个法比依家族的人作为使节，并以罗马共和国的名义声明，一定会阻止高卢对托斯卡纳的战争。当使节到达目的地时，他们发现高卢人和托斯卡纳人正准备交战，于是超过职责范围直接介入了冲突，帮助托斯卡纳人。如此一来事情发生了改变，高卢人发现后，他们将对托斯卡纳人的怒火转移到罗马人的身上。高卢人向罗马元老院提出抗议，要求将上述使节移交给他们发落，以弥补给他们造成的损失。但是这些使节不仅没有被移交给高卢人，也没有受到任何惩罚，反而被选为享有领事权的护民官。结果，高卢人看到本应受到惩处的人反而受到重用，就认为这是对他们的侮辱和蔑视，于是义愤填膺进军罗马并占领了除卡庇托山外的所有地区。罗马人因藐视正义而给自己带来了灾难，因为他们的使节违反了“万国公法”，本应该受到惩罚，而不是加官进爵。

这不禁让人思考，重视这些冒犯对每个共和国和君主来讲多么重要，不仅仅是对所有民众的冒犯，还有关系到个人的冒犯。毕竟，如果一个人受到公众或个人的严重伤害，却没有得到应有的公正对待，那么假如他生活在共和国中，他会为自己复仇，即使会导致共和国毁灭；假如处于君主统治下，且生性勇敢不屈，即使会惹火烧身，他也会费尽心机地报仇雪恨，不达目的誓不罢休。

为了验证这点，没有比马其顿国王菲利普（亚历山大的父亲）更好的例子了。菲利普国王的一个名叫阿塔罗斯的随从被一位名叫鲍桑尼亚的年轻贵族迷住了，几次三番向他表达爱意，但是却发现对方对其并无好感。眼看着无法得其所欲，他于是决定设计阴谋迫使鲍桑尼亚就范。因此，阿塔罗斯大摆酒宴，邀请鲍桑尼亚和其他贵族男爵参加，在其酒足饭饱之际，他抓住了鲍桑尼亚，把他绑了起来。然后他不光使用暴力满足自己的淫欲，而且为了羞辱鲍桑尼亚，他还让其他人也用同样下流不堪的方式虐待他。对此奇耻大辱，鲍桑尼亚向菲利普国王反复申诉，国王却让他稍安勿躁，耐心等候。后来国王不但没有为他复仇，反而任命阿塔罗斯为希腊省总督。看到他的仇敌不仅没有受到惩罚还被重用，于是鲍桑尼亚将作恶者阿塔罗斯和没有为其主持公正的菲利普国王均视为其怒火的宣泄对象。因此在一天早晨菲利普国王女儿嫁入伊庇鲁斯王国的亚历山大家族的庄严婚礼上，正当菲利普国王站在两个亚历山大族人和其儿子与女婿之间，要走向圣殿参加仪式时，鲍桑尼亚杀死了他。这件事与罗马人的遭遇相似，统治者均应引以为戒，决不应该轻视任何人，理所当然地以为如果往伤口上撒盐，受伤之人不会复仇，因为其会卷入危险和毁灭之中。

命运不想让人类阻碍她的计划，于是她蒙蔽了他们的头脑

仔细思考世事，我们会发现许多事情的发生和众多不幸的降临并非天意，毫无防备。因此，显而易见，此段论述在罗马事例中仍然适用，正如美德、宗教、规范的行为方面，同样的事情会经常发生在缺乏以上方面的城市和行省。泰特斯·李维用一个众所周知的事件详细而有力地说明了天意控制人事的道理。他说，为了让罗马人认识到他的力量，天意首先使法比依家族的人在出使高卢时表现不公正，借助其错误行为激怒了高卢人，使高卢对罗马宣战。然后又宣布罗马人无力抵抗高卢的进攻。首先，罗马人在邪恶笼罩的时期里唯一的希望卡美卢斯被流放到了阿尔代亚。然后，当高卢人逼近罗马时，他们没有像以前抵抗沃尔西人和附近其他敌人的多次入侵那样，任命一个独裁官。这也使他们变得虚弱，无法迅速集结部队，部队也根本没有时间武装起来并及时赶到离罗马十英里的阿里亚河岸与高卢人对阵。此时，护民官丢失了其惯有的勤勉来安营扎寨，既没有提前侦察地形，也没有修建壕沟和栅栏保护军营，更没有采取其他人为或天助的防御措施。备战时，指挥混乱，军队和指挥官也没有表现出罗马应有的军纪。战斗中没有人员伤亡，因为罗马军队一触即溃，大部分人逃到维伊，其余的人退守罗马，他们没有回家而是直接躲进卡庇托山。由于罗马元老院对罗马的防御一窍不通，他们甚至忘记关上城门。一些罗马元老逃走了，其他元老则和剩下的罗马人退据卡庇托山，他们在防守卡庇托山时恢复了一些军纪，把不能战斗的人留在城外，为应对长期围困收集他们能找到的所有粮食。不能战斗的人，像老人、妇女和儿童大部分逃到附近乡下，余下的人只能留在罗马听天由命。没有人知道前人是如何应对的，也没有人知道接下来要怎么做，因为没有人认为他们还是与祖先一样的罗马人。

对上述种种混乱的描述，泰特斯·李维总结如下：“当命运不想让人们反抗她的力量时，就蒙蔽人们的头脑至此地步。”

李维的结论是正确无疑的。人的一生既会遭遇坎坷，也会享受富贵，因此应宠辱不惊。人们发现其已经被天意给予种种美好的前景所驱使，要么走向毁灭，要么成就辉煌。据此，他们被给予或被剥夺成为美德之人的机会。命运的安排尽善尽美。当她想让一个人成为伟大事业的领导者之时，她会选择一个品行兼备、能抓住她所给予的时机的人。同样地，当她想让一个人制造灾难时，她会优先考虑可以帮助她达到目的的人。如果有任何人敢横加拦阻，她会杀死他或者剥夺他行善的所有能力。

从李维的论据中可清楚地看出，为了使罗马更加伟大，指引它铸就日后的辉煌，天意认为它必须先要经受磨难（在下本书的开篇会有详细的描述），但她并没有完全毁灭罗马。因为她只是将卡美卢斯流放，并没有害死他；虽然罗马被占领了，但卡庇托山没有沦陷；她这样安排是为了让罗马得不到有效的帮助。她致使罗马被占领，军队主力在阿里亚河畔被击溃，退守到维伊城，从而使罗马城无兵可守。在这些事情的设计之中，她同时也为罗马的再生准备了出路，即在维伊城还有罗马军队，而且卡美卢斯还在阿尔代亚，罗马在战无不胜、声名显赫的统帅的带领下，还可以发动积极攻势收复失地。

为了证实上述观点，我可能还可以列举出更多的现代事例，但并无此必要，此处给出的例子已经足矣。再次强调历史的真相，总体来说证明了人可以接受其命运，但不能反对它；我们可以自己安排它，但不可以破坏它。人应永不放弃，因为希望总是会有的，虽然不知道结局，也不知道通向希望的道路有多么曲折和凶险，但是因为有希望，无论命运会带来什么，无论要承受怎样的艰难困苦，我们都不应该绝望。

真正强大的共和国和君主不会靠金钱收买盟友，而是依靠美德和军队的威望

罗马人被围困在卡庇托山，虽然希望得到来自维伊和卡美卢斯的援救，但由于饥荒，他们不得不向高卢人求和，同意缴纳大笔黄金。当卡美卢斯率领军队抵达时，他们正在按照约定给黄金称重。因此，历史学家说，命运注定“罗马人不应该用金钱换取性命”。

此事不但引人注意，而且深刻说明了此共和国的行为特征。罗马从未购买城镇或者换取和平，因为其一直都是靠军队的威名取得二者。其他共和国却不曾做过类似事情。强国权力的象征之一就是它与其邻国的条约关系。当其处于支配地位，为了获得友谊，它的邻国想成为其附庸国，这是国家强大的明显标志；但是如果邻国虽然实力不济，却仍然能得到进贡，这是国家弱小的明显标志。

纵览罗马历史，你会看到马西利亚人、埃杜维、罗得斯岛人、锡拉库扎的希罗国王、欧迈尼斯国王和马西尼萨国王，都曾与罗马帝国为邻，愿意花费金钱向罗马进贡，以获取罗马的友谊，而只要求得到她的保护作为回报。在弱国，你会发现情况正好相反。首先，佛罗伦萨声名显赫的辉煌时代已经过去，罗马涅的领主都能从它那里收取钱财。同时，它也会给佩鲁贾人、卡斯泰拉尼人以及所有其他邻国赠款。如果佛罗伦萨国力强盛、兵强马壮，那么情况将正好相反，即为了得到它的保护，许多国家会向它进贡钱财，以得到它的友谊，而并非出卖它自己。

不止是佛罗伦萨人曾自贬身价，威尼斯人和法国国王也有过同样遭遇。后者的国家虽强盛，却习惯于给瑞士人和英国国王进贡。这样可以剥夺民众的武装，而且还因为，法国国王和上述提到的其他国家宁可享受现有剥削其人民的优势，不居安思危，也不愿意装腔作势地去保护其人民以使国家长治久安。像这样的荒唐统治，虽然可以暂时换取安宁，但是日久必然会引发危机、灾难和无法弥补的损失。佛罗伦萨人、威尼斯人和法国人花钱避战、自取其辱的事情不计其数，罗马人有且只有一次。佛罗伦萨人和威尼斯人曾买下许多城镇，但后来遭遇动乱时，他们却无法用刀剑来守住用黄金换来的城镇。罗马人只要依然享受自由，就会保持其优良传统。但是当其处于罗马皇帝统治之下时，皇帝逐渐荒唐堕落，远离光明，坠入黑暗，他们也开始向帕提亚人，有时向德国和其他邻国进贡，于是这个伟大帝国开始走向衰亡。

这种种不利情况的产生，是因为你剥夺了民众的武装。更糟糕的是，敌人的攻击力越强大，你会发现自己越虚弱。因为上述的统治者对居住在其统治范围内的臣民施行暴政，但是为了让其能阻敌于国门外，却对那些处于边境的民众施以仁慈。为了更好地防止敌人入侵，他资助邻近的领主和民众，为的是维持自己国家的统治，确保边境太平。但是一旦敌人越境侵犯，则无计可施。这样的国家没有意识到，其统治方式完全违背了正常规律。因为身体最需要加强的是心脏和重要器官，而不是四肢。如果没有四肢，人还可以继续存活，但是如果前者受了伤，人就会死去。这样国家就好比一个拥有全副武装的手脚而无任何心脏保护的身体。

佛罗伦萨因这种秩序的缺乏而遭受的恶果显而易见，也是可预见的。敌军越过边境，逼近它的心脏时，它会发现自己黔驴技穷。同理，几年以前威尼斯人也证明了这一点，如果他们的城市不是有护城河环绕，那么就没有希望了。在法国很少发生这种事，因为法国是一个大国，很少有比它更强大的敌人。尽管如此，1513年英国人入侵法国，整个国家陷入恐慌之中，国王和其他人都认为一次失败就会断送国王和国家。罗马人在这种情况下就与法国人不同，敌军越是接近罗马，他们发现罗马城的抵抗就会变得越坚决。汉尼拔入侵意大利，他发现尽管罗马三次惨败，损失了那么多将军和士兵，但它不仅依然能够抵抗敌人，而且最终赢得了战争。这都归功于“心脏”得到了最好的防护，而不是四肢。因为在这个国家中，主要人口是罗马人，也就是拉丁人，意大利的其他地方和殖民地也有相似的背景。因此，罗马拥有源源不断的兵员可以补充，延续战争。汉尼拔在坎尼取胜后派回信使，从迦太基亲罗马派首领汉诺对信使提出的问题中，就可以看出以上事实。在信使们赞颂汉尼拔的丰功伟绩后，汉诺问他们罗马人是否答应和谈，拉丁人和殖民地的城镇是否已经反叛罗马，这两个问题的答案都是否定的，因此汉诺说道：“这场战争仍然如开始一样远没有结束。”

可见，现今的共和国与古代共和国的作风迥异。正因如此，每天有多少成就铸成，就有多少失败降临。在缺乏美德之人的身上，命运展现了它的力量。因命运变迁，各个共和国和政府也随之而变，而且会一直持续下去，直到某个人带着古人的宠爱降临，他可以控制万物，如同太阳运行，命运之神不必时时展示她之所能。

相信流亡者是危险的事情

相信那些被驱逐出自己国家的流亡者是非常危险的事，鉴于这是每一个当权者都不得不解决的问题，因此这个观点在别的专题中可能并非错误。为了支持这一观点，举一个泰特斯·李维在其史书中曾引用过的典型例子，尽管这不在他的研究范围。亚历山大大帝进军亚洲时，他的一个亲戚——实际上是他叔叔——伊庇鲁斯王国亚历山大，受到卢卡尼亚流亡者的邀请，让其带领军队进入意大利，使其相信通过他们的斡旋，他能得到整个王国。带着他们的承诺和由此而生的希望，他进入意大利，结果被他们害死了，因为同城的公民答应，如果能杀死他，他们就可以回到自己的祖国。因此，我们应该反思那些被自己国家流放的人许下的协议和承诺的不可靠性，要弄清这种人是否言而有信，一定要牢牢记住：一旦他们有机会无须你的帮助就可以回归故土，他们将不顾对你许下的任何承诺，抛弃你投靠别人。相比空洞的承诺和希望，回家的渴望更强烈，以至于他们认为那是错误，并且狡诈地夸大：所以在他们所信与所说之间，他们相信他们使你有了这样的希望，如果你依赖它，你会一无所获或者自取灭亡。

亚历山大和雅典的地米斯托克利的例子足以明证。地米斯托克利被宣布为叛国者后，在亚洲大流士寻求庇护，他向大流士郑重承诺，如果大流士有决心，他会协助进攻希腊。但是后来他没有履行承诺，无论是因为出于愧疚还是害怕惩罚，地米斯托克利最终饮鸩自尽。由此可见，如果像地米斯托克利这样杰出的人物都会犯下如此错误，那么那些德行逊于他的人则更可能犯错，更可能被自己的欲望和冲动左右。因此，统治者应该对流亡者承诺的事情保持谨慎，因为他得到的往往是巨大的屈辱或伤害。

因为利用偷袭或城里居民提供的情报来夺取城镇，极少能够成功，所以我觉得探讨这个与下个章节无关，罗马人照样有很多攻城之法。

罗马人各种攻城之法

罗马人热衷于战争，所以他们总是在任何场合利用任何事情牟利，比如说花钱，以及任何能有所帮助的事情。这就是为什么他们不愿意围困城市，他们认为此战术代价太高，而且过于死板，围城的劣势更多地会抵消胜利带来的优势。因此他们认为最好是采用其他战术而不是围困。在罗马人长年的征战史上，极少有围困城市的事例。

为了得到一座城市，罗马人要么攻城，要么逼其投降。他们进攻时既会凭其强大军队而强攻，也会使用计谋。强攻时，他们会使用两个战术，一是在不破坏城墙的情况下，从所有方向同时进攻，称之为“给城市加冠”，因为所有军队都参与包围并与敌交战。运用这个战术，他们取得了多次胜利，甚至有的大城市在被第一次攻击时就在所难免，例如，西皮奥夺取了西班牙的新迦太基城。其次，当攻击失败后，他们就开始用攻城锥或其他围城器具破坏城墙，或者挖掘直通城里的地道，例如，维伊城就是这样被攻取的。再者，为了化解守军的高度优势，他们会建造木质塔楼，或在城墙外修筑土山，以便和守军处在同一高度。

为了抵抗上述进攻，城里的守军在面对罗马人第一个战术即全面进攻时，会很快暴露在危险面前，而且没有有效的对策。因为各处都需要守军防守，他们没有足够的预备队和援军，即使人手充足，也不是所有人都能英勇作战，一旦一处攻破，则全线溃败。这种情况时常发生，所以这个战术非常有效。但是，当第一轮进攻失利后，他们不会保持很久，因为这对军队来说很危险，它涉及太多战场，作为整体抵抗是可以的，但对于守军却无力突围。军队失去控制且疲惫不堪；但是如果能出其不意，他们只会尝试一次这种战术。如果在城墙上有突破口，可以暂时借助壁垒进行反击。对付地道，他们可以使用现有的武器或其他工具进行反地道战，如装满羽毛的大桶，点燃之后，把它们投入地道中，烟雾和恶臭会阻止敌人进入地道。如果受到塔楼攻击，他们可以尝试用火攻摧毁它。对付土山，他们可以在城墙的低处开个洞，此处是土山倚靠城墙的地方，然后将外面的泥土吸到城里来，因为泥土从外面堆起，却从内部被掏空，所以土山就垒不起来。

这些攻城战术都不能持久，所以他们要么安营扎寨，要么改变取胜策略，西皮奥在非洲就是这么做的。当他进攻尤蒂卡受挫后，在外面扎营寻机与迦太基军队交战，消灭他们。或者他们可以依靠围困战术，正如他们采用围困战术攻取了维伊、加普亚、迦太基、耶路撒冷和其他城市一样。

借助内应密谋夺城的例子是帕拉奥波利，罗马人在内应的接应下占领了它。罗马人和其他人时常尝试这种战术，但是很少成功。原因就是，即使最小的失误也会导致满盘皆输，这种失误很容易发生。一开始在阴谋计划时就有可能暴露，因为有人会去告发，所以很容易被发现。有时也是因为困难重重。除非你能找到借口，否则并不允许和他们交谈，但此种情况下你就必须要与敌人接触。即便计划顺利进行，没有被发觉，开始实施时还会遇到一大堆问题。如果你比约定时间提前或者推迟都会扰乱计划。再者，如果有任何意外的响声，像卡庇托山的白鹅那样，或者如果正常的过程被打断，即使是最小的错误或失误，进攻也会注定失败。除此之外，黑暗的夜晚会给执行危险任务的人增加恐惧，实际上大多数参与者不熟悉所要去往的地方。他们会迷茫、怯懦，轻微的意外也会使他们心惊胆战，任何错觉都足以使他们掉头逃跑。

在这样隐秘的夜间冒险中，比起西西尼亚人，阿拉托斯则更幸运，没有人被发现，然而，即使他很大胆，在白天公开进行，也会同样感到紧张。我们可以归因于他所具有的某种神秘品行，而不是使他们比其他人更幸运的带有夜间冒险特征的任何事物。虽然经常计划用此战术，但是极少能成功奏效。

城市的投降有可能是自愿的，也有可能是被迫的。如果是自愿的，一方面是因为某些外部情况使城市居民想得到他国的保护，如加普亚希望得到罗马的庇护。另一方面是渴望拥有仁慈的统治者，这种愿望是来自英明君主领导下的好政府，此君主会考虑那些自愿接受他统治的人民，如罗得斯岛人、马西利亚人和其他投降罗马的人。如果是被迫投降，可能是因为上述长期围困，也可能是因为想摆脱由于袭击、劫夺和其他难忍之事而生的苦难。

上述所有方法中，罗马人使用最多的是最后一种。在四百五十多年里，他们通过战场上的胜利和袭击使邻国筋疲力尽，通过条约能获得比他们对手更大的荣誉。这是他们最倚重的方法，虽然他们试过所有方法，但发现其他方法危险且无用。因为围城耗费时间，代价高昂，攻城则无把握且风险高，计谋也不可靠。他们也意识到，如果敌军被击溃，他们一天之内就可以占领敌国，然而，如果他们包围一座顽抗的城市，可能需要几年才能取得。

罗马人给予军队统帅自主权

如果一个人能够重视罗马民众和元老们采用的全部程序模式，他就能通过熟读李维的史书而有所斩获，最引人关注的一点是，他们会赋予执政官、独裁官和军队统帅在战场上的权力。这是非常高的权力，因为罗马元老只为自己保留了开战和确认和平条约的权力。其他所有权力都留给了执政官。举例来说，当民众和元老决定对拉丁人发动战争，他们将其余事情都留给执政官自行决定，可以决定如何战斗，以及选择进攻的城市。

很多例子都证实了这一点，尤其以远征托斯卡纳人一例为典型。执政官费边在苏特流姆附近击败了他们，接着计划带领军队穿过直通托斯卡纳的奇米尼森林。尽管战争在一片新的未探索过的危险地区进行，但是对于其计划，他没有与元老院商议，甚至没有告知他们。正好与之相反，元老院可以接受的行动就是进一步确认。听说了费边取得的胜利，元老院很想知道他下一步是否要穿过奇米尼森林进军托斯卡纳，他们认为最好不要冒险，于是派了两名使者去阻止费边进军。但是当使者到达时，费边已经到达托斯卡纳，并大获全胜，于是，使者干脆抛弃使命，将胜利的消息带回罗马，宣扬他赢得的荣誉。

凡是认真思考这种方式的人都会发现，善于使用它是非常明智的。如果元老院要求执政官一步步按照他们的指示指挥战争，那么他就会变得谨小慎微，反应迟缓。元老院认为胜利的荣耀不能全部归功于执政官，他们也要分享，因为战争原本是在他们指挥下进行的。而且，元老院本可以对一些不需要立即处理的事情提出建议，虽然元老们都是在军事方面经验丰富的人，但他们远在千里之外，并不熟悉战场的种种重要细节，因此无法给出正确的建议，会犯下许多错误。正因如此，他们更希望执政官自行决定，他们认为他会因热爱荣誉而尽力约束和节制自己的行为。

说到这点，我想唤起读者的注意，因为我注意到现今的共和国，像威尼斯和佛罗伦萨共和国，表现有所不同。如果他们的统帅、执政官或地方长官要安排战术，他们了解它并给出建议——这套程序与其他值得称赞的相同程序一样，让我们走上如今的道路。

对战略、策略、新装备和纪律的各种评论

如果敌人不惜一切代价决意与之交战，统帅则无法避战

“独裁官盖乌斯·苏尔比基乌斯与高卢人作战，在其作战时机和不利状况继续恶化时，不会孤注一掷与敌人决战。”对于所有人或大多数人都可能犯的错误，经常警告他们应对错误不是一件坏事。因此，我们现今处理重大事件的方法比不上古人的水平。在这个时候再次指出这点并不多余。如果说有什么已经违背了古代传统的话，那么一定是在军事方面，古人们看重的东西现在都消失了。这种不幸是由于共和国和君主已经将这些事情委托给其他人执行。为了避免危险，他们置身军事行动之外，虽然有时君主也会亲自带兵出征，但我不会因此认为他能作出值得称颂的事。实际上，他们参与军事行动，只是为了炫耀而非可敬的原因。这是事实，他们会偶尔检阅一下军队，保留统帅的头衔，他们犯错误的次数要比共和国少一些，尤其是意大利的那些共和国，他们严重依赖他人，自己则对战争一无所知，然而他们希望自己在军队眼中仍贵为君主，于是参与制定决策，结果犯下了数不清的错误。

虽然在别的地方讨论过一些错误，但我依旧无法对一些大错保持沉默。当这些懒散的君主或无能的共和国派遣他们的将军征战时，他们认为任命他去做的最明智的事情，不是在战场上与敌人交战，而是恰恰相反，防守敌人进攻高于一切。他们认为这么做是在效仿费边·马克西姆斯，即避免交战从而拯救罗马。但他们忽略了这样一个事实：这样的委任多半是荒谬或危险的。应谨记于心的一点是，如果敌军不惜一切代价决意与之交战，留在战场上的将军将无法避免战斗。因此，这样的委任相当于：“迫不得已时方可参战，否则不可主动进攻。”如果一个将军想留在战场又不想交战，那么唯一的保险办法就是，与敌军保持至少五十英里的距离，然后派出精锐的侦察员，如果敌人向你进军，你可以有时间远离他们。另一个方法就是躲在城里。但两个方法都极其危险。第一个方法会让你的国家受制于敌，英勇的君主宁可在战场上决一死战，也不愿意以他的臣民为代价拖延战争。第二个方法注定会失败，如果事情果真这样，把军队带进城里，你可能会被包围，而且用不了多久你就会被饥饿折磨而开城投降。因避战而采用这两个办法都极其不利。只要费边·马克西姆斯的军队依然英勇无畏使敌人不敢到你的阵前挑战，那么他采纳的坚守险要的计划就会一直有效。所以说费边没有避战，他只是更想利用他的优势进行交战。如果汉尼拔想与他交战，他本可以一整天等待他。但汉尼拔不敢在这样条件下和他交战。可以说汉尼拔和费边一样避战；但如果任何一方决意不惜代价决战，另一方将不得不采用三个方法之一，即前面已经说过的两个方法，还有逃跑。

以上所述千真万确，有很多例子可以清楚地证明，尤其是罗马人和马其顿的菲利普（珀修斯之父）之间的战争。当菲利普被罗马人攻击时，他决定不与之交战，如同费边·马克西姆斯一开始在意大利那样避免交战一样。他和他的军队驻扎在山顶上，建立防御工事，原以为罗马人不敢来找他交战。但是罗马人来了，和他交战，还把他从山上赶走了。他无力抵抗，和他大部分的军队一起逃跑了。恶劣难行的地形阻止了罗马人的追击，使他免遭彻底被歼。菲利普仍然不愿意与罗马人交战，他在罗马的附近扎营，不得不离开。他从失败经验中学会了如何避战，在山顶上扎营是不够的，也不能把自己关在城里。于是决定采用余下的方法，让自己与罗马的营地保持很远的距离。因此，当罗马人进驻这个省，他就转移到另一个省，如此这样捉迷藏，只要罗马人退走，他就回去。但最后他终于意识到靠拖延战争，他的处境会越来越糟，双方都让他的百姓遭受很多痛苦。他决定在战争中一决高下。于是在适当的时候，他与罗马人展开了正面决战。

在费边军队身处的情况下避免交战是有利的，对盖乌斯·苏尔比基乌斯也是如此，即当你有一支善战之师，敌人不敢应战，无法把你赶出防御工事时，或者当敌人在你的国家立足未稳，无法保证后勤补给供应时，这个方法有用，李维给出的理由是：“只要时机和不利状况每天都会使敌人的处境变得越坏，那么他就不愿意孤注一掷与敌人决战。”但是在其他情况下，避战会带来耻辱和危险，因为如果你逃跑了，正如菲利普那样，其结果会和被击溃一样糟糕，而且更可耻，以至于有损你的美德。尽管他成功逃脱了，但是那些无有利地形帮助的人可能就没有他那么幸运了。

无人否认汉尼拔是一位战争奇才。当他在非洲与西皮奥较量时，如果他能看出拖延战争的任何好处，他一定会这么做。或者，身为一名拥有一支常胜之师的高明统帅，他本可以效仿费边在意大利的做法。但是，他既然没有这么做，一定有更强有力的理由。他的军队已经集结完毕，他知道自己军费匮乏，缺少盟友，不能进行持久战，作为统帅，如果在他的军队被迫解散之前不与敌人进行决战，那么他一定是疯了。如果他继续等待，肯定会失败；但如果进攻，他可能会成功。

还有一点值得思考：如果你注定要失败，又试图赢得荣誉，那么与敌人战斗至最后一兵一卒将比其他让你蒙羞的方法更能让你得到敌人的尊敬。汉尼拔一定是被困境限制了手脚。另一方面，如果汉尼拔当时推迟交战，而西皮奥没有勇气进军攻击他坚固的工事，那么西皮奥本可以不会为此蒙受损失，因为他已经打败了西法克斯，并占领了非洲大部分城市，如同在意大利一样处境无忧。与汉尼拔的战争不是他当初对抗费边时的情景了，同样与高卢人的战争也不是他当初对抗苏尔比基乌斯时的情景了。

带领军队进攻别的国家而又想避免交战是不可能的。如果想进军敌国，敌军出现时，交战是不可避免的。如果在一座城市前列阵，也必须交战。我们这个时代就发生过这样的事情，当勃艮第公爵查尔斯在瑞士城镇穆尔滕前安营扎寨时，被瑞士人击溃了。同样，当法国军队包围诺瓦拉时，也被瑞士人击败了。

当被迫对抗多个敌人时，即使比敌人弱小，假如能抵挡住敌人的首次进攻，你实际上已经胜利了

罗马城民众的护民官的权力非常大，这很有必要，否则，他们就不可能监控贵族的野心。正如前述，在此情况下，贵族原本会很快腐蚀共和国。然而，我在别处提到过，因为体制内特有的弊病，导致了新的灾难，所以共和国必须颁布新的法令对抗他们。因此，护民官因权力在握而变得越来越傲慢，威胁了贵族和整个罗马。如果阿庇乌斯·克劳狄未提出制衡护民官权力的措施，那么由此产生的危险会对罗马的自由造成不利影响。这包括从他们中间甄别出哪些人怯懦、容易腐化，哪些人能投身于公众利益，以及当他们的建议与元老院的建议相左时，哪些人易被诱导以致反抗其他人的意志。这个措施在很大程度上限制了护民官过大的权力，有益于罗马。

这让我们不禁思考下面情况是如何发生的，众多力量联合起来对抗单一力量，虽然通过联合使其力量比对方高出许多，然而单一力量却被期望得更多，虽然力量比联合力量弱小，即使它很强大，单一力量还有许多联合力量所没有的众多优势，因此，其只要稍稍努力，较弱一方就可以瓦解联合力量，使原本强大的联盟变弱。我不再引证古代史中的例子，因为例子太多，但是我会用引用一些发生在我们时代的现代事例。

1483年，所有的意大利行省组成了反威尼斯联盟。威尼斯人失去了所有领土，他们的军队在战场也落败了，于是靠贿赂诱使取得米兰统治权的卢多维科爵士与其成功达成了协议，按照协议威尼斯人不仅收回了他们失去的土地，而且还获得菲拉拉国的一块领地。因此，虽然他们战败了，但是当和平来临时，他们却比之前更富有。

几年前，整个欧洲组成了反法同盟，但是在战争结束之前，西班牙退出了同盟，出于自身利益的考虑与法国人讲和，结果导致其他同盟国在很短的时间内也纷纷与法国达成和解。

由此结论显而易见。如果许多国家对一个国家宣战，那么这个国家摆脱此局面最好的方法是：它必须抵抗住第一轮的进攻，然后拖延时间，等待时机的来临。如果做不到这一点，许多危险将随之而生，威尼斯就遭遇了这种情况。如果可以拖住法国军队，有时间争取到反威尼斯联盟中的某个国家的支持，它就可能避免灾难的发生。但是威尼斯的军队不够强大到可以拖住敌军，没有时间劝说任何国家脱离联盟，因此失败了。我们注意到，罗马教皇在收复失地后，成了它的同盟国，随后西班牙也与其结盟。如果这两位君主有能力，他们本来很愿意帮助它拯救伦巴第，因为这样可以阻止法国在意大利称霸。因此，威尼斯人原本可以通过放弃部分领土，而保住其他部分。如果在战争爆发之前能实现的话，这将会是一个明智的选择，这样他们就不会被赶出来。但是在战争开始后，这样做反而会受到谴责，而且很可能没有作用。然而，在开战前，几乎没有威尼斯人预见到这种危险，更别说应对措施，也没有人给他们提出建议。

由此，我们的结论是，罗马元老院找到了从护民官的野心中挽救国家的方法，即设置多个护民官。所以，如果有很多人辅佐的君主非常英明地采取适当的措施化解联盟，那么他就能控制国家。

谨慎的统帅应该让他自己的军队绝对相信作战的必要性，但应避免迫使敌人也这么做

以上论述已经表明，生存欲望在人类生活中发挥了非常大的作用，它可以引领人们取得光荣的业绩。正如德高望重的哲学家在他们作品中写到的那样，如果没被生存欲望驱使，那么人最高贵的工具，即双手和舌头，就不可能完美地完成工作，或者将他们的工作带到前所未有的高度。因此，古代军队统帅意识到了生存欲望的作用，即当受到生存欲望的驱使，士兵就能在战斗中变得坚定不移，作战勇敢，因此他们会将其部队置于绝境中，另一方面，不让敌人有破釜沉舟的可能。为达此目的，他们经常会向敌军打开他们原本关闭的道路，而对自己的士兵封闭原本开放的道路。要想让一个城市能顽强抵抗，或者让军队在战争中勇敢作战，那么他首先应该做的就是，将这种生存欲望灌输到参战士兵的头脑中。

结果就是，谨慎的统帅在攻打和包围一城市时，应该考虑促使城中居民抵抗的生存欲望程度，从而估计出攻城的难度。如果发现促使他们守城的生存欲望非常大，他就应该知道围困将很困难，反之，将很容易。这就是为什么平定反叛的城市比首次攻取它时要困难得多。起初，他们不会担心因为抵抗而受到敌人的惩罚，于是轻易地投降了，但是后来他们害怕由于再次抵抗而受到惩罚，于是征服他们就会变得困难。这种固执源于邻国之间天然的仇恨。出于野心与嫉妒促使国家之间互相征伐，尤其是共和国之间，托斯卡纳就是例子，这种敌对和竞争使得征服对方变得艰难，而且艰难程度会越来越大。仔细思考一下佛罗伦萨城的邻国有哪些，威尼斯城的邻国有哪些，就不难理解，佛罗伦萨在战争中本不应该花费比威尼斯多，所得到的却比它少，因为威尼斯周边的城镇没有比佛罗伦萨周边城镇的抵抗更顽强。这是因为威尼斯人更习惯于在君主而不是自由城邦的统治下，而习惯于服从的城市通常不介意更换统治者，恰好相反，他们愿意这么做。因此，虽然威尼斯的邻国比佛罗伦萨的邻国更加强大，但由于这些城镇的抵抗并不顽强，所以威尼斯能比佛罗伦萨更快地征服他们，而后者的周围都是自由城邦。

我们回到这个论述的主题。当一位将军攻击一座城市时，他应该尽其所能使守军放弃生存欲望，以及他们顽抗的意志，如果他们害怕惩罚，则通过承诺赦免他们，如果他们害怕失去自由，则跟他们解释他们大多数人的公共利益不会受到侵犯，只是剥夺少数野心家的利益。这样做有助于攻取城市。虽然这些花言巧语很容易被人看穿，尤其是谨慎之人，但平民依然时常上当。因为他们渴望和平早日来临，于是对慷慨承诺掩盖下的陷阱视而不见。许多城市就是因此沦为奴役之地的。佛罗伦萨就是最近的例子。这发生在克拉苏和他的军队身上，虽然他意识到帕提亚的承诺是空洞的，但敌人的和平建议却使他的军队失去了抵抗的必要信念，他无法维持军队的志气，迷失了方向。如果重新审视自己的人生，我们就能看清这一点。

由于少数人的野心，撒姆尼人违反他们的条约，袭击和掠夺罗马同盟国的领土。后来他们派遣使节到罗马请求和平，提出愿意归还他们掠夺的东西，并交出导致战乱和抢掠的罪魁祸首，但他们的请求被罗马人拒绝了。当他们两手空空地回到撒姆尼后，撒姆尼军队的统帅克劳迪厄斯·庞提乌斯，在他著名的演说之一中指出：虽然他们这方希望和平，但是罗马人无论如何都想发动战争，生存欲望驱使他们必须参战，他说道：“如果生存欲望迫使人们参战，则战争是正当的，如果人们的希望寄于武力，则拿起武器就是他们的职责。”他将军队胜利的希望建立在此生存欲望上。

还有一个罗马事例中更值得注意的例子，即盖乌斯·曼利厄斯领导他的军队对抗维伊人，当一部分维伊人的军队突破他们的防御栅栏后，他急忙带领一队人马抵抗他们，为了不让维伊人逃掉，他在军营中的每个出口都设置了守卫。因此，当维伊人发现他们无路可逃时，反而勇猛异常，竟然杀死了曼利厄斯，如果不是一位护民官头脑清醒放他们出去，他们也许会将其他罗马人也杀死。因此，只要生存欲望仍在约束维伊人战斗，他们就会勇不可当，但是，当他们看见有路可逃时，反而只会想着逃跑，而不是战斗。

当沃尔西人和埃魁人的军队越过罗马边境时，罗马派遣执政官抵抗他们。维提乌斯·麦西乌斯指挥的沃尔西军队在战斗中，发现被罗马人的防御栅栏包围了。他知道要么战死，要么拼死作战求得生机，于是对他的士兵说：“跟我一起上，在战场上没有城墙和壁垒，只有刀剑对刀剑，虽然我们勇气相当，但生存欲望是我们最后的武器，也是最好的武器，你拥有这种优势。”因此，李维称生存欲望是“最后和最好的武器”。

全罗马最谨慎的统帅卡美卢斯，当他率领军队进入维伊城后，为了巩固取得的胜利，让敌人失去抵抗的最后一丝生存欲望，在维伊人能听见的情况下，大声发布命令：任何人只要放下武器，就不会受到伤害。结果就是维伊人扔掉了武器，整个城市几乎兵不血刃就屈服了。这个方法后来被很多将领效仿。

哪一方最值得相信，强将弱兵，还是弱将强兵？

科里奥兰纳斯被罗马驱逐出境后，投靠了沃尔西人，在那里集结了一支军队，借此向他的罗马同胞复仇。他开始向罗马进军，但是最终撤退了，原因是他对他母亲的爱，而非对罗马军队的爱。在对这件事情的评论中，李维说道：我们可以从中知道，罗马共和国更多是通过她将领的美德，而不是士兵的美德而成长。虽然沃尔西人以往总是失败，但这次他们本可以获胜，但由于科里奥兰纳斯是他们的统帅，才没有取胜。虽然李维提出这个观点，但在他的历史著作中有许多文章表明，没有统帅指挥的士兵们也曾表现出证明他们品行的非凡行为，在执政官死后，他们甚至比他战死前更加纪律严明，更加意志坚决。这样的事情发生在西班牙由西皮奥家族领导的罗马军队身上，尽管这两个统帅均战死了，但罗马士兵的品行不仅保护了自己，而且打败了敌人，为罗马共和国挽救了西班牙。考虑上述许多例子中只凭士兵的品行就赢得了战争，还有许多其他例子中是将军的品行发挥了同样的作用，所以我们可以说，将军与士兵需要彼此。

在这一点上，我们应该首先考虑哪一个更让人害怕：弱将强兵，还是强将弱兵。如果我们相信恺撒的观点，则双方同等重要。恺撒前往西班牙与阿夫拉涅乌斯和彼得利乌斯作战时，虽然对手有一流的军队，但是他没有表现出一丝恐惧，他说道，他是在和一支无将之师作战，以此表明统帅的无能。另外，当他前往塞萨利与庞培交手时，他说道：“我将遇到一位无兵之将。”

更进一步探讨此问题：究竟是常胜将军铸造了常胜之师，还是常胜之师成就了常胜将军。我倾向于这个观点：众人之力皆为一人之志，则易；而一人之力皆为众人之志，则难。当卢库勒斯被派遣与米特里达梯交战时，完全没有任何战争经验，然而他带领的军队很精锐而且有杰出的军官，很快他就成长为优秀的统帅。同样，罗马人因为人力短缺，武装了许多奴隶，并把他们交由森普罗尼乌斯·格拉古斯训练，在很短的时间里，他就把他们培养成了一支优秀的军队。曾在别处提到过的佩洛皮达斯和伊巴密浓达，当他们把底比斯从斯巴达人的奴役中解放出来后，在短期内将底比斯农夫打造成了优秀的战士，他们不仅能够对抗斯巴达的民兵，而且还打败了他们。

这场争论是势均力敌的，因为一方是好的，就可以使另一方变得和它一样好。一支优秀的军队，如果缺少一个英明的统帅就会变得躁动而危险，亚历山大死后的马其顿军以及内战中的老兵就是这样。因此，我们应该对有时间训练士兵并将他们全副武装的杰出统帅更有信心，而不是一个狂躁之徒被临时选为乱军的头头。更多的荣誉与赞美应该给予那些既能打败敌人，又能将军队在迎敌前训练成虎狼之师的将军们，因为他们展示出了双重的美德，即使将这种美德给予众人，使其成为严厉的纪律严明者，他们也远不能像那些将军那样受到尊敬和赞颂。

由于战争中新发明的出现或不熟悉的叫喊而产生的作用

许多事件都表明，在冲突和战争中因第一次被人看见或听到的事物而发生前所未有的事件非常重要，以罗马人与沃尔西人的战争为例。当奎因久斯发现他军队的一个侧翼在后撤，于是大声呵斥他们坚守阵线，因为另一个侧翼正在获胜，通过这些激励的话语，他让自己的士兵重新获得勇气，同时也让敌人惊恐万分，于是他获胜了。对于纪律严明的军队，这些话语会有很大作用，对于混乱不堪和军纪涣散的军队仍会有更大作用，可以说是，一语重于泰山。

举一个发生在我们时代的不同寻常的例子。几年前，佩鲁贾城因奥迪和巴利奥尼两支势力而分裂。后者当权之后，前者被流放了。但是在朋友的帮助下，巴利奥尼召集了一支军队，集结在靠近佩鲁贾的一座城镇里。在城内追随者的协助下，夜晚他们神不知鬼不觉地潜入城中，然后向广场的方向前进。因为城中的每个街头都设置了铁链阻挡道路，所以在奥迪军队的前列有一个人手持铁狼牙棒负责砸开固定铁链的锁，以便让骑兵通过。当呼喊声“拿起武器！”响起时，正在砸锁的人被后面的人群推挤得无法举起胳膊抡棒，于是，他大喊了一声“退后！”，这句话被后面的人一级级传下去，结果变成了“撤退！”。于是后面的人开始逃跑，一个接一个，其他人也随着自己人产生的混乱而溃逃。因此，奥迪人的计划就这么泡汤了，就因为一句不起眼的话。

严明的纪律不仅能使军队在战斗中保持有序的队列，而且也会防止一些小意外扰乱军心。仅以此原因，就说明平民大众在战争中毫无用处，因为任何谣言、喊声、骚动都会影响他们的情绪，使他们落荒而逃。因此训导是有必要的，高明的统帅应该委派专人听从其口头命令，并将命令传递给其他人。他应该使他的军队不去理会别人，军官们不得擅离职守。疏忽这些要点会导致无法控制的混乱。

至于疑兵之计，每位统帅都应该在战斗中尝试使用这种方法鼓舞士气，同时挫伤敌人的锐气，尤其是在侥幸获胜的战斗中非常有效。以罗马独裁官盖乌斯·苏尔比基乌斯为例。在他与高卢人作战时，他把武器分发给所有脚夫和随从们，让他们骑上骡子和其他乘骑，让他们伪装成一支骑兵部队，然后让他们手持旌旗隐蔽在山后。在战斗白热化的时候，命令他们收到信号后，出现在战场上，让敌人看到。如此疑兵之法，让高卢人惊恐万分，于是溃败了。有两件事是一位优秀统帅应该做的：第一，他应该知道是否应该采用新奇的战法惊吓敌人；第二，他应该保持警惕，观察敌人是否会用同样的花招来对付他，从而察觉出并化解它。

印度国王就是这么做的，但当塞米勒米斯注意到印度国王有很多大象后，为了威吓住他，让他看到她也有很多大象，于是将水牛和母牛的兽皮披在骆驼的背上伪装出许多假大象。但她的计谋让印度国王发现了，她的计划不仅无用，而且变成了她的劣势。同样，当独裁官玛莫库斯与费德奈人交战时，为了惊吓罗马人，在战斗最激烈的时候，他们命令许多军队将火把绑在长枪上从费德奈城出来，自以为借此就可以分散罗马人的注意力，结果自乱阵脚。

但须注意，这种计谋如果实大于虚，则可以用于占优势的一方，因为如果他们足够勇猛，弱点就不会很快被发现。但是如果虚大于实，则最好不要采用，或者如果采用了，要尽量多伪装一会儿，别让骗局很快被揭穿，就像盖乌斯·苏尔比基乌斯的“骡兵”做的那样。如果疑兵之术有内部弱点，只要走到近前就会被看穿，那将对你是百害而无益，就像塞米勒米斯的大象和费德奈人的火把一样。虽然一开始他让罗马军队变得有点不安，然而，独裁官赶过来，喝住他的士兵，告诉他们不要像胆小鬼一样被一点点小烟吓跑，应该转身冲过去，他高呼道：“既然你们无法用仁慈使他们安静，那么就用火焰摧毁费德奈。”这种方法被证明对费德奈人没有用处，他们是战斗的失败者。

军队的统帅应该只有一位，而非多位，令出多门是祸事

当费德奈人反叛并屠杀了罗马人派到费德奈的移民后，罗马人为了报仇雪耻任命了四位有领事权的护民官，其中一人留下保卫罗马，另外三个人被派遣去与费德奈人和维伊人交战。由于指挥权分散，护民官之间相互对立，虽然没有造成严重后果，但他们回到罗马时名誉扫地。幸亏罗马军队英勇善战，才没有因他们的无能而引发灾难。因此，当罗马人意识到问题根源后，就任命了一位独裁官，负责将三位护民官引发的混乱恢复正常。这表明，多人指挥同一支军队或者负责防御同一座城市毫无用处。泰特斯·李维对这件事是再明白不过，他写道：“三位有领事权的护民官向我们展示了在战争中令出多门是多么的徒劳无用，每个人都倾向于自己的意见，认为别人的都是错误的，于是他们给了敌人可乘之机。”

虽然这个例子足够说明号令不统一在战争中会引起混乱，我想再举两个例子，一个来自现代，另一个来自古代，能更好地支持这个观点。

1500年，在法国国王路易十二重新征服了米兰之后，他派出军队进军比萨城，想从佛罗伦萨人手中夺回它。军队由吉奥凡巴蒂斯塔·里多尔菲和卢卡·蒂·安东尼奥·第格利·阿尔卑兹同时指挥。因为吉奥凡巴蒂斯塔威望很高，而且经验丰富，卢卡将一切事务均交由他管理。虽然没有显露出，但卢卡通过沉默、疏忽和批评的方式表现出反对吉奥凡巴蒂斯塔的野心，结果他既没有为围城作战出力，也没有献计献策，表现得像自己并不存在。后来，因为某件事情的发生让吉奥凡巴蒂斯塔不得不返回佛罗伦萨。当卢卡一人独掌大权之后，事情发生了变化，他通过勇气、勤奋和明断表现出了他的价值，只要他的同僚还在军营，所有这些特质都不会被展示出来。

为了证实泰特斯·李维的话，引用另一个例子：罗马派遣一支军队讨伐在奎因久斯和他同僚阿格里帕指挥下的埃魁人。阿格里帕想从奎因久斯手中取得对战争的绝对控制权，他说道：“只有当最高指挥权在一人之手时，军队事务管理才会最明智。”

这和我们现在的共和国和君主的做法正好相反，为了加强管理，他们为一个地方加派了多名行政长官和多名军队指挥官，导致了难以形容的混乱。在我们的时代里，如果人们想找到灾难降临到意大利和法国军队上的原因，那么这是最有效的通途。总而言之，可以确信，将征战之事委托给一位才智平庸的人，要好过交给两位拥有同等权力的杰出之人。

给征战中统帅们的建议

为什么法国人曾被而且如今依旧被认为开战如虎，后继如鼠

高卢人在战斗激情的鼓舞下，时常在阿尼奥河岸上向罗马人提出挑战，这引发了他们与提图斯·曼利厄斯的战争。高卢人的斗志也使我想起泰特斯·李维曾数次说到他们，即在战斗刚开始的时候比男人更加勇敢，但是随着战斗的持续，他们会变得比女人还不如。至于为什么会这样，许多人认为这是本性使然，这正确无疑。但不能由此推断出曾使他们一开始勇敢战斗的本性，不能被规则控制以至于他们无法将勇猛坚持到底。

为了证明这一点，我们先了解一下军队的三种类型。第一种，既有斗志又有秩序。秩序能提升斗志和品德，这在罗马军队中得以体现。在他们的整个历史中，罗马军队总是秩序井然，军纪的使用由来已久。在纪律严明的军队中，没有人不按照军规行事。因此，罗马军队征服了全世界，他们是其他军队的榜样——没有人好吃懒做或嫖娼，而且没有执政官的命令，不会有人擅自执行军事或民事行动。不遵守纪律的军队不是真正的军队，即使他们做了不起的事，也是由于激情和冲动，而不是因为英勇。遵守纪律的品德能在恰当的时间以恰当的方式使用激情，军队不会因此遭遇困难或损失。严明的军纪能激发勇气和斗志，从而增加胜利的希望，只要军纪尚存，则胜利尤在。

与上述类型正好相反，第二种类型是只有激情而无纪律的军队，高卢人就是这样，他们在战斗中纪律涣散。如果第一次进攻受挫，他们就会动摇不定，因为激情不能维持长久，当他们的激情冷却下来，他们就无所依靠。罗马人，正好相反，因为他们纪律严明，所以他们不在乎危险，不会丧失胜利的信心，他们能保持坚定和顽强，自始至终用同样的勇气和品德进行战斗。当战斗意志被激发起来，他们就会勇往直前。

第三种类型的军队就是既无天生的斗志也无纪律进行补充的军队，就是我们时代的意大利军队，非常无能，除非遇到一支因意外而逃跑的军队，否则绝不可能获胜。没有必要引述更多例子，因为他们每时每刻都在证明着自己多么的软弱无能，毫无勇气可言。因此，泰特斯·李维的话简明扼要地阐述了优秀的军人和无能的军人是如何产生的，我引用帕披里乌斯·克塞在指责费边时所作的演讲：“没人会尊重人或众神，他们不会遵守统帅的法令或指示，他们会在和平或敌对的领土上到处游荡劫掠；他们会忘记自己的誓言，未经许可就脱离军队，而且他们很愿意这么做；他们会让旗帜无人守卫，不会再听从命令集结或解散；他们会为争夺领地而不停争斗，不管这个地方是否适宜，也不管统帅的命令；他们不会保留军团或军阶；就像一群强盗，盲目而狂躁，而不是守纪和尽职的军人。”在这段话中，我们能立刻看出我们时代的军人是否盲目而狂躁，或者是否守纪和尽职，他们远没达到军人的标准，而且远不及罗马人那样有斗志有纪律，或者仅仅像高卢人那样有战斗的激情。

大战前的小规模战斗是否有必要，如果统帅不这样做，怎么才能了解新的敌军

我们在上文提到过，在世事中，还有这种困境：当人们想将事情办得达到完美程度时，会发现灾祸总会与福祉同行，祸易变成福，这两者共存似乎是可能的。这是世之常情。正因如此，福祉总是难以得到，除非命运的眷顾为你消除天然的麻烦。我不得不说，这是曼利厄斯与高卢人的战争，对此泰特斯·李维说道：“这场战斗将决定整个战争的结局，高卢人的军队在恐惧中丢弃了他们的营地，最先逃进提泊坦，然后流窜到坎帕尼亚。”一方面，无论如何，优秀的统帅都应避免因偶然事件而损害军队的行为，因为他的军队不是雇佣兵，因此孤注一掷的冒险是极其鲁莽的，正如上文在谈论守卫关口时所述。

另一方面，当英明的统帅发觉他将与享誉盛名的不熟悉的敌军交战时，在决战之前，他们应让军队通过小规模的接触战来探得敌人的实力，从而了解敌人，继而找出应对之法，这可以消除因谣言和敌人声望而生的恐惧。对统帅而言，这么做至关重要。在此过程中，生存欲望会约束你去采用它，因为你不想看到自己置身危难之中，如果要和敌人交战，首先要让你的军队与敌人有所接触，从而使他们内心摆脱由敌人的声望而生的恐惧。

瓦列利乌斯·科尔维努斯受命指挥罗马军队对付撒姆尼人，但迄今罗马人没有与撒姆尼人交战的经验，对他们的作战能力也不了解。因此，泰特斯·李维说到瓦列利乌斯让罗马士兵与撒姆尼人进行小规模接触战，“于是他们可能就不再害怕未知的战争与敌人”。巨大的危险依然存在，如果你的士兵在接触战中被打败了，反而会增加他们的恐惧与胆怯，造成与你希望相反的局面，即你将使他们感到害怕，与你原本想让他们感到安全的初衷相反。于是这就是祸福之间紧密相连的事情之一，它们之间是如此密切，以至于很容易让你弄巧成拙。

有鉴于此，杰出的统帅应该采取一切预防措施，以防止消磨军队志气的危险事情发生。首战失利就是能打击士气的事情。因此对于接触战，应该慎重行事，除非有很大的优势，确信会获胜，否则就不应出战。也不应该试图据守关隘，因为那里无法使其军队施展开。也不应该防守城市，除非其损失将不可避免地使其灭亡。再者，如果决心守城，他应该安排他的军队与驻军协防以反击进攻，这样他所有的军队在应对围攻时就能发挥作用。否则，他就应放弃防守城市。放弃可能守不住的城市，保全军队，他不会在战争中失去声誉或取胜的希望。但是当你没有守住你原本打算防守的城市，而且人人皆知你在进行防守，那么损失将很严重而且可能是灾难性的。因此事实上，你会像高卢人那样，由于暂时的胜利而失去战争。

珀修斯的父亲即马其顿王国的菲利普，在他那个时代，是声誉显赫的战士，当他受到罗马人攻击时，主动放弃了他认为无法守住的大片国土，并采取坚壁清野的策略，作为谨慎之人，他认为如果他没有守住他原本打算防守的地方，他将失去声望，这远比故意让那些好像他不在乎的地方落入敌手要更加可怕。当坎尼的失利使罗马人行为变得更加残暴时，他们拒绝帮助他们的追随者和臣民，吩咐他们要尽力自我防御。这个做法要比帮助盟友防守却最终让他们失望要好得多，因为如果那样做，他们会同时失去盟友和自己的军队，但如果不那样做，失去的只是盟友。

话题重新回到小规模接触战，我坚持认为，如果一位统帅因为他对敌人一无所知而必须倚靠接触战，那么他应该在他处于绝对优势不会有任何闪失的时候行动。他应该像马里厄斯在与辛布里人作战时那样。辛布里人是一个凶猛的部落，他们前来掠夺意大利，因为他们凶暴残忍、人多势大，而且已经打败了一支罗马军队，所以马里厄斯在进军时非常害怕。他由此判断，在与敌人交战之前，他必须消除由于畏敌而在军队中蔓延的恐慌情绪，作为慎重的统帅，他不止一次将他的军队驻扎在辛布里人必经的关口附近，旨在让他的军队能躲在防御工事的后面，亲眼看到并熟悉敌军的模样，所以当他们看到敌军如此杂乱无序、辎重拖累、武器落后，甚至还有人赤手空拳时，他们打消了疑虑，重新燃起斗志。马里厄斯非常明智地使用了这个方法，其他人也应该积极效仿，不再招致上述危险，也不要像高卢人表现得那样，“他们由于一些偶然事件而害怕，最先逃进提泊坦，然后流窜到坎帕尼亚”。

既然在这段论述中提到过瓦列利乌斯·科尔维努斯，那么我将在下个章节中使用他关于统帅该如何表现的演说。

统帅怎样才能获得军队的信任

如上所述，瓦列利乌斯·科尔维努斯带兵与撒姆尼人交战。由于罗马人不熟悉他们的作战方式，为了安定军心、了解敌人，他让军队与敌人进行一些接触战，仅仅这么做是不够的，于是他决定对士兵们作战前演说，极有说服力地指出他们应该多么藐视敌人，他的演说唤起了士兵们及他自己的勇气。从李维记录的这个演说中，我们了解到统帅应如何表现以获得军队的拥戴。他说道：“仔细看看指挥和支持你们奋战的统帅！扪心自问一下，这个你们将要听命于他的人是否只是一个言过其实、光鲜但没有任何军事才能的演说家，他是否知道如何使用武器，冲锋在前，在战斗最激烈时上阵杀敌！我要你们，我勇敢的兄弟们，跟随我的脚步，而不是我的言语，不要只关注我的命令，而是视我为榜样，因为凭着我执政官的右手已经获得了无数的最高赞誉。”可以从演说中得知，他是否认真思索过，如果他想占据统帅的地位，他将如何去做；如果反其道行之，则无论是因运气或野心而取得的地位，都会在某个适当的时候毁掉他的名誉，而不是成就它。因为不是头衔成就了人的伟大，而是人成就了伟大的头衔。

我们须再次注意以上所述，当伟大的统帅在面对不熟悉的敌人时，他是否使用了非凡的方法来鼓舞久经沙场的军队，当他指挥一支新组建的从未见过敌人的军队时，他是否会殚精竭虑地训练他们。如果一支经验丰富的军队都会害怕不熟悉的敌人，那么从未上过战场的新军则情况更糟。然而事实上，这些困难通常会被优秀的统帅以他的谨慎行事化解，上文曾提及的罗马人格拉古和底比斯人伊巴密浓达都是这么做的，他们指挥没有经验的新军打败了经验丰富的老兵。

他们采取的方法就是先用数月时间训练军队，并通过模拟战使他们逐渐习惯服从命令，在对新军有足够信心的时候，再带领他们参加实战。因此，在不缺乏人力时，受过训练、掌握了作战技能的平民就能组成一支优秀的军队。所以说，拥有丰富人力的君主却缺乏善战的士兵，不是由于他的人民懦弱，而仅仅是由于他自己的懒惰与愚蠢。

统帅应该熟悉地形

在统帅必备的才能中，熟知地形和地利是其中之一。如果没有这方面综合详细的知识，那么他就无法有效指挥战斗。正如科学需要实践一样，如果渴望得到完美，就需要经常练习。这种练习和详细的知识通过狩猎获得的比其他锻炼更多。因此，古代作家告诉我们，在他们的时代，统治世界的英雄们都是在森林和追逐中成长起来。追逐不仅能为他们提供必不可少的知识，而且教会了他们在战争中的其他必需技能。因此，色诺芬在他的《居鲁士传记》这样说道，当他准备进攻亚美尼亚王国时，委派任务后，他提醒领受任务的下属，这些任务就像他们以前经常随他进行的狩猎活动一样。他说，那些他派往山区埋伏的人应该像在山脊设陷阱的猎人，而那些前往扫荡平原的人应该像捕猎的人，先将野兽从它的巢穴中赶出来，然后追逐它，直至把它赶到罗网中。

上文所述是为了表明，色诺芬认为狩猎活动与战争极为相似，所以，伟人们将狩猎视为高贵和必要的运动。没有比狩猎更简便的方法来获得地理知识，因为追逐猎物的过程为猎手提供了解地形的绝佳机会。同时它使猎手熟悉了当地的环境，轻松掌握了未知地区的细节。所有国家和地区的地理特征都具有一致性，于是在一个地区掌握的地理知识可以被借鉴到另一地区，但是没有任何经验的人很难掌握另一地区的地形，除非他在那里生活了很长时间，否则不可能了解当地环境。例如，实践过的人一眼就能看出平原的面积，山脉的高度，河谷的走向等等，因为他已经能学以致用了。

泰特斯·李维在普布利乌斯·德西乌斯的例子中阐明了这一观点。在撒姆尼人的战争中，普布利乌斯·德西乌斯是护民官，负责指挥执政官科尼利厄斯的军队，当执政官打算率领罗马军队进入一条可能会被撒姆尼人切断退路的山谷时，德西乌斯看出其中的巨大危险，于是对执政官说：“奥留斯·科尼利厄斯，你看到敌人上面的那座山峰了吗？如果我们能迅速占领它，它的险要位置可以保证我们的安全，撒姆尼人愚蠢地忽视了它。”在告诉大家德西乌斯的话之前，泰特斯·李维说：“普布利乌斯·德西乌斯，一个受过军事训练的护民官，观察到树木繁茂的山谷中有一座能威胁到敌人的山峰，虽然它不利于大部队进攻，但是轻装的小股部队却可以登上。”因此，执政官命令他带领三千名士兵占领了它，从而挽救了罗马军队。然后，当夜幕降临时，他思考如何能安全撤退，保全自己和他的部队，李维是这么记录的：“跟我来，让灯火继续亮着，我们去侦察一下敌人设置岗哨的地方，看看是否有办法逃出去。”他穿了件短小的军队斗篷，以免让敌人看到他是一位军官。

这件事证明了对于统帅而言了解地形的内在本质非常有用和必要，假如德西乌斯不是明智之人，没有这种本事，他就不可能看出占领那座山对罗马人有利，也不可能从远处看出如何占领此山，也不能在山顶被敌人四面包围时，发现一条在敌人严密防守下的出路，返回执政官的军队。从中我们可以推断出，德西乌斯一定有这样惊人的才能，才会使罗马军队占领山头转危为安，才会使他在敌人的重重包围中发现安全突围的生路。

人民的利益是至高无上的法律

在战争中使用欺诈不是可耻的事情

虽然使用欺诈是可憎的行为，但在战争中却值得称赞和夸耀。一个人使用欺诈战胜敌人，与他使用武力打败敌人一样值得赞许。我们可以从传记作家对伟人的评价中看出，他们赞扬汉尼拔和其他著名人物的这种行为。这样的例子举不胜举，在此不再赘述，但我想强调，关于失信或毁约的欺诈是不光彩的，虽然如上所述它会偶尔为你赢得国家或王国，但是不会为你带来荣誉。我所说的欺诈，是用于对付与你没有信用可言的敌人，即与战争有关的欺诈。例如，汉尼拔在佩鲁贾湖边假装逃跑，引诱罗马执政官和军队进入圈套，以及借助被点燃牛角的牛群逃出费边·马克西姆斯的包围。

庞提乌斯就善于使用欺诈，作为撒姆尼人的统帅，他在考地乌姆岔口使罗马军队落入圈套。他将自己的军队靠山埋伏好后，派出几个士兵化装成牧羊人，带着一群羊穿过平原。他们被罗马人抓住后被问到撒姆尼军队的位置，于是把庞提乌斯事先准备好的话告诉了罗马人，即撒姆尼军队已经动身去包围诺切拉。罗马执政官听信了他们的假情报，当罗马军队抵达那里时，他们马上被撒姆尼人包围在考地乌姆的悬崖峭壁之间。如果庞提乌斯能听从他父亲的建议，要么放罗马人一条生路，要么把他们赶尽杀绝，那么他用欺诈战术取得这场胜利就应该给他带来诸多荣誉，但是他采用了折中办法，即“既没有化敌为友，也没有彻底消灭敌人”，折中办法总是不利于国家事务，我在别的论述中已经提出过。

无论将面对耻辱还是荣誉，我们都应该保卫自己的国家，无论用什么手段都是正当的

如上文所说，罗马执政官和军队被撒姆尼人包围了。撒姆尼人极大地羞辱了罗马人，把他们的武器和装备都收缴了，强迫他们从牛轭下经过返回罗马。罗马执政官们惊恐万分，整个军队也陷入绝望中。罗马副将卢修斯·图鲁斯说道，为了拯救国家不应该拒绝任何可行的方法，罗马的存亡系于这支军队的存亡，应该想方设法地挽救它，无论用什么手段保卫国家都是正当的，无论带来的是耻辱还是光荣。因为如果这支军队保住了，罗马还有机会一雪前耻，但是如果没有成功，即便光荣地战死沙场，罗马及其自由也将随之湮没。所以，图鲁斯的建议最终被采纳了。

这个忠告值得关注，应该被每个为国家献策的公民遵守。当国家的安危依赖于所采用的决定时，就不应理会正义与非正义，善良或残酷，值得赞扬或有辱名誉。相反，任何其他顾虑都应置之不理，全心全意地执行能挽救国民生命与保全国家自由的措施。

这是法国人采纳的方法——他们所言与所行都是如此——为了捍卫他们的国王或他们王国的权力，没有人会发出不和谐的声音，“这样做会为国王带来耻辱”。他们说，国王没有作出可耻的决定，无论是福还是祸，无论他赢得还是葬送了整个王国。

城下之盟不应该被遵守

当执政官带着被剥夺武器且遭受撒姆尼人极尽羞辱虐待的军队回到罗马时，第一位在元老院发言的人说道，不应该遵守在考地乌姆达成的和平协议。他是罗马执政官斯普利乌斯·普斯图米尔斯。他认为，罗马人民不能受它束缚，只有他和其他承诺和平的人才受此约束。因此，如果人民想免除责任，他们应该将他和所有作出承诺的人当作犯人送给撒姆尼人。他坚决的要求最终使元老院让步了，于是他和其他人被当作囚犯交给了撒姆尼人，以此抗议和平无效。命运似乎垂青于普斯图米尔斯，撒姆尼人没有关押他，在他回到罗马后，在罗马人眼中他靠投降赢得的荣誉，竟然比在撒姆尼人眼中庞提乌斯靠胜利获得的还要多。

有两件事应该引起我们关注。一件事是，荣誉可以通过两个行为中的任意一个获得，即在正常情况下靠胜利取得，以及如果你能证明失败与你无关或者借助义举在失败中将功补过。另一件事是，你没有兑现被迫作出的承诺并不可耻。实际上，当武力威胁消除时，影响共和国的城下之盟总是自动瓦解。这样的例子在历史中随处可见，而且人人皆知，即使在现代也会发生。不仅仅是当武力威胁消除时君主不再遵守被胁迫的承诺，我们发现当最初作出承诺的原因不再适用时，其他承诺也会失效。无论这是否值得称颂，无论君主应该不应该如此行事，《君主论》中已经详细地探讨过。因此在这里无须再作说明。

导读

威廉·莎士比亚，这个从文艺复兴时期施施然走来的英国人，创造了文学世界的一个奇观：他的译本遍布全球，研究他的论著浩如烟海，他同时得到文学巨匠和普通读者的一致倾慕，他的作品完美地诠释了“经典”和“畅销”，他是普世的，是属于千秋万代的。大仲马曾经说：“除了上帝，莎士比亚创造的最多。”木心则更进一步，直言：“威廉，你是仅次于上帝的人。”

这样的评论，本来不可轻信，可是面对莎翁的一部部传世精品，我们只能哑口无言，只好看一遍，再看一遍，一任由他牵引，听他对世相人心、权力欲望，抽筋刮骨似的鞭辟，还有，感受一个文学家对天下一切的可悲可怜难以自禁的同情。莎士比亚不仅有一双天赋的慧眼，一份天纵的才情，写善恶两极时，痛快淋漓，直见性命，更有一颗金心，句句诚恳，对人事自有一份体谅。

对一部《哈姆雷特》的论述，也许已经可以撑起一座图书馆。但是莎士比亚之所以是莎士比亚，当还有另外一层伟大——在这本中英文都只有百十页的小书《论权力》里，没有曲折的情节，摘选莎作中有关权力的诸片段，处处易懂，但也处处都是警句——想必能做到随意抽取片言片语，都闪烁着金句光芒的，莎翁之作，仅次于《圣经》。

对于高高在上的君王，莎翁有刻骨铭心的嘲讽，但淳朴、实在，他嘲笑他们煊赫的排场和所得的奉承，在《李尔王》里对虚荣国王不留情面；他也体恤，借着亨利五世之口直言：“随着‘伟大’而来的，是多么难堪的地位啊……做了国王，多少民间所享受的人生乐趣他就得放弃”；同时，他还清醒，国王“除了地位、名衔、外表引起人们的敬畏与惶惑外——你还有什么呢”……不是李尔王执迷不悟，也不是亨利五世勤恳清明，而是莎士比亚，实在透彻。

透彻的莎翁自然也不会放过对庶人的针刺。他在《奥赛罗》里写出两种奴才相：有一种是天生的奴才，奴颜卑膝，为了粮草出卖一生；另有一种，则表面鞠躬如也，骨子里实利成癖。这样的感喟，并非出自知识，它来自一个敏感的文豪敏感的处世经验。这样的奴才代代都不稀缺，所以说，莎翁的写作超越了时代，因为他退得开，所以他看得透。人间百态，人性深层，写到这样悠游裕如的地步，他因此永恒。

而莎士比亚的金心，在这本书中最动人的体现，首推最后“恋人间的权力”部分的选段。当鲍西亚对着巴萨尼奥倾诉肺腑，慨言为妻的忠诚时，当罗密欧说“朱丽叶所在的地方就是天堂”，为爱陨殉时，我们有幸，读到了这世上最美的情书。后来人再写年少的爱恋，难以超越了。莎士比亚，他是世间所有懂爱之人的知音。

莎翁没有上过大学，可他的语言之优美、词汇之丰饶，令人感佩，这或许恰巧印证了那句“虎豹出自山野”吧。在无数的莎翁著作中译本中，朱生豪先生的译笔尤健，既雅且达，颇现原著精髓。作为读者，我们只有以阅读来贡献敬仰。

假若没有《哈姆雷特》和《罗密欧与朱丽叶》，文学世界将少了怎样两颗明珠？假若没有莎翁，世界文学史有没有塌下一角的感觉？实在不敢想象。因此只好打开书，再读一遍莎翁的金句，感叹他那颗金子般的心。

乔敏

政府权力

哈姆莱特　第三幕　第三场

罗森格兰兹　每一个庶民都知道怎样远祸全身，一个身负天下重寄的人，尤其应该时刻不懈地防备危害的袭击。君主的薨逝不仅是个人的死亡，它像一个旋涡一样，凡是在它近旁的东西，都要被它卷去同归于尽；又像一个矗立在最高山峰上的巨轮，它的轮辐上连附着无数的小物件，当巨轮轰然崩裂的时候，那些小物件也跟着它一齐粉碎。国王的一声叹息，总是伴随着全国的呻吟。

（朱生豪　译）

理查二世　第三幕　第二场

理查王　不必问他在什么地方。谁也不准讲那些安慰的话儿，让我们谈谈坟墓、蛆虫和墓碑吧；让我们以泥土为纸，用我们淋雨的眼睛在大地的胸膛上写下我们的悲哀；让我们找几个遗产管理人，商议我们的遗嘱——可是这也不必，因为我们除了把一具尸骸还给大地以外，还有什么可以遗留给后人的？我们的土地、我们的生命，一切都是波林勃洛克的，只有死亡和掩埋我们骨骼的一黄土，才可以算是属于我们自己的。为了上帝的缘故，让我们坐在地上，讲些关于国王们的死亡的悲惨的故事。有些是被人废黜的，有些是在战场上阵亡的，有些是被他们所废黜的鬼魂们缠绕着的，有些是被他们的妻子所毒毙的，有些是在睡梦中被杀的，全都不得善终。因为在那围绕着一个凡世的国王头上的这顶空洞的王冠之内，正是死神驻节的宫廷，这妖魔高坐在里边，揶揄他的尊严，讪笑他的荣华，给他一段短短的呼吸的时间，让他在舞台上露一露脸，使他君临万民，受尽众人的敬畏，一眨眼就可以致人于死命，把妄自尊大的思想灌注他的心头，仿佛这包藏着我们生命的血肉的皮囊，是一堵不可摧毁的铜墙铁壁一样。当他这样志得意满的时候，却不知道他的末日已经临近眼前，一枚小小的针就可以刺破他的壁垒，于是再会吧，国王！戴上你们的帽子，不要把严肃的敬礼施在一个凡人的身上；丢开传统的礼貌，仪式的虚文，因为你们一向都把我认错了；像你们一样，我也靠着面包生活，我也有欲望，我也懂得悲哀，我也需要朋友。既然如此，你们怎么能对我说我是一个国王呢？

（朱生豪　译）

雅典的泰门　第四幕　第三场

艾帕曼特斯　要是你披上这身寒酸的衣服，目的只是要惩罚你自己的骄傲，那么很好；可是你是出于勉强的，倘然你不再是一个乞丐，你就会再去做一个廷臣。自愿的贫困胜如不定的浮华；穷奢极欲的人要是贪得无厌，比最贫困而知足的人更要不幸得多了。你既然这样困苦，应该但求速死。

泰门　我不会听了一个比我更倒霉的人的话而去寻死。你是一个奴隶，命运的温柔的手臂从来不曾拥抱过你。要是你从呱呱坠地的时候就跟我们一样，可以随心所欲地享受这浮世的欢娱，你一定已经沉溺在无边的放荡里，把你的青春消磨在左拥右抱之中，除了一味追求眼前的淫乐以外，再也不会知道那些冷冰冰的人伦道德。可是我，整个的世界曾经是我的糖果的作坊。人们的嘴、舌头、眼睛和心都争先恐后地等候着我的使唤，虽然我没有这许多工作可以给他们做。无数的人像叶子依附橡树一般依附着我，可是经不起冬风的一吹，他们便落下枝头，剩下我赤裸裸的枯干，去忍受风雨的摧残：像我这样享福过来的人，一旦挨受这种逆运，那才是一件难堪的重荷。你却是从开始时候就尝到人世的痛苦的，经验已经把你磨炼得十分坚强了。你为什么厌恶人类呢？他们从来没有向你献过媚。你曾经有些什么东西给人家呢？倘然你要咒骂，你就得咒骂你的父亲，那个穷酸的叫花，他因为一时起兴，和一个女乞婆养下了你这世袭的穷光蛋来。滚开！快去！倘然你不是生下来就是世间最下贱的人，你就是个奸佞的小人。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利五世　第一幕　第二场

坎特伯雷　所以上天把人体当作一个政体，赋予了性质各不同的机能；不同的机能使一个个欲求不断地见之于行动；而每一个行动，就像系附着同一种目标或者是同一种对象，也必然带来了整体的服从。蜜蜂就是这样发挥它们的效能，这种昆虫，凭着自己天性中的规律把秩序的法则教给了万民之邦。它们有一个王，有各司其职的官员。有些像地方官，在国内惩戒过失；也有些像闯码头、走外洋去办货的商人；还有些像兵丁，用尾刺做武器，在那夏季的丝绒似的花蕊中间大肆劫掠，然后欢欣鼓舞，把战利品往回搬运——运到大王升座的宝帐中。那日理万机的蜂王，可正在视察那哼着歌儿的泥水匠把金黄的屋顶给盖上。一般安分的老百姓又正在把蜂蜜酿造；可怜那脚夫们，肩上扛着重担，硬是要把小门挨进；只听见冷冷的一声“哼”，原来那瞪着眼儿的法官把那无所事事、呵欠连连的雄蜂发付给了脸色铁青的刽子手。我的结论是：许许多多的事情只要环绕着一个共同的目的，不妨分头进行，就像从各个不同的角度发出的箭，射向一个目标，东西南北的道路都通向一个城镇，千百条淡水的河流汇聚在一片咸海里，许多线条结合在日晷的中心点——就像这样，千头万绪的事业一旦动手，共同完成一个使命，什么都顺利进行，不会有一点儿差错。所以，到法兰西去吧，我的君主！把你那“快乐的英格兰”一分为四，这四分之一就给你带到法兰西去大显威风，叫高卢族人人发抖。而我们，以三倍的力量在国内防守，要是再不能扎紧藩篱，不许野狗钻进来，那么活该我们倒霉，叫恶狗扑身，丧尽了咱们民族的勇敢与政治上机警的英名。

（方平　译）

科利奥兰纳斯　第二幕　第二场

吏乙　老实说一句，有许多大人物尽管口头上拼命讨好平民，心里却一点不喜欢他们；也有许多人喜欢了一个人，却不知道为什么要喜欢他，他们既然会莫名其妙地爱他，也就会莫名其妙地恨他。所以科利奥兰纳斯对于他们的爱憎漠不关心，正可以表示他真正了解他们的性格；他也由他们去看得一清二楚，满不在意。

吏甲　要是他对于他们的爱憎漠不关心，那么他既不会有心讨好他们，也不会故意冒犯他们。可是他对他们寻衅的心理，却比他们对他仇恨的心理更强，凡是可以表明他是他们的敌人的事实，他总是不加讳饰地表现出来。像这样有意装出敌视人民的态度，比起他所唾弃的那种取媚人民以求得他们欢心的手段来，同样是不足为法的。

吏乙　他替国家立下了极大的功劳，他的跻登高位，绝不像那些毫无寸尺之功、单凭着向人民曲意逢迎的手段滥邀爵禄的人们那样容易。他的荣誉彪炳在他们的眼前，他的功业铭刻在他们的心底，他们要是不作一声，否认这一切，那就是忘恩负义；要是颠倒是非，混淆黑白，那就是恶意中伤。

吏甲　别讲他了，他是一个可尊敬的人。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利五世　第四幕　第二场

亨利王　要国王负责！那不妨把我们的生命、灵魂，把我们的债务、我们的操心的妻子、我们的孩子以及我们的罪恶，全都放在国王头上吧！他得一股脑儿担当下来。随着“伟大”而来的，是多么难堪的地位啊！听凭每个傻瓜来议论他——他们想到、感觉到的，只是个人的苦楚！做了国王，多少民间所享受的人生乐趣他就得放弃！而人君所享有的，有什么是平民百姓所享受不到的——只除了排场，只除了那众人前的排场？你又算是什么呢——你偶像似的排场？你比崇拜者忍受着更大的忧患，又是什么神明？你收到多少租金，又带来了多少进账？啊，排场，让我看一看你的价值是多少吧！你凭什么法宝叫人这样崇拜？除了地位、名衔、外表引起人们的敬畏与惶恐外，你还有些什么呢？你叫人惶恐，为什么反而不及那帮诚惶诚恐的人来得快乐呢？你天天喝下肚去的，除了有毒的谄媚代替了纯洁的尊敬外，还有什么呢？啊，伟大的“伟大”呀，且等你病倒了，吩咐你那套排场来给你治病吧！你可认为那沸烫的发烧，会因为一大堆一味奉承的字眼而退去吗？凭着那打躬作揖，病痛就会霍然而愈吗？当你命令乞丐向你双膝跪下的时候，你能同时命令他把康健献给你吗？不，你妄自尊大的幻梦啊，你这样善于戏弄帝王的安眠。我这一个国王早已看破了你。我明白，无论帝王加冕的圣油、权杖和那金球，也无论那剑、那御杖、那皇冠、那金线织成和珍珠镶嵌的王袍、那加在帝号前头的长长一连串荣衔；无论是他高踞的王位，或者是那煊赫尊荣，像声势浩大的潮浪泛滥了整个陆岸——不，这一切辉煌无比的排场，也不能让你睡在君王的床上，就像一个卑贱的奴隶那样睡得香甜。一个奴隶，塞饱了肚子，空着脑子，爬上床去——干了一天辛苦活儿，就再看不见那阴森森的、从地狱里产生的黑夜。他倒像是伺候太阳神的一个小厮，从日出到日落，只是在阳光里挥汗，到了晚上，就在乐园里睡个通宵。第二天天一亮，又一骨碌起身，赶着替太阳神把骏马套上了车。年年月月，他就干着这营生，直到进入了坟墓。像这样，一个奴隶，欠缺的就只是煊赫的排场，要不然，他日出而作，日落而息，远远地胜过了做一个皇帝。他浑浑噩噩、安安稳稳地过着太平日子，全没想到做人君的为了维护这太平世界，对着孤灯，操着怎样一片心。他宵旰勤劳，到头来却是那村夫最受用。

（方平　译）

一报还一报　第一幕　第一场

公爵　关于政治方面的种种机宜，我不必多向你絮说，因为我知道你在这方面的经验阅历，胜过我所能给你的任何指示。对于地方上人民的习性，以及布政施教的宪章、信赏必罚的律法，你也都了如指掌，比得上任何博学练达之士，所以我尽可信任你的才能，让你自己去适宜应付。我给你这一道诏书，愿你依此而行。（以诏书授爱斯卡勒斯）来人，去唤安哲鲁过来。（一侍从下）你看，他这人能不能代理我的责任？因为我在再三考虑之下，已经决定当我出巡的时候，叫他摄理政务；他可以充分享受众人的畏惧爱敬，全权处置一切的事情。你以为怎样？

爱斯卡勒斯　在维也纳地方，要是有人值得受这样隆重的眷宠恩荣，那就是安哲鲁大人了。

公爵　他来了。（安哲鲁上。）

安哲鲁　听见殿下的召唤，小臣特来恭听谕令。

公爵　安哲鲁，在你的生命中有一种与众不同的地方，使人家一眼便知道你全部的为人。你自己和你所有的一切，倘不拿出来贡献于人世，仅仅一个人独善其身，那实在是一种浪费。上天生下我们，是要把我们当作火炬，不是照亮自己，而是普照世界。因为我们的德行倘不能推及他人，那就等于没有一样。一个人有了才华智慧，必须使它产生有益的结果。造物是一个工于算计的女神，她所给予世人的每一分才智，都要受赐的人知恩感激，加倍报答。可是我虽然这样对你说，也许我倒是更应该受你教益的，所以请你收下这道诏书吧，安哲鲁。（以诏书授安哲鲁）当我不在的时候，你就是我的全权代表，你的片言一念，可以决定维也纳人民的生死，年高的爱斯卡勒斯虽然先受到我的嘱托，他却是你的辅佐。

（朱生豪　译）

理查二世　第五幕　第五场

理查王　我正在研究怎样可以把我所栖身的这座牢狱和整个的世界两相比较，可是因为这世上充满了人类，这儿除了我一身之外，没有其他的生物，所以它们是比较不起来的。虽然这样说，我还要仔细思考一下。我要证明我的头脑是我心灵的妻子，我的心灵是我思想的父亲；它们两个产下了一代生生不息的思想，这些思想充斥在这小小的世界之上，正像世上的人们一般互相倾轧，因为没有一个思想是满足的。比较好的那些思想，例如关于宗教方面的思想，却和怀疑互相间杂，往往援用经文的本身攻击经文。譬如说，“来吧，小孩子们，”可是接着又这么说，“到天国去是像骆驼穿过针孔一般艰难的。”野心勃勃的思想总在计划不可能的奇迹，凭着这些脆弱无力的指爪，怎样从这冷酷的世界的坚硬的肋骨、我的凹凸不平的囚墙上，抓破一条出路。可是因为它们没有这样的能力，所以只能在它们自己的盛气之中死去。安分自足的思想却用这样的话安慰自己：它们并不是命运的最初的奴隶，不会是它的最后的奴隶；正像愚蠢的乞丐套上了枷，自以为许多人都在他以前套过枷，在他以后，也还有别的人要站在他现在所站的地方，用这样的思想掩饰他们的羞辱一样。凭着这一种念头，它们获得了精神上的宽裕，假借过去的人们同样的遭际来背负它们不幸的灾祸。这样我一个人扮演着许多不同的角色，没有一个能够满足他自己的命运：有时我是国王；叛逆的奸谋使我希望我是一个乞丐，于是我就变成了乞丐；可是压人的穷困劝诱我还不如做一个国王，于是我又变成了国王；一会儿忽然想到我的王位已经被波林勃洛克所推翻，那时候我就立刻化为乌有；可是无论我是什么人，无论是我还是别人，只要是一个人，在他没有彻底化为乌有以前，是什么也不能使他感到满足的。

（朱生豪　译）

雅典的泰门　第一幕　第一场

诗人　您瞧这一大群蝇营蚁附的宾客。在我的拙作中间，我勾画出了一个受尽世俗爱宠的人。可是我并不单单着力作个人的描写，我让我的恣肆的笔锋在无数的模型之间活动，不带一丝恶意，只是像凌空的鹰隼一样，一往直前，不留下一丝痕迹。

画师　您的意思我有点不大懂得。

诗人　我可以解释给您听。您瞧各种不同地位不同性情的人，无论是轻浮油滑的，或是严肃庄重的，都愿意为泰门大爷效劳服役。他的巨大的财产，再加上他的善良和蔼的天性，征服了各种不同的人，使他们乐于向他输诚致敬。从那些脸上反映出主人的喜怒的谄媚者起，直到憎恨自己的艾帕曼特斯，一个个在他的面前屈膝，只要泰门点点头，就可以使他们满载而归。

画师　我曾经看见他跟艾帕曼特斯在一起谈话。

诗人　先生，我假定命运的女神端坐在一座巍峨而幽美的山上，在那山麓下面，有无数智愚贤不肖的人劳心劳力，追求世间的名利，他们的眼睛都一致注视着这位主宰一切的女神。我把其中一个人代表泰门，命运女神用她象牙一样洁白的手招引他到她的身边，他是她眼前的恩宠，他的敌人也一齐变成了他的奴仆。

画师　果然是很巧妙的设想。我想这一个宝座、这一位命运女神和这一座山，在这山下的许多人中间只有一个人得到女神的招手，这个人正弓着身子向峻峭的山崖爬去，攀登到幸福的顶端，很可以表现出我们这儿的情形。

诗人　不，先生，听我说下去。那些在不久以前还和他同样地位的人，也有一些本来胜过他的人，现在都跟在他后面亦步亦趋。他的接待室里挤满了关心他的起居的人，他的耳朵中充满了一片有如向神圣祷告那样的低语，连他的马镫也被奉为神圣，他们从他那里呼吸到自由的空气。

画师　好，那便怎么样呢？

诗人　当命运突然改变了心肠，把她的宠儿一脚踢下山坡的时候，那些攀龙附凤之徒，本来跟在他后面匍匐膝行的，这时候便会冷眼看他跌落，没有一个人做他患难中的同伴。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世上篇　第一幕　第二场

福斯塔夫　呃，我说，乖乖好孩子，等你做了国王以后，不要让我们这些夜间的绅士们被人称为掠夺白昼的佳丽的窃贼。让我们成为狄安娜的猎户、月亮的嬖宠，让人家说，我们都是很有节制的人，因为正像海水一般，我们受着我们高贵纯洁的女王月亮的节制，我们是在她的许可之下偷窃的。

亲王　你说得好，一点不错，因为我们这些月亮的信徒们既然像海水一般受着月亮的节制，我们的命运也像海水一般起伏无定。举例说，星期一晚上出了死力抢下来的一袋金钱，星期二早上便会把它胡乱花去；凭着一声吆喝“放下”把它抓到手里，喊了几回“酒来”就花得一文不剩。有时潦倒不堪，可是也许有一天时来运转，两脚腾空，高升绞架。

（朱生豪　译）

理查二世　第三幕　第四场

园丁　去，你把那边垂下来的杏子扎起来，它们像顽劣的子女一般，使他们的老父因为不胜重负而弯腰屈背，那些弯曲的树枝你要把它们支撑住了。你去做一个刽子手，斩下那些长得太快的小枝的头，它们在咱们的共和国里显得太高傲了，咱们国里一切都应该平等的。你们去做各人的事，我要去割下那些有害的莠草，它们本身没有一点用处，却会吸收土壤中的肥料，阻碍鲜花的生长。

仆甲　我们何必在这小小的围墙之内保持着法纪、秩序和有条不紊的布置，夸耀我们雏形的治绩。你看我们那座以大海为围墙的花园，我们整个国土，不是莠草蔓生，她的最美的鲜花全都窒息而死，她的果树无人修剪，她的篱笆东倒西歪，她的花池凌乱无序，她的佳卉异草被虫儿蛀得枝叶凋残吗？

园丁　不要胡说。那容忍着这样一个凌乱无序的春天的人，自己已经遭到落叶飘零的命运；那些托庇于他的广布的枝叶之下，名为拥护他，实则在吮吸他的精液的莠草，全都被波林勃洛克连根拔起了。我的意思是说威尔特郡伯爵和布希、格林那些人们。

仆甲　什么！他们死了吗？

园丁　他们都死了，波林勃洛克已经捉住那个浪荡的国王。啊！可惜他不曾像我们治理这座花园一般治理他的国土！我们每年按着时季，总要略微割破我们果树的外皮，因为恐怕它们过于肥茂，反而结不出果子。要是他能够用同样的手段，对付那些威权日盛的人们，他们就可以自知戒饬，他也可以尝到他们忠心的果实。对于多余的旁枝，我们总是毫不吝惜地把它们剪去，让那结果的干枝繁荣滋长。要是他也能够采取这样的办法，他就可以保全他的王冠，不至于在嬉戏游乐之中把它轻易断送了。

（朱生豪　译）

李尔王　第三幕　第一场

高纳里尔　父亲，我们家里难道没有两倍这么多的仆人可以侍候您？依我说，不但用不着二十五个人，就是十个五个也是多余的。

里根　依我看来，一个也不需要。

李尔　啊！不要跟我说什么需要不需要。最卑贱的乞丐，也有他的不值钱的身外之物，人生除了天然的需要以外，要是没有其他的享受，那和畜类的生活有什么分别。你是一位夫人，你穿着这样华丽的衣服，如果你的目的只是为了保持温暖，那就根本不合你的需要，因为这种盛装艳饰并不能使你温暖。可是，讲到真的需要，那么天啊，给我忍耐吧，我需要忍耐！神啊，你们看见我在这儿，一个可怜的老头子，被忧伤和老迈折磨得好苦！假如是你们鼓动这两个女儿的心，使她们忤逆她们的父亲，那么请你们不要尽是愚弄我，叫我默然忍受吧。让我的心里激起了刚强的怒火，别让妇人所恃为武器的泪点玷污我的男子汉的面颊！不，你们这两个不孝的妖妇，我要向你们复仇，我要作出一些使全世界惊怖的事情来，虽然我现在还不知道我要怎么做。你们以为我将要哭泣？不，我不愿哭泣，我虽然有充分的哭泣的理由，可是我宁愿让这颗心碎成万片，也不愿流下一滴泪来。啊，傻瓜！我要发疯了！

（朱生豪　译）

十四行诗　九四

谁有力量损害人而不这样干，

谁不做人以为他们爱做的事，

谁使人动情，自己却石头一般，

冰冷、无动于衷，对诱惑能抗拒——

谁就恰当地承受上天的恩宠，

善于贮藏和保管造化的财富；

他们才是自己美貌的主人翁，

而别人只是自己姿色的家奴。

夏天的花把夏天熏得多芳馥，

虽然对自己它只自开又自落，

但是那花若染上卑劣的病毒，

最贱的野草也比它高贵得多：

极香的东西一腐烂就成极臭，

烂百合花比野草更臭得难受。

（梁宗岱　译）

裘力思·凯撒　第一幕　第二场

凯歇斯　嘿，老兄，他像一个巨人似的跨越这狭隘的世界，我们这些渺小的凡人一个个在他粗大的两腿下行走，四处张望着，替自己寻找不光荣的坟墓。人们有时可以支配他们自己的命运。要是我们受制于人，亲爱的勃鲁托斯，那错处并不在我们的命运，而在我们自己。勃鲁托斯和凯撒，“凯撒”那个名字又有什么了不得？为什么人们只是提起它而不提起勃鲁托斯？把那两个名字写在一起，您的名字并不比他的难看；放在嘴上念起来，它也一样顺口；称起重量来，它们是一样的重；要是用它们呼神召鬼，“勃鲁托斯”也可以同样感动幽灵，正像“凯撒”一样。凭着一切天神的名字，我们这位凯撒究竟吃些什么美食，才会长得这样伟大？可耻的时代！罗马啊，你的高贵血统已经中断了！自从洪水以后，什么时代你不曾产生比一个更多的著名人物？直到现在为止，什么时候人们谈起罗马，能够说，她的广大的城墙之内，只是一个人的世界？要是罗马给一个人独占了去，那么它真的变成无人之境了。啊！你我都曾听见我们的父老说过，从前罗马有一个勃鲁托斯，不愿让他的国家被一个君主所统治，正像他不愿让它被永劫的恶魔统治一样。

（朱生豪　译）

科利奥兰纳斯　第二幕　第三场

勃鲁托斯　你们难道不会凭着你们所受的教训，对他说当他还没有掌握权力、不过是政府里一个地位卑微的仆人的时候，他就是你们的敌人，老是反对着你们的自由和你们在这共和国里所享有的特权吗？你们难道不会对他说，现在他登上了秉持国家大权的地位，要是他仍旧怀着恶意，继续做平民的死敌，那么你们现在所表示的同意，不将要成为你们自己的咒诅吗？你们应当对他说，他伟大的功业，既然可以使他享有他所要求的地位而无愧色，但愿他仁厚的天性，也能够想到你们现在所给他的同情的赞助，而把他对你们的敌意变成友谊，永远做你们慈爱的执政。

西西涅斯　你们照这样对他说了以后，就可以触动他的心性，试探他的真正的意向。也许他会给你们善意的允诺，那么将来倘有需要的时候，你们就可以责令他履行旧约。也许那会激怒他的暴戾的天性，因为他是不能容忍任何拘束的，这样引动了他的恼怒，你们就可以他的恶劣的脾气做理由，拒绝他当执政。

勃鲁托斯　你们看他在需要你们好感的时候，会用这样公然侮蔑的态度向你们请求，难道你们没有想到当他有权力压迫你们的时候，他这种侮蔑的态度不会变成公然的伤害吗？怎么，你们胸膛里难道都是没有心的吗？或者，你们的舌头会反抗理智的判断吗？

西西涅斯　你们以前不是曾经拒绝过向你们请求的人吗？现在他并没有请求你们，不过把你们讥笑了一顿，你们却会毫不迟疑地给他同意吗？

市民丙　他还没有经过正式的确认，我们还可以拒绝他。

市民乙　我们一定要拒绝他，我可以号召五百个人反对他就任。

市民甲　好，就是一千个人也不难，还可以叫他们各人拉些朋友来充数。

勃鲁托斯　你们立刻就去，告诉你们那些朋友，说他们已经选了一个执政，他将会剥夺他们的自由，限制他们发言的权利，把他们当作狗一样看待，虽然为了要它们吠叫而豢养，可是往往因为它们吠叫而把它们痛打。

（朱生豪　译）

奥瑟罗　第一幕　第一场

伊阿古　我之所以跟随他，不过是要利用他达到我自己的目的。我们不能每个人都是主人，每个主人也不是都该让仆人忠心地追随他。你可以看到，有一辈天生的奴才，他们卑躬屈节，拼命讨主人的好，甘心受主人的鞭策，像一头驴子似的，为了一些粮草而出卖他们的一生，等到年纪老了，主人就把他们撵走。这种老实的奴才是应该抽一顿鞭子的。还有一种人，尽管表面上装出一副鞠躬如也的样子，骨子里却是为他们自己打算；看上去好像替主人做事，实际却靠着主人发展自己的势力，等捞足了油水，就可以知道他所尊敬的其实是他本人。像这种人还有几分头脑，我承认我自己就属于这一类。因为，老兄，正像你是罗德利哥而不是别人一样，我要是做了那摩尔人，我就不会是伊阿古。同样，虽说我跟随他，其实还是跟随我自己。上天是我的公证人，我这样对他赔着小心，既不是为了忠心，也不是为了义务，只是为了自己的利益，才装出这一副假脸。要是我表面上的恭而敬之的行为会泄露我内心的活动，那么不久我就要掏出我的心来，让乌鸦们乱啄了。世人所知道的我，并不是实在的我。

（朱生豪　译）

理查三世　第三幕　第七场

勃金汉　那就请听我冒昧陈词吧，您不该再三推辞，放弃至尊的宝座，那是您祖代相传的威权所在，是您福运降临，也是您世袭而来的名分。您奕奕皇室的世代光荣，岂能由您让给一支腐朽的系族。您在高枕无忧之中悠思遐想，而这块皇土正等待着大力扶持，为国家前途计，我们特来敦促您醒悟过来。如今纲常不振，面目全非，皇朝正统，平添枯枝残叶，无以生根，势必陷落深渊，从此湮没无闻。为了拯救这种颓运，我们衷心请求殿下亲自负起国家重任，掌握王权；不再为人作嫁，做一个护政者、家宰、代理人，或当一个卑贱的经手员；您应该维护血统，继承王业，本是您生来的权利，是您的领土，应归您自有。为此之故，我和市民们一起，还有您的虔诚热情的朋友们，都急切地催促着我来向殿下发出这正义呼声，求您垂听下情。

葛罗斯特　以我的地位或您的处境看来，我不知道该默然离去，还是该严斥您一番。如果我不予作答，您或许认为我是个守口如瓶的野心家，是我眼见您一厢情愿地把那辉煌的重担套上我的肩头，而我却默然承受下来了。如果我见您一片至诚，向我求告，我反而横加斥责，这岂不是我又杜绝了友辈的言路。因此，我该既不默然而去，也不严词驳斥，却把我的心头思念向您作明确的答复。您的热诚值得我衷心感激，但是对我要求过分，我自愧无能，怕难孚众望。首先，即使一切障碍都能扫除，我面前这条登基的道路已经铺平，创业时机已经成熟，只等我继承正统，可是我志气还不够高昂，我德行菲薄，瑕疵多端，缺陷重大，我宁愿闭门思过，以免卷入洪流。好比一叶扁舟，岂敢驶进大海，一旦涌上浪巅，欲罢不能，那就只好在彩光烟雾之中窒息而死了。好在今天还不需要我，感谢上帝。如果讲到需要，我正该多下功夫，自助助人。王室系族留下了王室子嗣，经过日换星移，自可成长起来，来日坐镇朝廷，你我都会臣服而乐事新君。您所要委我的重任，我加在他身上，是天命所归，也是他权分所在。上帝不容我强夺他的王权！

勃金汉　我的大人，这确实说明您心地磊落。无奈从多方考虑，您所顾念的都是些不可捉摸的细节。您说爱德华是您大哥的儿子，我们也如此说，却不出自他的妻。早先他和露西夫人订过婚约，至今还有您在世的母亲可以作证，后来又通过中间人去法国，向法王的姨妹波娜求婚结盟。此后两人都遭冷落，于是一个多儿的寡母，色衰福浅，竟然乞怜求诉，她虽青春已逝，年已半老，君王却贪淫无度，眉目传情，好比鹰鸟高飞半空，忽而窜落，以致伤风败俗，寡妇重婚。因此一场漠视法纪的结合传下了这个小爱德华，为了保持体面，称为太子。我本可深入揭露，但是为未亡人留些余地，我且话到口边暂留三分。所以，我的好大人，愿您亲自接过我们所呈献的至尊权位，即使不为我们和全国的幸福着想，也该把这祖传的尊贵血统继承下去，匡时拯世，恢复真正的纲纪。

市长　接受吧，好大人；您的市民在请求您了。

勃金汉　伟大的主君，莫拒绝这诚心的献礼。

凯茨比　呵！让他们欢庆吧，允许他们的合理请求吧！

葛罗斯特　唉！你们何必硬要把重担堆在我身上呢？我不配治理国家，不应称君王。务必请你们不要误会，我不能，也不愿，听从你们的要求。

勃金汉　如果您拒绝所请，一心为了爱护您的侄儿，不忍将他废黜。诚如我们在您日常与亲朋过往，处世接物之中，知道您一向心地温厚，待人体贴入微，无奈此刻我们已顾不得您接受与否，反正不能由您侄儿在我国称为君王；我们只好拥立他人继承王位，那样，您的王室势必声名扫地，倾覆无闻：现在我们谨作此决定，并向您告辞。市民们，走吧，我们不再请求了。

（勃金汉与市民们下。）

凯茨比　叫他们回来，好主君；接受他们的请求。您如果再不应允，全国都要遭殃了。

葛罗斯特　你们真要逼我负起这样烦心的重任吗？叫他们回来；我何尝是铁石心肠，虽然违拗我的心性，我岂能辜负盛情，顽固到底。（凯茨比下。）

（勃金汉及众人重上。）

葛罗斯特勃金汉贤弟，各位父老，你们既不顾我是否愿意，坚持要把命运的重担压上我肩头，勉强我负起重任，从此我就不得不任劳负重，忍受下去。但是万一在你们迫使我登位之后，假若有人暗中攻讦，或破口辱骂，那么此事既由你们促成，一切垢污糟蹋都应与我无关。上帝知道，你们也可能见到，这是一件多么违反我心愿的事。

市长　上帝祝福您，殿下！我们看见了真情，我们要让大家知道。

葛罗斯特　你们宣扬出去必须根据事实。

勃金汉　现在我向您称君道贺：理查王万岁，英国的尊君万岁！

全体　阿门。

（方重　译）

特洛伊罗斯与克瑞西达　第一幕　第三场

俄底修斯　特洛亚至今兀立不动，没有给我们攻下，赫克托的宝剑仍旧在它主人的手里，这都是因为我们漠视了军令的森严。看这一带大军驻屯的阵地，散布着多少虚有其表的营寨，都怀着各不相下的私心。大将就像是一个蜂房里的蜂王，要是采蜜的工蜂大家各自为政，不把采得的粮食归献蜂王，那么还有什么蜜可以酿得出来呢？尊卑的等级可以不分，那么最微贱的人，也可以和最有才能的人分庭抗礼了。满天的星辰，在运行的时候，都恪守着自身的等级和地位，遵循着各自不变的轨道，依照着一定的范围、季候和方式，履行它们经常的职责，所以灿烂的太阳才能高拱出天，洞察寰宇，纠正星辰的过失，遏恶扬善，发挥它的无上威权。可是众星如果出了常轨，陷入了混乱的状态，那么多少的灾祸、变异、叛乱、海啸、地震、风暴、惊骇，将要震撼、摧裂、破坏、毁灭这宇宙间的和谐！纪律是达到一切雄图的阶梯，要是纪律发生动摇，啊！那时候事业的前途也就变黯淡了。要是没有纪律，社会上的秩序怎么得以稳定？学校中的班次怎么得以整齐？城市中的和平怎么得以保持？各地间的贸易怎么得以畅通？法律上所规定的与生俱来的特权，以及尊长、君王、统治者、胜利者所享有的特殊权利，怎么得以确立不坠？只要把纪律的琴弦拆去，听吧！多少刺耳的噪音就会发出来；一切都是互相抵触；江河里的水会泛滥得高过堤岸，淹没整个世界；强壮的要欺凌老弱，不孝的儿子要打死他的父亲；威力将代替公理，没有是非之分，也没有正义存在。那时候权力便是一切，而凭仗着权力，便可以逞着自己的意志，放纵无厌的贪欲。欲望，这一头贪心不足的饿狼，得到了意志和权力的两重辅佐，势必至于把全世界供它的馋吻，然后把自己也吃下去。伟大的阿伽门农，这一种混乱的状态，只有在纪律被人扼杀以后才会发生。就是因为漠视了纪律，有意前进的才反而会向后退却。主帅被他属下的将领所轻视，那将领又被他的属下所轻视，这样上行下效，谁都瞧不起他的长官，结果就引起了猜忌争竞的心理，损害了整个军队的元气。特洛亚所以至今兀立不动，不是靠着它自己的力量，乃是靠着我们的这一种弱点；换句话说，它的生命是全赖我们的弱点替它支持下来的。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世下篇　第三幕　第一场

亨利王　我的几千个最贫贱的人民正在这时候酣然熟睡！睡眠啊！柔和的睡眠啊！大自然的温情的保姆，我怎样惊吓了你，你才不愿再替我闭上我的眼皮，把我的感觉沉浸在忘河之中？为什么，睡眠，你宁愿栖身在烟熏的茅屋里，在不舒适的草荐上伸展你的肢体，让嗡嗡作声的蚊虫催着你入梦，却不愿偃息在香雾氤氲的王侯的深宫之中，在华贵的宝帐之下，让最甜美的乐声把你陶醉？啊，你冥漠的神灵！为什么你在污秽的床上和下贱的愚民同寝，却让国王的卧榻变成一个表盒子或是告变的警钟？在巍峨高耸惊心眩目的桅杆上，你不是会使年轻的水手闭住他的眼睛吗？当天风海浪做他的摇篮，那巨大的浪头被风卷上高高的云端，发出震耳欲聋的喧声，即使死神也会被它从睡梦中惊醒的时候。啊，偏心的睡眠！你能够在那样惊险的时候，把你的安息给予一个风吹浪打的水手，可是在最宁静安谧的晚间，最温暖舒适的环境之中，你却不让一个国王享受你的厚惠吗？那么，幸福的卑贱者啊，安睡吧！戴王冠的头是不能安于他的枕席的。

（朱生豪　译）

家族权力

威尼斯商人　第三幕　第二场

鲍西娅　巴萨尼奥公子，您瞧我站在这儿，不过是这样的一个人。虽然为了我自己的缘故，我不愿妄想自己比现在的我更好一点，可是为了您的缘故，我希望我能够六十倍胜过我的本身，再加上一千倍的美丽，一万倍的富有。但愿我有无比的贤德、美貌、财产和亲友，好让我在您的心目中占据一个很高的位置。可是我这一身却是一无所有，我只是一个不学无术、没有教养、缺少见识的女子。幸亏她的年纪还不是顶大，来得及发愤学习；她的天资也不是顶笨，可以加以教导；尤其大幸的是，她有一颗柔顺的心灵，愿意把它奉献给您，听从您的指导，把您当作她的主人、她的统治者和她的君王。我自己以及我所有的一切，现在都变成您的所有了。刚才我还拥有着这一座华丽的大厦，我的仆人都听从着我的指挥，我是支配我自己的女王，可是就在现在，这屋子、这些仆人和这一个我，都是属于您的了，我的夫君。凭着这一个指环，我把这一切完全呈献给您。要是您让这指环离开您的身边，或者把它丢了，或者把它送给别人，那就预示着您的爱情的毁灭，我可以因此责怪您的。

（朱生豪　译）

李尔王　第一幕　第一场

李尔　现在我要向你们说明我的心事。把那地图给我。告诉你们吧，我已经把我的国土划成三部；我因为自己年纪老了，决心摆脱一切事务的牵萦，把责任交卸给年轻力壮之人，让自己松一松肩，好安安心心地等死。康华尔贤婿，还有同样是我心爱的奥本尼贤婿，为了预防他日的争执，我想还是趁现在把我的几个女儿的嫁妆当众分配清楚。法兰西和勃艮第两位君主正在竞争我的小女儿的爱情，他们为了求婚而住在我们宫廷里，也已经有好多时候了，现在他们就可以得到答复。孩子们，在我还没有把我的政权、领土和国事的重任全部放弃以前，告诉我，你们中间哪一个人最爱我？我要看看谁最有孝心，最有贤德，我就给她最大的恩惠。高纳里尔，我的大女儿，你先说。

高纳里尔　父亲，我对您的爱，不是言语所能表达的。我爱您胜过自己的眼睛、整个的空间和广大的自由；超越一切可以估价的贵重稀有的事物；不亚于赋有淑德、健康、美貌和荣誉的生命。不曾有一个儿女这样爱过他的父亲，也不曾有一个父亲这样被他的儿女所爱。这一种爱可以使唇舌无能为力，辩才失去效用，我爱您是不可以数量计算的。

考狄利娅（旁白）考狄利娅应该怎么好呢？默默地爱着吧。

李尔　在这些疆界以内，从这一条界线起，直到这一条界线为止，所有一切浓密的森林、膏腴的平原、富庶的河流、广大的牧场，都要奉你为它们的女主人；这一块土地永远为你和奥本尼的子孙所保有。我的二女儿，最亲爱的里根，康华尔的夫人，你怎么说？

里根　我跟姊姊具有同样的品质，您凭着她就可以判断我。在我的真心之中，我觉得她刚才所说的话，正是我爱您的实际的情形，可是她还不能充分说明我的心理：我厌弃一切凡是敏锐的知觉所能感受到的快乐，只有爱您才是我无上的幸福。

考狄利娅（旁白）那么，考狄利娅，你只好自安于贫穷了！可是我并不贫穷，因为我深信我的爱心比我的口才更富有。

李尔　这一块从我们这美好的王国中划分出来的三分之一的沃壤，是你和你的子孙永远世袭的产业，和高纳里尔所得到的那份同样广大、同样富庶，也同样佳美。现在，我的宝贝，虽然是最后的一个，却并非最不在我的心头，法兰西的葡萄和勃艮第的乳酪都在竞争你的青春之爱，你有些什么话，可以换到一份比你的两个姊姊更富庶的土地？说吧。

考狄利娅　父亲，我没有话说。

李尔　没有？

考狄利娅　没有。

李尔　没有只能换到没有，重新说过。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世下篇　第二幕　第三场

潘西夫人　啊！可是为了上帝的缘故，不要去参加这种战争吧。公公，您曾经毁弃过对您自己更有切身关系的诺言。您的亲生的潘西，我那心爱的哈利，曾经好多次引颈北望，盼他的父亲带着援兵到来，可是他终于望了个空。那时候是谁劝您不要出兵的？两重的荣誉已经丧失了，您自己的荣誉和您儿子的荣誉。讲到您自己的荣誉，愿上帝扫清它的雾障吧！他的荣誉却是和他不可分的，正像太阳永远高悬在苍苍的天宇之上一样；全英国的骑士都在他的光辉鼓舞之下，表现了他们英雄的身手。他的确是高贵的青年们的一面立身的明镜。谁不曾学会他的步行的姿态，等于白生了两条腿。说话急速不清本来是他天生的缺点，现在却成为勇士们应有的语调，那些能够用低声而迂缓的调子讲话的人，都宁愿放弃他们自己的特长，模拟他这一种缺点。这样无论在语音上、步态上、饮食娱乐上、性情气质上、治军作战上，他的一言一动，都是他人效法的规范。然而他，啊，天神一般的他！啊，人类中的奇男子！这盖世无双的他，却得不到您的援助，你竟忍心让他在不利的形势中，面对着狰狞可怖的战神。让他孤军苦战，除了霍茨波的英名之外，再也没有可以抵御敌人的武力，您是这样离弃了他！千万不要，啊！千万不要再给他的亡魂这样的侮辱，把您对于别人的信誉看得比您对于他的信誉更重。让他们去吧。那司礼大臣和那大主教的实力是很强大的，要是我那亲爱的哈利有他们一半的军力，今天也许我可以攀住霍茨波的颈项，听他谈起蒙穆斯的死了。

诺森伯兰　哎哟，贤媳！你用这样悲痛的申诉重新揭发我往日的过失，使我的心都寸寸碎裂了。

（朱生豪　译）

理查三世　第四幕　第四场

玛格莱特王后　我曾称你为我的幸运墙上所加的浮雕；称你为可怜的阴影，一个画中王后。你无非把我过去的声势来模仿，为一场大悲剧做了一些动听的剧情说明。哪怕你一时趾高气扬，终究要堕入尘埃。你枉做了一对伶俐的孩子的母亲。过去的一切都成了梦境、泡影、一块高贵的招牌、一面炫耀的旗帜，突兀招展着供人射击。一国之后做了笑柄，在舞台上不过串演着一个配角。如今你丈夫何在？你兄弟何在？你孩子何在？人生乐趣又何在？谁还来跪求你，高呼着“神佑吾后”？一向对你卑躬屈节的大臣们哪儿去了？追随你的大队人马又哪儿去了？前后对照就看清了你的处境：快乐的妻子成为最不幸的寡妇；幸福的母亲却在因为身为母亲而悲伤；坐听人诉的人反向人哭诉；国后变为愁眉蹙额的贱婢；从前轻慢我而今遭我轻慢；从前人人怕你，如今单怕一人；一向发号施令，如今无人听命。可见天道循环，赏罚分明，你只落得在时间的鹰爪下做个牺牲者；你倘若只顾怀念过去，同时又无法摆脱目前的处境，你的苦难将更难忍受。你既僭占了我的名位，岂能不分摊其中的苦楚？如今你的傲骨分挑着我的重担，我正好抽出我劳顿的肩头，把这全副担子都卸给你。再会吧，约克的夫人，厄运的王后；英国的这些忧伤，将在法国供我作笑料。

（方重　译）

仲夏夜之梦　第一幕　第一场

伊吉斯　我怀着满心的气恼，来控诉我的孩子，我的女儿赫米娅。走上前来，狄米特律斯。殿下，这个人，是我答应把我女儿嫁给他的。走上前来，拉山德。殿下，这个人引诱坏了我的孩子。你，你，拉山德，你写诗句给我的孩子，和她交换着爱情的纪念物；你在月夜到她的窗前用做作的声调歌唱着假作多情的诗篇；你用头发编成的腕环、戒指、虚华的饰物、琐碎的玩具、花束、糖果——这些可以强烈地骗诱一个稚嫩的少女之心的“信使”来偷得她的痴情；你用诡计盗取了她的心，煽惑她使她对我的顺从变成倔强的顽抗。殿下，假如她现在当着您的面仍旧不肯嫁给狄米特律斯，我就要要求雅典自古相传的权利，因为她是我的女儿，我可以随意处置她。按照我们的法律，逢到这样的情况，她要是不嫁给这位绅士，便应当立时处死。

忒修斯　你有什么话说，赫米娅？当心一点吧，美貌的姑娘！你的父亲对于你应当是一尊神明。你的美貌是他给予的，你就像在他手中捏成的一块蜡像，他可以保全你，也可以毁灭你。狄米特律斯是一个很好的绅士呢。

赫米娅　拉山德也很好啊。

忒修斯　他本人当然很好，但是要做你的丈夫，如果不能得到你父亲的同意，那么比起来他就要差一筹了。

赫米娅　我真希望我的父亲和我有同样的看法。

忒修斯　实在还是应该你依从你父亲的看法才对。

赫米娅　请殿下宽恕我！我不知道是什么一种力量使我如此大胆，也不知道在这里披诉我的心思将会怎样影响到我的美名，但是我要敬问殿下，要是我拒绝嫁给狄米特律斯，会有什么最恶的命运临到我的头上？

忒修斯　不是受死刑，便是永远和男人隔绝。因此，美丽的赫米娅，仔细问一问你自己的心愿吧！考虑一下你的青春，好好地估量一下你血脉中的搏动。倘然不肯服从你父亲的选择，就想想看能不能披上尼姑的道服，终生幽闭在阴沉的庵院中，向着凄凉寂寞的明月唱着暗淡的圣歌，做一个孤寂的修道女了此一生？她们能这样抑制热情，到老保持处女的贞洁，自然应当格外受到上天的眷宠。但是结婚的女子有如被采下炼制过的玫瑰，香气留存不散，比之孤独地自开自谢，奄然朽腐的花儿，在尘俗的眼光看来，总是要幸福得多了。

赫米娅　就让我这样自开自谢吧，殿下，我不愿意把我的贞操奉献给我心里并不敬服的人。

（朱生豪　译）

冬天的故事　第一幕　第二场

赫米温妮　假如您需要我们，我们就在园里，我们就在那边等着您好吗？

里昂提斯　随你们便吧，只要你们不飞到天上去，总可以找得到的。我现在在垂钓，虽然你们没有看见我放下钓线去。好吧，好吧！瞧她那么把嘴向他送过去！简直像个妻子对她正式的丈夫那样无所顾忌！（波力克希尼斯、赫米温妮及侍从等下）已经去了！一顶绿头巾已经稳稳地戴上了！去玩去吧，孩子，玩去吧。你妈在玩着，我也在玩着，可是我扮的是这么一个丢脸的角色，准要给人喝倒彩嘘下了坟墓去的，轻蔑和讥笑便是我的葬钟。去玩去吧，孩子，玩去吧。要是我不曾弄错，那么乌龟这东西确是从来便有的。即使在现在，当我说这话的时候，一定就有许多人抱着他的妻子，却不知道她在他不在的时候早已给别人揩过油；他自己池子里的鱼，已经给他笑脸的邻居捞了去。我道不孤，聊堪自慰。假如有了不贞的妻子的男人全都怨起命来，世界上十分之一的人类都要上吊死了。补救的办法是一点没有的。正像有一个荒淫的星球，照临人世，到处惹是招非。你想，东南西北，无论哪处都抵挡不过肚子底下的作怪；魔鬼简直可以带了箱笼行李堂而皇之地进出呢。我们中间有千万个人都害着这毛病，但自己却不觉得。

（朱生豪　译）

暴风雨　第一幕　第二场

米兰达　亲爱的父亲，假如你曾经用你的法术使狂暴的海水兴起这场风浪，请你使它们平息了吧！天空似乎要倒下发臭的沥青来，但海水腾涌到天的脸上，把火焰浇熄了。唉！我瞧着那些受难的人们，我也和他们同样受难：这样一只壮丽的船，里面一定载着好些尊贵的人，一下子便撞得粉碎！啊，那呼号的声音一直打进我的心坎。可怜的人们，他们死了！要是我是一个有权力的神，我一定要叫海沉进地中，不让它把这只好船和它所载着的人们一起这样吞没了。

普洛斯彼罗　安静些，不要惊骇！告诉你那仁慈的心，一点灾祸都不会发生。

米兰达　唉，不幸的日子！

普洛斯彼罗　不要紧的。凡我所做的事，无非是为你打算，我的宝贝！我的女儿！你不知道你是什么人，也不知道我从什么地方来，你也不会想到我是一个比普洛斯彼罗——一所十分寒碜的洞窟的主人，你的微贱的父亲——更出色的人物。

（朱生豪　译）

终成眷属　第二幕　第三场

国王　你看不起她，不过因为她地位低微，那我可以把她抬高起来。要是把人们的血液倾注在一起，那颜色、重量和热度都难以区别，偏偏在人间的关系上，会划分这样清楚的鸿沟，真是一件怪事。她倘然是一个道德上完善的女子，你不喜欢她，只因为她是一个穷医生的女儿，那么你重视虚名甚于美德，这就错了。穷巷陋室，有德之士居之，可以使蓬荜增辉，世禄之家，不务修善，虽有盛名，亦将惰败。善恶的区别，在于行为的本身，不在于地位的有无。她有天赋的青春、智慧和美貌，这一切的本身即是光荣；最可耻的，却是那些席父祖的余荫、不知绍述先志、一味妄自尊大的人。最好的光荣应该来自我们自己的行动，而不是倚恃家门。虚名是一个下贱的奴隶，在每一座墓碑上说着谎话，倒是在默默无言的一荒土之下，往往埋葬着忠臣义士的骸骨。有什么话好说呢？只要你能因为这女子的本身而爱她，我可以给她其余的一切，她的贤淑美貌是她自己的嫁妆，光荣和财富是我给她的赏赐。

勃特拉姆　我不能爱她，也不想爱她。

国王　你要是抗不奉命，一定要自讨没趣的。

海丽娜　陛下圣体复原，已经使我欣慰万分，其余的事情，不必谈了。

国王　这与我的信用有关，为使它不受损害，我必须运用我的权力。来，骄横傲慢的孩子，握着她的手，你才不配接受这一件卓越的赐予呢。你的愚妄狂悖，不但辜负了她的好处，也已经丧失了我的欢心。你以为她和你处在天平的不平衡的两端，却不知道我站在她的一面，便可以把两方的轻重倒转过来。你也没有想到你的升沉荣辱，完全操在我的手中。为了你自己的好处，赶快抑制你的轻蔑，服从我的旨意。我有命令你的权力，你有服从我的天职，否则你将永远得不到我的眷顾，让年轻的愚昧把你拖下了终身蹭蹬的深渊，我的愤恨和憎恶将要用王法的名义降临到你的头上，没有一点怜悯宽恕。快回答我吧。

勃特拉姆　求陛下恕罪，我愿意捐弃个人的爱憎，服从陛下的指示。当我一想起多少恩荣富贵，都可以随着陛下的一言而予夺，我就觉得适才我所认为最卑贱的她，已经受到陛下的宠眷，而和出身贵族的女子同样高贵了。

（朱生豪　译）

一报还一报　第二幕　第四场

安哲鲁　谁会相信你呢，依莎贝拉？我的洁白无瑕的名声，我的持躬的严正，我的振振有词的驳斥，我的柄持国政的地位，都可以压倒你的控诉，使你自取其辱，人家会把你的话当作挟嫌诽谤。我现在一不做二不休，不再控制我的情欲，你必须满足我的饥渴，放弃礼法的拘束，解脱一切的忸怩，这些对你要请求的事情是有害无利的。把你的肉体呈献给我，来救你弟弟的性命，否则他不但不能活命，而且因为你的无情冷酷，我要叫他遍尝各种痛苦而死去。明天给我答复，否则我要听任感情的支配，叫他知道些厉害。你尽管向人怎样说我，我的虚伪会压倒你的真实。（下。）

依莎贝拉　我将向谁诉说呢？把这种事情告诉别人，谁会相信我？凭着一条可怕的舌头，可以操纵人的生死，把法律供自己的驱使，是非善恶，都由他任意判断！我要去看我的弟弟，他虽然因为一时情欲的冲动而堕落，可是他是一个爱惜荣誉的人，即使他有二十颗头颅，他也宁愿让它们在二十个断头台上被人砍落，而不愿让他姊姊的身体遭受如此的污辱。依莎贝拉，你必须活着做一个清白的人，让你的弟弟死去吧，贞操是比兄弟更为重要的。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世下篇　第四幕　第五场

亲王　我再也想不到还会听见您说话。

亨利王　你因为存着那样的愿望，哈利，所以才会产生那样的思想。我耽搁得太长久，害你等得厌倦了。难道你是那样贪爱着我的空位，所以在时机还没有成熟以前，就要攫取我的尊荣吗？啊，傻孩子！你所追求的尊荣，是会把你压倒的。略微再等一会儿，因为我的尊严就像一片乌云，只有一丝微风把它托住，一下子就会降落下来，我的白昼已经昏暗了。你所偷去的东西，再过几小时就可以名正言顺地归你所有，可是你却在我临死的时候，充分证实了我对你的想法。你的平生行事，都可以表明你没有一点爱父之心，现在我离死不远了，你还要向我证实你的不孝。你把一千柄利刃藏在你的思想之中，把它们在你那石块一般的心上磨得雪亮锋快，要来谋刺我的只剩半小时的生命。嘿！难道你不能容忍我再活半小时吗？那么你就去亲手掘下我的坟墓吧，叫那快乐的钟声响起来，报知你加冕的喜讯，而不是我死亡的噩耗。让那应该洒在我的灵榇上的所有的眼泪，都变成涂抹你的头顶的圣油；让我和被遗忘的泥土混合在一起，把那给你生命的人丢给蛆虫吧。贬斥我的官吏，废止我的法令，因为一个无法无天的新时代已经到来了。哈利五世已经加冕为王！起来吧，浮华的淫乐！没落吧，君主的威严！你们一切深谋远虑的老臣，都给我滚开！现在要让四方各处游手好闲之徒聚集在英国的宫廷里了！邻邦啊，把你们的莠民败类淘汰出来吧。你们有没有什么酗酒谩骂、通宵作乐、杀人越货、无所不为的流氓恶棍？放心吧，他不会再来烦扰你们了，英国将要给他不次的光荣，使他官居要职，爵登显秩，手握大权，因为第五代的哈利将要松开奢淫这条野犬的羁勒，让它向每一个无辜的人张牙舞爪了。啊，我的疮痍未复的可怜的王国！我用尽心力，还不能戡定你的祸乱，在朝纲败坏、法纪荡然的时候，你又将怎样呢？啊！你将要重新变成一片荒野，豺狼将要归返它们的故居。

亲王　啊！恕我，陛下。倘不是因为我的眼泪使我哽咽得说不出话来，我决不会默然倾听您这番沉痛的严训而不加分辩的。这是您的王冠，但愿永生的上帝保佑您长久享有它！（他还回王冠并跪下。）要是我对它怀着私心，并不只是因为它是您的尊荣的标记而珍重它，让我跪在地上，永远站不起来。上帝为我作证，当我进来的时候，看见陛下的嘴里没有一丝气息，我是怎样地感到寒心！要是我的悲哀是虚伪的，啊！让我就在我现在这一种荒唐的行为中死去，再没有机会给世人看看我将要怎样洗心革面，做一个堂堂的人物。我因为进来探望您，看见您仿佛死了的样子，我自己，主上，也几乎因悲痛而死去，当时我就用这样的话责骂这顶王冠，就像它是有知觉的一般，我说：“追随着您的烦恼已经把我的父亲杀害了，所以你这最好的黄金却是最坏的黄金。别的黄金虽然在质地上不如你，却可以炼成祛病延年的药水，比你贵重得多了。可是你这最纯粹的，最受人尊敬重视的，却把你的主人吞噬下去。”我一面这样责骂它，陛下，一面就把它试戴在我的头上，认为它是在我的面前杀死我的父亲的仇敌，我作为忠诚的继承者应该要和它算账。可是假如它使我的血液中感染着欢乐，或是使我的精神上充满着骄傲，假如我的悖逆虚荣的心灵对它抱着丝毫爱悦的情绪，愿上帝永远不让它加在我头上，使我像一个最微贱的奴隶一般向着它战栗下跪！

亨利王啊，我儿！上帝让你把它拿了去，好叫你用这样贤明的辩解，格外博取你父亲的欢心。过来，哈利，坐在我的床边，听我这垂死之人的最后的遗命。（哈里王子坐在了床边。）上帝知道，我儿，我是用怎样诡诈的手段取得这一顶王冠。我自己也十分明白，它戴在我的头上，给了我多大的烦恼。可是你将要更安静更确定地占有它，不像我这样遭人嫉视，因为一切篡窃攘夺的污点，都将随着我一起埋葬。它在人们的心目之中，不过是我用暴力攫取的尊荣，那些帮助我得到它的人都在指斥我的罪状，他们的怨望每天都在酿成斗争和流血，破坏这粉饰的和平。你也看见我曾经冒着怎样的危险，应付这些大胆的威胁，我做了这么多年的国王，不过在反复串演着这一场争杀的武戏。现在我一死之后，情形就可以改变过来了，因为我是用非法手段获得的，在你却是合法继承的权利。可是你的地位虽然可以比我稳定一些，然而人心未服，余憾尚新，你的基础还没有十分巩固。那些拥护我的人们，也就是你所必须认为朋友的，他们的锐牙利刺还不过新近拔去；他们用奸险的手段把我扶上高位，我不能不对他们怀着疑虑，怕他们会用同样的手段把我推翻。为了避免这一种危机，我才多方剪除他们的势力，并且正在准备把许多人带领到圣地作战，免得他们在国内闲居无事，又要发生觊觎王座的图谋。所以，我的哈利，你的政策应该是多多利用对外的战争，使那些心性轻浮的人们有向外活动的机会，不至于在国内为非作乱，旧日的不快的回忆也可以因此而消失。我还有许多话要对你说，可是我的肺力不济，再也说不下去了。上帝啊！恕宥我用不正当的手段取得这一顶王冠，愿你能够平平安安享有它！

亲王陛下，您好容易挣来这一顶王冠，好容易把它保持下来，现在您把它给了我，我当然对它有合法的所有权。我一定要用超乎一切的努力，不让它从我的手里失去。

（朱生豪　译）

战争和暴力中的权力

裘力思·凯撒　第二幕　第一场

勃鲁托斯　只有叫他死这一个办法，我自己对他并没有私怨，只是为了大众的利益。他将要戴上王冠，那会不会改变他的性格是一个问题，蝮蛇是在光天化日之下出现的，所以步行的人必须刻刻提防。让他戴上王冠？不！那等于我们把一个毒刺给了他，使他可以随意加害于人。把不忍之心和威权分开，那威权就会被人误用。讲到凯撒这个人，说一句公平话，我还不曾知道他什么时候一味感情用事，不受理智的支配。可是微贱往往是初期野心的阶梯，凭借着它一步步爬上了高处，他一旦登上了最高的一级之后，便不再回顾那梯子，他的眼光仰望着云霄，瞧不起他从前所恃为凭借的低下的阶段。凯撒何尝不会这样？所以，为了怕他有这一天，必须早一点防备。既然我们反对他的理由，不是因为他现在有什么可以指责的地方，所以就得这样说：照他现在的地位要是再扩大些权力，一定会引起这样那样的后患；我们应当把他当作一颗蛇蛋，与其让他孵出以后害人，不如趁他还在壳里的时候就把他杀死。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利五世　第四幕　第一场

亨利王　皇上就跟我一样，也是一个人罢了。一朵紫罗兰花儿他闻起来，跟我闻起来还不是一样？他头上和我头上合顶着一方天，他也不过用眼睛来看、耳朵来听啊！把一切荣衔丢开，还他一个赤裸裸的本相，那么他只是一个人罢了。虽说他的心思寄托在比我们高出一层的事物上，可是好比一只在云霄里飞翔的老鹰，他有时也不免降落下来，栖息在枝头和地面上。所以，当他有理由害怕的时候，他就像我们一样，感到了害怕，不用问，那心头的滋味也跟我们的感觉差不多。可是照理说，谁也不能叫他感到一丝恐惧，否则的话，他一流露出来，可不要瓦解军队的士气。

培茨　尽管他外表装得怎样勇敢，今夜又这样冷，可是我相信，他心里希望自己宁可浸在泰晤士河里，哪怕河水齐到了脖子。我也但愿他在那儿，而我呢，就在他身边——只要能离开此地，我们还有什么好计较的？

亨利王　不跟你们说瞎话——我愿意代替国王捧着良心说句话——我认为他不会希望不在眼前这个地方，跑到任何别的地方去。

培茨　那么我但愿他独自守在这块地方吧。这样，他当然免不了要献出一笔赎金来，许许多多可怜虫因此也就保全了生命啦。

亨利王　我敢说，你对他不至于一点儿敬爱都没有，竟希望就只他一个人守在这儿，你这么说，无非是试探别人的口气罢了。照我看，我无论死在什么地方，也没有像跟国王死在一块儿那样叫我称心的了，因为他是师出有名的，他的战争是正义的。

威廉斯　这就不是我们所能了解的了。

培茨　啊，或者说，这就不是我们所该追究的了。因为说到了解不了解，只要我们知道自己是国王的臣民，那就够了。即使他是站在理亏的一边，只要我们这些人是服从我们国王的，也就消除了我们的罪名。

威廉斯　可是，如果这不是师出有名，那么国王头上的这笔账可有得他算了。打一场仗，有多少的腿、多少的胳膊、多少的头要给砍下来，将来有一天，它们又结合在了一起，就会一齐高声呼号：“我们死在这样一个地方！”有的在咒天骂地，有的在喊叫军医，有的在哭他抛下了苦命的妻，有的高嚷他欠了人家的债还没还，也有的一声声叫他甩手不管的孩子——我只怕死在战场上的人很少有死得像个样儿的！人家既然要流你的血，还能跟你讲什么慈悲？我说，如果这帮人不得好死，那么把他们领到死路上去的国王就是罪孽深重了。苦的是小百姓，他们要是违抗了君命，那就是违反了做百姓的名分。

亨利王　照这样说来，假如有个儿子，父亲派他出洋去做生意，结果他却带着一身罪孽葬身在海里了，那么照你的一套看法，这份罪孽就应当归在把他派出去的父亲的头上。或者是，有一个奴仆，受了主人的嘱咐，运送一笔钱，却在半路上遭了打劫，还没来得及忏悔就给强盗杀死了，你也许要把那个主人叫作害这个仆人堕入地狱的主使者。不过，这不是那么一回事。国王手下的兵士他们一个个怎样结局、收场，国王用不着负责。做父亲的对于儿子，做主人的对于奴仆，也是这样，因为他们派给他们任务的时候，并没有把死派给他们。再说，国王出兵，就算他是完全理直气壮的，一旦到了在战场上见个高低，他也无从叫所有的兵士都免除了罪孽。很难说，有些兵士曾经蓄意谋杀过人，有些兵士拿虚伪的山盟海誓骗取了姑娘的贞操，有些兵士曾经犯过抢劫的案子、破坏了安宁和秩序，正好拿战争作避难所。现在，这帮人逃脱了法网，躲过了罪有应得的惩罚——虽然人们是给他瞒过了，他却插翅难逃上帝的手心！战争是他的一张拘票，战争是他的报应，这帮人过去触犯了王法，现在就在国王的战争中领受惩罚。他们为了怕死就投了军，他们以为这样就得救了，不料反而遭了殃。那么要是他不得好死，入了地狱，国王负什么责任？正像他们从前犯下不敬上帝的罪不能由他负责一样。为这罪恶，他们现在得了报应！每个臣民都有为国效忠的本分，可是每个臣民的灵魂却是属于他自己掌管的。

（方平　译）

哈姆莱特　第四幕　第四场

哈姆莱特　我所见到、听到的一切，都好像在对我谴责，鞭策我赶快进行我的蹉跎未就的复仇大愿！一个人要是把生活的幸福和目的，只看作吃吃睡睡，他还算是个什么东西？简直不过是一头畜生！上帝造下我们来，使我们能够这样高谈阔论、瞻前顾后，当然要我们利用他所赋予我们的这一种能力和灵明的理智，不让它们白白废掉。现在我明明有理由、有决心、有力量、有方法，可以动手干我所要干的事，可是我还是在大言不惭地说：“这件事需要做。”可是始终不曾在行动上表现出来。我不知道这是因为像鹿豕一般健忘呢，还是因为三分懦怯一分智慧的过于审慎的顾虑。像大地一样显明的榜样都在鼓励我，瞧这一支勇猛的大军，领队的是一个娇养的少年王子，勃勃的雄心振起了他的精神，使他蔑视不可知的结果，为了区区弹丸大小的一块不毛之地，拼着血肉之躯，去向命运、死亡和危险挑战。真正的伟大不是轻举妄动，而是在荣誉遭遇危险的时候，即使为了一根稻秆之微，也要慷慨力争。可是我的父亲给人惨杀，我的母亲给人污辱，我的理智和感情都被这种不共戴天的大仇所激动，我却因循隐忍，一切听其自然，看着这两万个人为向博取一个空虚的名声，视死如归地走向他们的坟墓里去，目的只是争夺一方还不够给他们作战场或者埋骨之所的土地，相形之下，我将何地自容呢？啊！从这一刻起，让我摒除一切的疑虑妄念，把流血的思想充满我的脑际！

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世下篇　第一幕　第三场

巴道夫　要是我们把这次战争的运命完全寄托在希望上，那希望对于我们是无益而有害的，正像我们在早春时候所见的初生的蓓蕾一般，希望不能保证它们开花结实，无情的寒霜早已摧残了它们的生机。当我们准备建筑房屋的时候，我们首先要测量地基，然后设计图样；打好图样以后，我们还要估计建筑的费用，要是那费用超过我们的财力，就必须把图样重新改绘，设法减省一些人工，或是放弃这一项建筑计划。现在我们所进行的这件伟大的工作，简直是推翻一个旧的王国，重新建立一个新的王国，所以我们尤其应该熟察环境，详定方针，确立一个稳固的基础，询问测量师，明了我们自身的力量，是不是能够从事这样的工作，对抗敌人的压迫。否则要是我们徒然在纸上谈兵，把战士的名单代替了实际上阵的战士，那就像一个人打了一幅他的力量所不能建筑的房屋的图样，造了一半就中途停工，丢下那未完成的屋架子，让它去受凄风苦雨的吹淋。

（朱生豪　译）

麦克白　第一幕　第七场

麦克白　要是干了以后就完了，那么还是快一点干。要是凭着暗杀的手段，可以攫取美满的结果，又可以排除了一切后患。要是这一刀砍下去，就可以完成一切、终结一切、解决一切——在这人世上，仅仅在这人世上，在时间这大海的浅滩上，那么来生我也就顾不到了。可是在这种事情上，我们往往逃不过现世的裁判；我们树立下血的榜样，教会别人杀人，结果反而自己被人所杀；把毒药投入酒杯里的人，结果也会自己饮鸩而死，这就是一丝不爽的报应。他到这儿来本有两重信任：第一，我是他的亲戚，又是他的臣子，按照名分绝对不能干这样的事；第二，我是他的主人，应当保障他身体的安全，怎么可以自己持刀行刺？而且，这个邓肯秉性仁慈，处理国政，从来没有过失，要是把他杀死了，他生前的美德，将要像天使一般发出喇叭一样清澈的声音，向世人昭告我的弑君重罪。“怜悯”像一个赤身裸体在狂风中飘游的婴儿，又像一个御气而行的天婴，将要把这可憎的行为揭露在每一个人的眼中，使眼泪淹没叹息。没有一种力量可以鞭策我实现自己的意图，可是我跃跃欲试的野心，却不顾一切地驱着我去冒颠踬的危险。

（朱生豪　译）

理查三世　第五幕　第五场

里士满　那就该是披甲发令的时间了。亲爱的同胞们，时间已经十分紧迫，我无法和你们尽情多谈了；可是大家只消记住这一点，上帝和正义都在同我们一起作战；圣洁的圣徒们和冤死的人们都在为我们祈祷，他们站在我们面前像一座高耸的堡垒；除了理查之外，他手下的人没有一个不宁愿我们战胜，唯恐他得到胜利。要知道他们所跟从的这个人是个什么样的人呢？弟兄们，他确实是一个杀人如麻的暴君；他在人血中成长，靠流血起家；利用他原有的地位以扩展势力，屠宰他自己的谋士，过河拆桥；一颗卑劣的假宝石，空凭英国的王座来衬托出光芒，其实是装错了地位，满不相称；他始终与上帝为敌。你们既和上帝的敌人交战，做上帝的战士必得天道庇佑；如果你们挥着汗除恶歼暴，功成名遂之后，自可高枕无忧；如果你们为国家战胜公敌，国家自然会把肥甘犒赏你们；如果你们为保护妻孥的安全而战，你们的妻孥就会来迎接胜利者回家园；如果你们把儿女救出了虎口，你们的子孙就可在你们的晚年承欢报恩。所以，为上帝之名和这一切权益，举旗前进，凭自愿拔刀杀敌去吧。至于我，为了这英勇的一役要激战一场，甚至不惜寒土埋冷骨；但是我若幸而获胜，这胜利的果实要和你们每一个士卒共享。击鼓吹号吧，奋勇欢呼起来；上帝与圣乔治在此！里士满与胜利！

（方重　译）

亨利六世中篇　第一幕　第一场

约克　安佐和缅因白白送给了法国人，巴黎已经丧失了，这些地区丢了以后，诺曼底省就处于极不安全的状态。萨福克签订了合约条款，贵族们都已同意，亨利也愿意用两个公爵的采邑换取一个公爵的标致女儿。为了这些事，我也怪不得他们；在他们看来，这些都算得什么？他们送掉的原是你的东西，而不是他们自己的东西。海盗们把抢来的财富尽情挥霍，收买朋友，赏赐娼妓，直到花干净，也毫不吝惜。而那不幸的物主却只能唉声叹气，搓手摇头，战兢兢地站在一旁，眼看着自己的东西被人分配完毕，全都带走，自己只能忍饥挨饿，对自己的财产连碰都不敢碰一下。我约克正是处于这样的地位：我自己的土地被人家换掉了、出卖了，我只能坐在一旁，忍气吞声。在我看来，英格兰、法兰西、爱尔兰，这些国土都是我心头之肉，都是我生命的寄托。而他们竟然把安佐和缅因送给了法国人！这真是一件令人泄气的消息，那法兰西，如同英格兰的肥沃土地一样，原是我想要弄到手的。总有一天我约克要把自己的东西收归己有。为了这个目的，我不妨站到萨立斯伯雷父子这一边来，在外表上对骄横的亨弗雷公爵表现一下拥戴的态度。等时机一到，我就提出对王冠的要求，那才是我所追求的最高目标。可是，约克呵，你得耐心一点，要等待时机成熟。当别人入睡的时候，你得保持清醒，留心伺察，把国家的内幕刺探清楚。亨利替英国花了许多钱买来一位王后，他正陶醉在新媳妇的爱河之中，等他和亨弗雷同其他的贵族们一旦发生破裂，我就要高举乳白色的玫瑰，使那空气里充满它的芬芳，我要树起绣有约克家族徽记的旗帜，对兰开斯特家族进行搏斗。我要使用武力，迫使他交出王冠，这些年来，在他的书呆子般的统治之下，英格兰的威望是一天天低落了。

（章益　译）

暴风雨　第三幕　第三场

爱丽儿　你们是三个有罪的人，操纵着下界一切的天命使得那贪馋的怒海重又把你们吐了出来，把你们抛在这没有人居住的岛上，你们是不配居住在人类中间的。你们已经发狂了。（阿隆佐、西巴斯辛等拔剑）即使像你们这样勇敢的人，也没有法子免除一死。你们这辈愚人！我和我的同伴们都是运命的使者，你们的用风、火熔炼的刀剑不能损害我们身上的一根羽毛，正像把它们砍向呼啸的风、刺向分而复合的水波一样，只显得可笑。我的伙伴们也是刀枪不入的。而且即使它们能够把我们伤害，现在你们也已经没有力量把臂膀举起来了。（阿隆佐、西巴斯辛等吃惊地站着。）好生记住吧，我来就是告诉你们这句话，你们三个人是在米兰把善良的普洛斯彼罗篡逐的恶人，你们把他和他的无辜的婴孩放逐在海上，如今你们也受到同样的报应了。为着这件恶事，上天虽然并不把惩罚立刻加在你们身上，却并没有轻轻放过，已经使海洋陆地，以及一切有生之伦，都来和你们作对了。你，阿隆佐，已经丧失了你的儿子；我再向你宣告，活地狱的无穷的痛苦——一切死状合在一起也没有那么惨，将要一步步临到你生命的途程中。除非痛改前非，以后洗心革面，做一个清白的人，否则在这荒岛上面，天谴已经迫在眼前了！

（爱丽儿在雷鸣中隐去。柔和的乐声复起，精灵们重上，跳舞且作揶揄状，把空桌抬下。）

普洛斯彼罗　你把这怪鸟扮演得很好，我的爱丽儿，这一桌酒席你也席卷得妙，我叫你说的话你一句也没有漏去；就是那些小精灵们也都是生龙活虎，各自非常出力。我的神通已经显出力量，我这些仇人们已经惊惶得不能动弹，他们都已经在我的权力之下了。

（朱生豪　译）

科利奥兰纳斯　第一幕　第一场

市民甲　我们都是苦百姓，贵族才是好市民。那些有权有势的人吃饱了，装不下的东西就可以救济我们。他们只要把吃剩下来的东西趁着新鲜的时候赏给我们，我们就会以为他们是出于人道之心来救济我们。可是在他们看来，我们都是不值得救济的。我们的痛苦饥寒，我们的枯瘦憔悴，就像是列载着他们的富裕的一张清单，他们享福就是靠了我们受苦。让我们举起我们的武器来复仇，趁我们还没有瘦得只剩几根骨头。天神知道我说这样的话，只是迫于没有面包吃的饥饿，不是因为渴于复仇。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世上篇　第一幕　第三场

霍茨波　啊，那就难怪他那位做了国王的叔父恨不得要让摩提默在荒凉的山谷之间饿死了。可是你们把王冠加在这个健忘的人的头上，为了他的缘故，蒙上教唆行弑的万恶的罪名，难道你们就这样甘心做一个篡位者的卑鄙的帮凶，一个弑君的刽子手，受尽无穷的咒诅吗？啊！恕我这样不知忌讳，直言指出你们在这狡诈的国王手下充任了何等的角色。难道你们愿意让当世的舆论和未来的历史提起这一件可羞的事实，说是像你们这样两个有地位有势力的人，却会作出那样不义之事——上帝恕宥你们的罪恶！——把理查，那芬芳可爱的蔷薇拔了下来，却扶植起波林勃洛克，这一棵刺人的荆棘？难道你们愿意让他们提起这一件更可羞的事实，说是你们为了那个人蒙受这样的耻辱，结果却被他所愚弄、摈斥和抛弃？不，现在你们还来得及赎回你们被放逐的荣誉，恢复世人对你们的好感；报复这骄傲的国王所加于你们的侮蔑吧，他每天每晚都在考虑着怎样酬答你们的辛劳，他是不会吝惜用流血的手段把你们处死的。所以，我说……

华斯特　静下来，侄儿！别多说了。

（朱生豪　译）

理查三世　第四幕　第三场

提瑞尔　一桩血腥的暴行已经完成；真是这片国土之上还未见过的一件罪大恶极的惨案。我曾唆使戴登和福列司特一起去硬着心肠下这毒手，可是他俩虽然是嗜血暴徒，听了那番临死前的悲诉，也竟顽石点头，像孩提一般流下热泪来。“看哪，”戴登说，“这幼嫩的孩子们躺在那儿。”“就这样，”福列司特说，“他俩这样相互抱住，白蜡似的纯洁臂膀缠得好紧，那嘴唇就像枝头的四瓣红玫瑰，娇滴滴地在夏季的馥郁中亲吻。枕边放着一本祈祷书，我险些，”福列司特说道，“心头软下来，然而那魔鬼呵。”这个恶汉停住了。这时戴登又续道：“我们把开天辟地以来所未有的美品，天公的精心杰作，竟一手给闷死了。”他俩就这样受到良心的责备，话也说不出来。那时我们分了手，我便来向血腥的国王复命：他来了。（理查王上。）

提瑞尔　祝您万福，我的主君！

理查王　好提瑞尔，你的消息是叫我高兴的吗？

瑞尔　如果我完成了您交下的使命就能叫您高兴的话，那就请您高兴吧，因为这件事已经办成了。

理查王　你看见他们确已死了？

提瑞尔　看见了，我的主君。

理查王　埋葬了吗，好提瑞尔？

提瑞尔　伦敦塔中的牧师把他们埋了，至于埋在哪儿，怎样埋的，我却不知道。

理查王　晚饭后到我这里来，提瑞尔，我要你告诉我他们死时的经过，同时不妨先想一想我该如何酬谢你，怎样满足你的欲望。再见，等你来。

提瑞尔　我敬向您告辞。

理查王　克莱伦斯的儿子我已经关禁起来，他的女儿我已把她嫁给了穷人，爱德华的两个儿子睡进了亚伯拉罕的怀抱里，我妻安辞别了人世。现在我知道布列塔尼的里士满觊觎着我的侄女小伊利莎白，借这一结合，妄图争得王冠，我就去找她，再当个快乐幸福的求婚郎。

（方重　译）

雅典的泰门　第五幕　第四场

艾西巴第斯　吹起喇叭来，让这个怯懦的、淫秽的城市知道我们的大军已经来到。

（吹谈判信号。元老等登城。）

艾西巴第斯　在今天以前，由你们胡作非为，肆行不义，把你们的私心当作公道；在今天以前，我自己以及一切睡在你们权力的阴影下面的人，谁都是叉手彷徨，有冤莫诉。现在忍无可忍的时间已经到了，蹲伏惯了的脊骨，在重重的压迫之下，喊出“受不住了”的呼声。现在无告的冤苦将要坐在你们宽大的安乐椅上喘息，短气的骄横将要狼狈奔逃了。

元老甲　尊贵的少年将军，你当初因为些微的误会一怒而去的时候，虽然你还是无拳无勇，我们无须恐惧你的报复，可是我们仍旧召你回来，好意抚慰你，用逾量的恩宠洗刷我们负心的罪戾。

元老乙　就是对于改换了形貌的泰门，我们也曾用谦恭的使节和优渥的允诺恳求他眷念我们的城市。我们并不全是冷酷无情的人，也不该不分皂白地同受战争的屠戮。

元老甲　我们这一座城墙，并不是建立于得罪你的那些人之手；这些巍峨的高塔、标柱和学校，更不应该为了私人的错误而同归毁灭。

元老乙　当初驱迫你出亡的那些人，因为自愧缺少应付非常的才能，心中惭疚，都已忧郁逝世了。尊贵的将军，带领你的大军，高扬你的旗帜，开进我们的城中吧！要是你不顾上天好生之德，你的复仇的欲望必须得到满足，那么请你在十人中杀死一人，让那不幸接触你的锋刃的作为牺牲吧。

（朱生豪　译）

理查二世　第三幕　第三场

波林勃洛克（向诺森伯兰伯爵）贵爵，请你到那座古堡的顽强的墙壁之前，用铜角把谈判的信号吹进它的残废的耳中，为我这样传言：亨利·波林勃洛克屈下他的双膝，敬吻理查王的御手，向他最尊贵的本人致献臣服的诚意和不二的忠心。就在他的足前，我准备放下我的武器，遣散我的军队，只要他能答应撤销我的放逐的判决，归还我的应得的土地。不然的话，我要利用我的军力的优势，让那从被屠杀的英国人的伤口中流下的血雨浇溉夏天的泥土。可是我的谦卑的忠顺将会证明用这种猩红的雨点浸染理查王的美好的青绿的田野，绝不是波林勃洛克的本意。去，这样对他说。我们就在这儿平坦的草原上整队前进。让我们进军的时候不要敲起惊人的鼓声，这样可以让他们从那城堡的摇摇欲倾的雉堞之上，看看我们雄壮的军容。我想理查王跟我上阵的时候，将要像水火的交攻一样骇人，那彼此接触时的雷鸣巨响，可以把天空震破。让他做火，我愿意做柔顺的水；雷霆之威是属于他的，我只向地上浇洒我的雨露。

（朱生豪　译）

科利奥兰纳斯　第四幕　第五场

科利奥兰纳斯　我的名字是卡厄斯·马歇斯，我曾经把极大的伤害和灾祸加在你和一切伏尔斯人的身上，我的姓氏科利奥兰纳斯就是最好的证明。辛苦的战役、重大的危险、替我这负恩的国家所流过的血，结果只是换到了这一个空洞的姓氏，为你对我所怀的怨恨留下一个创巨痛深的记忆。只有这名字还留着。残酷猜忌的人民，得到了我们那些怯懦的贵族的默许，已经一致遗弃了我，抹杀了我一切的功绩，让那些奴才们把我轰出了罗马。这一种不幸的遭遇，使我今天来到你的家里。不要误会我，以为我想来向你求恩乞命，因为要是我怕死的话，我就应该远远地躲开你。我只是因为出于气愤，渴想报复那些放逐我的人，所以才到这儿来站在你的面前。要是你也有一颗复仇的心，想要替你自己和你的国家洗雪耻辱，你的机会到了，你正可以利用我的不幸，达到你自己的目的，因为我将要用地狱中一切饿鬼的怨毒，来与我的腐败的祖国作战。可是你要是没有这样的胆量，也不想追求远大的前程，那么一句话，我也已经厌倦人世，愿意伸直我的颈项，听任你的宰割，让你一泄这许多年来郁积在心头的怨恨。你要是不杀我，你就是个傻瓜，因为我一向是你的死敌，曾经从你祖国的胸前溅下了无数吨的血。要是让我活在世上，对于你永远是一个耻辱，除非你能够跟我合作。

（朱生豪　译）

亨利四世下篇　第四幕　第一场

威斯摩兰　那么，大主教，我要把您作为我的发言的主要对象。要是叛乱不脱它的本色，不过是一群乌合之众的暴动，在少数嗜杀好乱的少年领导之下，获得那些无赖贱民的拥护。要是它果然以这一种适合于它的本性的面目出现，那么您，可尊敬的神父，以及这几位尊贵的勋爵，决不会厕身于他们的行列，用你们的荣誉替卑劣残暴的叛徒丑类张目。您，大主教，您的职位是借着国内的和平而确立的，您的须髯曾经为和平所吹拂，您的学问文章都是受着和平的甄陶，您的白袍象征着纯洁、圣灵与和平的精神，为什么您现在停止您的优美的和平的宣讲，高呼着粗暴喧嚣的战争的口号，把经典换了甲胄，把墨水换了鲜血，把短笔换了长枪，把神圣的辩舌化成了战场上的号角？

约克　为什么我要采取这样的行动？这是您对我所发的疑问。我的简单的答案是这样的：我们都是害着重病的人；过度的宴乐和荒淫已经使我们遍身像火烧一般发热，我们必须因此而流血；我们的前王理查就是因为染上这一种疾病而不治身亡的。可是，我的最尊贵的威斯摩兰伯爵，我并不以一个医生自任，虽然我现在置身在这些战士们的中间，我并不愿做一个和平的敌人。我的意思不过是暂时借可怖的战争为手段，强迫被无度的纵乐所糜烂的身心得到一些合理的节制，对那开始遏止我们生命活力的障碍作一番彻底的扫除。再听我说得明白一些：我曾经仔细衡量过我们的武力所能造成的损害和我们自己所身受的损害，发现我们的怨愤比我们的过失更重。我们看见时势的潮流奔赴着哪一个方向，在环境的强力的挟持之下，我们不得不适应大势，离开我们平静安谧的本位。我们已经把我们的不满列为条款，在适当的时间，我们将要把它们公开宣布。这些条款在很久以前，我们曾想呈递给国王，但多方祈求仍不能邀蒙接受。当我们受到侮辱损害，准备申诉我们的怨苦的时候，我们总不能得到面谒国王的机会，而那些阻止我们看见他的人，也正就是给我们最大的侮辱与损害的人。新近过去的危机——它用血写成的记忆还留着鲜明的印象，以及当前每一分钟所呈现的险象，使我们穿起了这些不合身的武装，我们不是要破坏和平，而是要确立一个名实相符的真正和平。

（朱生豪　译）

恋人间的权力

特洛伊罗斯与克瑞西达　第三幕　第二场

特洛伊罗斯　那么我的克瑞西达为什么这样不容易征服呢？

克瑞西达　似乎不容易征服，可是，殿下，当您第一眼看着我的时候，我早就给您征服了——恕我不再说下去，要是我招认得太多，您会看轻我的。我现在爱着您，可是直到现在为止，我还能够控制我自己的感情。不，说老实话，我说了谎了；我的思想就像一群顽劣的孩子，倔强得不受他们母亲的管束。瞧，我们真是些傻瓜！为什么就要唠唠叨叨说这些话呢？要是我们不能替自己保守秘密，谁还会对我们忠实呢？我虽然这样爱您，却没有向您求爱。然而说老实话，我却希望我自己是个男子，或者我们女子也像男子一样有先启口的权利。亲爱的，快叫我止住我的舌头吧，因为我这样得意忘形，一定会说出使我后悔的话来。瞧，瞧！您这么狡猾地一声不响，已经使我从我的脆弱当中流露出我的内心来了。封住我的嘴吧。

特洛伊罗斯　好，虽然甜蜜的音乐从您嘴里发出。

（他吻了她。）

（朱生豪　译）

十四行诗　一五零

哦，从什么威力中你取得这力量，

连缺陷也能把我的心灵支配？

教我诬蔑我可靠的目光撒谎，

并矢口否认太阳使白天明媚？

何来这化臭腐为神奇的本领，

使你的种种丑恶不堪的表现

都具有一种灵活强劲的保证，

使它们，对于我，超越一切至善？

谁教你有办法使我更加爱你，

当我听到和见到你种种可憎？

哦，尽管我钟爱着人家所嫌弃，

你总不该嫌弃我，同人家一条心：

既然你越不可爱，越使得我爱，

你就该觉得我更值得你喜爱。

（梁宗岱　译）

维罗那二绅士　第三幕　第一场

凡伦丁　与其活着受煎熬，何不一死了事？死不过是把自己放逐出自己的躯壳。西尔维娅已经和我合成一体，离开她就是离开我自己，这不是和死同样的刑罚吗？看不见西尔维娅，世上还有什么光明？不能和西尔维娅在一起，世上还有什么乐趣？我只好闭上眼睛假想她在旁边，用这样美好的幻影寻求片刻的陶醉。除非夜间有西尔维娅陪着我，否则夜莺的歌唱只是不入耳的噪音；除非白天有西尔维娅在我的面前，否则我的生命将是一个不见天日的长夜。她是我生命的精华，我要是不能在她的煦护拂庇之下滋养生机，就要干枯憔悴而死。即使能逃过他这可怕的判决，我也仍然不能逃避死亡；因为我留在这儿，结果不过一死，可是离开了这儿，就是离开了生命所寄托的一切。

（朱生豪　译）

无事生非　第三幕　第一场

希罗　爱神在上，我也知道像他这样的人品是值得享受世间一切至美至好的事物的，可是造物造下的女人的心，没有一颗比得上像贝特丽丝那样骄傲冷酷的。轻蔑和讥嘲在她的眼睛里闪耀着，把她所看见的一切贬得一文不值，她因为自恃才情，所以什么都不放在眼里。她不会恋爱，也从来不想到有恋爱这件事，她是太自命不凡了。

欧苏拉　不错，我也是这样想。所以还是不要让她知道他对她的爱情，免得反而遭到她的讥笑。

希罗　是呀，你说得很对。无论怎样聪明、高贵、年轻、漂亮的男子，她总要把他批评得体无完肤：要是他面孔长得白净，她就发誓说这位先生应当做她的妹妹；要是他皮肤黑了点儿，她就说上帝在打一个小花脸的图样的时候，不小心涂上了一大块墨渍；要是他是个高个儿，他就是柄歪头的长枪；要是他是个矮子，他就是块刻坏了的玛瑙坠子；要是他多讲了几句话，他就是个随风转的风标；要是他一声不响，他就是块没有知觉的木头。她这样指摘着每一个人的短处，至于他的纯朴的德行和才能，她却绝口不给它们应得的赞赏。

欧苏拉　真的，这种吹毛求疵可不敢恭维。

希罗　是呀，像贝特丽丝这样古怪得不近人情，真叫人不敢恭维。可是谁敢去对她这样说呢？要是我对她说了，她会把我讥笑得无地自容，用她的俏皮话儿把我揶揄死呢！所以还是让培尼狄克像一堆盖在灰里的火一样，在叹息中熄灭了他的生命的残焰吧。与其受人讥笑而死——这就像痒得要死那样难熬——还是不声不响地闷死了好。

（朱生豪　译）

驯悍记　第四幕　第一场

彼特鲁乔　我已经开始巧妙地把她驾驭起来，希望能够得到美满的成功。我这只悍鹰现在非常饥饿，在她没有俯首听命以前，不能让她吃饱，不然她就不肯再练习打猎了。我还有一个制服这鸷鸟的办法，使她能呼之则来，挥之则去。那就是总叫她睁着眼，不得休息，拿她当一只乱扑翅膀的倔强鹞子一样对待。今天她没有吃过肉，明天我也不给她吃；昨夜她不曾睡觉，今夜我也不让她睡觉，我要故意嫌被褥铺得不好，把枕头、枕垫、被单、线毯向满房乱丢，还说都是为了爱惜她才这样做。总之她将要整夜不能合眼，倘然她昏昏思睡，我就骂人吵闹，吵得她睡不着。这是用体贴为名惩治妻子的法子，我就这样克制她的狂暴倔强的脾气。要是有谁知道还有比这更好的驯悍妙法，那么我倒要请教请教。

（朱生豪　译）

鲁克丽丝受辱记　第281—301行

正好比稀稀禾苗，被萋萋恶草掩蔽，

审慎的顾虑几乎被猖狂的欲念窒息。

他竖起耳朵倾听，偷偷举步前移，

满怀无耻的希冀，满腹无聊的猜疑；

希冀、猜疑仿佛是恶人的两名仆役，

让他们相忤的主张交错于他的脑际，

使他一会儿想收兵，一会儿又想进袭。

潜思中，他恍惚瞥见她天仙一般的形象，

还恍惚瞥见柯拉廷，也与她同在那厢；

向她望着的那只眼，搅得他心神迷惘；

向她望着的那只眼，却较为虔敬忠良，

不肯屈从于这种背信弃义的意向，

发出纯真的呼吁，求心灵作出主张；

但心灵既经腐蚀，竟投向恶的一方。

这就大大怂恿了他那卑劣的情思：

见心灵洋洋自得，它们也踌躇满志，

涨满了他的淫欲，像分秒填满了小时；

自吹互捧过了头，它们越来越骄恣，

竟与它们的统帅——心灵毫无二致。

听任奸邪的欲念如此癫狂地指使，

罗马王子直驱鲁克丽丝的卧室。

（杨德豫　译）

仲夏夜之梦　第五幕　第一场

忒修斯　情人们和疯子们都富于纷乱的思想和成形的幻觉，他们所理会到的永远不是冷静的理智所能充分了解。疯子、情人和诗人，都是幻想的产儿：疯子眼中所见的鬼，多过于广大的地狱所能容纳；情人，同样是那么疯狂，能从埃及人的黑脸上看见海伦的美貌；诗人的眼睛在神奇的、狂放的一转中，便能从天上看到地下，从地下看到天上。想象会把不知名的事物用一种形式呈现出来，诗人的笔再使它们具有如实的形象，空虚的无物也会有了居处和名字。强烈的想象往往具有这种本领，只要一领略到一些快乐，就会相信那种快乐的背后有一个赐予的人。夜间一转到恐惧的念头，一株灌木一下子便会变成一头熊。

（朱生豪　译）

罗密欧与朱丽叶　第三幕　第三场

罗密欧　这是酷刑，不是恩典。朱丽叶所在的地方就是天堂；这儿的每一只猫、每一只狗、每一只小小的老鼠，都生活在天堂里，都可以瞻仰到她的容颜，可是罗密欧却看不见她。污秽的苍蝇都可以接触亲爱的朱丽叶的皎洁的玉手，从她的嘴唇上偷取天堂中的幸福，那两片嘴唇是这样的纯洁贞淑，永远含着娇羞，好像觉得它们自身的相吻也是一种罪恶。苍蝇可以这样做，我却必须远走高飞，它们是自由的，我却是一个放逐的流徒。你还说放逐不是死吗？难道你没有配好的毒药、锋锐的刀子或者无论什么致命的利器，而必须用“放逐”两个字把我杀害吗？放逐！啊，神父！只有沉沦在地狱里的鬼魂才会用到这两个字，伴着凄厉的呼号。你是一个教士，一个替人忏罪的神父，又是我的朋友，怎么忍心用“放逐”这两个字来寸磔我呢？

（梁宗岱　译）

终成眷属　第一幕　第一场

海丽娜　唉！要是真的只是这样倒好了。我不是想我的父亲，我这些滔滔的眼泪，虽然好像是一片孺慕的哀忱，却不是为他而流。他的容貌怎样，我也早就忘记了，在我的想象之中，除了勃特拉姆以外没有别人的影子。我现在一切都完了！要是勃特拉姆离我而去，我还有什么生趣？我正像爱上了一颗灿烂的明星，痴心地希望着有一天能够和它结合。他是这样高不可攀，我不能逾越我的名分和他亲近，只好在他的耀目的光华下，沾取他的几分余晖，安慰安慰我的饥渴。我的爱情的野心使我备受痛苦，希望和狮子匹配的驯鹿，必须为爱而死。每时每刻看见他，是愉快也是苦痛。我默坐在他的旁边，在心版上深深地刻画着他的秀曲的眉毛，他的敏锐的眼睛，他的迷人的鬈发，他那可爱的脸庞上的每一根线条，每一处微细的特点，都会清清楚楚地摄在我的心里。可是现在他去了，我的爱慕的私衷，只好以眷怀旧日的陈迹为满足。

（朱生豪　译）

十四行诗　五七

既然是你奴隶，我有什么可做，

除了时时刻刻伺候你的心愿？

我毫无宝贵的时间可消磨，

也无事可做，直到你有所驱遣。

我不敢骂那绵绵无尽的时刻，

当我为你，主人，把时辰来看守；

也不敢埋怨别离是多么残酷，

在你已经把你的仆人辞退后；

也不敢用妒忌的念头去探索

你究竟在哪里，或者为什么忙碌，

只是，像个可怜的奴隶，呆想着

你所在的地方，人们会多幸福。

爱这呆子是那么无救药得呆

凭你为所欲为，他都不觉得坏。

（梁宗岱　译）

爱的徒劳　第一幕　第二场

亚马多　我爱上了那被她穿在她的卑贱的鞋子里的更卑贱的脚所践踏的最卑贱的地面。要是我恋爱了，我将要破坏誓约，那就是说了一句虚伪的谎。虚伪的谎怎么可以换到真实的爱呢？爱情是一个魔鬼，是一个独一无二的罪恶的天使。可是参孙也曾被它引诱，他是个力气很大的人；所罗门也曾被它迷惑，他是个聪明无比的人。赫拉克勒斯的巨棍也敌不住丘匹德的箭镞，所以一个西班牙人的宝剑怎么能够对抗得了呢？不消一两个回合，我的剑法就要完全散乱了。什么直刺，什么横劈，在他看来都是不值一笑。他的耻辱是被人称为孩子，他的光荣却是征服成人。别了，勇气！锈了吧，宝剑！静下来，战鼓！因为你们的主人在恋爱了。是的，他在恋爱了。即景生情的诗神啊，帮助我！因为我相信我要写起十四行诗来了。想吧，智慧；写吧，笔！我有足够的诗情，可以写满几大卷的对开大本呢。

（朱生豪　译）

罗密欧与朱丽叶　第一幕　第一场

罗密欧　啊，吵吵闹闹的相爱，亲亲热热的怨恨！啊，无中生有的一切！啊，沉重的轻浮，严肃的狂妄，整齐的混乱，铅铸的羽毛，光明的烟雾，寒冷的火焰，憔悴的健康，永远觉醒的睡眠，否定的存在！我感觉到的爱情正是这么一种东西，可是我并不喜爱这一种爱情。你不会笑我吗？

班伏里奥　不，兄弟，我倒是有点儿想哭。

罗密欧　好人，为什么呢？

班伏里奥　因为瞧着你善良的心承受这样的痛苦。

罗密欧　唉！这就是爱情的错误，我自己已经有太多的忧愁重压在我的心头，你对我表示的同情，徒然使我在太多的忧愁之上再加上一重忧愁。爱情是叹息吹起的一阵烟，恋人的眼中有它净化了的火星，恋人的眼泪是它激起的波涛。它又是最智慧的疯狂，哽喉的苦味，吃不到嘴的蜜糖。

（朱生豪　译）

安东尼与克莉奥佩特拉　第四幕　第十六场

克莉奥佩特拉　什么都没有了，我只是一个平凡的女人，平凡的感情支配着我，正像支配着一个挤牛奶、做贱工的婢女一样。我应该向不仁的神明怒掷我的御杖，告诉他们当他们没有偷去我们的珍宝的时候，我们这世界是可以和他们的天国媲美的。如今一切都只是空虚无聊，忍着像傻瓜，不忍着又像疯狗。那么在死神还不敢侵犯我们以前，就奔进了幽秘的死窟，是不是罪恶呢？怎么啦，我的姑娘们？唉，唉！高兴点儿吧！哎哟，怎么啦，查米恩！我的好孩子们！啊，姑娘们，姑娘们，瞧！我们的灯熄了，它暗下去了，各位好朋友，提起勇气来，我们要埋葬他，一切依照最庄严、最高贵的罗马的仪式，让死神乐于带我们同去。来，走吧。容纳着那样一颗伟大的灵魂的躯壳现在已经冰冷了。啊，姑娘们，姑娘们！我们没有朋友，只有视死如归的决心。

（朱生豪　译）

十四行诗　二六

我爱情的至尊，你的美德已经

使我这藩属加强对你的拥戴，

我现在寄给你这诗当作使臣，

去向你述职，并非要向你炫才。

职责那么重，我又才拙少俊语，

难免要显得赤裸裸和她相见，

但望你的妙思，不嫌它太粗鄙，

在你灵魂里把它的赤裸裸遮掩；

因而不管什么星照引我前程，

都对我露出一副和悦的笑容，

把华服加给我这寒碜的爱情，

使我配得上你那缱绻的恩宠。

那时我才敢对你夸耀我的爱，

否则怕你考验我，总要躲起来。

（梁宗岱　译）

驯悍记　第五幕　第二场

彼特鲁乔　凯瑟琳，你去告诉这些倔强的女人，做妻子的应该向她们的夫主尽些什么本分。

寡妇　好了，好了，别开玩笑了，我们不要听这些个。

彼特鲁乔　说吧，先讲给她听。

寡妇　用不着她讲。

彼特鲁乔　我偏要她讲，先讲给她听。

凯瑟丽娜　哎呀！展开你那颦蹙的眉头，收起你那轻蔑的瞥视，不要让它伤害你的主人，你的君王，你的支配者。它会使你的美貌减色，就像严霜噬噬着草原，它会使你的名誉受损，就像旋风摧残着蓓蕾；它绝对没有可取之处，也丝毫引不起别人的好感。一个使性的女人，就像一池受到激动的泉水，混浊可憎，失去一切的美丽，无论怎样喉干吻渴的人，也不愿把它啜饮一口。你的丈夫就是你的主人、你的生命、你的所有者、你的头脑、你的君王；他照顾着你，扶养着你，在海洋里陆地上辛苦操作，夜里冒着风波，白天忍受寒冷，你却穿得暖暖的住在家里，享受着安全与舒适。他希望你贡献给他的，只是你的爱情，你的温柔的辞色，你的真心的服从；你欠他的好处这么多，他所要求于你的酬报却是这么微薄！一个女人对待她的丈夫，应当像臣子对待君王一样忠心恭顺；倘使她倔强使性，乖张暴戾，不服从他正当的愿望，那么她岂不是一个大逆不道、忘恩负义的叛徒？应当长跪乞和的时候，她却向他挑战；应当尽心竭力服侍他、敬爱他、顺从他的时候，她却企图篡夺主权，发号施令：这一种愚蠢的行为，真是女人的耻辱。我们的身体为什么这样柔软无力，耐不了苦，熬不起忧患？那不是因为我们的性情必须和我们的外表互相一致，同样温柔吗？听我的话吧，你们这些倔强而无力的可怜虫！我的心从前也跟你们一样高傲，也许我有比你们更多的理由，不甘心向人俯首认输，可是现在我知道我们的枪矛只是些稻草，我们的力量是软弱的，我们的软弱是无比的，我们所有的只是一个空虚的外表。所以你们还是挫抑你们无益的傲气，跪下来向你们的丈夫请求怜爱吧。为了表示我的顺从，只要我的丈夫吩咐我，我就可以向他下跪，让他因此而心中快慰。

（朱生豪　译）

特洛伊罗斯与克瑞西达　第二幕　第二场

特洛伊罗斯　假如我今天娶了一个妻子，我的选择是取决于我的意志，我的意志是受我的耳目所左右。假如在选定以后，我的意志又不满于我的选择，那么我怎么可以避免既成的事实呢？一方面逃避责任，一方面又不损害自己的荣誉，这样的事是不可能的。我们把绸缎污毁了以后，就不能再拿它向商家退换；我们也不因为已经吃饱，就把剩余的食物倒在肮脏的阴沟里。当初大家都赞成帕里斯去向希腊人报复，你们的一致同意鼓励了他的远行，善于捣乱的海浪和天风，也协力帮助他一帆风顺地到了他的目的地。因为希腊人俘虏了我们一个年老的姑母，他夺回了一个希腊的王妃作为交换，她的青春和娇艳掩盖了朝暾的美丽。我们为什么留住她不放？因为希腊人没有放还我们的姑母，她是值得我们保留的吗？啊，她是一颗明珠，它的高贵的价值，曾经掀动过千百个国王迢迢渡海而来，大家都要做一个觅宝的商人。你们不能不承认帕里斯的前去并不是失策，因为你们大家都喊着“去！去！”你们也不能不承认他带回了光荣的战利品，因为你们大家都拍手欢呼，说她的价值是不可估计的。那么你们现在为什么要诋毁从你们自己的智慧中产生的果实，把你们曾经估计为价值超过海洋和陆地的宝物重新贬斥得一文不值呢？啊！赃物已经偷了来了，我们却不敢把它保留下来，这才是最卑劣的偷窃！这样的盗贼是不配偷窃这样的宝物的。

（朱生豪　译）

安东尼与克莉奥佩特拉　第一幕　第一场

菲罗　嘿，咱们主帅这样迷恋，真太不成话啦。从前他指挥大军的时候，他的英勇的眼睛像全身盔甲的战神一样发出棱棱的威光，现在却如醉如痴地尽是盯在一张黄褐色的脸上。他的大将的雄心曾经在激烈的鏖战里涨断了胸前的扣带，现在却失掉一切常态，甘愿做一具风扇，扇凉一个吉卜赛女人的欲焰。瞧！他们来了。

（喇叭奏花腔。安东尼及克莉奥佩特拉率侍从上；太监掌扇随侍。）

菲罗　留心看着，你就可以知道他本来是这世界上三大柱石之一，现在已经变成一个娼妇的弄人了，瞧吧。

克莉奥佩特拉（向安东尼）要是那真的是爱，告诉我多么深。

安东尼　可以量深浅的爱是贫乏的。

（朱生豪　译）

奥瑟罗　第一幕　第三场

罗德利哥　我该怎么办？我承认这样痴心是一件丢脸的事，可是我没有力量把它补救过来呀。

伊阿古　力量！废话！我们变成这样那样，全在于我们自己。我们的身体就像一座园圃，我们的意志是这园圃里的园丁；不论我们插荨麻、种莴苣、栽下牛膝草、拔起百里香，或者单独培植一种草木，或者把全园种得万卉纷披，让它荒废不治也好，把它辛勤耕垦也好，那权力都在于我们的意志。要是在我们的生命之中，理智和情欲不能保持平衡，我们血肉的邪心就会引导我们到一个荒唐的结局。可是我们有的是理智，可以冲淡我们汹涌的热情、肉体的刺激和奔放的淫欲。我认为你所称为“爱情”的，也不过是那样一种东西。

（朱生豪　译）

十四行诗　一三一

尽管你不算美，你的暴虐并不

亚于那些因美而骄横的女人；

因为你知道我的心那么糊涂，

把你当作世上的至美和至珍。

不过，说实话，见过你的人都说，

你的脸缺少使爱呻吟的魅力：

尽管我心中发誓反对这说法，

我可还没有公开否认的勇气。

当然我发的誓一点也不欺人；

数不完的呻吟，一想起你的脸，

马上联翩而来，可以为我作证：

对于我，你的黑胜于一切秀妍。

你一点也不黑，除了你的人品，

可能为了这缘故，诽谤才流行。

（梁宗岱　译）

Power in government

Hamlet, Act III, Scene 3

rosencrantz:
The single and peculiar life is bound
With all the strength and armour of the mind
To keep itself from noyance, but much more
That spirit upon whose weal depends and rests
The lives of many. The cease of majesty
Dies not alone, but like a gulf doth draw
What's near it with it. It is a massy wheel
Fixed on the summit of the highest mount,
To whose huge spokes ten thousand lesser things
Are mortised and adjoined, which when it falls
Each small annexment, petty consequence,
Attends the boist'rous ruin. Never alone
Did the King sigh, but with a general groan.

Richard II, Act III, Scene 2

king richard:
Of comfort no man speak.
Let's talk of graves, of worms, and epitaphs,
Make dust our paper and with rainy eyes
Write sorrow on the bosom of the earth.
Let's choose executors and talk of wills,
And yet not so, for what can we bequeath
Save our deposed bodies to the ground?
Our lands, our lives, and all are Bolingbroke's,
And nothing can we call our own but death,
And that small model of the barren earth
Which serves as paste and cover to our bones.
For God's sake, let us sit upon the ground
And tell sad stories of the death of kings:
How some have been deposed, some slain in war,
Some haunted by the ghosts they have deposed,
Some poisoned by their wives, some sleeping killed,
All murdered. For within the hollow crown
That rounds the mortal temples of a king
Keeps Death his court; and there the antic sits,
Scoffing his state and grinning at his pomp,
Allowing him a breath, a little scene,
To monarchize, be feared, and kill with looks,
Infusing him with self and vain conceit,
As if this flesh which walls about our life
Were brass impregnable; and humoured thus,
Comes at the last, and with a little pin
Bores through his castle wall; and farewell, king.
Cover your heads and mock not flesh and blood
With solemn reverence. Throw away respect,
Tradition, form, and ceremonious duty,
For you have but mistook me all this while.
I live with bread, like you; feel want,
Taste grief, need friends. Subjected thus,
How can you say to me I am a king?

Timon of Athens, Act IV, Scene 3

apemantus:
If thou didst put this sour cold habit on
To castigate thy pride, 'twere well, but thou
Dost it enforcedly. Thou'dst courtier be again
Wert thou not beggar. Willing misery
Outlives incertain pomp, is crowned before.
The one is filling still, never complete,
The other at high wish. Best state, contentless,
Hath a distracted and most wretched being,
Worse than the worst, content.
Thou shouldst desire to die, being miserable.

timon:
Not by his breath that is more miserable.
Thou art a slave whom fortune's tender arm
With favour never clasped, but bred a dog.
Hadst thou like us from our first swathe proceeded
The sweet degrees that this brief world affords
To such as may the passive drudges of it
Freely command, thou wouldst have plunged thyself
In general riot, melted down thy youth
In different beds of lust, and never learned
The icy precepts of respect, but followed
The sugared game before thee. But myself,
Who had the world as my confectionary,
The mouths, the tongues, the eyes and hearts of men
At duty, more than I could frame employment,
That numberless upon me stuck, as leaves
Do on the oak, have with one winter's brush
Fell from their boughs, and left me open, bare
For every storm that blows. I to bare this,
That never knew but better, is some burden.
Thy nature did commence in sufferance, time
Hath made thee hard in't. Why shouldst thou hate men?
They never flattered thee. What hast thou given?
If thou wilt curse, thy father, that poor rag,
Must be thy subject, who in spite put stuff
To some she-beggar and compounded thee
Poor rogue hereditary. Hence, be gone.
If thou hadst not been born the worst of men
Thou hadst been a knave and flatterer.

Henry V, Act I, Scene 2

canterbury:
True. Therefore doth heaven divide
The state of man in divers functions,
Setting endeavour in continual motion;
To which is fixed, as an aim or butt,
Obedience. For so work the honey-bees,
Creatures that by a rule in nature teach
The act of order to a peopled kingdom.
They have a king, and officers of sorts,
Where some like magistrates correct at home;
Others like merchants venture trade abroad;
Others like soldiers, armed in their stings,
Make boot upon the summer's velvet buds,
Which pillage they with merry march bring home
To the tent royal of their emperor,
Who busied in his majesty surveys
The singing masons building roofs of gold,
The civil citizens lading up the honey,
The poor mechanic porters crowding in
Their heavy burdens at his narrow gate,
The sad-eyed justice with his surly hum
Delivering o'er to executors pale
The lazy yawning drone. I this infer:
That many things, having full reference
To one consent, may work contrariously.
As many arrows, loosed several ways,
Fly to one mark, as many ways meet in one town,
As many fresh streams meet in one salt sea,
As many lines close in the dial's centre,
So may a thousand actions once afoot
End in one purpose, and be all well borne
Without defect. Therefore to France my liege.
Divide your happy England into four,
Whereof take you one quarter into France,
And you withal shall make all Gallia shake.
If we with thrice such powers left at home
Cannot defend our own doors from the dog,
Let us be worried, and our nation lose
The name of hardiness and policy.

Coriolanus, Act II, Scene 2

second officer: There hath been many great men that have flattered the people who ne'er loved them; and there be many that they have loved they know not wherefore, so that if they love they know not why; they hate upon no better a ground. Therefore for Coriolanus neither to care whether they love or hate him manifests the true knowledge he has in their disposition, and out of his noble carelessness lets them plainly see it.

first officer: If he did not care whether he had their love or no he waved indifferently 'twixt doing them neither good nor harm, but he seeks their hate with greater devotion than they can render it him, and leaves nothing undone that may fully discover him their opposite. Now to seem to affect the malice and displeasure of the people is as bad as that which he dislikes, to flatter them for their love.

second officer: He hath deserved worthily of his country, and his ascent is not by such easy degrees as those who, having been supple and courteous to the people, bonneted, without any further deed to have them at all into their estimation and report. But he hath so planted his honours in their eyes and his actions in their hearts that for their tongues to be silent and not confess so much were a kind of in-grateful injury. To report otherwise were a malice that, giving itself the lie, would pluck reproof and rebuke from every ear that heard it.

first officer: No more of him. He's a worthy man.

Henry V, Act IV, Scene 2

king harry:
Upon the King:
‘Let us our lives, our souls, our debts, our care-full wives,
Our children, and our sins, lay on the King.’
We must bear all. O hard condition,
Twin-born with greatness, subject to the breath of every fool,
Whose sense no more can feel
But his own wringing. What infinite heartsease
Must kings neglect that private men enjoy?
And what have kings that privates have not too,
Save ceremony, save general ceremony?
And what art thou, thou idol ceremony?
What kind of god art thou, that suffer'st more
Of mortal griefs than do thy worshippers?
What are thy rents? What are thy comings-in?
O ceremony, show me but thy worth.
What is thy soul of adoration?
Art thou aught else but place, degree, and form,
Creating awe and fear in other men?
Wherein thou art less happy, being feared,
Than they in fearing.
What drink'st thou oft, instead of homage sweet,
But poisoned flattery? O be sick, great greatness,
And bid thy ceremony give thee cure.
Think'st thou the fiery fever will go out
With titles blown from adulation?
Will it give place to flexure and low bending?
Canst thou, when thou command'st the beggar's knee,
Command the health of it? No, thou proud dream
That play'st so subtly with a king's repose.
I am a king that find thee, and I know
'Tis not the balm, the sceptre, and the ball,
The sword, the mace, the crown imperial,
The intertissued robe of gold and pearl,
The farced title running fore the king,
The throne he sits on, nor the tide of pomp
That beats upon the high shore of this world.
No, not all these, thrice-gorgeous ceremony,
Not all these, laid in bed majestical,
Can sleep so soundly as the wretched slave
Who with a body filled and vacant mind
Gets him to rest, crammed with distressful bread;
Never sees horrid night, the child of hell,
But like a lackey from the rise to set
Sweats in the eye of Phoebus, and all night
Sleeps in Elysium; next day, after dawn
Doth rise and help Hyperion to his horse,
And follows so the ever-running year
With profitable labour to his grave.
And but for ceremony such a wretch,
Winding up days with toil and nights with sleep
Had the forehand and vantage of a king.
The slave, a member of the country's peace,
Enjoys it, but in gross brain little wots
What watch the King keeps to maintain the peace,
Whose hours the peasant best advantages.

Measure for Measure, Act I, Scene 1

duke:
Of government the properties to unfold
Would seem in me t'affect speech and discourse,
Since I am put to know that your own science
Exceeds in that the lists of all advice
My strength can give you. Then no more remains
But this: to your sufficiency, as your worth is able,
And let them work. The nature of our people,
Our city's institutions and the terms
For common justice, you're as pregnant in
As art and practice hath enriched any
That we remember.

He gives Escalus papers.

There is our commission,
From which we would not have you warp.

(To a lord)

Call hither,
I say bid come before us Angelo.

(To Escalus)

What figure of us think you he will bear?
For you must know we have with special soul
Elected him our absence to supply,
Lent him our terror, dressed him with our love,
And given his deputation all the organs
Of our own power. What think you of it?

escalus:
If any in Vienna be of worth
To undergo such ample grace and honour
It is Lord Angelo.

Enter Angelo

duke:
Look where he comes.

angelo:
Always obedient to your grace's will,
I come to know your pleasure.

duke:
Angelo,
There is a kind of character in thy life
That to th'observer doth thy history
Fully unfold. Thyself and thy belongings
Are not thine own so proper as to waste
Thyself upon thy virtues, they on thee.
Heaven doth with us as we with torches do,
Not light them for themselves; for if our virtues
Did not go forth of us, 'twere all alike
As if we had them not. Spirits are not finely touched
But to fine issues, nor nature never lends
The smallest scruple of her excellence
But, like a thrifty goddess, she determines
Herself the glory of a creditor,
Both thanks and use. But I do bend my speech
To one that can my part in him advertise.
Hold therefore, Angelo.
In our remove be thou at full ourself:
Mortality and mercy in Vienna
Live in thy tongue and heart. Old Escalus,
Though first in question, is thy secondary.
Take thy commission.

Richard II, Act V, Scene 5

king richard:
I have been studying how I may compare
This prison where I live unto the world,
And for because the world is populous,
And here is not a creature but myself,
I cannot do it. Yet I'll hammer it out.
My brain I'll prove the female to my soul,
My soul the father, and these two beget
A generation of still-breeding thoughts,
And these same thoughts people this little world
In humours like the people of this world.
For no thought is contented. The better sort,
As thoughts of things divine, are intermixed
With scruples, and do set the faith itself
Against the faith, as thus:‘Come, little ones’,
And then again,
‘It is as hard to come as for a camel
To thread the postern of a small needle's eye.’
Thoughts tending to ambition, they do plot
Unlikely wonders: how these vain, weak nails
May tear a passage through the flinty ribs
Of this hard world, my ragged prison walls;
And for they cannot, die in their own pride.
Thoughts tending to content flatter themselves
That they are not the first of fortune's slaves,
Nor shall not be the last, like seely beggars,
Who, sitting in the stocks, refuge their shame
That many have, and others must, set there;
And in this thought they find a kind of ease,
Bearing their own misfortunes on the back
Of such as have before endured the like.
Thus play I in one person many people,
And none contented. Sometimes am I king,
Then treason makes me wish myself a beggar,
And so I am. Then crushing penury
Persuades me I was better when a king.
Then am I kinged again, and by and by
Think that I am unkinged by Bolingbroke,
And straight am nothing. But whate'er I be,
Nor I, nor any man that but man is,
With nothing shall be pleased till he be eased
With being nothing.

Timon of Athens, Act I, Scene 1

poet:
You see this confluence, this great flood of visitors.
I have in this rough work shaped out a man
Whom this beneath world doth embrace and hug
With amplest entertainment. My free drift
Halts not particularly, but moves itself
In a wide sea of tax. No levelled malice
Infects one comma in the course I hold,
But flies an eagle flight, bold and forth on,
Leaving no tract behind.

painter:
How shall I understand you?

poet:
I will unbolt to you.
You see how all conditions, how all minds,
As well of glib and slipp'ry creatures as
Of grave and austere quality, tender down
Their service to Lord Timon. His large fortune,
Upon his good and gracious nature hanging,
Subdues and properties to his love and tendance
All sorts of hearts. Yea, from the glass-faced flatterer
To Apemantus, that few things loves better
Than to abhor himself; even he drops down
The knee before him, and returns in peace,
Most rich in Timon's nod.

painter:
I saw them speak together.

poet:
Sir, I have upon a high and pleasant hill
Feigned Fortune to be throned. The base o'th'mount
Is ranked with all deserts, all kind of natures
That labour on the bosom of this sphere
To propagate their states. Amongst them all
Whose eyes are on this sovereign lady fixed
One do I personate of Lord Timon's frame,
Whom Fortune with her ivory hand wafts to her,
Whose present grace to present slaves and servants
Translates his rivals.

painter:
'Tis conceived to scope.
This throne, this Fortune, and this hill methinks,
With one man beckoned from the rest below,
Bowing his head against the steepy mount
To climb his happiness, would be well expressed
In our condition.

poet:
Nay sir, but hear me on.
All those which were his fellows but of late,
Some better than his value, on the moment
Follow his strides, his lobbies fill with tendance,
Rain sacrificial whisperings in his ear,
Make sacred even his stirrup, and through him
Drink the free air.

painter:
Ay, marry, what of these?

poet:
When Fortune in her shift and change of mood
Spurns down her late beloved, all his dependants,
Which laboured after him to the mountain's top
Even on their knees and hands, let him fall down,
Not one accompanying his declining foot.

Henry IV, Part I, Act I, Scene 2

sir john oldcastle: Marry then, sweet wag, when thou art king let not us that are squires of the night's body be called thieves of the day's beauty. Let us be‘Diana's foresters’,‘gentlemen of the shade’,‘minions of the moon’, and let men say we be men of good government, being governed, as the sea is, by our noble and chaste mistress the moon, under whose countenance we steal.

prince harry: Thou sayst well, and it holds well too, for the fortune of us that are the moon's men doth ebb and flow like the sea, being governed as the sea is by the moon. As for proof now: a purse of gold most resolutely snatched on Monday night and most dissolutely spent on Tuesday morning, got with swearing‘lay by!’and spent with crying‘bring in!’, now in as low an ebb as the foot of the ladder and by and by in as high a flow as the ridge of the gallows.

Richard II, Act III, Scene 4

gardener (to First Man):
Go, bind thou up young dangling apricots
Which, like unruly children, make their sire
Stoop with oppression of their prodigal weight.
Give some supportance to the bending twigs.
(To Second Man) Go thou, and, like an executioner,
Cut off the heads of too fast-growing sprays
That look too lofty in our commonwealth.
All must be even in our government.
You thus employed, I will go root away
The noisome weeds which without profit suck
The soil's fertility from wholesome flowers.

first man:
Why should we, in the compass of a pale,
Keep law and form and due proportion,
Showing as in a model our firm estate,
When our sea-walled garden, the whole land,
Is full of weeds, her fairest flowers choked up,
Her fruit trees all unpruned, her hedges ruined,
Her knots disordered, and her wholesome herbs
Swarming with caterpillars?

gardener:
Hold thy peace.
He that hath suffered this disordered spring
Hath now himself met with the fall of leaf.
The weeds which his broad spreading leaves did shelter,
That seemed in eating him to hold him up,
Are plucked up, root and all, by Bolingbroke —
I mean the Earl of Wiltshire, Bushy, Green.

second man:
What, are they dead?

gardener:
They are; and Bolingbroke
Hath seized the wasteful King. O, what pity is it
That he had not so trimmed and dressed his land
As we this garden! We at time of year
Do wound the bark, the skin of our fruit trees,
Lest, being over-proud in sap and blood,
With too much riches it confound itself.
Had he done so to great and growing men,
They might have lived to bear, and he to taste,
Their fruits of duty. Superfluous branches
We lop away, that bearing boughs may live.
Had he done so, himself had borne the crown,
Which waste of idle hours hath quite thrown down.

King Lear, Act III, Scene 1

goneril:
Hear me, my lord.
What need you five-and-twenty, ten, or five,
To follow in a house where twice so many
Have a command to tend you?

regan:
What need one?

lear:
O, reason not the need! Our basest beggars
Are in the poorest thing superfluous.
Allow not nature more than nature needs.
Man's life is cheap as beast's. Thou art a lady.
If only to go warm were gorgeous,
Why, nature needs not what thou, gorgeous, wear'st,
Which scarcely keeps thee warm. But for true need,
You heavens, give me that patience, patience I need.
You see me here, you gods, a poor old man,
As full of grief as age, wretched in both.
If it be you that stirs these daughters' hearts
Against their father, fool me not so much
To bear it tamely. Touch me with noble anger
And let not women's weapons, water-drops,
Stain my man's cheeks. No, you unnatural hags,
I will have such revenges on you both
That all the world shall — I will do such things —
What they are, yet I know not; but they shall be
The terrors of the earth. You think I'll weep.
No I'll not weep. I have full cause of weeping,

Storm and tempest.

But this heart shall break into a hundred thousand flaws
Or ere I'll weep. O Fool, I shall go mad!

Sonnet 94

They that have power to hurt and will do none,
That do not do the thing they most do show,
Who moving others are themselves as stone,
Unmoved, cold, and to temptation slow;
They rightly do inherit heaven's graces
And husband nature's riches from expense;
They are the lords and owners of their faces,
Others but stewards of their excellence.
The summer's flower is to the summer sweet,
Though to itself it only live and die,
But if that flower with base infection meet
The basest weed outbraves his dignity.
For sweetest things turn sourest by their deeds:
Lilies that fester smell far worse than weeds.

Julius Caesar, Act I, Scene 2

cassius:
Why, man, he doth bestride the narrow world
Like a Colossus, and we petty men
Walk under his huge legs and peep about
To find ourselves dishonourable graves.
Men at sometime were masters of their fates.
The fault, dear Brutus, is not in our stars
But in ourselves, that we are underlings.
Brutus and Caesar: what should be in that‘Caesar’?
Why should that name be sounded more than yours?
Write them together: yours is as fair a name.
Sound them: it doth become the mouth as well.
Weigh them: it is as heavy. Conjure with 'em:
‘Brutus’will start a spirit as soon as‘Caesar’.
Now in the names of all the gods at once,
Upon what meat doth this our Caesar feed
That he is grown so great? Age, thou art shamed.
Rome, thou hast lost the breed of noble bloods.
When went there by an age since the great flood,
But it was famed with more than with one man?
When could they say till now, that talked of Rome,
That her wide walls encompassed but one man?
Now is it Rome indeed, and room enough
When there is in it but one only man.
O you and I have heard our fathers say
There was a Brutus once that would have brooked
Th'eternal devil to keep his state in Rome
As easily as a king.

Coriolanus, Act II, Scene 3

brutus (to the citizens):
Could you not have told him
As you were lessoned? When he had no power
But was a petty servant to the state
He was your enemy, ever spake against
Your liberties and the charters that you bear
I'th'body of the weal; and now arriving
A place of potency and sway o'th' state,
If he should still malignantly remain
Fast foe to th' plebeii, your voices might
Be curses to yourselves. You should have said
That as his worthy deeds did claim no less
Than what he stood for, so his gracious nature
Would think upon you for your voices and
Translate his malice towards you into love,
Standing your friendly lord.

sicinius (to the citizens):
Thus to have said
As you were foreadvised had touched his spirit
And tried his inclination, from him plucked
Either is gracious promise, which you might,
As cause had called you up, have held him to,
Or else it would have galled his surly nature,
Which easily endures not article
Tying him to aught. So putting him to rage,
You should have ta'en th'advantage of his choler
And passed him unelected.

brutus (to the citizens):
Did you perceive
He did solicit you in free contempt
When he did need your loves, and do you think
That his contempt shall not be bruising to you
When he hath power to crush? Why, had your bodies
No heart among you? Or had you tongues to cry
Against the rectorship of judgement?

sicinius (to the citizens):
Have you
Ere now denied the asker, and now again,
Of him that did not ask but mock, bestow
Your sued-for tongues?

third citizen:
He's not confirmed, we may deny him yet.

second citizen:
And will deny him.
I'll have five hundred voices of that sound.

first citizen:
I twice five hundred, and their friends to piece 'em.

brutus:
Get you hence instantly, and tell those friends
They have chose a consul that will from them take
Their liberties, make them of no more voice
Than dogs that are as often beat for barking
As therefor kept to do so.

Othello, Act I, Scene 1

iago:
I follow him to serve my turn upon him.
We cannot all be masters, nor all masters
Cannot be truly followed. You shall mark
Many a duteous and knee-crooking knave
That, doting on his own obsequious bondage,
Wears out his time much like his master's ass,
For naught but provender, and when he's old, cashiered.
Whip me such honest knaves. Others there are
Who, trimmed in forms and visages of duty,
Keep yet their hearts attending on themselves,
And throwing but shows of service on their lords
Do well thrive by 'em, and when they have lined their coats
Do themselves homage. These fellows have some soul,
And such a one do I profess myself; for, sir,
It is as sure that you are Roderigo,
Were I the Moor I would not be Iago.
In following him I follow but myself.
Heaven is my judge, not I for love and duty,
But seeming so for my peculiar end.
For when my outward action doth demonstrate
The native act and figure of my heart
In compliment extern, 'tis not long after
But I will wear my heart upon my sleeve
For daws to peck at. I am not what I am.

Richard III, Act III, Scene 7

buckingham:
Know then, it is your fault that you resign
The supreme seat, the throne majestical,
The sceptred office of your ancestors,
Your state of fortune and your due of birth,
The lineal glory of your royal house,
To the corruption of a blemished stock,
Whiles in the mildness of your sleepy thoughts —
Which here we waken to our country's good —
The noble isle doth want her proper limbs.
Her face defaced with scars of infamy,
Her royal stock graft with ignoble plants
And almost shouldered in the swallowing gulf
Of dark forgetfulness and deep oblivion,
Which to recure we heartily solicit
Your gracious self to take on you the charge
And kingly government of this your land,
Not as Protector, steward, substitute,
Or lowly factor for another's gain,
But as successively, from blood to blood,
Your right of birth, your empery, your own.
For this, consorted with the citizens,
Your very worshipful and loving friends,
And by their vehement instigation,
In this just cause come I to move your grace.

richard gloucester:
I cannot tell if to depart in silence
Or bitterly to speak in your reproof
Best fitteth my degree or your condition.
Your love deserves my thanks, but my desert,
Unmeritable, shuns your high request.
First, if all obstacles were cut away
And that my path were even to the crown,
As the ripe revenue and due of birth,
Yet so much is my poverty of spirit,
So mighty and so many my defects,
That I would rather hide me from my greatness —
Being a barque to brook no mighty sea —
Than in my greatness covet to be hid,
And in the vapour of my glory smothered.
But, God be thanked, there is no need of me,
And much I need to help you, were there need.
The royal tree hath left us royal fruit,
Which, mellowed by the stealing hours of time,
Will well become the seat of majesty
And make, no doubt, us happy by his reign.
On him I lay that you would lay on me,
The right and fortune of his happy stars,
Which God defend that I should wring from him.

buckingham:
My lord, this argues conscience in your grace,
But the respects thereof are nice and trivial,
All circumstances well considered.
You say that Edward is your brother's son,
So say we too, but not by Edward's wife,
For first was he contract to Lady Lucy,
Your mother lives a witness to his vow,
And afterward, by substitute, betrothed
To Bona, sister to the King of France.
These both put off, a poor petitioner,
A care-crazed mother to a many sons,
A beauty-waning and distressed widow
Even in the afternoon of her best days,
Made prize and purchase of his wanton eye,
Seduced the pitch and height of his degree
To base declension and loathed bigamy.
By her in his unlawful bed he got
This Edward, whom our manners call the Prince.
More bitterly could I expostulate,
Save that for reverence to some alive
I give a sparing limit to my tongue.
Then, good my lord, take to your royal self
This proffered benefit of dignity,
If not to bless us and the land withal,
Yet to draw forth your noble ancestry
From the corruption of abusing times
Unto a lineal, true-derived course.

mayor (to Richard):
Do, good my lord. Your citizens entreat you.

buckingham (to Richard):
Refuse not, mighty lord, this proffered love.

catesby (to Richard):
O make them joyful. Grant their lawful suit.

richard gloucester:
Alas, why would you heap this care on me?
I am unfit for state and majesty.
I do beseech you, take it not amiss,
I cannot, nor I will not, yield to you.

buckingham:
If you refuse it, as, in love and zeal,
Loath to depose the child, your brother's son,
As well we know your tenderness of heart
And gentle, kind, effeminate remorse,
Which we have noted in you to your kindred,
And equally indeed to all estates,
Yet know, whe'er you accept our suit or no,
Your brother's son shall never reign our king;
But we will plant some other in the throne,
To the disgrace and downfall of your house.
And in this resolution here we leave you.
Come, citizens. 'Swounds, I'll entreat no more.

richard gloucester:
O do not swear, my lord of Buckingham.
Exeunt Buckingham and some others.

catesby:
Call him again, sweet prince. Accept their suit.

(another):
If you deny them, all the land will rue it.

richard gloucester:
Will you enforce me to a world of cares?
Call them again.

Exit one or more.

I am not made of stone,
But penetrable to your kind entreats,
Albeit against my conscience and my soul.

Enter Buckingham and the rest.

Cousin of Buckingham, and sage, grave men,
Since you will buckle fortune on my back,
To bear her burden, whe'er I will or no,
I must have patience to endure the load.
But if black scandal or foul-faced reproach
Attend the sequel of your imposition,
Your mere enforcement shall acquittance me
From all the impure blots and stains thereof.
For God doth know, and you may partly see,
How far I am from the desire of this.

mayor:
God bless your grace! We see it and will say it.

richard gloucester:
In saying so you shall but say the truth.

buckingham:
Then I salute you with this royal title:
Long live kind Richard, England's worthy king!

(all but richard):
Amen.

Troilus and Cressida, Act I, Scene 3

ulysses:
Troy, yet upon his basis, had been down
And the great Hector's sword had lacked a master
But for these instances:
The specialty of rule hath been neglected,
And look how many Grecian tents do stand
Hollow upon this plain: so many hollow factions.
When that the general is not like the hive
To whom the foragers shall all repair,
What honey is expected? Degree being vizarded,
Th'unworthiest shows as fairly in the masque
[...]
The heavens themselves, the planets, and this centre,
Observe degree, priority, and place,
Infixture, course, proportion, season, form,
Office and custom, in all line of order.
And therefore is the glorious planet Sol,
In noble eminence enthroned and sphered
Amidst the other, whose med'cinable eye
Corrects the ill aspects of planets evil
And posts like the commandment of a king,
Sans check, to good and bad. But when the planets
In evil mixture to disorder wander,
What plagues and what portents, what mutiny?
What raging of the sea, shaking of earth?
Commotion in the winds, frights, changes, horrors
Divert and crack, rend and deracinate
The unity and married calm of states
Quite from their fixture. O when degree is shaked,
Which is the ladder to all high designs,
The enterprise is sick. How could communities,
Degrees in schools, and brotherhoods in cities,
Peaceful commerce from dividable shores,
The primogenity and due of birth,
Prerogative of age, crowns, sceptres, laurels,
But by degree stand in authentic place?
Take but degree away, untune that string,
And hark what discord follows. Each thing meets
In mere oppugnancy. The bounded waters
Should lift their bosoms higher than the shores
And make a sop of all this solid globe;
Strength should be lord of imbecility,
And the rude son should strike his father dead.
Force should be right; or rather, right and wrong,
Between whose endless jar justice resides,
Should lose their names, and so should justice too,
Then everything includes itself in power:
Power into will, will into appetite,
And appetite, an universal wolf,
So doubly seconded with will and power,
Must make perforce an universal prey,
And last eat up himself. Great Agamemnon,
This chaos, when degree is suffocate,
Follows the choking;
And this neglection of degree it is,
That by a pace goes backward in a purpose
It hath to climb. The general's disdained
By him one step below; he, by the next;
That next, by him beneath. So every step,
Exampled by the first pace that is sick
Of his superior, grows to an envious fever
Of pale and bloodless emulation.
And 'tis this fever that keeps Troy on foot,
Not her own sinews. To end a tale of length:
Troy in our weakness lives, not in her strength.

Henry IV, Part II, Act III, Scene 1

king henry:
How many thousand of my poorest subjects
Are at this hour asleep? O sleep, O gentle sleep,
Nature's soft nurse, how have I frighted thee
That thou no more wilt weigh my eyelids down
And steep my senses in forgetfulness?
Why rather, sleep, liest thou in smoky cribs,
Upon uneasy pallets stretching thee,
And hushed with buzzing night-flies to thy slumber,
Than in the perfumed chambers of the great,
Under the canopies of costly state
And lulled with sound of sweetest melody?
O thou dull god, why li'st thou with the vile
In loathsome beds, and leav'st the kingly couch
A watch-case, or a common 'larum-bell?
Wilt thou upon the high and giddy mast
Seal up the ship-boy's eyes, and rock his brains
In cradle of the rude imperious surge,
And in the visitation of the winds,
Who take the ruffian billows by the top,
Curling their monstrous heads and hanging them
With deafing clamour in the slippery clouds,
That, with the hurly, death itself awakes?
Canst thou, O partial sleep, give thy repose
To the wet sea-boy in an hour so rude,
And in the calmest and most stillest night,
With all appliances and means to boot,
Deny it to a king? Then happy low, lie down.
Uneasy lies the head that wears a crown.

Power in the family

The Merchant of Venice, Act III, Scene 2

portia:
You see me, Lord Bassanio, where I stand,
Such as I am. Though for myself alone
I would not be ambitious in my wish
To wish myself much better, yet for you
I would be trebled twenty times myself,
A thousand times more fair, ten thousand times more rich,
That only to stand high in your account
I might in virtues, beauties, livings, friends,
Exceed account. But the full sum of me
Is sum of something which, to term in gross
Is an unlessoned girl, unschooled, unpractised,
Happy in this, she is not yet so old
But she may learn; happier than this,
She is not bred so dull but she can learn;
Happiest of all is that her gentle spirit
Commits itself to yours to be directed
As from her lord, her governor, her king.
Myself and what is mine to you and yours
Is now converted. But now I was the lord
Of this fair mansion, master of my servants,
Queen o'er myself; and even now, but now,
This house, these servants, and this same myself
Are yours, my lord's. I give them with this ring,
Which when you part from, lose, or give away,
Let it presage the ruin of your love,
And be my vantage to exclaim on you.

King Lear, Act I, Scene 1

lear:
Meantime we shall express our darker purpose.
Give me the map there. Know that we have divided
In three our kingdom, and 'tis our fast intent
To shake all cares and business from our age,
Conferring them on younger strengths while we
Unburdened crawl toward death. Our son of Cornwall,
And you, our no less loving son of Albany,
We have this hour a constant will to publish
Our daughters' several dowers, that future strife
May be prevented now. The princes France and Burgundy —
Great rivals in our youngest daughter's love —
Long in our court have made their amorous sojourn,
And here are to be answered. Tell me, my daughters,
Since now we will divest us both of rule,
Interest of territory, cares of state,
Which of you shall we say doth love us most,
That we our largest bounty may extend
Where nature doth with merit challenge? Goneril,
Our eldest born, speak first.

goneril:
Sir, I love you more than words can wield the matter,
Dearer than eyesight, space, and liberty,
Beyond what can be valued, rich or rare,
No less than life, with grace, health, beauty, honour,
As much as child e'er loved or father found,
A love that makes breath poor and speech unable;
Beyond all manner of so much I love you.

cordelia (aside):
What shall Cordelia speak? Love and be silent.

lear (to Goneril):
Of all these bounds even from this line to this,
With shadowy forests and with champaigns riched,
With plenteous rivers and wide-skirted meads,
We make thee lady. To thine and Albany's issues
Be this perpetual. What says our second daughter?
Our dearest Regan, wife of Cornwall?

regan:
I am made of that self mettle as my sister,
And prize me at her worth. In my true heart
I find she names my very deed of love;
Only she comes too short, that I profess
Myself an enemy to all other joys,
Which the most precious square of sense possesses,
And find I am alone felicitate
In your dear highness' love.

cordelia (aside):
Then, poor Cordelia,
And yet not so, since I am sure my love's
More ponderous than my tongue.

lear (to Regan):
To thee and thine hereditary ever
Remain this ample third of our fair kingdom,
No less in space, validity, and pleasure
Than that conferred on Goneril. (to Cordelia) Now our joy,
Although our last and least, to whose young love
The vines of France and milk of Burgundy
Strive to be interessed: what can you say to draw
A third more opulent than your sisters? Speak.

cordelia:
Nothing, my lord.

lear:
Nothing?

cordelia:
Nothing.

lear:
Nothing will come of nothing.

Henry IV, Part II, Act II, Scene 3

lady percy:
O yet, for God's sake, go not to these wars!
The time was, father, that you broke your word
When you were more endeared to it than now,
When your own Percy, when my heart's dear Harry,
Threw many a northward look to see his father
Bring up his powers; but he did long in vain.
Who then persuaded you to stay at home?
There were two honours lost, yours and your son's.
For yours, the God of heaven brighten it!
For his, it stuck upon him as the sun
In the grey vault of heaven, and by his light
Did all the chivalry of England move
To do brave acts. He was indeed the glass
Wherein the noble youth did dress themselves.
He had no legs that practised not his gait;
And speaking thick, which nature made him blemish,
Became the accents of the valiant.
For those that could speak low and tardily
Would turn their own perfection to abuse
To seem like him. So that in speech, in gait,
In diet, in affections of delight,
In military rules, humours of blood,
He was the mark and glass, copy and book,
That fashioned others. And him, O wondrous him!
O miracle of men! Him did you leave,
Second to none, unseconded by you,
To look upon the hideous god of war
In disadvantage, to abide a field
Where nothing but the sound of Hotspur's name
Did seem defensible; so you left him.
Never, O never do his ghost the wrong
To hold your honour more precise and nice
With others than with him. Let them alone.
The Marshal and the Archbishop are strong.
Had my sweet Harry had but half their numbers,
Today might I, hanging on Hotspur's neck,
Have talked of Monmouth's grave.

northumberland:
Beshrew your heart,
Fair daughter, you do draw my spirits from me
With new lamenting ancient oversights.

Richard III, Act IV, Scene 4

queen margaret:
I called thee then‘vain flourish of my fortune’,
I called thee then, poor shadow,‘painted queen’,
The presentation of but what I was,
The flattering index of a direful pageant,
One heaved a-high to be hurled down below,
A mother only mocked with two fair babes,
A dream of what thou wast, a garish flag
To be the aim of every dangerous shot,
A sign of dignity, a breath, a bubble,
A queen in jest, only to fill the scene.
Where is thy husband now? Where be thy brothers?
Where are thy two sons? Wherein dost thou joy?
Who sues, and kneels, and says‘God save the Queen’?
Where be the bending peers that flattered thee?
Where be the thronging troops that followed thee?
Decline all this and see what now thou art:
For happy wife, a most distressed widow;
For joyful mother, one that wails the name;
For queen, a very caitiff, crowned with care;
For one being sued to, one that humbly sues;
For she that scorned at me, now scorned of me;
For she being feared of all, now fearing one;
For she commanding all, obeyed of none.
Thus hath the course of justice whirled about
And left thee but a very prey to time,
Having no more but thought of what thou wert
To torture thee the more, being what thou art.
Thou didst usurp my place, and dost thou not
Usurp the just proportion of my sorrow?
Now thy proud neck bears half my burdened yoke,
From which, even here, I slip my weary head,
And leave the burden of it all on thee.
Farewell, York's wife, and queen of sad mischance.

A Midsummer Night's Dream, Act I, Scene 1

egeus:
Full of vexation come I, with complaint
Against my child, my daughter Hermia.
Stand forth Demetrius. My noble lord,
This man hath my consent to marry her.
Stand forth Lysander. And, my gracious Duke,
This hath bewitched the bosom of my child.
Thou, thou, Lysander, thou hast given her rhymes
And interchanged love tokens with my child.
Thou hast by moonlight at her window sung
With feigning voice verses of feigning love,
And stol'n the impression of her fantasy
With bracelets of thy hair, rings, gauds, conceits,
Knacks, trifles, nosegays, sweetmeats; messengers
Of strong prevailment in unhardened youth.
With cunning hast thou filched my daughter's heart,
Turned her obedience which is due to me
To stubborn harshness. And, my gracious Duke,
Be it so she will not here before your grace
Consent to marry with Demetrius,
I beg the ancient privilege of Athens:
As she is mine, I may dispose of her,
Which shall be either to this gentleman
Or to her death, according to our law
Immediately provided in that case.

theseus:
What say you Hermia? Be advised, fair maid.
To you your father should be as a god,
One that composed your beauties, yea, and one
To whom you are but as a form in wax,
By him imprinted, and within his power
To leave the figure or disfigure it.
Demetrius is a worthy gentleman.

hermia:
So is Lysander.

theseus:
In himself he is,
But in this kind, wanting your father's voice,
The other must be held the worthier.

hermia:
I would my father looked but with my eyes.

theseus:
Rather your eyes must with his judgement look.

hermia:
I do entreat your grace to pardon me.
I know not by what power I am made bold,
Nor how it may concern my modesty
In such a presence here to plead my thoughts,
But I beseech your grace that I may know
The worst that may befall me in this case
If I refuse to wed Demetrius.

theseus:
Either to die the death, or to abjure
For ever the society of men.
Therefore, fair Hermia, question your desires.
Know of your youth, examine well your blood,
Whether, if you yield not to your father's choice,
You can endure the livery of a nun,
For aye to be in shady cloister mewed,
To live a barren sister all your life,
Chanting faint hymns to the cold fruitless moon.
Thrice blessed they that master so their blood
To undergo such maiden pilgrimage;
But earthlier happy is the rose distilled
Than that which, withering on the virgin thorn,
Grows, lives, and dies in single blessedness.

hermia:
So will I grow, so live, so die, my lord,
Ere I will yield my virgin patent up
Unto his lordship whose unwished yoke
My soul consents not to give sovereignty.

The Winter's Tale, Act I, Scene 2

hermione:
If you would seek us,
We are yours i'th' garden. Shall's attend you there?

leontes:
To your own bents dispose you. You'll be found,
Be you beneath the sky. I am angling now,
Though you perceive me not how I give line.
Go to, go to!
How she holds up the neb, the bill to him,
And arms her with the boldness of a wife
To her allowing husband!

Exeunt Polixenes and Hermione.

Gone already.
Inch-thick, knee-deep, o'er head and ears a forked one!
Go play, boy, play. Thy mother plays, and I
Play too, but so disgraced a part, whose issue
Will hiss me to my grave. Contempt and clamour
Will be my knell. Go play, boy, play. There have been,
Or I am much deceived, cuckolds ere now,
And many a man there is, even at this present,
Now, while I speak this, holds his wife by th'arm,
That little thinks she has been sluiced in's absence,
And his pond fished by his next neighbour, by
Sir Smile, his neighbour. Nay, there's comfort in't,
Whiles other men have gates, and those gates opened,
As mine, against their will. Should all despair
That have revolted wives, the tenth of mankind
Would hang themselves. Physic for't there's none.
It is a bawdy planet, that will strike
Where 'tis predominant; and 'tis powerful. Think it:
From east, west, north, and south, be it concluded,
No barricado for a belly. Know't,
It will let in and out the enemy
With bag and baggage. Many thousand on's
Have the disease and feel't not.

The Tempest, Act I, Scene 2

miranda:
If by your art, my dearest father, you have
Put the wild waters in this roar, allay them.
The sky, it seems, would pour down stinking pitch,
But that the sea, mounting to th' welkin's cheek,
Dashes the fire out. O, I have suffered
With those that I saw suffer! A brave vessel,
Who had, no doubt, some noble creature in her,
Dashed all to pieces! O, the cry did knock
Against my very heart! Poor souls, they perished.
Had I been any god if power I would
Have sunk the sea within the earth, or ere
It should the good ship so have swallowed and
The fraughting souls within her.

prospero:
Be collected.
No more amazement. Tell your piteous heart
There's no harm done.

miranda:
O woe the day!

prospero:
No harm.
I have done nothing but in care of thee,
Of thee, my dear one, thee, my daughter, who
Art ignorant of what thou art, naught knowing
Of whence I am, nor that I am more better
Than Prospero, master of a full poor cell
And thy no greater father.

All's Well That Ends Well, Act II, Scene 3

king:
'Tis only title thou disdain'st in her, the which
I can build up. Strange is it that our bloods,
Of colour, weight, and heat, poured all together,
Would quite confound distinction, yet stands off
In differences so mighty. If she be
All that is virtuous, save what thou dislik'st —
‘A poor physician's daughter’— thou dislik'st
Of virtue for the name. But do not so.
From lowest place when virtuous things proceed,
The place is dignified by th' doer's deed.
Where great additions swell's, and virtue none,
It is a dropsied honour. Good alone
Is good without a name, vileness is so:
The property by what it is should go,
Not by the title. She is young, wise, fair.
In these to nature she's immediate heir,
And these breed honour. That is honour's scorn,
Which challenges itself as honour's born,
And is not like the sire. Honours thrive
When rather from our acts we them derive
Than our foregoers. The mere word's a slave,
Debauched on every tomb, on every grave
A lying trophy, and as oft is dumb
Where dust and dammed oblivion is the tomb
Of honoured bones indeed. What should be said?
If thou canst like this creature as a maid
I can create the rest. Virtue and she
Is her own dower; honour and wealth from me.

bertram:
I cannot love her, nor will strive to do't.

king:
Thou wrong'st thyself. If thou shouldst strive to choose —

helen:
That you are well restored, my lord, I'm glad.
Let the rest go.

king:
Mine honour's at the stake, which to defeat
I must produce my power. Here, take her hand,
Proud, scornful boy, unworthy this good gift,
That dost in vile misprision shackle up
My love and her desert; that canst not dream,
We, poising us in her defective scale,
Shall weigh to the beam; that wilt not know
It is in us to plant thine honour where
We please to have it grow. Check thy contempt,
Obey our will, which travails in thy good;
Believe not thy disdain, but presently
Do thine own fortunes that obedient right
Which both thy duty owes and our power claims,
Or I will throw thee from my care for ever
Into the staggers and the careless lapse
Of youth and ignorance, both my revenge and hate
Loosing upon thee in the name of justice
Without all terms of pity. Speak. Thine answer.

bertram:
Pardon, my gracious lord, for I submit
My fancy to your eyes. When I consider
What great creation and what dole of honour
Flies where you bid it, I find that she, which late
Was in my nobler thoughts most base, is now
The praised of the King, who, so ennobled,
Is as 'twere born so.

Measure for Measure, Act II, Scene 4

angelo:
Who will believe thee, Isabel?
My unsoiled name, th'austereness of my life,
My vouch against you, and my place i'th' state,
Will so your accusation overweigh
That you shall stifle in your own report,
And smell of calumny. I have begun,
And now I give my sensual race the rein.
Fit thy consent to my sharp appetite.
Lay by all nicety and prolixious blushes
That banish what they sue for. Redeem thy brother
By yielding up thy body to my will,
Or else he must not only die the death,
But thy unkindness shall his death draw out
To ling'ring sufferance. Answer me tomorrow,
Or by the affection that now guides me most,
I'll prove a tyrant to him. As for you,
Say what you can, my false o'erweighs your true.

Exit.

isabella:
To whom should I complain? Did I tell this
Who would believe me? O perilous mouths
That bear in them one and the selfsame tongue
Either of condemnation or aproof,
Bidding the law make curtsy to their will,
Hooking both right and wrong to th'appetite,
To follow as it draws! I'll to my brother.
Though he hath fall'n by prompture of the blood,
Yet hath he in him such a mind of honour
That had he twenty heads to tender down
On twenty bloody blocks, he'd yield them up
Before his sister should her body stoop
To such abhorred pollution.
Then Isabel live chaste, and brother die.
More than our brother is our chastity.

Henry IV, Part II, Act IV, Scene 5

prince harry:
I never thought to hear you speak again.

king henry:
Thy wish was father, Harry, to that thought.
I stay too long by thee. I weary thee.
Dost thou so hunger for mine empty chair
That thou wilt needs invest thee with my honours
Before thy hour be ripe? O foolish youth,
Thou seek'st the greatness that will overwhelm thee!
Stay but a little, for my cloud of dignity
Is held from falling with so weak a wind
That it will quickly drop. My day is dim.
Thou hast stol'n that which after some few hours
Were thine without offence, and at my death
Thou hast sealed up my expectation.
Thy life did manifest thou loved'st me not,
And thou wilt have me die assured of it.
Thou hidst a thousand daggers in thy thoughts,
Whom thou hast whetted on thy stony heart
To stab at half an hour of my life.
What, canst thou not forbear me half an hour?
Then get thee gone and dig my grave thyself,
And bid the merry bells ring to thine ear
That thou art crowned, not that I am dead.
Let all the tears that should bedew my hearse
Be drops of balm to sanctify thy head.
Only compound me with forgotten dust.
Give that which gave thee life unto the worms.
Pluck down my officers, break my decrees;
For now a time is come to mock at form.
Harry the Fifth is crowned. Up, vanity!
Down, royal state! All you sage counsellors, hence!
And to the English court assemble now
From every region apes of idleness!
Now, neighbour confines, purge you of your scum!
Have you a ruffian that will swear, drink, dance,
Revel the night, rob, murder, and commit
The oldest sins the newest kind of ways?
Be happy, he will trouble you no more.
England shall double gild his treble guilt;
England shall give him office, honour, might;
For the fifth Harry from curbed licence plucks
The muzzle of restraint, and the wild dog
Shall flesh his tooth on every innocent.
O my poor kingdom, sick with civil blows!
When that my care could not withhold thy riots,
What wilt thou do when riot is thy care?
O, thou wilt be a wilderness again,
Peopled with wolves, thy old inhabitants.

prince harry:
O pardon me, my liege! But for my tears,
The moist impediments unto my speech,
I had forestalled this dear and deep rebuke
Ere you with grief had spoke and I had heard
The course of it so far. There is your crown.

(He returns the crown and kneels.)

And He that wears the crown immortally
Long guard it yours! If I affect it more
Than as your honour and as your renown,
Let me no more from this obedience rise,
Which is my most true and inward duteous spirit
Teacheth this prostrate and exterior bending.
God witness with me, when I here came in
And found no course of breath within your majesty,
How cold it struck my heart. If I do feign,
O, let me in my present wildness die,
And never live to show th'incredulous world
The noble change that I have purposed.
Coming to look on you, thinking you dead,
And dead almost, my liege, to think you were,
I spake unto this crown as having sense
And thus upbraided it:‘The care on thee depending
Hath fed upon the body of my father,
Therefore thou best of gold art worst of gold.
Other, less fine in carat, is more precious,
Preserving life in medicine potable,
But thou, most fine, most honoured, most renowned,
Hast eat thy bearer up.’Thus, my royal liege,
Accusing it, I put it on my head,
To try with it, as with an enemy
That had before my face murdered my father,
The quarrel of a true inheritor.
But if it did infect my blood with joy
Or swell my thoughts to any strain of pride,
If any rebel or vain spirit of mine
Did with the least affection of a welcome
Give entertainment to the might of it,
Let God for ever keep it from my head,
And make me as the poorest vassal is,
That doth with awe and terror kneel to it.

king henry:
O my son,
God put it in thy mind to take it hence,
That thou mightst win the more thy father's love,
Pleading so wisely in excuse of it!
Come hither, Harry, sit thou by my bed,
And hear, I think, the very latest counsel
That ever I shall breathe.

Prince Harry sits by the bed.

God knows, my son,
By what bypaths and indirect crook'd ways
I met this crown; and I myself know well
How troublesome it sat upon my head.
To thee it shall descend with better quiet,
Better opinion, better confirmation;
For all the soil of the achievement goes
With me into the earth. It seemed in me
But as an honour snatched with boist'rous hand,
And I had many living to upbraid
My gain of it by their assistances,
Which daily grew to quarrel and to bloodshed
Wounding supposed peace. All these bold fears
Thou seest with peril I have answered;
For all my reign hath been but as a scene
Acting that argument. And now my death
Changes the mood, for what in me was purchased
Falls upon thee in a more fairer sort,
So thou the garland wear'st successively.
Yet though thou stand'st more sure than I could do,
Thou art not firm enough, since griefs are green,
And all thy friends — which thou must make thy friends —
Have but their stings and teeth newly ta'en out,
By whose fell working I was first advanced,
And by whose power I well might lodge a fear
To be again displaced; which to avoid
I cut them off, and had a purpose now
To lead out many to the Holy Land,
Lest rest and lying still might make them look
Too near unto my state. Therefore, my Harry,
Be it thy course to busy giddy minds
With foreign quarrels, that action hence borne out
May waste the memory of the former days.
More would I, but my lungs are wasted so
That strength of speech is utterly denied me.
How came I by the crown, O god forgive,
And grant it may with thee in true peace live!

prince harry:
My gracious liege,
You won it, wore it, kept it, gave it to me,
Then plain and right must my possession be,
Which I with more than with a common pain
'Gainst all the world will rightfully maintain.

Power in war and violence

Julius Caesar, Act II, Scene 1

brutus:
It must be by his death. And for my part
I know no personal cause to spurn at him
But for the general. He would be crowned.
How that might change his nature, there's the question.
It is the bright day that brings forth the adder
And that craves wary walking. Crown him: that!
And then I grant we put a sting in him
That at his will he may do danger with.
Th'abuse of greatness is when it disjoins
Remorse from power. And to speak truth of Caesar,
I have not known when his affections swayed
More than his reason. But 'tis a common proof
That lowliness is young ambition's ladder,
Whereto the climber-upward turns his face;
But when he once attains the upmost round,
He then unto the ladder turns his back,
Looks in the clouds, scorning the base degrees
By which he did ascend. So Caesar may.
Then lest he may, prevent. And since the quarrel
Will bear no colour for the thing he is,
Fashion it thus: that what he is, augmented,
Would run to these and these extremities;
And therefore think him as a serpent's egg,
Which, hatched, would as his kind grow mischievous
And kill him in the shell.

Henry V, Act IV, Scene 1

harry: I think the King is but a man, as I am. The violet smells to him as it doth to me; the element shows to him as it doth to me. All his senses have but human conditions. His ceremonies laid by, in his nakedness he appears but a man, and though his affections are higher mounted than ours, yet when they stoop, they stoop with the like wing. Therefore, when he sees reason of fears, as we do, his fears, out of doubt, be of the same relish as ours are. Yet, in reason, no man should possess him with any appearance of fear, lest he, by showing it, should dishearten his army.

bates: He may show what outward courage he will, but I believe, as cold a night as 'tis, he could wish himself in Thames up to the neck. And so I would he were, and I by him, at all adventures, so we were quit here.

king harry: By my troth, I will speak my conscience of the King. I think he would not wish himself anywhere but where he is.

bates: Then I would he were here alone. So should he be sure to be ransomed, and a many poor men's lives saved.

king harry: I dare say you love him not so ill to wish him here alone, howsoever you speak this to feel other men's minds. Methinks I could not die anywhere so contented as in the King's company, his cause being just and his quarrel honourable.

williams: That's more than we know.

bates: Ay, or more than we should seek after. For we know enough if we know we are the King's subjects. If his cause be wrong, our obedience to the King wipes the crime of it out of us.

williams: But if the cause be not good, the King himself hath a heavy reckoning to make, when all those legs and arms and heads chopped off in a battle shall join together at the latter day and cry all,‘We died at such a place’— some swearing, some crying for a surgeon, some upon their wives left poor behind them, some upon the debts they owe, some upon their children rawly left. I am afeard there are few die well that die in a battle, for how can they charitably dispose of anything when blood is their argument? Now, if these men do not die well it will be a black matter for the King that led them to it — who to disobey were against all proportion of subjection.

king harry: So, if a son that is by his father sent about merchandise do sinfully miscarry upon the sea, the imputation of his wickedness, by your rule, should be imposed upon his father, that sent him. Or if a servant, under his master's command transporting a sum of money, be assailed by robbers and die in many irreconciled iniquities, you may call the business of the master the author of the servant's damnation. But this is not so. The King is not bound to answer the particular endings of his soldiers, the father of his son, nor the master of his servant, for they purpose not their deaths when they propose their services. Besides, there is no king, be his cause never so spotless, if it come to the arbitrament of swords, can try it out with all unspotted soldiers. Some, peradventure, have on them the guilt of premeditated and contrived murder; some, of beguiling virgins with the broken seals of perjury; some, making the wars their bulwark, that have before gored the gentle bosom of peace with pillage and robbery. Now, if these men have defeated the law and outrun native punishment, though they can outstrip men, they have no wings to fly from God. War is his beadle. War is his vengeance. So that here men are punished for before breach of the King's laws, in now the King's quarrel. Where they feared the death, they have borne life away, and where they would be safe, they perish. Then if they die unprovided, no more is the King guilty of their damnation than he was before guilty of those impieties for the which they are now visited. Every subject's duty is the King's, but every subject's soul is his own.

Hamlet, Act IV, Scene 4

hamlet:
How all occasions do inform against me
And spur my dull revenge! What is a man
If his chief good and market of his time
Be but to sleep and feed? A beast, no more.
Sure, he that made us with such large discourse,
Looking before and after, gave us not
That capability and god-like reason
To fust in us unused. Now whether it be
Bestial oblivion, or some craven scruple
Of thinking too precisely on th'event —
A thought which, quartered, hath but one part wisdom
And ever three parts coward — I do not know
Why yet I live to say,‘This thing's to do’,
Sith I have cause and will and strength and means
To do't. Examples gross as earth exhort me,
Witness this army of such mass and charge,
Led by a delicate and tender prince,
Whose spirit with divine ambition puffed
Makes mouths at the invisible event,
Exposing what is mortal and unsure
To all that fortune, death, and danger dare,
Even for an eggshell. Rightly to be great
Is not to stir without great argument
But greatly to find quarrel in a straw
When honour's at the stake. How stand I, then,
That have a father killed, a mother stained,
Excitements of my reason and my blood,
And let all sleep while, to my shame, I see
The imminent death of twenty thousand men
That, for a fantasy and trick of fame,
Go to their graves like beds, fight for a plot
Whereon the numbers cannot try the cause,
Which is not tomb enough and continent
To hide the slain. O from this time forth
My thoughts be bloody or be nothing worth!

Henry IV, Part II, Act I, Scene 3

lord bardolph:
Yes, if this present quality of war,
Indeed the instant action, a cause on foot,
Lives so in hope, as in an early spring
We see th'appearing buds, which to prove fruit
Hope gives not so much warrant as despair
That frosts will bite them. When we mean to build
We first survey the plot, then draw the model;
And when we see the figure of the house,
Which if we find outweighs ability,
What do we then but draw anew the model
In fewer offices, or at least desist
To build at all? Much more in this great work —
Which is almost to pluck a kingdom down
And set another up — should we survey
The plot of situation and the model,
Consent upon a sure foundation,
Question surveyors, know our own estate,
How able such a work to undergo,
To weigh against his opposite; or else
We fortify in paper and in figures,
Using the names of men instead of men,
Like one that draws the model of an house
Beyond his power to build it, who, half-through,
Gives o'er, and leaves his part-created cost
A naked subject to the weeping clouds,
And waste for churlish winter's tyranny.

Macbeth, Act I, Scene 7

macbeth:
If it were done when 'tis done, then 'twere well
It were done quickly. If th'assassination
Could trammel up the consequence and catch
With his surcease success, that but this blow
Might be the be-all and end-all, here;
But here upon this bank and shoal of time,
We'd jump the life to come. But in these cases
We still have judgement here, that we but teach
Bloody instructions which, being taught, return
To plague th'inventor. This even-handed justice
Commends th'ingredience of our poisoned chalice
To our own lips. He's here in double trust:
First, as I am his kinsman and his subject,
Strong both against the deed; then, as his host,
Who should against his murderer shut the door,
Not bear the knife myself. Besides, this Duncan
Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been
So clear in his great office, that his virtues
Will plead like angels, trumpet-tongued against
The deep damnation of his taking-off,
And pity, like a naked new-born babe,
Striding the blast, or heaven's cherubin, horsed
Upon the sightless couriers of the air,
Shall blow the horrid deed in every eye
That tears shall drown the wind. I have no spur
To prick the sides of my intent, but only
Vaulting ambition which o'erleaps itself
And falls on th'other.

Richard III, Act V, Scene 5

henry, earl of richmond:
Why then, 'tis time to arm, and give direction.
Much that I could say, loving countrymen,
The leisure and enforcement of the time
Forbids to dwell on. Yet remember this:
God and our good cause fight upon our side.
The prayers of holy saints and wronged souls,
Like high-reared bulwarks, stand before our forces.
Richard except, those whom we fight against
Had rather have us win than him they follow.
For what is he they follow? Truly friends,
A bloody tyrant and a homicide;
One raised in blood, and one in blood established;
One that made means to come by what he hath,
And slaughtered those that were the means to help him;
A base, foul stone, made precious by the foil
Of England's chair, where he is falsely set;
One that hath ever been God's enemy.
Then, if you fight against God's enemy,
God will, in justice, ward you as his soldiers.
If you do sweat to put a tyrant down,
You sleep in peace, the tyrant being slain.
If you do fight against your country's foes,
Your country's fat shall pay your pains the hire.
If you do fight in safeguard of your wives,
Your wives shall welcome home the conquerors.
If you do free your children from the sword,
Your children's children quites it in your age.
Then, in the name of God and all these rights,
Advance your standards! Draw your willing swords!
For me the ransom of this bold attempt
Shall be my cold corpse on the earth's cold face;
But if I thrive, to gain of my attempt,
The least of you shall share his part thereof.
Sound drums and trumpets, bold and cheerfully!
God and Saint George! Richmond and victory!

Henry VI, Part II, Act I, Scene 1

york:
Anjou and Maine are given to the French,
Paris is lost, the state of Normandy
Stands on a tickle point now they are gone.
Suffolk concluded on the articles,
The peers agreed, and Henry was well pleased
To change two dukedoms for a duke's fair daughter.
I cannot blame them all — what is't to them?
'Tis thine they give away and not their own!
Pirates may make cheap pennyworths of their pillage,
And purchase friends, and give to courtesans,
Still revelling like lords till all be gone,
Whileas the seely owner of the goods
Weeps over them and wrings his hapless hands,
And shakes his head, and, trembling, stands aloof,
While all is shared and all is borne away,
Ready to starve and dare not touch his own.
So York must sit and fret and bite his tongue
While his own lands are bargained for and sold.
Methinks the realms of England, France, and Ireland
Bear that proportion to my flesh and blood
As did the fatal brand Althaea burnt
Unto the prince's heart of Calydon.
Anjou and Maine both given unto the French!
Cold news for me, for I had hope of France,
Even as I have of fertile England's soil.
A day will come when York shall claim his own
And therefore I will take the Neville's parts,
And make a show of love to proud Duke Humphrey,
And, when I spy advantage, claim the crown.
Then, York, be still a while till time do serve.
Watch thou, and wake when others be asleep,
To pry into the secrets of the state —
Till Henry, surfeit in the joys of love
With his new bride and England's dear-bought queen,
And Humphrey with the peers be fall'n at jars.
Then will I raise aloft the milk-white rose,
With whose sweet smell the air shall be perfumed,
And in my standard bear the arms of York
To grapple with the house of Lancaster;
And force perforce I'll make him yield the crown
Whose bookish rule hath pulled fair England down.

The Tempest, Act III, Scene 3

ariel:
You are three men of sin, whom destiny,
That hath to instrument this lower world
And what is in't, the never surfeited sea,
Hath caused to belch up you; and on this island
Where man doth not inhabit, you 'mongst men
Being most unfit to live. I have made you mad,
And even with suchlike valour men hang and drown
Their proper selves.

Alonso, Sebastian, and Antonio draw.

You fools! I and my fellows
Are ministers of fate. The elements
Of whom your swords are tempered may as well
Wound the loud winds, or with bemocked-at stabs
Kill the still-closing waters, as diminish
One dowl that's in my plume. My fellow ministers
Are like invulnerable. If you could hurt,
Your swords are now too massy for your strengths
And will not be uplifted.

Alonso, Sebastian, and Antonio stand amazed.

But remember,
For that's my business to you, that you three
From Milan did supplant good Prospero —
Exposed unto the sea, which hath requit it,
Him and his innocent child — for which foul deed,
The powers, delaying not forgetting, have
Incensed the seas and shores, yea, all the creatures,
Against your peace. Thee of thy son, Alonso,
They have bereft, and do pronounce by me
Ling'ring perdition — worse than any death
Can be at once — shall step by step attend
You and your ways, whose wraths to guard you from,
Which here in this most desolate isle else falls
Upon your heads, is nothing but heart's sorrow
And a clear life ensuing.

He ascends and vanishes in thunder. Then, to soft music, enter the spirits again and dance with mocks and mows, and they depart, carrying out the table.

prospero:
Bravely the figure of this harpy has thou
Performed, my Ariel; a grace it had devouring.
Of my instruction hast thou nothing bated
In what thou hadst to say. So with good life
And observation strange my meaner ministers
Their several kinds have done. My high charms work,
And these mine enemies are all knit up
In their distractions. They now are in my power.

Coriolanus, Act I, Scene 1

first citizen: We are accounted poor citizens, the patricians good. What authority surfeits on would relieve us. If they would yield us but the superfluity while it were wholesome we might guess they relieved us humanely, but they think we are too dear. The leanness that afflicts us, the object of our misery, is as an inventory to particularize their abundance. Our sufferance is a gain to them. Let us revenge this with our pikes ere we become rakes, for the gods know I speak this in hunger for bread, not in thirst for revenge.

Henry IV, Part I, Act I, Scene 3

hotspur:
Nay, then I cannot blame his cousin King
That wished him on the barren mountains starve.
But shall it be that you that set the crown
Upon the head of this forgetful man,
And for his sake wear the detested blot
Of murderous subornation, shall it be
That you a world of curses undergo,
Being the agents or base second means,
The cords, the ladder, or the hangman, rather?
O pardon me that I descend so low
To show the line and the predicament
Wherein you range under this subtle King!
Shall it for shame be spoken in these days,
Or fill up chronicles in time to come,
That men of your nobility and power
Did gage them both in an unjust behalf,
As both of you, God pardon it, have done:
To put down Richard, that sweet, lovely rose,
And plant this thorn, this canker, Bolingbroke?
And shall it in more shame be further spoken
That you are fooled, discarded, and shook off
By him for whom these shames ye underwent?
No, yet time serves wherein you may redeem
Your banished honours and restore yourselves
Into the good thoughts of the world again,
Revenge for the jeering and disdained contempt
Of this proud King, who studies day and night
To answer all the debt he owes to you
Even with the bloody payment of your deaths.
Therefore I say —

worcester:
Peace cousin, say no more.

Richard III, Act IV, Scene 3

tyrell:
The tyrannous and bloody act is done —
The most arch deed of piteous massacre
That ever yet this land was guilty of.
Dighton and Forrest, whom I did suborn
To do this piece of ruthless butchery,
Albeit they were fleshed villains, bloody dogs,
Melted with tenderness and mild compassion,
Wept like two children in their deaths' sad story.
‘O thus’, quoth Dighton,‘lay the gentle babes’;
‘Thus, thus’, quoth Forrest,‘girdling one another
Within their alabaster innocent arms.
Their lips were four red roses on a stalk,
And in their summer beauty kissed each other.
A book of prayers on their pillow lay,
Which once’, quoth Forrest,‘almost changed my mind.
But O, the devil’— there the villain stopped,
When Dighton thus told on,‘We smothered
The most replenished sweet work of nature,
That from the prime creation e'er she framed.’
Hence both are gone, with conscience and remorse.
They could not speak, and so I left them both,
To bear this tidings to the bloody king.

Enter King Richard.

And here he comes. All health my sovereign lord.

king richard:
Kind Tyrell, am I happy in thy news?

tyrell:
If to have done the thing you gave in charge
Beget your happiness, be happy then,
For it is done.

king richard:
But didst thou see them dead?

tyrell:
I did my lord.

king richard:
And buried, gentle Tyrell?

tyrell:
The chaplain of the Tower hath buried them,
But where, to say the truth, I do not know.

king richard:
Come to me, Tyrell, soon, at after-supper,
When thou shalt tell the process of their death.
Meantime, but think how I may do thee good,
And be inheritor of thy desire.
Farewell till then.

tyrell:
I humbly take my leave.

king richard:
The son of Clarence have I pent up close.
His daughter meanly have I matched in marriage,
The sons of Edward sleep in Abraham's bosom,
And Anne, my wife, hath bid this world goodnight.
Now for I know the Breton Richmond aims
At young Elizabeth, my brother's daughter,
And by that knot looks proudly o'er the crown,
To her go I, a jolly thriving wooer.

Timon of Athens, Act V, Scene 5

alcibiades:
Sound to this coward and lascivious town
Our terrible approach.

A parley sounds. The senators appear upon the walls.

Till now you have gone on and filled the time
With all licentious measure, making your wills
The scope of justice. Till now myself and such
As slept within the shadow of your power
Have wandered with our traversed arms and breathed
Our sufferance vainly. Now the time is flush,
When crouching marrow, in the bearer strong,
Cries of itself‘No more’. Now breathless wrong
Shall sit and pant in your great chairs of ease
And pursy insolence shall break his wind
With fear and horrid flight.

first senator:
Noble and young,
When thy first griefs were but a mere conceit,
Ere thou hadst power or we had cause of fear,
We sent to thee to give thy rages balm,
To wipe out our ingratitude with loves
Above their quantity.

second senator:
So did we woo
Transformed Timon to our city's love
By humble message and by promised means.
We were not all unkind, nor all deserve
The common stroke of war.

first senator:
These walls of ours
Were not erected by their hands from whom
You have received your grief, nor are they such
That these great tow'rs, trophies, and schools should fall
For private faults in them.

second senator:
Nor are they living
Who were the motives that you first went out.
Shame that they wanted cunning, in excess,
Hath broke their hearts. March, noble lord,
Into our city with thy banners spread.
By decimation and a tithed death,
If thy revenges hunger for that food
Which nature loathes, take thou the destined tenth,
And by the hazard of the spotted die
Let die the spotted.

Richard II, Act III, Scene 3

bolingbroke (to Northumberland):
Noble lord,
Go to the rude ribs of that ancient castle,
Through brazen trumpet send the breath of parley
Into his ruined ears, and thus deliver:
Henry Bolingbroke
Upon his knees doth kiss King Richard's hand
And sends allegiance and true faith of heart
To his most royal person, hither come
Even at his feet to lay my arms and power,
Provided that my banishment repealed
And lands restored again be freely granted.
If not, I'll use the advantage of my power,
And lay the summer's dust with showers of blood
Rained from the wounds of slaughtered Englishmen,
The which how far off from the mind of Bolingbroke
It is such crimson tempest should bedrench
The fresh green lap of fair King Richard's land,
My stooping duty tenderly shall show.
Go, signify as much, while here we march
Upon the grassy carpet of this plain.
Let's march without the noise of threat'ning drum,
That from this castle's tottered battlements
Our fair appointments may be well perused.
Methinks King Richard and myself should meet
With no less terror than the elements
Of fire and water when their thund'ring shock
At meeting tears the cloudy cheeks of heaven.
Be he the fire, I'll be the yielding water.
The rage be his, whilst on the earth I rain
My waters: on the earth, and not on him.

Coriolanus, Act IV, Scene 5

coriolanus:
My name is Caius Martius, who hath done
To thee particularly, and to all the Volsces,
Great hurt and mischief. Thereto witness may
My surname Coriolanus. The painful service,
The extreme dangers, and the drops of blood
Shed for my thankless country, are requited
But with that surname — a good memory
And witness of the malice and displeasure
Which thou shouldst bear me. Only that name remains.
The cruelty and envy of the people,
Permitted by our dastard nobles, who
Have all forsook me, hath devoured the rest,
And suffered me by th'voice of slaves to be
Whooped out of Rome. Now this extremity
Hath brought me to thy hearth. Not out of hope —
Mistake me not — to save my life, for if
I had feared death, of all the men i'th'world
I would have 'voided thee, but in mere spite
To be full quit of those my banishers
Stand I before thee here. Then if thou hast
A heart of wreak in thee that wilt revenge
Thine own particular wrongs and stop those maims
Of shame seen through thy country, speed thee straight,
And make my misery serve thy turn. So use it
That my revengeful services may prove
As benefits to thee; for I will fight
Against my cankered country with the spleen
Of all the under-fiends. But if so be
Thou dar'st not this, and that to prove more fortunes
Thou'rt tired, then, in a word, I also am
Longer to live most weary and present
My throat to thee and to thy ancient malice,
Which not to cut would show thee but a fool,
Since I have ever followed thee with hate,
Drawn tuns of blood out of thy country's breast,
And cannot live but to thy shame unless
It be to do thee service.

Henry IV, Part II, Act IV, Scene 1

westmorland:
Then, my lord,
Unto your grace do I in chief address
The substance of my speech. If that rebellion
Came like itself, in base and abject routs,
Led on by bloody youth, guarded with rags,
And countenanced by boys and beggary,
I say, if damned commotion so appeared
In his true native and most proper shape,
You, reverend father, and these noble lords
Had not been here to dress the ugly form
Of base and bloody insurrection
With your fair honours. You, Lord Archbishop,
Whose see is by a civil peace maintained,
Whose beard the silver hand of peace hath tutored,
Whose white investments figure innocence,
The dove and very blessed spirit of peace,
Wherefore do you so ill translate yourself
Out of the speech of peace that bears such grace
Into the harsh and boist'rous tongue of war,
Turning your books to graves, your ink to blood,
Your pens to lances, and your tongue divine
To a loud trumpet and a point of war?

archbishop of york:
Wherefore do I this? So the question stands.
Briefly, to this end: we are all diseased,
And with our surfeiting and wanton hours
Have brought ourselves into a burning fever,
And we must bleed for it; of which disease
Our late King Richard, being infected, died.
But my most noble lord of Westmorland,
I take not on me here as a physician,
Nor do I as an enemy to peace
Troop in the throngs of military men,
But rather show a while like fearful war
To diet rank minds, sick of happiness,
And purge th'obstructions which begin to stop
Our very veins of life. Hear me more plainly.
I have in equal balance justly weighed
What wrongs our arms may do, what wrongs we suffer,
And find our griefs heavier than our offences.
We see which way the stream of life doth run,
And are enforced from our most quiet shore
By the rough torrent of occasion;
And have the summary of all our griefs,
When time shall serve, to show in articles,
Which long ere this we offered to the King,
And might by no suit gain our audience.
When we are wronged and would unfold our griefs
We are denied access unto his person,
Even by those men that most have done us wrong.
The dangers of the days but newly gone,
Whose memory is written on the earth
With yet appearing blood, and the examples
Of every minute's instance, present now,
Hath put us in these ill-beseeming arms,
Not to break peace, or any branch of it,
But to establish here a peace indeed,
Concurring both in name and quality.

Power of love, between men and women

Troilus and Cressida, Act III, Scene 2

troilus:
Why was my Cressid then so hard to win?

cressida:
Hard to seem won, but I was won, my lord,
With the first glance that ever — pardon me,
If I confess much you will play the tyrant.
I love you now, but till now not so much
But I might master it. In faith, I lie.
My thoughts were like unbridled children, grown
Too headstrong for their mother. See, we fools!
Why have I blabbed? Who shall be true to us,
When we are so unsecret to ourselves?
But though I loved you well I wooed you not.
And yet, good faith, I wished myself a man,
Or that we women had men's privilege
Of speaking first. Sweet, bid me hold my tongue,
For in this rapture I shall surely speak
The thing I shall repent. See, see, your silence,
Cunning in dumbness, in my weakness draws
My soul of counsel from me. Stop my mouth.

troilus:
And shall, albeit sweet music issues thence.

He kisses her.

Sonnet 150

O from what power hast thou this powerful might
With insufficiency my heart to sway,
To make me give the lie to my true sight
And swear that brightness doth not grace the day?
Whence hast thou this becoming of things ill,
That in the very refuse of thy deeds
There is such strength and warrantise of skill
That in my mind thy worst all best exceeds?
Who taught thee how to make me love thee more
The more I hear and see just cause of hate?
O though I love what others do abhor,
With others thou shouldst not abhor my state.
If thy unworthiness raised love in me,
More worthy I to be beloved of thee.

The Two Gentlemen of Verona, Act III, Scene 1

valentine:
And why not death, rather than living torment?
To die is to be banished from myself,
And Silvia is my self. Banished from her
Is self from self, a deadly banishment.
What light is light if Silvia be not seen?
What joy is joy if Silvia be not by?
Unless it be to think that she is by,
And feed upon the shadow of perfection.
Except I be by Silvia in the night
There is no music in the nightingale.
Unless I look on Silvia in the day
There is no day for me to look upon.
She is my essence, and I leave to be
If I be not by her fair influence
Fostered, illumined, cherished, kept alive.
I fly not death to fly his deadly doom,
Tarry I here I but attend on death,
But fly I hence, I fly away from life.

Much Ado About Nothing, Act III, Scene 1

hero:
O god of love! I know he doth deserve
As much as may be yielded to a man.
But nature never framed a woman's heart
Of prouder stuff than that of Beatrice.
Disdain and scorn ride sparkling in her eyes,
Misprising what they look on, and her wit
Values itself so highly that to her
All matter else seems weak. She cannot love,
Nor take no shape nor project of affection,
She is so self-endeared.

ursula:
Sure, I think so.
And therefore certainly it were not good
She knew his love, lest she'll make sport at it.

hero:
Why, you speak truth. I never yet saw man,
How wise, how noble, young, how rarely featured,
But she would spell him backward. If fair-faced,
She would swear the gentleman should be her sister;
If black, why nature, drawing of an antic,
Made a foul blot; if tall, a lance ill-headed;
If low, an agate very vilely cut;
If speaking, why, a vane blown with all winds;
If silent, why, a block moved with none.
So turns she every man the wrong side out,
And never gives to truth and virtue that
Which simpleness and merit purchaseth.

ursula:
Sure, sure, such carping is not commendable.

hero:
No, not to be so odd and from all fashions
As Beatrice is cannot be commendable.
But who dare tell her so? If I should speak
She would mock me into air. O, she would laugh me
Out of myself, press me to death with wit.
Therefore let Benedick, like covered fire,
Consume away in sighs, waste inwardly.
It were a better death than die with mocks,
Which is as bad as die with tickling.

The Taming of the Shrew, Act IV, Scene 1

petruccio:
Thus have I politicly begun my reign,
And 'tis my hope to end successfully.
My falcon now is sharp and passing empty,
And till she stoop she must not be full-gorged,
For then she never looks upon her lure.
Another way I have to man my haggard,
To make her come and know her keeper's call;
That is, to watch her as we watch these kites
That bate and beat and will not be obedient.
She ate no meat today, nor none shall eat.
Last night she slept not, nor tonight she shall not.
As with the meat, some undeserved fault
I'll find about the making of the bed,
And here I'll fling the pillow, there the bolster,
This way the coverlet, another way the sheets,
Ay, and amid this hurly I intend
That all is done in reverent care of her,
And in conclusion she shall watch all night,
And if she chance to nod I'll rail and brawl
And with the clamour keep her still awake.
This is a way to kill a wife with kindness,
And thus I'll curb her mad and headstrong humour.
He that knows better how to tame a shrew,
Now let him speak. 'Tis charity to show.

‘The Rape of Lucrece’, lines 281—301

As corn o'ergrown by weeds, so heedful fear
Is almost choked by unresisted lust.
Away he steals with open list'ning ear,
Full of foul hope and full of fond mistrust,
Both which as servitors to the unjust
So cross him with their opposite persuasion
That now he vows a league, and now invasion.

Within his thought her heavenly image sits,
And in the selfsame seat sits Collatine.
That eye which looks on her confounds his wits,
That eye which him beholds, as more divine,
Unto a view so false will not incline,
But with a pure appeal seeks to the heart,
Which once corrupted, takes the worser part,

And therein heartens up his servile powers
Who, flattered by their leader's jocund show,
Stuff up his lust as minutes fill up hours,
And as their captain, so their pride doth grow,
Paying more slavish tribute than they owe.
By reprobate desire thus madly led
The Roman lord marcheth to Lucrece' bed.

A Midsummer Night's Dream, Act V, Scene 1

theseus:
Lovers and madmen have such seething brains,
Such shaping fantasies that apprehend
More than cool reason ever comprehends.
The lunatic, the lover, and the poet
Are of imagination all compact.
One sees more devils than vast hell can hold:
That is the madman. The lover, all as frantic,
Sees Helen's beauty in a brow of Egypt.
The poet's eye, in a fine frenzy rolling,
Doth glance from heaven to earth, from earth to heaven,
And as imagination bodies forth
The forms of things unknown; the poet's pen
Turns them to shapes and gives to airy nothing
A local habitation and a name.
Such tricks hath strong imagination
That if it would but apprehend some joy
It comprehends some bringer of that joy.
Or in the night, imagining some fear;
How easy is a bush supposed a bear!

Romeo and Juliet, Act III, Scene 3

romeo:
'Tis torture and not mercy. Heaven is here,
Where Juliet lives, and every cat and dog
And little mouse, every unworthy thing,
Live here in heaven and may look on her,
But Romeo may not. More validity,
More honourable state, more courtship lives
In carrion flies than Romeo. They may seize
On the white wonder of dear Juliet's hand,
And steal immortal blessing from her lips,
Who, even in pure and vestal modesty,
Still blush, as thinking their own kisses sin.
But Romeo may not; he is banished.
Flies may do this, but I from this must fly.
They are free men, but I am banished.
And sayst thou yet that exile is not death?
Hadst thou no poison mixed, no sharp-ground knife,
No sudden mean of death, though ne'er so mean,
But‘banished’to kill me.‘Banished’?
O friar, the damned use that word in hell.
Howling attends it. How hast thou the heart,
Being a divine, a ghostly confessor,
A sin-absolver and my friend professed,
To mangle me with that word‘banished’?

All's Well That Ends Well, Act I, Scene 1

helen:
O were that all! I think not on my father,
And these great tears grace his remembrance more
Than those I shed for him. What was he like?
I have forgot him. My imagination
Carries no favour in't but Bertram's.
I am undone. There is no living, none,
If Bertram be away. 'Twere all one
That I should love a bright particular star
And think to wed it, he is so above me.
In his bright radiance and collateral light
Must I be comforted, not in his sphere.
Th'ambition in my love thus plagues itself.
The hind that would be mated by the lion
Must die for love. 'Twas pretty, though a plague,
To see him every hour, to sit and draw
His arched brows, his hawking eye, his curls,
In our heart's table — heart too capable
Of every line and trick of his sweet favour.
But now he's gone, and my idolatrous fancy
Must sanctify his relics.

Sonnet 57

Being your slave, what should I do but tend
Upon the hours and times of your desire?
I have no precious time at all to spend,
Nor services to do, till you require;
Nor dare I chide the world-without-end hour
Whilst I, my sovereign, watch the clock for you,
Nor think the bitterness of absence sour
When you have bid your servant once adieu;
Nor dare I question with my jealous thought
Where you may be, or your affairs suppose,
But like a sad slave stay and think of naught
Save, where you are, how happy you make those.
So true a fool is love that in your will,
Though you do anything, he thinks no ill.

Love's Labour's Lost, Act I, Scene 2

armado: I do affect the very ground, which is base, where her shoe, which is baser, guided by her foot, which is basest, doth tread. I shall be forsworn, which is a great argument of falsehood, if I love. And how can that be true love which is falsely attempted? Love is a familiar; love is a devil. There is no evil angel but love. Yet was Samson so tempted, and he had an excellent strength. Yet was Solomon so seduced, and he had a very good wit. Cupid's butt-shaft is too hard for Hercules' club, and therefore too much odds for a Spaniard's rapier. The first and second cause will not serve my turn: the passado he respects not, the duello he regards not. His disgrace is to be called boy, but his glory is to subdue men. Adieu, valour; rust, rapier; be still, drum; for your manager is in love, yea, he loveth. Assist me some extemporal god of rhyme, for I am sure I shall turn sonnet. Devise wit, write, pen, for I am for whole volumes, in folio.

Romeo and Juliet, Act I, Scene 1

romeo:
Why then, O brawling love, O loving hate,
O anything of nothing first create,
O heavy lightness, serious vanity,
Misshapen chaos of well-seeming forms,
Feather of lead, bright smoke, cold fire, sick health,
Still-waking sleep, that is not what it is!
This love feel I, that feel no love in this.
Dost thou not laugh?

benvolio:
No coz, I rather weep.

romeo:
Good heart, at what?

benvolio:
At thy good heart's oppression.

romeo:
Why, such is love's transgression.
Griefs of mine own lie heavy in my breast,
Which thou wilt propagate to have it pressed
With more of thine. This love that thou hast shown
Doth add more grief to too much of mine own.
Love is a smoke made with the fume of sighs,
Being purged, a fire sparkling in lovers' eyes,
Being vexed, a sea nourished with lovers' tears.
What is it else? A madness most discreet,
A choking gall and a preserving sweet.

Antony and Cleopatra, Act IV, Scene 13

cleopatra:
No more but e'en a woman, and commanded
By such poor passion as the maid that milks
And does the meanest chores. It were for me
To throw my sceptre at the injurious gods,
To tell them that this world did equal theirs
Till they had stol'n our jewel. All's but naught.
Patience is sottish, and impatience does
Become a dog that's mad. Then is it sin
To rush into the secret house of death
Ere death dare come to us? How do you, women?
What, what, good cheer! Why, how now, Charmian?
My noble girls! Ah, women, women! Look,
Our lamp is spent; it's out. Good sires take heart.
We'll bury him and then what's brave, what's noble.
Let's do it after the high Roman fashion
And make death proud to take us. Come away.
This case of that huge spirit now is cold.
Ah, women, women! Come. We have no friend
But resolution, and the briefest end.

Sonnet 26

Lord of my love, to whom in vassalage
Thy merit hath my duty strongly knit,
To thee I send this written embassage
To witness duty, not to show my wit;
Duty so great which wit so poor as mine
May make seem bare in wanting words to show it,
But that I hope some good conceit of thine
In thy soul's thought, all naked, will bestow it;
Till whatsoever star that guides my moving
Points on me graciously with fair aspect,
And puts apparel on my tattered loving,
To show me worthy of thy sweet respect.
Then may I dare to boast how I do love thee;
Till then, not show my head where thou mayst prove me.

The Taming of the Shrew, Act V, Scene 2

petruccio:
Katherine, I charge thee tell these headstrong women
What duty they do owe their lords and husbands.

widow:
Come, come, you're mocking. We will have no telling.

petruccio:
Come on, I say, and first begin with her.

widow:
She shall not.

petruccio:
I say she shall, and first begin with her.

katherine:
Fie, fie, unknit that threat'ning, unkind brow,
And dart not scornful glances from those eyes
To wound thy lord, thy king, thy governor.
It blots thy beauty as frosts do bite the meads,
Confounds thy fame as whirlwinds shake fair buds,
And in no sense is meet or amiable.
A woman moved is like a fountain troubled,
Muddy, ill-seeming, thick, bereft of beauty,
And while it is so, none so dry or thirsty
Will deign to sip or touch one drop of it.
Thy husband is thy lord, thy life, thy keeper,
Thy head, thy sovereign, one that cares for thee,
And for thy maintenance commits his body
To painful labour both by sea and land,
To watch the night in storms, and the day in cold,
While thou liest warm at home, secure and safe,
And craves no other tribute at thy hands
But love, fair looks, and true obedience,
Too little payment for so great a debt.
Such duty as the subject owes the prince,
Even such a woman oweth to her husband;
And when she is froward, peevish, sullen, sour,
And not obedient to his honest will,
What is she but a foul, contending rebel,
And graceless traitor to her loving lord?
I am ashamed that women are so simple
To offer war where they should kneel for peace,
Or seek for rule, supremacy, and sway
When they are bound to serve, love, and obey.
Why are our bodies soft, and weak, and smooth,
Unapt to toil and trouble in the world,
But that our soft conditions and our hearts
Should well agree with our external parts?
Come, come, your froward and unable worms,
My mind hath been as big as one of yours,
My heart as great, my reason haply more,
To bandy word for word and frown for frown;
But now I see our lances are but straws,
Our strength as weak, our weakness past compare,
That seeming to be most which we indeed least are.
Then vail your stomachs, for it is no boot,
And place your hands below your husband's foot,
In token of which duty, if he please,
My hand is ready, may it do him ease.

Troilus and Cressida, Act II, Scene 2

troilus:
I take today a wife, and my election
Is led on in the conduct of my will,
My will enkindled by mine eyes and ears,
Two traded pilots 'twixt the dangerous shores
Of will and judgement. How may I avoid
Although my will distaste what it elected
The wife I chose? There can be no evasion
To blench from this and to stand firm by honour.
We turn not back the silks upon the merchant
When we have spoiled them, nor the remainder viands
We do not throw in unrespective sewer
Because we now are full. It was thought meet
Paris should do some vengeance on the Greeks;
Your breath of full consent bellied his sails,
The seas and winds, old wranglers, took a truce
And did him service. He touched the ports desired
And for an old aunt whom the Greeks held captive
He brought a Grecian Queen, whose youth and freshness
Wrinkles Apollo's and makes stale the morning.
Why keep we her? The Grecians keep our aunt.
Is she worth keeping? Why, she is a pearl
Whose price hath launched above a thousand ships
And turned crowned kings to merchants.
If you'll avouch 'twas wisdom Paris went,
As you must needs, for you all cried,‘Go, go!’
If you'll confess he brought home noble prize,
As you must needs, for you all clapped your hands
And cried,‘Inestimable!’Why do you now
The issue of your proper wisdoms rate
And do a deed that never fortune did:
Beggar the estimation which you prized
Richer than sea and land? O theft most base,
That we have stol'n what we fear to keep!
But thieves unworthy of a thing so stol'n,
That in their country did them that disgrace
We fear to warrant in our native place.

Antony and Cleopatra, Act I, Scene 1

philo:
Nay, but this dotage of our General's
O'erflows the measure. Those his goodly eyes
That o'er the files and musters of the war
Have glowed like plated Mars, now bend, now turn
The office and devotion of their view
Upon a tawny front. His captain's heart,
Which in the scuffles of great fights hath burst
The buckles on his breast, reneges all temper,
And is become the bellows and the fan
To cool a gipsy's lust.

Flourish. Enter Antony, Cleopatra, her ladies, the train, with eunuchs fanning her.

Look where they come.
Take but good note and you shall see in him
The triple pillar of the world transformed
Into a strumpet's fool. Behold and see.

cleopatra (to Antony): If it be love indeed, tell me how much.

antony:
There's beggary in the love that can be reckoned.

Othello, Act I, Scene 3

roderigo: What should I do? I confess it is my shame to be so fond, but it is not in my virtue to amend it.

iago: Virtue? A fig! 'Tis in ourselves that we are thus or thus. Our bodies are our gardens, to the which our wills are gardeners, so that if we will plant nettles or sow lettuce, set hyssop and weed up thyme, supply it with one gender of herbs or distract it with many, either to have it sterile with idleness or manured with industry, why, the power and incorrigible authority of this lies in our wills. If the beam of our lives had not one scale of reason to peise another of sensuality, the blood and baseness of our natures would conduct us to cool our raging motions, our carnal stings, our unbitted lusts; whereof I take this that you call love to be a sect or scion.

Sonnet 131

Thou art as tyrannous, so as thou art,
As those whose beauties proudly make them cruel,
For well thou know'st to my dear doting heart
Thou art the fairest and most precious jewel.
Yet, in good faith, some say that thee behold,
Thy face hath not the power to make love groan.
To say they err I dare not be so bold,
Although I swear it to myself alone;
And to be sure that is not false I swear
A thousand groans but thinking on thy face,
One on another's neck do witness bear
Thy black is fairest in my judgement's place.
In nothing art thou black save in thy deeds,
And thence this slander as I think proceeds.

译者导读

伊曼努尔·康德（Immanuel Kant，1724—1804），德国思想家、哲学家、天文学家、星云说的创立者之一，德国古典哲学的创始人。其学说深刻地影响了此后的哲学，开启了德国唯心主义和康德主义的诸多流派，被认为是对现代欧洲最具影响力的思想家之一，也是启蒙运动最后一位主要哲学家。康德一生著述颇丰，其中核心的著作合称“三大批判”，即《纯粹理性批判》《实践理性批判》和《判断力批判》，这三本哲学著作的问世是康德批判哲学体系诞生的真正标志。

康德一生的研究涉猎广泛，对自然科学、美学、神学、巫术等都有研究，但有一个问题是一直贯穿其中的，那就是哲学研究应该如何进行：是从理性的观点出发，从普遍真理中推导出有关事物的真理，还是从经验出发通过观察得出普遍的结论。

康德的研究以1770年为界可分为前期和后期两个阶段，前期主要研究自然科学，而后期则主要研究哲学。前期的主要研究成果有1755年发表的《自然通史和天体论》，提出了太阳系起源的星云假说。后期的研究成果就是前面提到的“三大批评”。

本书收集的是他后期的四篇作品，即“对‘什么是启蒙’的回答”（1784年）、“论永久和平：一个哲学素描”（1795年）、“回答‘人类是否在持续地改进’问题的新尝试”（1797年）、“关于人类历史开端的猜想”（1786年）。

在《对“什么是启蒙”的回答》中，康德对“什么是启蒙”进行了探讨。他认为，启蒙是人类从自我导致的不成熟状态中觉醒。为什么即使大自然早就把人类从远距离指导的桎梏中解放出来了，仍然有大量的人保持着不成熟的状态，他得出的结论是：懒惰和怯懦。这种不成熟的状态成为了一种惯性。康德指出，要使公众得到启蒙，最为需要的是自由，是在一切事物中公开地运用自己的理性的自由。理性的运用又分为个人运用和公开利用。理性的个人运用是一个人在其被委任的职位或工作中对自己理性的使用。理性的公开利用是臣民们公开运用他们的理性，将他们更好地起草法律的想法公之于众。康德认为，只有自己已经启蒙并且拥有一支能够保障公共安全的军队的统治者才会允许公众理性地思考，而按照人的尊严来对待人，允许他们进行理性的思考对于政府是有益的。

“永久和平：一个哲学素描”应该是康德为人类贡献的最后一篇有深远影响的论著，其中提出的世界公民、世界联邦、不干涉内政的主权国家的原则至今仍有现实意义。论文分两部分阐述了康德关于国际社会保持和平的法哲学理论。第一部分是关于各个国家之间的永久和平的预备条款，用六项条文鼓励缔结和平条约，并以和平条约为依据逐步使常备军无用武之地，从而达到废除常备军的目的。第二部分是国家间永久和平的正式条款，提出建立共和制的市民宪法和以联邦主义为基础的国际法。康德期望以共和制国家的联合以实现国际社会的永久和平。他提出的国际永久和平的思想至今仍深刻地影响着现代国际法和外交准则。

在“回答‘人类是否在持续地改进’问题的新尝试”中，康德探讨了“人类文明史是如何发展的”这个问题。他认为，人类进步的历史必须以某种经验为起点。人类的进步是某个事件发挥作用产生的必然结果。而这个事件是指被自然权利所规定的宪法的演进，即一个共和制的宪法。人们所渴望的国家的实际形式可能是共和制，或者它可能只是在治理模式上是共和制的。

康德预言人类会实现这一目标。而要做到世界不断地改进就要进行大众的启蒙，公开地教给人民对自己国家的义务和权利。一旦一个共和制的宪法被制定出来，它就最有权威阻止战争，当权者会越来越少地使用暴力，而越来越多地遵从法律。这最终会延伸到不同民族之间的外部关系上，直至一个世界公民社会的建立。当人类不断前进时，人的善行会更多，这就是人类能获得的好处。

在“关于人类历史开端的猜想”中，康德阐述了对历史、人性及人类社会的看法，这可以看作是康德历史哲学的重要部分。在这篇论文中，康德猜想了人类自由的最初发展史并给出了一个优美的诠释。人类起初只有动物性的本能，他必须靠本能的指引，听从上帝的命令。第一步是理性的促动，把饮食知识扩大到本能的限度之外。第二步是理性很快让人感到它的存在，并且寻求超越本能的界限扩大食物的知识，这标志着理性驾驭了冲动的意识。第三步反映在对未来的预测上，这是人类优势的决定性因素。因为具有了这种预见性，人类能够为长远的目标做好准备。但是由于这同样的能力，当人类预见到不确定性时，会产生最无穷无尽的担心和焦虑。第四步，人类意识到人才是大自然的真正目的，地球上没有谁能与其抗衡，因此可以把动物看成手段和工具，但是人人平等，人不能像对待动物一样对待其他的人，而应当把他们看作能平分大自然礼物的人。在对人性考察的基础上，康德看到了恶的手段背后隐蔽的善的目的。

康德的作品以晦涩难懂而著称，译者在翻译的过程中参考了其他译者的翻译文本，力求做到语言上清楚明白，希望能以此来减少读者的阅读困难，若有疏漏之处，敬请批评指正。

对“什么是启蒙”的回答

启蒙，是指人类从自我导致的不成熟状态中觉醒。这种不成熟状态是指在缺乏指导下无力运用自我理性的状态。造成它的原因并非人们缺乏理性，而是在无人指导之下缺乏决心和勇气来运用理性。因此，启蒙的口号是“勇于智慧”，即有勇气运用自己的理性！

即使大自然早已把人类从远距离指导的桎梏中解放，懒惰和怯懦使很多人依然快乐地保持着不成熟状态；同样的原因，一些人很容易自命为另一些人的守护者。保持不成熟状态是如此方便：如果有一本书代替我理解，一个精神导师指导我的良知，一个医生评判我的饮食，等等，我就不需要做任何努力。只要金钱能够解决的，我就不需要思想；其他人很快就能替我做这些累人的工作。那些好心接过指导工作的守护者不久就发现，太多的人，不分性别，认为迈向成熟不仅困难重重而且相当危险。这些守护者起初为这些驯化了的动物而着迷，小心翼翼地防止其越雷池一步。他们下一个策略就是展示危险，使其不敢尝试在没有帮助的情况下行走；危险实际上并不那么大，因为他们一定会在摔过几次跟头之后最终学会走路。但是，这样的例子具有恐吓性，通常会吓得他们不敢再尝试。

然而，让每一个个体找到脱离不成熟状态的路十分困难，不成熟状态已经成为他们的第二特征。他们甚至变得喜欢这种状态，随着时间的推移，真得再没有能力运用自己的理性，因为他从未被允许作出这种尝试。规章和程式，这些合理使用或者说是误用他天资的机械工具，就是对他永久性不成熟状态的禁锢。倘若有人扔掉这些枷锁，他依然会不确定是否能够跃过甚至是最窄的壕沟，因为他不习惯这种自由运动。因此，只有少数人能够通过头脑训练成功地脱离这种不成熟状态，继续大胆前行。

相比之下，公众有更多的机会进行自我启蒙。倘若公众被赋予了自由，他们的自我启蒙的确几乎是不可避免的，因为总会有少数人独立思考，他们甚至存在于被指定的大众守护者中间。这些守护者一旦扔掉不成熟状态的枷锁，就会传播尊重个人价值、尊重人人需有独立思考之责任的理念。这样做引人瞩目的一点是，如果之前被守护者锢入枷锁中的公众被唤醒，或许最终会迫使守护者自己留在枷锁中。宣传偏见是非常有害的，因为偏见最终会报复到最初宣扬它的人的身上。因此，公众只能慢慢获得启蒙。一场革命或许能够结束独裁暴政与强权压迫，但是它从不会带来真正的思想革命；取而代之的是新的偏见，如同它们所取代的旧观念一样，成为掌控缺乏思想自由的大众的枷锁。

对于这种启蒙而言，它所需要的只是自由，而这种自由是所有自由形式中最没有恶意的，即在所有事情上公开运用理性的自由。但是我听到各方在说，不要争辩！军官说，不要争辩，列队行进；税务官说，不要争辩，交税；神职人员说，不要争辩，相信！（世界上只有一个统治者说，想怎么争辩就怎么争辩，想争辩什么就争辩什么，但是，服从！）这些都意味着对自由无处不在的限制。但是哪种限制阻碍启蒙，哪种限制不但不阻碍反而促进启蒙？我的回答是：人的理性的公开运用必须总是自由的，这本身就能带来人类的启蒙。理性的个人运用或许常常受到严格的限制，但并不会过度地阻碍启蒙的进步。我所谓的理性的公开运用，是指像一位学者向读者大众阐述观点那样对自己理性的运用。而理性的个人运用，我把它定义为，一个人在其被委任的职位或工作中对自己理性的运用。

在一些关乎公众全体利益的事务中，我们需要一定的机制，在此机制下，一些成员必须完全服从调配，这样他们才能通过一份人为的共同协议，为政府雇用而服务于公共利益（或者至少不会损害公共利益）。在这种情况之下，争辩当然是不被允许的，顺从是必要的。但是，作为机器零部件的单个个人而言，他们认为自己也是公众甚或世界社会的一员，那么就像一位学者通过写作用真正意义上的文字向公众阐述观点一样，他或许的确能做到一边争辩，同时又不妨害自己所受雇从事的事务。然而，如果一个从上司那里领命的军官在执行时公开质疑这一命令的适当性或者有用性，后果是非常有害的。他必须完全地服从命令。但是，我们无法禁止他像学者一样对军事事务中的错误进行观察，也不能禁止他将自己的观察公之于众以供评判。公民不能拒绝缴纳税赋。一个被通知纳税的人，对于这些税赋自以为是的批评，会被当作导致抗命的暴行而受到处罚。然而，一个公民，作为一个博学的个体，公开地阐述这类税赋措施的不恰当甚至是不公平，并没有违反其公民责任。同理，一个受雇于教堂的神职人员有责任根据其所服务教堂的相关教义指导他的受众。但是作为一个学者，他完全有自由也有责任经过深思熟虑，出于善意地将这些教义的谬误之处公之于众，同时为更好地组织宗教和教会的相关事宜提供建议。这一过程中并没有对良心的拷问。作为一个教会的积极服务者，他在履行职责时所教授，并由他呈现出的，就是他职务的一个结果，是他被雇来用一种指定的方式和以其他人的名义而宣讲的。他会说，我们的教会教这个和那个，这些就是教会所引用的论据。然后，他尽量从自己都无法完全信服的戒律中找寻出更多的实际价值。而这些戒律事实上也包含着真理，因此他能够加以阐释。无论如何，在这些教义中没有与宗教本质相悖的内容。如果神职人员认为在这些教义中存在违背宗教本质的内容，他就不会心安理得地履行其职责，就会辞职。然而，这种理性的运用纯粹是私人性质的，因为教区无论多大都不过是私人聚会。这样看来，作为牧师也不会是自由的，因为他是在履行外界赋予的使命。与此相反，如果作为一个用作品感染公众（例如，整个世界）的学者，一位公开运用理性的神职人员应当享受无限的自由，能够自由表达，否则就等同于说人们精神世界的守护者本身不成熟，而这种说法是荒唐的，并且永远是荒唐的。

神职人员团体，例如一个教会法院或者是教务评议会，是否应当宣誓对不可改变的信条负有忠实义务，以确保全天候地为其信徒进而为其他人提供监护？我的回答是，这不可能。这种旨在永远阻止人类的启蒙而订立的契约，即使它由最高权力机构、神圣罗马帝国国会或最庄严的和平条约所认可，也完全没有法律效力。一个时代不能通过誓约将下一个时代放在这样一个位置上，使其无法拓展和修正知识，特别是在像启蒙这样重要的问题上寻求进步。这是违反人性的犯罪，因为人性的原始目标正是在此方面取得进步。后代人因此完全有权利将这些协议看作是毫无权威并且是犯罪而摒弃它们。检验一项具体措施能否成为法律，我们只需看一个民族是否将这项法律施加于自身；在没有更好的解决方法之前，这也可作为在某个特定的短暂时期内引进一项制度的方法。这也意味着每个公民，特别是神职人员，会被给予像学者一样在其著述中公开评论现行制度不足的自由。与此同时，这项新制度会继续存在，直到公众对于这些事物的看法有所进步，一致同意通过一项议案提交给国王。这是为了保护那些有更深刻认识的会众改变其宗教信仰，但并不会阻碍那些希望维持原状的会众。终其一生皈依一个没有人可以公开质疑的宗教是绝对不可取的，因为，这会抹杀人们进步的一个阶段，因此对后代是毫无益处，甚至是有害的。一个人自己或许在有限的一段时间内，在应当知道的事物上延迟启蒙；但是完全放弃这种启蒙，不管是为其个人还是为其后代，都意味着侵犯和践踏人类神圣的权利。但是人们不愿意强加于自身的东西，更不会被统治者所强加，因为统治者取得立法权力正是靠汇集人们集体意愿于他一身。只要他看到所有的真实存在或者是想象中的进步无碍于社会秩序，就会允许臣民做任何他们认为必要的完成自我救赎的事情，这与他无关。他的责任是制止任何人阻碍别人完成自我救赎。倘若他把臣民用写作阐述宗教观点的举动纳入政府的监控之中，那的确有损其王权。而如果他的强权基于其自以为是的意见，他会受到谴责。而如果他利用至高无上的权力支持少数独裁者对臣民进行精神统治，他就更是民众谴责的众矢之的。

如果现在问，我们当前是否生活在一个已经启蒙的时代，答案是：不，但我们的确生活在一个启蒙时代。当前，要全体人类能够无需外部指导也可以自信熟练地运用自身对宗教事务的理解，我们还有很长的路要走。但是，确有清晰的迹象表明，这条道路正被开辟出来，使人们可以沿着这个方向自由前行；普遍启蒙的障碍也正逐渐减少，使人类可以摆脱自身的蒙昧幼稚。从这个角度而言，我们的时代是启蒙时代，是腓特烈的时代。

如果一个君主认为，他在宗教事务中的职责不是命令其臣民，而是给予他们充分的自由，或者他自己甚至不接受“宽容”这一略显自负的头衔，那么这个君主自身就启蒙了；他值得受到现代以及后代人的赞扬，因为他（从政府的角度）率先将人类从蒙昧中解放，让所有人自由地运用理性解决所有事情。在他的统治之下，宗教显贵们尽管有政府职务，也会尽力像学者一样自由而公开地发表自己的判断和观点，接受世界的评判，即使这些观点有时偏离了宗教的教义；那些不受官职限制的人更是如此。这种自由的精神也会传播到国外，传播到那些与外部阻力斗争的国家，而阻力则来自于政府对自身功能的曲解。对于此类政府，现在有一个出色的实例，能够证明自由可以丝毫不妨碍公共和谐与联邦的统一。只要没有人为设置的条件蓄意使人们停留在野蛮状态，人们自己就会逐渐走出野蛮。

我将宗教事务描述为启蒙的焦点——启蒙即指人类摆脱自身的蒙昧。这首先是因为我们的统治者对于做艺术和科学方面的监护人不感兴趣，第二点是因为宗教蒙昧是最有害和不光彩的。但是，对于在艺术和科学方面崇尚自由的君主而言，他会进一步地延伸其主张，因为他认识到，如果允许臣民们公开运用自己的理性，将关于立法的更好观点公之于众，那么，即便这会引发他们对现有法律的正面批评，也不会产生任何危险，哪怕是君主的法律也安全无虞。面前就有一个绝好的例子：我们现今尊敬的这位君主没有别人能比得上。

但是，只有一位自身启蒙、不怕鬼魂，手中又拥有一支纪律严明且数量众多的军队以保障公共安全的统治者，才会说出共和国政府不敢说的话：你们可以就任何事情随意争论，但要服从！从中我们可以看到人类事务的一个奇怪而出乎意料的模式（如果在更广的范围上看，我们总能发现这一现象，即近乎所有事情都是矛盾的）。高度的公民自由看似对一个民族的思想自由颇有裨益，但它也为后者筑起了不可逾越的障碍。相反，较低程度的公民自由给思想自由足够的空间，使其可以充分扩展。因此，一旦大自然精心培育的胚芽，即人类自由思考的趋势和天职在这一硬壳中生长，它就会作用于人们的心智，促使人们自由行动的能力逐渐增强。最终，它甚至会影响政府的原则；政府会发现，它们尊重人们便会从中受益，人们不是一台机器。 [1]

柯尼斯堡-普鲁士
1784年9月30日

永久和平：一个哲学素描

“永久和平”

一位荷兰旅店的店主曾经把具有讽刺意味的碑文连同一张坟墓的图片放在旅馆留言板上；我们不必费心询问这是否涉及广义上的男人，还是特指国家元首（国家元首们从不厌倦战争），或者仅是指那些幸福地梦想着永久和平的哲学家。本篇文章的作者事先做个保留。实践政治家倾向于不可一世地把政治理论家仅仅看作是研究人员而轻视他们。实践政治家认为，政治理论家抽象的主张不会危及国家安全，因为国家必须建立在实践原则的基础之上，因此，允许释放其所有的不满似乎是安全的。老于世故的政治家对此不必理会。因此，接下来的就是，如果实践政治家不前后矛盾的话，在与理论家争辩的时候，他们就不应当宣布理论家随意、公开表述过的观点对国家具有什么危险。根据这个保留条款，本文作者自认为将受到正确和恰当的保护，不会被恶意曲解。

第一部分　包含国家间永久和平的先决条款

1.“如果对未来战争存有秘密的保留条件，则和平结论的得出是无效的。”

如果情况是这样的话，这仅仅是个停战期，是敌对的延续，不是和平。和平意味着所有敌对的结束，将形容词“永久”加在和平之前已经有些冗长。和平条约的缔结消除了未来战争的所有存在理由，尽管这些理由对签约双方仍尚未可知，也不管他们是如何敏锐地、精心地从旧文件中拼凑出了这些理由。对于未来过去的托辞是否能再次生效，各方都可能对此持有精神上的保留。这种保留不会被特别地提出，因为双方都对继续打仗感到筋疲力尽，尽管他们心存恶念，希望抓住第一个机会达到目的。但是如果我们考虑这些保留意见本身，它们不过是耶稣式的狡辩。它们不配一位统治者的尊严，正如按照这种推理逻辑，它们不配一位国务大臣的尊严一样。

但是，如果依据政治权宜之计的“启蒙”动向，我们相信一个国家真正的光荣在于采取一切办法不断增强实力，不过，上述的判断看上去确实既迂腐又充满了学究气。

2.“凡现存的独立国家，不论大小，他国皆不得通过继承、交换、买卖或赠送的方式获得。”

一个国家，不像其脚下的土地那样是一种财产。它是一个由人组成的社会。只有它能对自己下命令或者进行自我处置。正像一棵树，它有自己的根，把它如同嫩芽一样移植到另一个国家去是中止其道德人格的存在，而把它当作了商品。这与原始契约的初衷背道而驰。没有了原始契约这一初衷，保障一个民族的权利是不可想象的。 [2]每一个人都知道这样获得国家权利带给欧洲的危险（因为这种实践在其他大陆是不为人知的）。人们认为国家之间可以彼此联姻。这提供了一种新的产业，即权力能够通过家庭结盟而增强，不需要耗费精力，与此同时土地财产也得以扩展。同理，当一国军队受雇于另一国去打击属于一方的敌人时，臣民们因此就会被当作或错误地当作可随意支配的物体加以使用。

3.“常设军队将逐渐全部被废除。”

常设军队一直是为战争而准备的。它们不断用战争威胁着其他国家的安全。它们通过武装毫无限制的士兵的数量刺激国家之间相互赶超。由于军队自身就是侵略战争的根源，维持常设军队的费用最终使和平演变成了战争，而战争解决了军费开支的负担。再有，雇凶杀人或者被杀似乎是把这些人当成某些人（国家）手中的武器，这不能与人内在人格中的权利原则相提并论。如果公民们不时接受自愿的军事训练是为保护自己和家园免遭外部的侵犯，这就是另外一回事了。但是如果是增加财富而不是增加士兵人数也是一样，这也会被其他国家看作是军事威胁，会促使其采取防御性的攻击，因为一个国家有三种力量——军事力量、联盟力量、财富力量——第三者可能是战争最可靠的工具。如果发现另一国所拥有的财富并不匮乏的话，战争就会频繁发生。

4.“任何国家债务合约都不得与该国外部事务相关联。”

为国家经济寻求帮助，不论是内援还是外援都是没有什么可疑的（例如，改善公路状况、重新安置移民、储存粮食以备饥荒时用，等等）。但是，如果一种借贷制度被列强用作征服别国的工具，那它体现的是财力最危险的形式。因为当这些债务现在不被追讨时，它们却在无限制地增长（因为不是所有的债主会同时要求还债）。由商业民族在本世纪发明的这个精巧体系所提供的军事经费可以超过所有其他国家可提供的总和。通过这一借贷制度可以为工业和贸易提供商业上的刺激，从而使经济崩溃推迟相当一段时间，但是债务国最终会被税收赤字压垮。这种战争的延缓，加上当权者的好战倾向（这似乎是与人性不可分离的特性），外债就是永久和平道路上的障碍。因此，外债必须在和平协定的先决条款中被禁止，否则国家的破产就在所难免，由此产生的损失可能殃及其他无辜的国家，给其造成伤害；其他国家因此有充分的理由联合起来一致对付这样一个国家。

5.“任何国家不得强行干涉他国的宪法和政府。”

什么能使这种干涉合情合理呢？当然不是一个国家在另一个国家的事务中引发的造谣和冒犯行为；这应当是对他国的一种警示，是一个民族由于目无法纪而招来恶魔的例证。一个自由的人给另一个人树立的坏榜样与他对后者的伤害是不同的。如果一个国家由于内部的纷争想分成两部分，每一部分自成一国，声称拥有原来的那个国家，那情况就不一样了。如果一个外部的国家想要给予其中的一个国家帮助，在这种情况下不能认定为是对这个国家宪法的干涉，因为其正属于无政府状态。只要这种内部矛盾没有解决，外部势力的干涉就是对一个独立民族权利的干涉，因为这个民族的人民在与其自身的疾病作斗争。这种干涉是一种积极的冒犯，会给所有其他国家的自治带来不安全感。

6.“与另一个国家交战的国家不允许有下列仇视行为，因为这些行为会在未来的和平时期导致彼此缺乏信任。这些行为包括在敌对国家进行暗杀或者投毒，违反协议，煽动叛国等。”

这些都是不光彩的行径。即使在战争时期，对敌对方的态度也必须存在某种信任，否则和平协议就不可能达成，敌对就会演变成毁灭性的战争。毕竟，战争仅仅是，在没有公正的法庭用司法权威评判的情况下，一个国家用武力争取权利的令人惋惜的权宜之计。在这些案例中，双方都不能被称作是非正义的敌人，因为那样做就已经假设了一个法官的裁决。冲突的结局，如同所谓“上帝的审判”的案例，可以决定谁是对的一方。国家间的惩罚性战争是难以想象的，因为它们之间没有优劣之分。接下来是，毁灭性的战争使交战双方及其权利同时受损，永久的和平只存在于巨大的人类坟墓里。此类战争及其导致战争的种种因素必须坚决禁止。但是上面所列的那些手段会引发这样的战争，因为这些糟糕透顶的技艺，除了特别令人厌恶之外，一旦被拿来运用就不仅仅局限于战争本身。例如，战争会使用间谍，这只会利用别人的不诚实为自己谋利（这种做法永远不会完全消失）。这种做法会延续至和平时期，因此完全损害到和平的宗旨。

所有上面列出的条款，如果客观地或者联系当权者的意图审视，属于禁止性法律。有些法律是最严格的，不管情况如何变化，它们都是有效的，要求立即禁止有关行为（第1、5、6条）。其他的条款（第2、3、4条），尽管它们也是公平条款，却允许根据所适用情形保有一定的自由度。后者不一定立即执行，只要它们的最终目的没有受到忽视（例如，根据第2项条款恢复某些国家的自由）。但是，这些条款的延期执行并非遥遥无期，而仅仅作为一种手段，用以避免生硬地执行，从而导致无法达到设立此条款目的的结果。第2条的情况是，禁止只与获得的方式有关，与国家的政治状况无关。尽管这个现状不被合法政府支持，但是在每个国家的公共意见中，在公认的推定取得的时代，这被认为是合法的。 [3]

第二部分　包含国家间永久和平的正式条款

共同生活的人们之间的和平状态与自然状态是不同的。自然状态即是一种战争状态。因为即使没有主动的敌意行为，也不断存在危险的爆发。因此和平状态必须是正式建立的，因为敌对状态的延缓本身无法保障和平。除非一个邻居在另一个邻居的要求下为其作出保证（这只能在一个法制国家实现），否则后者都会视前者为敌人。 [4]

永久和平的第一个正式条款：每个国家的市民宪法应当是共和政体。

一部共和制的宪法建立在三条原则基础之上。第一，社会成员中所有的成员都享有自由。第二，每个人都依靠一个共同的法律体系。第三，每个公民都享有司法平等。 [5]宪法是唯一一个缘自原始契约思想的法律文件。一个民族所有的正当立法必须建立在其基础之上。因此，就权利而言，共和制本身就是每一种市民宪法的原始基础，剩下所要问的问题是，它是否是通向永久和平的唯一宪法。

共和制宪法不仅自身起源纯粹（因为它来源于纯粹的权利概念），而且它还提供了获得所渴望结果的前景，例如，一个永久的和平。理由如下：是否宣战需要征得公民的同意，很自然，公民们会非常犹豫是否投赞成票，因为宣战意味着他们要承担战争的所有悲惨后果。例如，他们要亲自参战，要从他们自己的资源中抽出战争的费用，痛苦地修复灾难的创伤，承担负债的压力，而负债的压力由于新战争的不断威胁而永远无法减轻。然而，在宪法之下的臣民并非公民的情况下，即在非共和政体之下，战争是世界上最简单的事。由于一国之君不是一个公民，而是国家的拥有者，战争不会让他作出任何的牺牲：他的宴会、狩猎、享乐消遣的宫殿、节日的狂欢都一如既往。他因此会决定宣战。他之所以这样做并没有合理的理由，只是一种消遣。他会毫无顾虑地将辩护的事情交给外交使团——他们一直是为此目的作准备的——以为了国家繁荣而战为开战的理由。

共和制的宪法常常和民主制的宪法相混淆，下面的解释可以避免这种错误。国家的各种形式既可以依据行使最高权力人的不同而定，也可以依据其统治者统治的方式而定。有三种可能的形式，依据是统治权是在个人、少数人组成的团体，还是在所有组成公民社会的人们手中（例如，独裁政体、贵族统治、民主政体，即王子政权、贵族政权、人民政权）。第二种分类取决于政府的形式，（例如，普通大众成为人民的普遍意愿）与国家如何依据宪法（例如，由于普遍意愿变成了法案，因此人群成为了民族）以什么样的方式行使其全部权力。在这种情况下，政府的形式或者是共和政体或者是专制政体。共和主义是一种政治体制，即执行权力（政府）与司法权力分离。独裁主义在这样的一个国家横行，其法律的制定和执行由同一个权力完成。它只有在统治者把人民意愿当成自己意愿时才会反映人民的意愿。在这三种政体中，民主政体也可能是一种暴政，因为它设立了一种执行权力，通过这个执行权力，所有公民针对一个人作决定，并且不经过这个人的同意，因此，决定是由大家作出的，又不是由大家作出的。这意味着普遍的意愿自相矛盾，也与自由相矛盾。

任何没有代议制的政府都是非正常现象，因为一个人，同一个人不能同时是立法者和其自我意愿的执行者，如同逻辑推理中一般命题不能同时是次要命题一样。即使其他两种政治宪法（例如，独裁政体和贵族政体）因其给独裁政府留有足够的空间而总是存在缺陷，它们还会与这样的政府联系在一起，因为这个政府秉承代议制精神。因此，弗里德里克二世说，他仅仅是国家最高级别的仆人， [6]而在一个民主宪法之下，这种态度不可能存在，因为民主政体中的每一个人都想成为一个统治者。我们因此可以说一个国家统治者的数量越少其代表权力越大，宪法也更体现其共和的本质，并通过逐渐改革最终实现这一本质还是有希望的。由于这个原因，实现这个唯一完美的合法宪法，在一个贵族政体里比在一个君主政体中更加困难。在一个民主政体中，通过暴力革命有可能得以实现。但是人们比关心宪法的形式更加关心政府的模式， [7]尽管更要看宪法在多大程度上符合政府的意图。但是如果政府的模式要与权利的概念相一致，它必须建立在代议制的基础上。这种代议制能够使一个民主国家成为可能，不管采用何种形式的宪法，没有这种民主代表制度，暴政和暴力就会出现。所谓古希腊和古罗马时期的共和制没有采用这种民主代表制度，因此它们也毫无例外地以暴政而告终，尽管在一个人的统治之下，这种体制相对来说依然可以忍受。

永久和平的第二个正式条款：各国的权利应当建立在自由国家联盟的基础上。

我们可以用评判独立于任何外部的法律约束、生活在一种自然状态下的个人的方式评判自己归属于民族国家的哪些民族，因为仅仅依据他们是邻居这一事实，他们就彼此构成威胁。每个国家为了自身的安全能够也应当要求其他国家与自己一道进入一种宪法体制，这种宪法体制类似于市民宪法，从而使每个人的权利得以维护；这就意味着建立一个各民族的联盟。但是，这种联盟与一个国际性的国家不同。一个国际性国家的想法是自相矛盾的，因为每个国家都包含一个上级（法律制定者）和一个下级（遵守法律的人们）的关系，而几个民族组成一个国家就是建立一个民族。这与我们最初的设想相矛盾，因为我们是从民族相互之间的关系出发考虑各民族权利的，它们隶属于不同的国家，而不是联合成为一个整体。

我们带着极大的蔑视看待没有法律约束的自由与残暴的生活方式。他们宁愿陷于无休止的争斗中也不愿意遵从法律的约束，因为他们喜欢愚蠢的自由，而不喜欢理性的自由。我们认为这是人性的野蛮、粗俗和残暴。我们因此期盼每一个文明的民族自我组成国家，尽快摒弃如此可耻的状态。但是与此期望背道而驰的是，每个国家都认为其君主不需遵从任何外部法律的约束，其统治者的光荣就在于命令数以千计的人为了一个事业而赴汤蹈火，而这个事业与他们毫无关系，统治者自己却不需冒任何风险。 [8]欧洲野蛮民族与美国民族的主要区别就在于，当一些美国的部落被他们的敌人完全吃掉时，欧洲人知道如何更好地利用这些战败者而不是简单地吃掉他们：他们宁愿利用战败者来增加被统治者的数量，并用增加武器的办法去扩大战争的范围。

尽管在法律统治下的公民社会中，对于人性的剥夺被深深地掩盖了，但在不同民族间不受约束的相互关系中还是赤裸裸地展现了出来。因此，人们不禁要问，权利一词是不是还没有完全从军事政治中被驱除，是不是还没有哪个国家胆敢公开宣称要消灭权利一词。尽管他们富有哲理和外交性的条款没有也不会有极微小的法律效力，胡果·格劳修斯、塞缪尔·普芬多夫、瓦特尔和其他人（他们是可怜的安慰者）的言论仍在军事侵略中被引用，因为这样的国家不受一个共同的外部约束所制约。因此，也没有先例表明，一个国家因为听从了上面提及的尊贵的人的言论而停止其军事行动。这种每个国家对权利概念的敬畏表明，人类拥有伟大的道德能力，能够战胜自身的邪恶（因为他不能否认邪恶的存在），并且希望其他人也能够这样做；否则权利一词就永远不会被企图彼此宣战的国家所使用，除非是在嘲弄的意义上，正如某位高卢王子所宣称的：“自然界赋予强壮者驯服弱者的特权。”由于没有外部的特别法庭审判其主张，那么各国寻求自身权利的办法只能是战争。但是军事胜利不能保证权利，一个和平协议可以终结当前的战争，却不能终结普遍的战争状态，而发动一场新的战争的理由总是能够找到的。的确，这样的一种事态也不能说完全不公平，因为它允许每个当事方在决定自己事情时充当法官。自然权利允许我们说生活在无法无天状态下的人应当摒弃这种状态，而各民族的权利却不允许我们对国家说同样的话。因为作为国家，它们已经有了一个合法的内部宪法，因此，它们超越了其他民族的权利概念并将根据自身对于权利概念的理解将自己纳入一个更加广泛的合法体制中。另一方面，作为司法道德的最高权威，理智绝对谴责战争，并把建立和平作为当即的使命。但是，如果没有一个国家间的协议，是不能宣布并确保和平的。因此，一种特定的团体，我们可以称之为“和平联盟”的组织便应运而生了。它与和平协议不同，后者结束了一场战争，而前者是寻求结束所有的战争。这一联盟并不力求获得像国家那样的权力，而仅仅是维护和确保每个国家的自由以及其他结盟国家的自由。这并不意味着它们服从于公法以及执行它们的强制性权力，就像自然状态中的人们一样。这种联邦主义的想法逐渐延伸至所有的国家，达到永久的和平，是可行并且具有现实意义的。因为如果一个强大的、受到启蒙的民族在机缘下形成共和国，这将为其他国家形成联盟提供一个活动中心。其他国家会加入第一个国家的行列，并在尊重各国权利的共识下保障了各国的自由。通过一系列这类联盟的形成，达成共识的国家数量会越来越多。

一个民族这样说是可以理解的。它说：“我们之间将没有战争。我们将组成一个国家，自己指定最高的立法、执行和司法的权利机构，用和平方式解决我们之间的矛盾。”但是，如果这个国家说，“我自己和其他国家之间将没有战争，尽管我不承认任何最高的立法权力能够确保我的权利，而它的权利我也应当予以保障。”除非我能依靠一些公民社会联合体的替代品，例如，一个自由的联邦，否则我便不能对我的权利的保障有信心。如果说国际权利的概念想具有某种意义的话，理性必须能够与这种联盟相随相伴。

国际权利的概念如果理解为战争的权利，那么这一概念就变得毫无意义了。因为这就等于认可了这样的现实，即决定什么是合法的存在，并非通过普遍有效的外部法律而是通过以武力作支撑的片面行为准则。这也可以理解为，持有这种观点的人相互诋毁是完全公平的，因此只能在巨大的坟墓中找寻永久的和平，坟墓中埋葬着所有对暴力的恐惧和那些对暴力负责的人们。只有一种理性的办法能使国家与其他国家在没有法律的、纯粹的战争状态中共存。如同一个一个的人，他们必须放弃野蛮和没有法律约束的自由，将自己纳入公法的管辖之内，从而形成一个国际性的国家，该国家持续增大直至容纳地球上所有的民族。但是，因为根据目前国际性权利的概念，这不是国家的意愿，建立一个世界性共和国的积极想法无法得到实现。如果所有都不失去的话，也最好可以找到一个替代品，即建立一个逐渐扩张的联邦来防止战争。后者可以检查目前人们蔑视法律对抗伙伴的倾向，尽管一直存在战争再一次爆发的危险。（正如维吉尔的诗句所言：“邪恶的狂怒张开血盆大口，疯狂地肆虐着。”） [9]

永久和平的第三个正式条款：世界性权利应当限制在全球友好的前提下。

正如以下条款所示，我们在这里不是关注慈善，而是关注权利。在这一语境下，友好意味着当一个陌生人在到达他国领土时不会受到恶意的对待。他的确可以不被收留，倘若这样做不会导致其死亡，但是只要他在碰巧进入的那个地方表现平和，他就不应当受到恶意的对待。这个陌生人不能要求受到客人般的款待，因为那样需要一个特别友好的协议，根据这个协议，他可能会在一定时间内成为当地家庭的一员。他或许仅仅能够要求有度假权，因为所有人有权共同拥有地球表面，所以所有人都有权在属于其他人的地域出现。由于地球是一个球体，人们无法划定一个无限的区域，必须尽可能地忍受彼此的共存。没有人在占有地球某个特定部分时享有更大的权利。人类群体被地球表面不可居住部分的海洋和沙漠所分隔，即使是这样，船舶和骆驼（沙漠之舟）使得他们能够穿越这些无主地而靠近他们的同伴，利用人类共享地球表面的权利作为社会交往的一种形式。沿海居民在连接海洋的水域掠夺船只，奴役被俘海员的不友好行为，以及沙漠居民认为靠近游牧部落就可以掠夺他们的做法都是违反自然权利的。但是这种友好的自然权利，例如，陌生人的权利，不会延伸到超越条件使得他们企图与当地居民建立关系的地步。这样，彼此有距离的各大洲也能够进入共同的和平关系，可能最终受到公法的规范，从而将人类逐渐向一个世界性公民体制靠拢。

如果我们比较大陆上文明国度的不友好行为，特别是商业国家的不友好行为，它们展现出的对外国和外国人的不公平行为似乎耸人听闻（对于占领外国和控制外国人情况是一样的）。美洲、黑人国家、香料群岛、好望角等等在被发现时被看作是无主地，因为土著居民被忽视了。在东印度（印度斯坦），外国军队仅仅以建立贸易站点为借口侵入。这导致了当地人受到压迫，印度各邦陷入战争、饥荒、叛乱、背叛，以及一系列折磨人类的罪恶行径。

中国 [10]和日本在经历了这些客人的骚扰后智慧地对他们进行了限制。中国允许他们停靠在其领土周围，却禁止其进入；而日本只允许荷兰这一个欧洲民族靠岸，但是却像对待囚徒一样将荷兰人与当地人分隔开。最为糟糕的是（或者从道德的角度评判是最好的），商业国家并没有因为其暴力行为而获益，因为他们所有的贸易公司都处在崩溃的边缘。糖料群岛（the Sugar Islands），一个最残酷最绞尽脑汁实行奴隶制的地方，根本不盈利。这些岛屿只是服务于为战船培养船员的不怎么光彩的间接目的，从而帮助欧洲进行战争。所有这些都是强权的杰作，他们不停地拿虔诚做文章。他们希望被看作是被选中的信奉者，与此同时却享受着不公平的战果。

地球上的各民族不同程度地进入了一个全球性的社会。它已经发展到这种程度，即发生在世界某地的人权侵犯行为会被世界各地感受到。世界公民权利的想法因此并非太不切合实际也太过勉强，它是对未形成条文的政治和国际权利的一个必要补充，将其发展成为一个人类的世界性权利。只有在这种条件下，我们才能自我恭维一下说，我们正在继续向着永久的和平进发。

补充条款一：关于保障永久和平

自然这个伟大的艺术家是永久和平的保障者。自然的运作过程可视性地展现了其在人类中创造和谐的设想，甚至是有悖于人类的意愿并通过他们之间不和谐的方式达到。这种规划，倘若我们认为其运行法则不为人所知，则被冠以“命运”之称。如果我们在世界的发展中审视其富有目的性的设计，它展现出一个主宰更高事业的内在智慧，给人类完成客观目标指明道路，并且确定了世界的进化；我们称之为神意。 [11]我们实际上观察不到自然的这种诡计，我们甚至不能推断其存在。但是，在各种事物的关系和目的之间，我们能够并且必须运用它，以便将自然的诡计与人类的诡计作类比。神意与结果的关系以及与结果的一致只能被设想成是一种想法，由理性直接告诉我们。然而，这一想法的确是难以触摸的理论，它具有有效性并且在实践中有非常真实的基础，正如永久和平的概念，我们有责任运用上面提到的自然的机制去推动它。在只关心理论而不是宗教的语境下，我们也应当注意并且谈及自然，这更是人类理性的局限而不是神意的问题，因为理性必须在可能的经验的边界内处理因果关系。谦逊禁止我们谈论神意，因为这就意味着戴上伊卡洛斯的翅膀，假定要靠近其神妙莫测的奥秘。

在我们更确切地界定这一保障之前，我们必须首先检查一下自然将演员们放置在其伟大壮观的场面的情景，因为正是这种情景要求有和平的保障。下一步我们可以探求这种保障是以何种形式提供的。

大自然的安排是这样的：首先，她关心人类能够在他们所定居的地方生存。第二，她通过战争的方式将人类驱逐到四面八方，甚至让人类居住在最恶劣的地区。第三，她用同样的方法迫使人类或多或少地建立司法关系。苔藓在北冰洋最寒冷的荒野中依然能够生长，这本身就是一个奇迹；驯鹿能从积雪中将苔藓挖出，让其成为食物，并使自己成为奥斯提亚克斯人或者萨莫耶德斯人的牲畜。同理，盐碱沙漠中有骆驼，它们仿佛是为在沙漠中行走而生，这样它们也会被利用。当我们认识到如下事实时，自然被设计的证据会更清晰地展现：北冰洋的海岸不仅住着毛皮动物，而且有海豹、海象、鲸鱼，它们的肉和脂肪为当地人提供了食物和能量。自然界（如下的）关照（行为）引发更多的敬仰。自然界将漂流木带到没有树的地方，谁也不知道这些漂流木来自哪里。当地人如果没有这些材料，他们就无法造船和造武器，或者是建造住所来居住。他们与动物的斗争已经很吃力，因而彼此之间能够和平相处。但是，可能正是战争把他们驱赶到了这些地区。在征服地球的过程中，所有动物中人类首先驯服的战争工具就是马。在国家建立之后较为奢侈的时期大象才被驯服。播种叫作谷物的某种草也是一样；这些谷物的原始特性并不为我们所知。培养和种植各种各样的水果也是一样（在欧洲，大概只有两个品种即沙果树和野生梨）。只有在国家形成、土地固定，人们摒弃了猎人、 [12]渔民、牧羊人没有法律规范的自由生活并完成向农业生活方式的过渡后，这种艺术才能产生。接着，盐和铁被发现了——它们是各民族间贸易的最初物品。这样国家间首次彼此进入和平的关系，甚至与最远的同伴达成相互理解、互利和平的关系。

大自然看到人们能够居住在地球上的各个地方；大自然的意愿是他们应当住在各个地方，甚至有悖于他们自己的意愿。这个义务并非基于责任的概念，或者是基于道德法则要求他们完成的。相反，自然选择战争作为达到这一目的的手段。

我们可以观察到民族通过其语言的一致性展现其后代的一体性。北冰洋上的萨莫耶德斯人和相距二百英里的阿尔泰山里说同一种语言的另一群人就属于这种情况。另一群蒙古族裔骑马征战，把其中的一个部落驱赶到了最荒蛮的北极地区，这显然不是这群人的意愿。 [13]同样的，欧洲最北部地区的芬兰人（在那里他们被称为拉普人）现在与匈牙利人远远相隔，这两群人在语言上是相互联系的，他们被哥特人和萨马特人从中分开了。除了战争还能有谁会这么做。大自然在地球上散播人群的方法能让爱斯基摩人占据最北部，因为他们和其他美洲族群不同，有可能是古代欧洲探险者的后裔。佩沙拉人被用同样的方式驱赶到南方的火地岛。然而，战争本身不需要特别的动机，因为人性中好战的基因仿佛与生俱来。好战甚至被看作是高贵的，使人们受到荣誉感的激励，且并无自私的动机。因此，好战的勇气，连同美洲人的野蛮及其中世纪欧洲伙伴的野蛮，被看作拥有伟大的、直接的价值，不仅仅是在战争时期，也在即将产生战争的时期。因此战争常常是因为要展现这一品质而开始的，于是战争本身被赋予了一种内在的尊严，甚至哲学家们把战争看作是对人产生尊贵影响的事，完全忘却了希腊谚语所说“战争是坏的，因为它在毁灭魔鬼的同时制造出更多的魔鬼”。大自然为了达到其目的对动物种类中的人类亦如法炮制。

我们现在来谈谈关于永久和平的前景的核心问题。大自然对于人们认定的自己的责任做了什么？例如，大自然是如何帮助推动其道德目标的？大自然如何能够保证，依据自由法则人应当做的（但还没有做）实际上会由自然的力量做到又无损于人的自由？这个问题提出了公权利三个领域的问题，即政治、国际和世界公民的权利。如果我说自然愿意让这个或者那个发生，这并不意味着自然赋予我们责任去做这样的事，因为责任只能在具有可行性的理由时才能赋予，并且在没有任何外部限制的情况下实行。相反，自然不管我们是否愿意都会这么做，“命运引领着愿意的人，但是也拽着不愿意的人”。

1.即使人们不被内部的分歧所驱使而服从公法的强制力，战争也会从外部制造出同样的效果。因为根据上面所描述的自然的安排，每个民族都会发现自己要面对邻近一个民族的挑战，因此被迫形成一个国家以对付另一个民族的武装力量。如今共和制宪法是唯一一个完全公正地保护人权的宪法。但它也最难建立，且更难维护，因此许多人认为这样的宪法只能在天使的国度里成为可能，因为人类有追逐私利的倾向，因而没有能力遵循一个极其自然的宪法。但是，事实上，自然会帮助理智的、普遍的人类意愿，人类的意愿那么令人羡慕，在实践中又是那么无能为力。意愿只会让人们为国家创建一个好的机构，他们有能力做这件事。人们这样安排这个机构使得他自利的能量相互抵消，每个人中和或者抵消其他人的破坏力量。就理智而言，结果是一样的，仿佛人类的自私倾向不存在，因此，人，即使自己缺乏道德也会被迫成为一个好的公民。建立国家的问题甚至能被一个由魔鬼组成的民族所解决（只要他们拥有知性）。可以表述如下：“为了建立一个由理智者组成的组织，这些理智者为了生存需要普遍适用的法律，但是每个个体倾向于把自己排除在这些法律的约束之外，宪法必须如此设计，即即使公民的私人看法彼此相左，但是这些不同的观点能够相互抑制致使公民的公共行为一致，仿佛他们并没有过这些邪恶的观点。”这样的问题必须是可以解决的。因为这个任务不包括人类道德水平的提高，它仅仅意味着寻找出如何将自然的机理运用于人类，让他们彼此仇视的情绪迫使他们遵守强制的法律，并因此创造一个和平的条件，使得法律能够得到执行。我们甚至可以看到这个原则在现存的国家间起作用（尽管这还并不完美）。因为在它们的外部关系中，它们已经接近了权利的想法，尽管这样做的理由不是其内部的道德观点。同理，我们不能期望它们的道德态度产生一个完善的政治宪法。相反，正是通过后者，人们才能够期望获得一个好的道德文化。因此，自私的倾向在其外部关系中自然地相互排斥的自然机理可以被理智所利用以达到其目的，即权利统治。内部和外部的和平因此得到深化与确保，只要这种和平就在国家权力可控的范围内。我们或许因此说自然决定让权利最终占上风。人类忽略的事情最终会自动发生，尽管多少有些不便。正如鲍特维克所指出的那样：“如果芦苇弯得太狠就会断裂；索要太多将一无所获。”

2.国际权利的观点假定许多独立的相邻国家独自存在。国家的事务基本上是战争，除非有一个联盟防止敌对行为的爆发。但是依据理智性的想法，这样一个国家依旧比独立国家联合体更受期待，它统治着其他的国家，创造出一个统一的王朝。随着政府力量的加强，法律逐渐地失去其影响力。一个没有灵魂的暴政，在粉碎了善的萌芽之后最终陷入无政府状态。因此，每个国家（或者其统治者）都渴望，尽可能占领整个世界以获取持久的和平。但是自然的愿望恰好相反。自然用两种办法，即语言和宗教的不同，来分离国家并阻止它们合并。 [14]这些当然可能制造双方的敌意，为战争提供条件；但是，随着文化的发展，人类逐渐地转向原则上的一致，他们有了相互的理解及和平。与吞噬了所有人的能量和埋葬了自由的暴政不同，这种和平是由力量的均衡与最激烈的较量所缔造和保障的。

3.因此，大自然智慧地将国家分开，尽管每个国家的愿望，依据国际权利的论点，是采用武力或是计谋将其他国家统一在其麾下。另一方面，大自然也通过国家之间的共同利益将它们联合起来。商业精神迟早会支配并抓住每个民族，而这不能与战争共存。在所有可以利用的国家权力（或者手段）中，财政权力是最可以依靠的。因此，国家发现它们不得不推动高尚的和平事业，尽管不是出于道德的动机。当世界上有战争爆发的威胁时，国家会试图通过调停避免它，仿佛它们已经为了这个目的而进入永久的同盟一样。依据事物的自然规律，大的军事联盟很难形成，也更难取得成功。

这样，大自然通过人类意愿自身的机制确保永久和平。虽然我们不能从理论上预言未来，但获得永久和平的可能性足以成为务实的目标。大自然赋予我们责任去努力实现这一目标，而这并非一个空洞的幻想。

补充条款二：论永久和平的秘密条款

在处理关于公权利的事务时，有一个秘密条款（客观地看或者是从其内容上看）是矛盾的。主观上说，例如，对于记述这一条款的人而言，一个条款可能正好包含一个秘密要素，因为这个人会认为公开地宣称自己为条款的创立者有损个人尊严。

这类条款的唯一条目包含在下列句子中：“哲学家们关于公共和平条件的论述，应当被那些武装起来准备战争的国家引为忠告。”

在与其他国家关系的原则问题上向臣民们（哲学家）寻求指导，这对于一个国家的司法机关似乎有些耻辱，因为我们必须自然地将最高级别的智慧归功于司法机关；但是，我们仍然强烈建议这样做。国家因此悄悄寻求哲学家们的帮助，并使之成为一个秘密。换句话说，这将允许他们公开而自由地评说关于战争和维和的准则。如果没有人禁止他们的讨论，他们的确会主动这么做。国家间没有特别、正式地安排让他们同意这样做，因为这样的协议已经包含在人类作为道德的立法者所承担的义务中。然而，这并不意味着国家必须承认哲学家的原则优于法学家的声明（法学家代表的是国家的权力），只是哲学家应当有解释其思想的机会。将权利的天平和公平之剑作为其象征的法学家常常使用后者，不仅仅是为了免除外来影响对前者的作用，而且也会在天平的一只托盘不下沉时把剑扔在它上面（被征服的人惨了）。除非法学家同时也是哲学家，就道德层面而言，他有强烈的愿望这么做，因为他的工作仅仅是执行现有法律，而不是探寻这些法律是否需要改进。法学家的表现仿佛他的这一低级学科实际上是高级学科一样，原因很简单，因为这里面伴随着权力（其他的两个学科也是如此）。但是哲学在众多学科组成的权力层中占据非常低的位置。因此，我们被告知，哲学是神学的女仆，与其他学科的关系也相似，诸如此类的话。但是这个女仆是在她仁慈的主人前面高擎火炬还是在其身后托着裙裾还远不清楚。

人们并不期待国王会哲学化或者哲学家将成为国王，这也不是他们想要的，因为拥有权力毫无疑问地会破坏理智的自由评判。国王们或者是主权国家的人民（例如，那些用主张人人平等的法律进行自治的人们）不应当迫使哲学家们消失或者是保持沉默，而是应当允许他们公开发表见解。让阳光照亮他们，这一点至关重要。哲学家一族天生就是不会形成恶意的团伙或俱乐部，他们不会有传播叛乱舆论的嫌疑。

附录

一、关于永久和平，道德与政治的不一致

道德，作为我们行为应当遵守的、具有约束力法则的集合，从客观的角度来说，基本上属于实践的范畴。如果我们曾经知晓责任这一概念的影响力，那么说我们不能遵守道德法则就是荒唐的。因为如果是这样的话，责任的概念就会自动地失去道德（没有人被迫做他没有能力做的事）。因此，作为权利应用分支的政治和作为权利理论分支的道德之间不会有矛盾（也就是，在理论与实践之间）。这样的矛盾只会在道德被用作权宜之计时才会发生，例如，某人选取最有用的手段牟取一己之私利，这无异于否认道德的存在。

如果政治说，“你要像蛇一样狡猾”，道德就会加上“像鸽子一样无害”。如果这两条规范不能在同一诫条中并存，那么政治与道德之间确实存在着不一致。但是如果要统一两者，再假定它们的对立就是荒唐的，此种矛盾如何解决的问题，甚至不能拿来做思考练习。“诚实是最好的政策”的格言包含着一个与现实常常相反的理论，这是事实。然而，另一个理论命题“诚实胜过任何政策”超越了所有的反对意见，它的确是任何政策不可分割的条件。道德的上帝不会向暴力的监护人朱庇特投降，因为朱庇特也要听从命运的安排。简而言之，理智还没有获得充分的启蒙，不能发现那一系列已经确定的因素，这些因素会允许它准确地预测人类活动可喜或可悲的结局。它只会希望结果与愿望相符。但是，理智总是清晰地告诉我们，如何做才能行走在责任的轨道上，正如智慧规则所要求的那样，给我们指明达到最终目标的道路。

但是，对其而言道德是纯理论的实干家冷漠拒绝我们的善意的愿望，即使他承认我们能做我们应当做的事。他将其论点建立在如此断言之上，即从人性的角度我们能够事先断言，人类永远不会做必要的事以便达到永久和平的目标。所有遵循自由原则，生活在一个符合法律的框架内（全体意志的个别统一）的个体，对于达到这个目的还不够，这是千真万确的。在这个如此困难的问题解决之前，所有人必须一起渴望达到这个目标，只有这样公民社会才能作为一个整体存在。由于在一个共同的愿望出现之前，一个特别的统一的事业必须能够统一所有个体的不同愿望，因为没有一个个体能够创造这样一个事业，实践中唯一的一种执行意愿的办法、一个开创国家权利的途径就是武力。在武力的一致权威之下，公权利最终得到保障。

我们事先当然期望实际的经验与原始的理论观点将会存在不小的偏差。因为我们不能假设立法者的道德观点是这样的，即无序的民众在统一成为一个民族后，立法者会让他们依据自己的公共意愿创造一个符合法律的体制。

或许可以这样说，一旦一个人自己手上掌握了权力，他就不会让人们给他立法。同样道理，一个自治的、不受外部法律约束的国家也不会让自身依赖于其他国家的评判；甚至于整个大洲，如果感觉自身比另一个大洲优越，它就会毫不犹豫地扩展自己的地盘，不管另一个国家是否挡了自己的路，它也要统治那个国家。这样，理论为政治的、国际的或者世界公民权利所设计的所有计划演变成了空洞和不切实际的想法。但是，基于人性原则的实践可以希望为其政治机会主义体系找到一个坚实的基础。

当然，如果既没有自由又没有基于自由的道德法则，只有当一切发生了或者能够发生的事简单遵循自然的机械的工作机制，政治才是利用自然治理人的艺术。这构成了实践的智慧的整体。那么，权利的概念仅仅是一个空洞的想法。但是，如果我们认为非常有必要将权利的概念与政治结合，或者甚至使权利成为政治的限制条件，那就必须承认这两者相互兼容。我也的确可以想象一个讲道德的政治家，例如，某人将政治权宜之计的原则运用完美使其与道德共存；但是我难以想象一个政治的道德家，例如，一个人运用其道德规则去适应作为政治家的优势。

道德的政治家会遵循这样的原则：如果在国家关系中或是在政治体制中犯了不可避免的错误，国家元首有义务尽可能迅速地改正错误。应当确认这些政治制度是为确保自然权利——它在实践理性的观念中是树立在我们面前的一个模型——而建立的，甚至于必须牺牲自我的利益。与所有政治权宜之计背道而驰的原则是：在没有一个更好的体制取而代之的情况下破坏现有政治或世界公民的联盟。在这种情况下，这一原则与道德一致。尽管要求立刻用暴力的手段修订宪法中的错误是荒谬的，但是要求当权者警醒并向正确方向改进依然是必要的，这是为宪法能够不断地接近权利法律所规定的最佳状态。即使一个国家现有宪法规定的是一个专制的统治政权，它也可以用共和的方式自治。这个国家将逐渐地到达一个阶段，人民会受到法律权威思想的影响，如同国家有着武力作为支撑一样，人民将能够创造一种基于权利的司法体系。然而，如果一个更合法的体制是通过不合法的方式获得的，例如，由于以前糟糕的体制导致了暴力革命而建立起来的，即使采用暴力或者叛变破坏旧宪法的每个人在革命过程中应当得到处罚，也不允许带领人民恢复原来的状态。但是，关于国家间的外部关系，即使国家是专制的体制（因此在与外敌的关系中处于强势），只要这个国家随时有可能被其他国家吞并，则该国家不得被要求废弃其体制；因此，在必须有政治改进计划的同时，也要允许等待一个更好的时机执行这个计划。 [15]

可能出现这样的情况：专制的道德学家，例如，那些在实践中犯了错误，屡屡有悖于政治的深谋远虑，采纳或者推荐不成熟的措施，经验必然会将他们逐渐带出与自然对立的状态，使他们采纳更好的办法。但是，道德化的政治家试图掩盖有悖于权利的政治原则，以人性没有能力获得理性所认定的一个理念为借口。他们因此使进步成为不可能，使对权利的侵犯永久化。

这些老于世故的政治家没有采纳他们所吹嘘的正确的实践，而是固守着令人厌恶的把戏，因为他们仅仅是为了剥削人民（倘若可能的话就剥削整个世界），通过用这种方式影响当权者以确保其一己之私利。他们就像进军政治的律师一样（例如，对这些人而言，法律是一份职业，不是立法的事情）。他们的职责不是探讨立法本身，而是遵循当前法律的指引，他们总是认为现有的法律构成最好，因为它遵循一个合适的机械的秩序。但是，这种技能或许给他们一种幻觉：他们也能够根据权利的概念（先验而非经验的）判断任何政治体制的原则。他们或许吹嘘说他们了解人们（因为他们不得不与许多人相处，这也是意料之中的），尽管他们不了解人及其潜能，因为这要求站在更高的人类学制高点上。

他们继续依据理性所规定的政治法和国际法行事，用诸如此类的概念武装头脑。但是他们只能在欺骗的状态下走这一步，因为他们会遵循一贯的程序，用机械的方式运用在专制统治下形成的强制性法律，甚至在理性观念只考虑合法强制的领域，与自由的原则相一致。这一自由的原则自身就可以使公正建立的政治体制成为可能。这位实践者相信他能实地解决这个问题，忽略理性的观念，从迄今为止仍然幸存的那些体制（很大程度上是不合法的）的结构中获得经验。尽管没有公开，但是他为着这个目的遵循了一些准则，这些准则可以粗略地表述为如下的诡辩术。

1.先做然后解释这样做的理由。抓住任何国家自身享有或者是对邻国人民享有的侵犯权利的有利机会，正当的理由可以更容易、更简洁地提出。这比事先想出说服的理由，然后等待出现反驳的理由来得更现成，而使用暴力的事实可以更轻而易举地掩盖过去。这在第一个案例中尤其显得正确。国家的最高权力机构也是立法机构，必须无可争议地服从。这样鲁莽行事本身呈现出的是内在的信念，即这种行为是正确与公正的。成功之神就是最好的支持者。

2.倘若你是暴君，否认这一点。例如，如果你犯了罪，为了诱导你的人民走向绝望进而造反，否认你有罪。反过来，坚持这是对方不妥协造成的；或者如果你掌控了对相邻民族的控制权，就说人性应当对此负责，因为如果他不先于其他人付诸暴力，他或许会确信这些人将先行动并压制他。

3.离间和统治。如果在选择你作为其统治者的人群中有一些特权者，确保离间他们，并且让他们与人民产生对立。如果你用虚假的承诺给他们以更大的自由，一切将依靠你的绝对意愿。如果你为了同外国打交道，在它们中间制造纷争是一个接一个征服它们行之有效的方法，而这表面看起来是为弱者提供帮助。

必须承认，没有人会被这些政治准则所蒙蔽，因为它们人所共知。人们不会为这些准则而感到羞耻，仿佛它们的不公平都太过显而易见。因为执掌大权者从不为公众如何评价他们而感到尴尬，只会在意对彼此的评价。关于上面列举的那些原则，即使它们为公众所知，掌权者也不会感到羞耻。只有当他们失败时才会感到羞耻，因为他们都认同这些准则的道德地位。他们拥有政治荣誉。如果他们采用想要采用的办法扩充权力， [16]他们总能依靠这些准则。人们如何在国家好战的本性中创造和平，从所有这些不道德、机会主义的信条的迂回曲折中，至少这些是清楚的：人们很少能像在私人领域那样在公共领域逃避权利的概念，他们也不敢公开地将政治仅仅依托在机会主义的机理中，从而全然拒绝遵守公权利的概念（这一点在国际权利中特别显著）。相反，他们给这些概念所有的荣耀，尽管他们或许也找出一百条理由和诡计在实践中逃避它们，并假装承认唯有残酷的暴力和诡计能够获得政权，而政权是所有权利的来源，也是凝聚权力的纽带。

为了结束这种诡辩术（它掩盖了事实上的不公平），也为了让那些制造假象却又发号施令的人承认，是他们在宣传权势而不是权利（他们用的是发号施令者的口气），发现永久和平产生的最终原则是好的，由此能使人们对自我或者是对别人看法的幻影破灭。应当表明，所有挡在永久和平之路上的魔鬼源自这样的事实，即政治道德家的出发点正是道德政治家的中止点。他（政治道德家）因此视目的第一，原则第二（即原则服从于目的，例如，如同把马车放在马之前），因此，挫败了他自己想使政治和道德协调一致的目的。

为确保实践哲学自身的一致性，首先有必要解决一个问题，即在实践理性的问题上，我们是否应当从它的实体原则出发，也就是，作为一个意志对象的目的，或者还是应当从它的形式原则，即人们在外部关系上的自由出发。后一种原则表述为“用这样的方式行动，就是你能够希望你的信条成为一个宇宙法则（不管最终的结果是什么）”。

后一项原则必须毫无疑问地占据领先地位。作为权利的一项原则，它有绝对的必要性。只有当允许目的实现的经验主义的条件假定存在时，前者是有必要的。如果这个目的也同永久和平的目标一样是一项义务的话，那它自身应当从引导外在行为的准则之形式上的原则中产生。现在前者（也就是，实体的）的原则是政治道德家的原则，它把政治的、国际的、世界公民的权利问题仅仅当作技术任务处理。但是后者的（也就是，形式的）原则却是讲道德的政治家的原则，是一个道德任务。道德任务与技术问题在带来永久和平方面完全不同。永久和平值得拥有，不仅因为它有现实的好处，还因为它是出于人的责任意识而必须发生的事态。

对于第一个（政治权宜之计的问题）问题的解答，需要更多自然的知识，以便人们运用其运行机制实现想要达到的目的。然而，以其对永久和平的影响而言，无论涉及公权利三部分中的哪一部分，所有这些并不确定。在长时间内很好地维持人民的顺从和成功是靠严格的纪律约束，还是靠满足他们的虚荣心；是给每一个体或者是几位领袖以最大权力，还是通过设立贵族办公室或者是受人欢迎的内部政府，历史提供了各种各样效果相反的例子。共和制是唯一的例外，它只能是一位讲道德的政治家的目标。基于大臣们草拟的法律的一项国际权利的情形就更具有不确定性，因为这项权利实际上仅仅是空洞的文字，因为它是依靠含有秘密保留条款的条约，而这些秘密条款是可以被违背的。另一方面，第二个问题，即政治智慧的问题，仿佛自动地解决了一样。显而易见，它战胜了所有的诡计，直达目标，只要我们牢记，它不可能通过暴力的、鲁莽的方式实现，必须在有利机会到来之时稳步地实现。

我们或许因此可以提出如下的建议：首先寻求纯粹实践理性的王国及其正当性，你的目标（永久和平的保佑）将会添加给你们。对道德而言，关于它的公权利的原则（因此涉及一个可推断的政治准则）有一个特别的特点，即越少将行为绑定想要达到的目的（不管是物质的还是道德的优势），它就越多地与目标相协调一致。其中的缘由正是公众的愿望，在一个人群或者由各色人等组成的共同关系中，决定人群中什么是对的。但是，这个所有人意愿的组合，倘若用一种持续的方式付诸实践，它也能成为导致目的结果的动因，并对权利概念产生影响。例如，一个民族应当以自由、平等作为权利的唯一核心，这是道德政治的一个原则。这个原则不是基于权宜之计而是出于义务。另一方面，政治的道德家们不值得聆听，不管他们如何争论进入社会的一群人的自然技巧或者声称这一技巧会使上面的原则无效，从而阻碍其实施，或者试图用古代和现代的糟糕体制证明他们的观点（例如，没有代表制度的民主政体）。这样的理论特别具有破坏性，因为他们可能自身制造出他们所预测的那个魔鬼。由于把人类与其他有生命的机体归为一类，他们仅仅需要清醒地认识到，他们不是自由生物，就能成为他们眼中所有地球生物中最可怜的那一类。

“即使世界上所有的流氓都必须死亡也要让正义当政”的名言听上去有些夸张，但它是真实的。这是一项明智的权利原则，它堵塞了狡诈或者暴力的邪恶之路。但是，不能把这误解为，例如，这是一种允许人们以最严苛的态度运用自己权利（这与伦理义务相冲突）的许诺，而应当把它看作是当权者不能拒绝的职责，或者是出于对他人的怜悯或厌恶而剥夺的权利。这就要求国家应当有一部依据权利原则制定的宪法。它统一其他邻国甚至是更遥远的国度，就其分歧达成一个合法的解决方案，从而形成类似一个统一的世界性国家的实体。这一主张只是意味着无论结果如何，政治信条不能被因信奉这些信条而逐渐增长的利益或幸福的前景所影响，例如，每个国家把政治智慧看作最高经验原则。它们应当仅仅被正确职责的纯粹概念所影响，例如，被一种基于纯粹的理性演绎原则而产生的职责所影响。如果这世界上鲜有坏人，世界的末日也不会到来。道德上的魔鬼天生就有自我毁灭和自相矛盾的遗传特性（特别是在有类似头脑的人们的关系中），因此善的道德准则有出路，尽管这种进步是缓慢的。

因此，从客观或者是理论的角度而言，道德与政治之间没有冲突。从主观的角度说（也就是，关于自私的性情，由于其不是建立在理性的格言的基础上，因此它不能被称作实践），这个冲突将会也应当保持活跃，因为它扮演着美德磨刀石的角色。依据“你不能对麻烦投降，要更加大胆地挑战它”的原则，美德的真正勇气在于必须面对我们自身的邪恶并战胜它的诡计，而不在于坚定地对抗魔鬼并且作出牺牲。这个原则太过危险、太过背信弃义，因为它易于利用人性的弱点为侵犯正义的行为作辩解。

政治的道德家或许确实可以说，统治者和人民之间，或者一个民族和另一个民族之间，即使因为暴力或者狡诈陷入冲突状态也不会彼此不公平地对待，尽管他们完全不公平地拒绝尊重权利的概念，而权利概念是唯一能够建立永久和平的。如果一方侵犯了另一方的利益，而这另一方恰好在无法无天地针对他，那么确实发生在他们身上、使双方耗尽力量的事就是完全公正的。他们的民族将得以生存并继续不间断地延续这一过程，一直到最遥远的未来，于是，后代人可以把他们当作警示的榜样，以此为戒。这样安排世界事务的天意成为理所当然。人类的道德准则从来就不会泯灭。依据这个原则运用权利想法的理性，随着文化的不断进步而不断增强，与此同时，侵权的负罪感随之增加。如果我们假设人类永远不能或不愿达到更好的状态，地球创造出如此一个道德败坏的种类这样一个事实，是任何神义论都无法解释的。但是，这样一种判断对我们来说还是太得意了。我们理论上不能把智慧的构想归于我们无法理解其特性的最高权力。

如果我们不假设权利的纯粹原则具有客观现实性，也就是，这些原则不能够应用于实践，我们会不自觉地得出这样的结论。不管经验主义政治会如何唱反调，一国的人民，连同相关的国家必须相应地照此行事。因此，一个真正的政治体制如果不首先对道德表示敬意就会寸步难行。政治本身是一门颇具难度的艺术，因为没有其他艺术要求与道德结合。一旦道德与政治产生冲突，道德就会解开政治无法解开的结。

人的权利必须被看作是神圣的，不管统治者可能会作出怎样巨大的牺牲。这里没有折衷的办法。开发混合的办法，诸如介于权利和实用之间、附条件的权利，毫无用处。所有政治家在权利面前必须屈膝跪倒，尽管政治或许希望到达一个持久辉煌的阶段作为回报，无论这一过程多么缓慢。

第二部分　依据公权利的先验概念论政治与道德的一致性

如果从法理学家通常定义的公权利考虑，我从其物质方面摘录要点（如同一个国家内人们之间各种各样的经验关系或者是国家间彼此的关系），我得到的是公共性的正式属性。由于每次要求权利都潜在地拥有这种属性，没有这种属性就不会有正义（这种正义会被设想为是众所周知的），也不会有权利，因为权利只会来自正义。

权利的每次诉求都必须具有这一公共品质。由于能够轻易评判权利诉求是否以某种特殊的情况呈现，也就是，是否能与相关行为人的原则相结合，它提供给我们一个现成、可见的现象，能够在理性中发现推论。如果它不能与行为人的原则协调一致，我们立刻看出这一诉求的错误（也就是，不正当性），像是纯粹理性的一个实验。

我们在政治和国际权利的概念中提取了所有经验主义的成分之后（包括人性中导致高压政治的罪恶一面），我们可以列举如下公权利的“先验规则”的主张：影响他人权利的所有行为都是错误的，假如其准则不能与公开的准则相一致。

这一原则不仅仅应当被看作是伦理上的（也就是，属于美德理论），而且应当被看作是法理上的（也就是，影响到人权）。一个我没有挫败感就不能公开宣布的准则，一个要成功就要不惜一切代价保密的准则，一个我一旦公开宣布就会不可避免地引起抵触的准则，只会引发这种必然、普遍的对我的反对，因为它本身是非正义的，因此对每个人都构成威胁。除此之外，这纯粹是一个消极的测试，例如，它只是测试什么是不正确的一种手段。如同任何功利一样，它不证自明，此外，它也非常容易运用，这一点在下面关于公权利的例子中可以看到。

1.在一个国家的内部权利中，或许有一个许多人认为难以回答的问题，尽管运用公开性的先验原理能轻而易举地解决这个问题。表述如下：“一个民族用反叛来推翻所谓暴君的强权统治是不是一个正确的方法？”人民的权利被侵犯了，毫无疑问，如果暴君被罢黜的话，他就没有受到不公正的待遇。然而，如果臣民用这种方式寻求他们的权利，那就是大错特错了。如果他们在后来的冲突中被击败，继而不得不忍受最残酷的惩罚，那么他们就不能有一丝一毫对于不公正的抱怨。

如果我们试图用权利原则的教条推论解决这个问题，对于这种做法赞成和反对意见的争论能有很多种说法。但是权利问题公开性的先验原则能够绕开这种冗长的讨论。依据这一原则，在缔结公民契约之前，人们会问是否胆敢在特定场合下将反叛的意图公之于众。显而易见，如果针对一国的首脑最终使用暴力，这成为建立一个政治实体的条件的话，人民应当宣布有权统治其统治者。但是，如果是这样的话，统治者就不会是统治者了；或者作为建立国家的先决条件，双方都被授予权力，那么，国家自身的存在就成为不可能，这也是人民的愿望。如果反叛依据的准则众所周知，它会战胜自身的目的，不会成功。这一准则因此不得不保密。从这个事实看，反叛的非正义性因此显现。

但是，对于一国之主而言隐藏其意图是没有必要的。他或许会公开说将惩罚任何反叛行为，把元凶处死，尽管人们相信这一国之主自己才是第一个违反基本法的人。如果他意识到自己掌控着不可抗拒的最高权力（任何市民宪法都必须以此为前提，因为一名统治者如果没有足够的权力，无法保护他的每一个子民，令他们不受伤害，那么这位统治者也无权对人民发号施令），他不必担心如果其准则人人皆知，自己就无法达到目的。如果人民反叛成功，一国之主便成为臣民；但是如果他开始一轮新的反叛以夺回王位，那其行为是不正当的，他也不必害怕承担其在位时应承担的责任。

2.我们现在谈谈国际权利。我们只有在假设一些法律条件存在的基础上谈及国际权利，例如，赋予一个人某项权利是因为外部环境许可。作为公权利的一种形式，就定义而言，它预示着一种普遍的愿望，这种愿望公开地分给每一个个体，这是他应有的权利。这个法理状态一定来自某种契约，与一个国家如何起源不同，一个必须不能依据强制性的法律，但是在很大程度上呈现一种永久的、自由的联合状态，如同上面所提及不同国家的联盟。如果没有某种法定条件，积极地将各种各样物理上或者道德上的人联系在一起，权利唯一可能的形式是私密的。这里又一次牵扯到了政治与道德的冲突（后者以权利理论的形式出现）。在相关准则中，公开性的标准又一次得以轻松适用，条件是合约的单一目的是在缔约国之间及其有关他国之间维护和平，决不考虑军事占领。我们因此面对政治和道德的自相矛盾，以及与其相应的解决办法。

（a）如果这些国家中的一个国家向另一个国家承诺了什么，不管是提供协助、割让部分国土、提供救助或者是其他类似行为，当其自身利益处于危险之中时，是否可以不承担信守承诺的责任？它应当被看作是双面人：一方面，作为一国之君主，他不对国土内任何人负责；另一方面，仅仅作为最高政治官员，他又对国家负责。这样得出的结论是国家（或者是其统治者）可以免于承担责任。但是，如果一个国家的统治者想要让人知道这是他的行为准则，其他人会自然远离他，或者是团结其他国家以对抗他的主张。这证明，这样的政治体系，尽管极其狡诈，如果在公开的基础上运作会打败其自身的目的，因此上述的准则一定是错误的。

（b）如果一个邻国成长到一定规模而引起其他国家的不安，人们能假定说，因为它能够压迫其他国家了，所以它就会希望压迫其他国家吗？尽管还没有冒犯的行为发生，这是否给予了弱势一方积蓄准备进攻它的力量的权利？如果一个国家公诸天下，称其遵循这一准则，它一定只会更快地招致魔鬼的到来。因为强权者能够先于弱者行动，弱者或许可以联合，而这种联合，对于知道如何运用分而治之策略的国家而言，只是不堪一击的苇草。因此，这种政治利己的准则，倘若公之于众，就不会实现自己的目的，这就证明这个准则是不正义的。

（c）如果一个小国，就其地理位置而言，地处一个大国的领土之内，而这个大国需要这片领土为己所用，那么，这个大国吞并这个小国就是合理的吗？很容易看到，大国无论如何不能让人知道它遵循这样的准则。因为，一来那些小国会适时联合，二来其他大国会对此举争论不休，使这个计划一经公开就不可实行。这是不正义的表现。事实上，这是非常严重的不正义，因为，对象的弱小并不意味着对它采取的不正义行为就不严重。

3.至于世界公民的权利问题，我这里就悄悄略过了，因为与国际权利的准则相比，它的准则容易形成，也容易评定。国际权利的准则或许与公共性不匹配，我们因此能够得出一个好的判断：（就权利的理论而言）政治和道德并不一致。我们也应当有必要知道与国际权利相一致的准则是什么。我们不能简单地得出结论说所有公开的准则就是正义的，因为有决定权的人没有必要隐藏其准则。任何国际权利实现的前提是一个法制国家的存在，因为没有国家的存在就没有公权利。在国家之外存在的权利，例如，处于原始状态的权利，则仅仅是私权利。现在我们从以上论述已经看到，为减少战争而建立的国家联盟是唯一合法的安排，是能够与自由相一致的。政治与道德只有在一个联盟中才能相一致，因此，建立一个联盟是有必要的，并且应当给予优先地位，这点已经由权利原则说明了。所有政治精明的正确的基础就是以尽可能全面的形式建立这样一个联盟。因为没有这个目标，所有的推论都是不智慧且蒙着面纱的所谓的正义。这种虚伪的政治有其诡辩术，堪与虚伪狡诈的学者们相媲美。它包括思想上的保留，因此公共契约的形成是这样的：人们可以根据自己的需要诠释这些契约（例如，在事实的现状和权利的现状之间作出区别）。这也包括盖然论，也就是，它试图把罪恶的企图栽赃给他国，或者是用他国获得统治地位的可能性作为破坏其他和平国家的合法理由。最后，它还有哲学之罪的原则，即如果一个大得多的国家在这个过程中获得了所谓的世界普遍利益的话，那么，霸占一个小国就可以被看作是一件可以原谅的小事。 [17]

所有这些都与政治的复杂性及其与道德的关系相关，政治总是利用道德的分支以期达到目的。但是博爱和尊重人权这两个方面是义务。博爱仅仅是一个有条件的义务，而尊重人权则是无条件、绝对势在必行的。任何一个人，如果他希望体验正义行为的甜蜜感觉，就必须首先完全确信他没有侵犯人权。政治能轻易地向道德妥协，因为两者都要求人们放弃他们的权利而屈从统治者。但是当轮到讲道德时（也就是，权利理论），道德要求政治应当积极地顺从它，而政治发现不被任何合约所限制更可取，从而倾向于不承认权利理论有任何实际价值，并且将所有责任减化为仅仅是善意的行为。这种政治体系的神秘花招能够轻易地被打败，如果哲学将其准则公之于众，它会允许哲学家公开他们自己的准则吗？

我现在呈现另一个先验的、积极的公权利原则。它可以表述如下：“所有要求公开的准则，如果想要实现自己的目的，就既能够与政治也能够与权利协调一致。”

如果他们只能通过公开才能达到目的，那么他们必须遵循公众的目标，即幸福。政治的特殊任务是与公众的目标相和谐。但是，倘若这个目标的实现仅仅是通过公开（例如，分解对所采纳的准则的不信任）就能达到，那么遭到质疑的准则也必须同公权利谐调一致，因为只有在这个权利范围内才能满足每个人的需要。然而，我必须等待另一个场合对这一原则进行进一步解释和讨论。我们已经看到，如果一个人抽掉与幸福相联系的所有条件，例如，法律的实质，而单单看到普遍的有法律状态的形式，那么这是一个先验的公式。

如果在现实中实现公权利是一项义务（通过一个不确定的渐进过程），如果也有坚实的基础希望我们将会成功，那么，永久和平终将取代迄今为止被错误地称作和平条约的想法将不再只是空想。相反，随着解决的办法被逐渐找到，这个任务也在不断地向完成迈进，因为我们可以希望达到同样程度的进步所需要的时间会越来越短。

回答“人类是否在持续地改进”问题的新尝试

1　我们在寻求什么样的知识？

我们所寻求的是人类历史的一部分。然而，它不是一部过去的历史，而是一部未来的历史，即一部预见性的历史。但是，如果它不是可知的自然法则（如同可预知的自然法则，如日食和月食一样），只能通过超自然的发现才能获得。它必须是可占卜或先知的历史。 [18]除此之外，我们这里不考虑人类的自然史（我们应当问，是否有新的种族会在未来的时间里出现），而是人类的文明史。我们不是研究具体的人类的概念，而是整个的人类，以种族分布，以尘世的社团相聚。所有这些都表明，我们在问人类作为一个整体是否正不断地进步。

2　我们如何能获得这样的知识？

我们能够通过描述这些事件获得对于事物预示性、历史性的描述。这些事件的推论预示它们实际上会发生。但是怎么才能先验地有一个历史推论呢？答案是如果先知本身导致和制造了他所预示的事件，这是可能的。

犹太先知预测他们的国家迟早会面临衰退和完全的解体。他们是自身命运的建造者。作为人民的领袖，他们将如此繁重的负担载入宪法，以至于他们的国家就其自身权利而言变得不适合生存，特别是在与其邻国的关系中。因此，祭祀的哀歌自然没有人听，因为这些雷同的牧师固执地坚持他们自己在宪法中创造的信条，以便他们自己能够万无一失地、确定地预知结果。

我们的政治家的表现完全一样。随着他们影响力的扩大，他们在其教区越来越成功。人们必须接受他们的现状。他们告诉我们，事实并不像世界上消息闭塞的学究或者是好性情的幻想家想象的那样。但是，他们应当被解读为我们用不公平的胁迫、用政府所擅长的奸诈的诡计使他们变成了现在的样子。他们不妥协并且倾向于造反，如果约束稍稍松弛一些的话，就会有令人遗憾的结果发生。这样，聪明的预言家的使命就完成了。

各种各样的占卜也不时地预示着宗教的完全衰退、反基督者的立刻出现，他们做着最精确地测算到的事情为的是创造自己所描述的事态。因为他们并不关心教区的道德准则，而道德准则是能够直接引发进步的。取而代之的是，他们把历史信仰作为中心任务，假设这些会间接地产生同样的结果。尽管他们或许引致机械的遵从，但是他们不能制造道德观念的一致。因此，这些牧师们开始抱怨他们自己制造的对宗教的漠视。这是他们不需要预言的特殊天赋就能够预料到的。

3　我们希望了解的未来概念的划分

我们的预言可能有三种形式：与其他的生物种类相联系，在其当前的道德水准上（即如同不停地围绕一个固定点旋转），人类或者是不断地倒退和衰退，或者是不断地进步和改进，或者处于一种永久的静止状态。

第一种情况可以定为道德恐怖主义。第二种情况是快乐说（如果人类进步的目标已经远观可见的话，这种情况可以定为千年至福说）。第三种情况可以被称作阿布德里主义。因为后一种情况，由于普遍的静止在道德事件中是不可能的，在无休止的流动中并不能产生更多的效果，如果其主体在一个地方保持静止不动的话。

a.人类历史的恐怖主义概念

人类退化的过程不可能无限期地继续，因为人类在达到一定的节点后会就会灭亡。结果是当滔天罪行不断地积累又积累，由此产生的恶持续增加时，我们说，“不能变得更糟了”。这时候，似乎审判的日子就到了。虔诚的狂热者已经梦想着一切的重生。当前一个世界被一把火烧掉之时，一个崭新的世界就此诞生。

b.人类历史的快乐概念

我们或许很容易同意这样的观点，善和恶的总量能够保持不变，在任何一个个体中也不会增加亦不会减少。一个人善的品质如何增加？这只能通过其自身的作用，在他能够这样做之前，他首先需要储存更多的善才行。毕竟，没有任何效应能超出其生效因素的制约。人的善必须因此保持在一定水平之下，与其相混合的恶的水平相协调，以便人类不能超越一个限度而做进一步的改进。因此，快乐说，怀揣着快乐的希望，看上去不堪一击。它的人类不断进步和改进的想法对于人类可预见的历史似乎没有什么用处。

c.人类阿布德里主义的假设作为未来历史的定义

这一观点可能有众多的拥护者。沿着“善”的道路快速前行却又不能坚持走下去，相反，他们会修订进步的计划，不惜一切代价避免被一个单一的目标所束缚（甚至仅仅出于渴望变化）。建设为的是破坏。担负起从山下滚石上山的任务，仅仅是为了让石头再滚下来。这就是我们种族的因勤奋导致的愚蠢行为。综上所述，人类自然特征中恶与善的融合是彼此中和的过程，结果是单调乏味的（或者是静止，如同下面要谈到的）。这种前进和后退的空洞运动，伴随着罪与善的不断交替，意味着我们地球上的成员们的互动应当仅仅被看作是一场闹剧。以理性的眼光看，这并不能带给人类更高的价值，其他动物种类的互动代价更小，并且是无意识的。

4　进步的问题不能直接由经验解决

尽管人们发现，人类作为一个整体在一个不确定的长时间内前进和进步，就我们种族的身体特点而言，没有人能够保证其衰退的时代在特殊时刻没有开始。与此相反，如果它加速地衰退，那么我们就没有理由放弃希望，希望我们正要达到一个转折点，凭借我们种族的道德特点，我们的事情将向好的方向转变。我们与自由行动的生物打交道，他们能够事先预测应该做什么，但是不能预测他们实际上将会做什么，谁有能力做，如果事情变坏了，他们因自身的行动蒙受了罪恶，他们认为这些罪恶是改进的强大动力。正如埃贝·阔亚所说：“可怜的人类！你们中间没有什么是永恒的，只有反复无常。”

或许因为我们已经选择了错误的观点来思考人类事务的过程，后者对我们来说如此的荒唐。从地球上看，星球有时候向前运动，有时候向后运动，有时保持静止不动。但是从太阳上看，从理性的角度考虑，它们如同哥白尼猜想所说持续地沿着惯常的轨道运行。然而，有些并不缺乏智慧的思想家喜欢坚持自己对事物的解释，坚持他们最初的观点，甚至甘愿冒着将自身陷入地谷圆和周转圆的荒唐境地。然而，这是我们的不幸，我们在试图预测自由运动时不能采取一种极端的观点。在所有人类智慧之上是上帝的旨意，其效力甚至扩展到使人类的行动获得自由。尽管人们或许能看到后者，却不能准确地预测未来（在神的眼中这一差别不存在），因为在其预测任何事情之前，在需要获得被自然法则掌控的一个关联时，在处理未来的自由行动时，必须在没有暗示和指导的情况下进行。

如果有可能给人类有限的、天生的、不变的善，我们当然能够预测人类的普遍进步，因为这包含着人类自己能控制的事。但是，如果人类的自然属性中就有不明比例的善与恶，便没有人能够知道自身的行动会带来什么后果。

5　人类的预言史必须始于某种经验

在人类事务中，必然存在着一些经验或者其他的东西。一个实际发生的事件或许显示人类具有自我改善的素质和力量（因为其行动应当有自由）。但是，只有当帮助这一事件产生的情形出现时，这一事件才能被预测为一个现存原因的结果。总的来说，这些情形一定在某一时间会出现（如同计算游戏机会的可能性），这是可以预料的，但是不可能确定此事是否在我的人生中出现，我是否会经历此事，因此就不能够证实原始的判断。

我们因此必须寻找一个事件，它能显示这样一个原因的存在。这个原因在人类中漫不经心地活跃着，也不管何时会发生作用。它或许会使我们得出这样的结论：作为其活动的一个不可避免的结果，人类正在作出改进。这个推论能扩展到以前的历史，以便展示人类一直是在进步；用这种方式，被选作一个事例的这一事件本身不会被看作是过去进步的原因，只会被看作是历史的印记。它或许用来证实人类这一整体存在的趋势，不是一系列的个体（因为这样会导致没完没了的列举和计算），而是散布在地球上的国家和种族群体。

6　发生在我们时代的能证实人类道德倾向的事件

讨论的事件不包括任何这些人类的重大行为或过错。这些行为或过错以前很大，在他们的眼中微不足道；甚或是以前很小但在他们的眼中变得很重大。这些事件导致古老的、显赫一时的国家像中了魔咒一般消失了，而其他的国家则从地球深处崛起取代了它们的地位。不，与这些毫无关系。我们这里考虑的仅仅是在重大政治事件发生时旁观者在公众场合的态度。因为他们公开地对事件参与者的一方表示无私的同情，甚至冒着他们的偏心会给自身带来很大不利的风险。他们的反应表明人类作为一个整体分享着一些共同特征，它同时表明，（因为它的无私性）人类拥有其道德特征，或者至少是在制造道德特征。这不仅仅允许我们期盼人类的进步，其本身就是一种进步，其影响力对当前也是很大的。

我们看到的发生在我们这个时代的由智慧的人民所组成的民族正发起的革命，它可能成功，也可能失败。革命可能充满了悲惨和残暴以至于一个思维正常的人不敢付出如此代价作同样的尝试，即使他期望作第二次的尝试时会获得成功。

但是我认为，这种革命在所有没有赶上它的观众心中燃起渴望，引起没有参加者的同情，尽管表达这种同情的口号充满着危险。因此，除了人类的道德性情之外，不可能有其他什么能够引起这种同情心了。

这里起作用的道德原因由两个因素构成。其一，每个人都有权给自己建立一个自己认为合适的公民体制，不受其他力量的影响。其二，人们能够拥有的、唯一本质上正确的、道德上良好的体制的出现是为了避免侵略战争（例如，惟一可能的宪法是共和制宪法，至少就其概念而言）。 [19]服从于这些条款并由此杜绝战争这一造成灾难和道德腐化的源头，就不仅是一个目标，而且也是一项义务了。倘若这一目的得到承认，人类，由于其脆弱性，就有了一个被动的保障。它将逐渐地改进，或者至少它不会在进步的过程中受到干扰。

所有这些，连同人们拥抱美德的激情与热情，（尽管不能为激情鼓掌，因为所有如此的激情是该受到指责的），给下面的主张以历史性的支持。这一主张具有人类学的意义。真正的热情总是单纯指向理想，特别是指向纯道德（例如，权利的概念），它不会掺杂着自私的利益。金钱上的奖赏不能激励革命志士的激情和灵魂的强大，而权利的概念本身就可以激励他们，甚至旧的军事贵族的荣誉概念在革命军面前也不值一提。他们 [20]属于人民，将全部热情倾注在人民的权利上，并自视为人民的保护者。因此，身处局外的旁观者对他们的兴奋报以同情，但没有丝毫的意图积极参与他们的事务。

7　人类的预言史

在这些原则中，一定存在着某种道德的东西，理性认为它不仅纯粹而且（因为其伟大而划时代的影响）人类的灵魂将之视为一种责任。再有，它视人类为一个完完全全的人的联盟（不是个体，而是人类作为一个整体），因为他们为普遍、无私的同情必将获得成功而欢欣鼓舞，并不遗余力地促使其成功。

然而，正谈及的这个事不是革命的现象，而是（正如埃尔哈特所说）被自然权利所规定的宪法的演变。这样的一部宪法不能通过激烈的斗争获得，因为内外战争将会毁灭迄今为止一切的法定秩序；但是，它会引领我们为了一个不好战的宪法而奋斗，例如，一个共和宪法。人们所渴望的国家的实际形式可能是共和制，或者它可能只是在治理模式上是共和制的。而国家可能被一个单一的统治者（君主）依法统治，依据一个民族根据普遍的权利原则制定的法律执政。

即使没有预言家的头脑，我现在也坚持认为自己能够通过我们这个时代的方方面面和种种迹象预测人类将会达到这个目的，它将一步步地进步而不会退步。发生在人类历史上的这种现象是不会被忘记的，因为它显示了人性中一种改进的天赋和力量。这种改进是没有哪一个政治家能够通过研究过去的事件想出来的。只有天性和自由，结合权利的原则才能够使我们预测这些。但是事件发生的确切时间必须是不确定的，要看机会。

但是，即使我们所描述事件的预想目的不能在目前情况下实现，或者一个民族的革命或宪法性改革最终失败了，或者如果宪法性改革持续了一段时间，一切将回复其原来的状态（正如政治家现在所预言的那样），我们自身的哲学预言将不会失去其力量。因为发生的事件太重大了，与人类的利益又紧密相连，其广泛影响遍及世界的各个国家，当适宜条件允许的情况下，各个民族都会尝试做同样的事情。由于它是人类一个如此重大的关切，所设想的宪法必定在某个时刻最终达到稳定的程度，不断重复的经验将会植入每个人的心田。

因此，人类总是在进步并将继续以同样方式发展这一命题，这不仅仅是一个为了实际目的而推出的美好说法。无论不信服者说些什么，它都能在最严格的理论论证中站得住脚。如果一个人不仅考虑可能发生在一个特定国家的事件，而且考虑该事件给地球上可能逐渐参与其中的所有民族带来的影响，那么，一幅远景图就向着无边的未来展开了。当然，这不会是真的。如果自然改变的第一个时代在人类出现之前（根据卡姆帕与布鲁门巴赫所说的）淹没了动物和植物王国的话，那么，随之而来的第二个时代给予人类同样的待遇，以便其他生物可能占领这个舞台，诸如此类。对于全能的自然或者不如说与其难以理解的最高原因相比，人是微不足道的。但是，如果人类的统治者视人为微不足道，并且这样对待他，要么像对待牲畜一样对待他，或者是将其用作达到自己目的的工具，或者是为他设下圈套让他在争斗中厮杀，残害他的同胞，这就不仅仅是一件小事，而是对创造天地的终极目的背叛。

8　针对世界不断进步的准则公开性方面的困难

普遍的启蒙是对于公众就其所属国家的权利和义务的公开指导。由于这只涉及自然权利，以及能够从公众意识中产生的权利，权利的倡导者和诠释者不是国家指定的官员，而是权利教师，也就是，哲学家。后者（权利教师），鉴于他们给予自己的充分自由，是国家的绊脚石，它唯一的愿望是统治；他们因此被授予了启蒙者的称号，被看作是对国家的威胁。然而，他们并不用熟稔的口吻对人民（人民对他们及其作品并不太注意），但是用尊敬的口吻对国家，请求国家把人民的合理需求放在心上。如果一个民族希望诉说自己的疾苦，这样做的唯一办法就是公开性。因此，在关于自然权利的诉求问题上，哪怕仅仅涉及它最低限度的要求，禁止公开将阻碍一个民族的进步。

被某个民族的合法措施所隐瞒的另一件事（这是足够明显的）是宪法的真正属性。对大不列颠的人民说他们生活在绝对君主制下是对其尊严的一种冒犯。据说，其宪法通过两院限制君王的意愿。两院代表的是人民的利益。然而，每个人都清楚地知道君王对这些代表的影响如此之大、如此之万无一失，以至于前面提到的两院根本不作决定，除了殿下所希望和通过大臣们推荐的决定除外。后者不时地推出决定，知道并且确实确认其决定涉及矛盾问题（例如奴隶买卖的废除），仅仅为了证明议会的虚假自由。但是，这种方法暗藏着不鼓励人民寻求真正的、正确的宪法的效果，因为他们以为已经从发生在面前的事例中发现了宪法。因此，一个虚假形式的公开性用君主制受到法律限制 [21]的假象欺骗人们，与此同时那些用贿赂赢得的代表秘密地将他们置于一个君主的统治之下。

所有形式的国家都是基于宪法思想建立的。宪法的思想与人的自然权利相一致，因此，那些遵守法律的人也应当与立法者步调一致。如果我们从纯粹理性的角度思考共同体，它可能被称作是不切合实际的理想。这个不切合实际的理想是想象的、空洞的、虚构的事物，是所有市民宪法的外在现象，是停止所有战争的一种手段。建立在此种思想之上并用自由的法律治理的公民社会是实践的一个范例。它只会通过一个费力的过程，并且经过无数次的战争和冲突才会实现。宪法，一旦作为一个整体获得通过，是最有权威阻止战争的，也是所有美好事物的摧毁者。因此，缔造这样一部宪法是我们的责任。与此同时，创立宪法将是一个相当长的过程。君王有责任采取共和的方式治理国家，尽管他们或许会采取独裁统治。换句话说，他们应当依据自由法律的精神对待人民，一个成熟理智的民族会给自己开这样的处方，尽管这些法律在表面上并未征得人民的同意。

9　人类从不断的改进中得到什么益处？

随着人类的前行，其积蓄的好处利益并不是不断增长的道德能量。其态度的合法性将产生不断增长的基于责任的行动，不管这些行动背后的动机是什么。换言之，益处将源自人们更多、更成功的善行，也就是，源自人们道德品质的外在现象。因为我们只有依赖经验数据（我们的经验），而我们的推测依据的是经验数据。也就是说，我们推测的依据是行动的物质上的起因，而不是包含什么应该发生的责任概念的道德动机。道德动机能够由纯粹的推断性思维的过程所决定。

当权者会越来越少地使用暴力，而越来越多地遵从法律。毫无疑问，一个共同体内部在司法行动中会有更多的仁慈，更少的争吵，更多的对信守承诺的信任等等，部分原因是对荣誉的热爱，部分原因是对一个人长处的深刻认识。这最终会延伸到不同人之间的外部关系上，直至一个世界公民社会的建立。然而，这样的进步并不意味着人类道德能力有丝毫的增加，因为这会要求一种新的创造或者超自然的影响。我们不应该对人类不断改进的过程期望太高。我们应当鄙视那些把人民希望进步的愿望看成是头脑过热的政治家。 [22]

10　对于进步遵从的顺序，我们期待的是什么？

答案是：不是通常的从下而上，而是从上而下的顺序。

期待在知识和道德文化中教育年轻人，并佐之以宗教教义，先通过家庭指导，然后是由低级到高级的一系列的学校教育，最终不仅把他们变成了合格公民，而且使他们成长为能够不断持续行善的人，这样的计划极少能获得期望的成功。一方面，人们相信教育孩子的费用不应当由他们出，而应当由国家担负。另一方面，国家（正如比兴哀叹的）又没有钱支付给合格的老师，使他们满怀激情地履行职责，因为国家需要把全部的钱用于战争。除此之外，上面所述教育的整个体制将会崩溃，除非它是依据深思熟虑的计划和国家最高权力的意图所设计的，然后不断维持统一的行动。这就意味着国家也要不时改革自己，寻求改革而不是革命，这样才能不断地进步。但是那些掌管教育者也是人，他们自己也应接受过良好的教育。从人性的脆弱和能够强化其效果的角度看，我们能够期望人类对于进步的希望只有在一个更高智慧的积极条件下才能够实现（我们是看不见的，这叫天佑）。在人类能够完成的一切事务的范围内，或者说可以期待的任何事情，只能通过他们被动的智慧达到目的。在后一种情况下，他们发现他们被迫确保战争的发生，这是道德的最大障碍，进步的始终不变的敌人，首先渐渐变得更加慈善，然后更加不频繁，最后作为侵略的模式而完全消失。他们将进入基于权利基本原则的宪法时代，其特征即为不需要伪装其力量而又有能力不断进步和改进。

结论

一个医生天天都安慰病人，希望他们尽快康复，告诉这个病人他的脉搏好多了，那个病人他的粪便或者是分泌物有了很大改善，等等。这个医生的一个朋友有一天来访，医生的第一个问题是：“你怎么样？我的朋友！你的病怎么样了？”他的朋友回答：“你觉着呢，单单是康复就整得我半死了！”

如果政治上的灾难使得他开始对人类的福利和进步失望，我不会指责他。但是，我对休谟提到的药物抱有信心，因为它应当能够加速病人的痊愈。他说：“当我现在看到卷入战争的各个民族时，就仿佛目睹了两个醉汉在一家瓷器店相互攻击。因为不仅仅是他们彼此造成的伤害需要很长时间康复，他们还必须赔偿造成的所有损失（弗里吉亚人学习智慧太晚了）。”但是当前战争的痛楚将迫使政治预言家们承认，人类必须很快转向更好的方向，而这个转机已经在眼前。

关于人类历史开端的猜想

为了填补历史纪录的空白，在历史纪录叙述的过程中，在各种各样的切入点引入猜想当然是允许的。因为这些空白之前和之后有什么，也就是，较为遥远的原因和相对的后果，能够使我们有合理的自信发现其过程中的原因，因此，进行可以使人理解的干涉。但是，仅仅依靠猜想完成一个历史性的描述比为一部小说草拟出一个计划也强不了多少。的确，这样一种历史记述不能被看作是猜想的历史，仅仅只能被看作是虚构的作品。然而，在涉及那段历史的起点时，自以为是地介绍人类行动的历史也是允许的，因为如果开始是一个自然的产品，它或许可以用猜想的方法获得发现。换言之，这可以不通过创造，而可以从经验中推断，假设历史之初所经历的与现在所经历的相差无几，也谈不上什么不妥。人性中关于自由的最初的发展历史与其后来的发展历史确有不同，因此，必须只依据历史纪录。

然而，猜想不应当提出不恰当的要求，要求我们对其表示赞同。正相反，他们不应当将猜想看作严肃的活动示人，而应当仅仅作为一种练习。这种以理性作支撑的想象或许是一种健康的脑力活动。结果是，这些猜想不能与那些历史描述相提并论。历史描述是对同一事件的记录，这些经过事物检验的记录与出自自然哲学的东西大相径庭。由于这个原因，又由于我要踏上的旅程仅仅是一场愉快之旅，我或许会希望获得一个神圣的文件作为我的地图，同时预测这个插上了想象翅膀的旅程。尽管没有理智的经验的指引，我也将准确地遵循与神圣的历史记录相同的轨迹。读者将把这个文件放在面前，可能会每一步都参照它，看看哲学家在概念的帮助下遵循的路径是否与《圣经》故事所描述的一致。

如果我们不沉湎于漫无边际的猜想，我们必须从人类理智难以推断出的自然原因入手，即人类的存在入手。这些人类也必须完完全全是成熟的，因为他们没有母亲的养育。他们必须是一对夫妻，这样他们才能够繁衍后代。除此之外，必须是只有一对夫妻，以免这些人是陌生人但彼此接近时发生战争，以免大自然被指责已经遭遇失败，因为它允许来自祖先的后代采取最适当的方法促进社会性，这是人类使命的最终目的。毫无疑问，出自同一个家庭的所有人类的共同后代才是达到这一目的的最好办法。然后，我把这对夫妻放在一个免受野生动物袭击，而大自然提供了一切生存的条件的地方，比如，一个气候温和的花园中。还有，我想象他们并没有处在最原始的状态，而是处在有技巧地使用其自身力量的相当的进化阶段。如果我试图填补这个有相当长时间的鸿沟的话，读者或许会发现太多的推测、太少的可能性。第一人类可以站立和行走。他可以说话， [23]的确能说话，也就是，在有条理的概念的帮助下说话，最终思考。这些都是他必须为自己着想要获得的技能（如果技能是特有的，也是能继承的，这与经验不一样）。我假设他已经拥有了这些技能，因为我希望仅仅从道德的角度考虑人类行为的发展。这有必要假设他们已经拥有了这些技能。

最初，新来者必须完全依靠本能的指引，即所有动物都听从上帝的命令：允许其享用某些东西，如食物，但是同时禁止他使用其他的东西（《创世纪》，III，2-3）。然而，这也没有必要假定某种特别的本能已经失去。它可能只是嗅觉和味觉器官，还有存在于后者和消化器官之间的某种通感。换句话说，是一种时至今日仍明显存在的能力，即事先能够意识到一种食物是否适合食用的能力。我们甚至不用假定这种感知在第一对夫妻身上比现在的人更敏锐，因为众所周知，只运用感知的人的感知能力与那些还进行思考的人差别巨大，后者对自身的感知较少注意。

只要缺乏经验的人遵循自然的召唤，他就是幸福的。但是，理性很快会让人感到它的存在，并且寻求超越本能的界限扩大食物的知识。它通过比较平时饮食和不同于本能的、在属性上却相似的官能，例如视觉感受（《创世纪》，III，6），做到了这一点。即使本能没有建议做这些，这个实验也有成功的可能，只要本能没有与之背道而驰。但是，正是理性的特性使得理性在想象力的帮助下能够产生欲望，这欲望不仅缺乏相应的自然的推动力，而且与后者不一致。这种欲望，被认为是淫荡，渐渐地造成一整套多余的、甚至是不自然的淫荡倾向。最初想摒弃这种自然冲动的倾向或许很微弱。但是第一次实验的结果是具有重大意义的，人类开始意识到其理性的存在，这种天赋可以超越所有动物所受的限制。这对人类的生活方式起着决定性的作用。这或许只是一种果子，因为它与他之前品尝到的那些果子看上去相似，这鼓励着他去尝试。或许还有一个动物的例子，尽管某种食物对人类有相反或是有害的影响，这种食物对这种动物有着天然的对抗。然而，这给了理性最初的诱导，让它与自然的命令相对抗（《创世纪》，III，1），尽管这遭到自然的反对，但是自由地选择做尝试，又因为尝试是第一次，或许并不能获得期望的结果。不管伤害多么微小，它已足够让人们的眼界大开（《创世纪》，III，7）。他发现了自身选择生活道路的一种能力，不必像其他动物一样被某种生存方式所束缚。但是，实现这种优势的短暂快感瞬间被他应当如何运用新发现的能力所引起的焦虑和恐惧所替代，因为他不知道这隐藏的财富或者其长远的影响是什么。跟以前一样，他站在了一个悬崖的边缘。本能指引他得到所渴望得到的每个物体，现在众多的物体展现在面前，他还不知道如何在它们中间作出选择。现在既然他已经尝到了自由的滋味，再让他回到本能支配的状态已经不可能了。

大自然给予每个个体的本能除了对食物的本能以外还有性的本能。大自然通过性的本能确保每种生物的生存。一旦理性觉醒，它在这一领域的影响也会被感受到。男人们很快发现性的驱动力对动物来说仅仅是阶段性的，而对他们来说不仅可以延长，甚至可以由于想象力的作用而变得更为兴奋。尽管想象力的对象离感觉越远，它发挥的作用就越小，但是它更加频繁地起作用，从而避免纯粹的动物欲望得到满足之后所产生的厌倦感。无花果树叶与其说是发展的第一个阶段的佐证，不如说是更加强大的理性的产物。因为将物体撤离感官以制造一种更加紧密和长久的趋势本身已经显示了对于冲动的某种理性的控制，这不像在理性第一阶段那样仅仅是一种能力，多多少少地听从冲动的摆布。拒绝是一种办法。它是理想主义的助推器：它展现了从纯粹的动物欲望发展成爱情的过程，也展现了从单纯是惬意的感觉到对美的欣赏（最初只限于对人本身的美的欣赏，后来也包括欣赏大自然的美）。进一步来说，人类作为一个有道德的生物发展的第一个动力是他的彬彬有礼，他通过礼仪赢得其他人的尊重（例如，藏起一切可能引起蔑视的举动），也作为所有社交的适宜的基础。像这样一个小小的开端，对于开启思想的新方向具有划时代意义的效果，这比随后的、一系列的文化发展更为重要。

理性在介入人基本的、立即感受到的需求之后，它所采取的第三个步骤反映在对未来的预测上。这一能力不仅仅是享受现在的生活，而且是看到未来——常常是不久的将来。这是人类优势最具决定性的证据。因为具有了这种预见性，人类能够为长远的目标做好准备。但是由于这同样的能力，当它预见到不确定性时，会产生最无穷无尽的担心和焦虑。这一点所有其他动物都不必承受（《创世纪》，III，13-19）。那些需要供养自己、妻子、和未来的孩子的男人们预料到了他们工作的负担。女人们预料到了大自然给她们的性别添加上的辛苦（生养孩子），还有更有权势的丈夫们要其承受的困苦。男女两性都理解并预料到了，在辛劳工作一生的尽头，在这幅图画的背景中，所有动物都需要面临却并不被关注的命运，即死亡。他们仿佛谴责自己，把用理智给自己带来的所有病痛看作是一种罪过。或许他们唯一的安慰和保证是在后代身上延续。他们后代的命运或许好于他们，或许作为一个家庭的成员，能够消除父母们的痛苦（《创世纪》，III，16—20）。

理智走的第四步也是最后一步，是把人类提升到了高于动物世界的境地，即理性意识到人是大自然真正的目的，地球上没有谁能够在这一点上与其抗衡。当他第一次对着羊群说“你身上的羊毛是大自然给你的，但不是给你用的，而是给我的”，然后他剥下羊皮穿在自己身上（《创世纪》，III，21），他意识到凭借人性他比所有的动物都享有优先权。他现在不再把这些动物看成是同胞了，而把它们看作是他达到目的的手段和工具。这一动向表明，对如下区别的认识，即人不能像对待动物一样对待其他的人，而应当把他们看作能够平分大自然礼物的人。这就作了一个铺垫，为理性在对待同胞时强加在人类意愿中的种种限制作个铺垫。这种铺垫对建立一个社会更重要，比爱情和天生的倾向更重要。

因此，人类与所有理性的生物享有平等的地位，不管他们处于什么等级，因为他可以宣称自己就是目的，也让别人接受他，不被其他生物用作达到其目的的工具。这不能仅仅被看作是满足种种倾向的一个手段，是人与更高级生物无条件平等的基础。因为即使更高级生物在天赋上无可比拟地比他优越，他们也没有权利随心所欲地利用他。结果是，这个理智的第四步就是人类从自然的子宫中释放出来。这种地位上的改变毫无疑问地带给他荣耀，与此同时也带来了危险。因为这种改变把他从无害的、安全的童年的保护花园中赶出来扔到了广阔的世界上。这个花园不需要他做什么而给他提供了一切，而在这个世界上则有那么多的忧虑、劳作和未知的魔鬼在静候着他。在未来，生活的艰辛将唤起他对伊甸园的向往，在那里他可以在安静和永久和平的环境中做梦或者虚度光阴。但是，焦躁不安的理性无法抗拒地驱使他发展天生的能力，它站在他和想象中天赐的福祉中间，不让他回到粗野的简单的状态中去（《创世纪》，III，24）。理性要求他耐心听命于他所厌恶的劳作，完成他所鄙视的琐事，甚至忘记对死亡的恐惧进而喜欢所有那些琐事，并害怕失去它们。

注解

从对人类最早的历史记述中可以得出如下的结论：人类从伊甸园——这个人类理性的第一个家园——中出现是人类从粗鲁、纯粹的动物状态过渡到人类的状态，从本能主导的状态到理性主导的状态，一言以蔽之，从自然庇护的状态到自由的状态。当我们考虑人类的目的地时，他通过这样的变化使有所失还是有所得不再是一个问题，而是相当简单地通向完美的进步过程。不管他的第一次尝试有多少缺点，即使他们被允许作一系列进一步的尝试，当这一事业代表的是整个种群由坏到好的进程，而就个体而言，情况却不是这样。在理性觉醒之前，没有禁忌和戒条，因此，触犯禁忌也是不可能的。但是，当理性不顾其自身的弱小开始起作用，不遗余力地与兽性发生激烈冲突之时，罪恶可能因而产生。更为糟糕的是，随着理性的增长，灾难出现了；这些灾难与幼稚天真的状态完全不同。因此，从道德的角度说，这个国家的第一步是一种衰退。从自然的角度来说，这种衰退是一种惩罚，因为它导致了迄今为止许多不为人知的罪恶的出现。然而，自然的历史始于善，因为这是上帝的作品；但是，自由的历史始于恶，因为这是人类的作品。对于只看个人自由的行使的个体而言，这样的转变代表的是失去。对于关注种群结果的大自然，它代表的是获得。因此，个体有理由为自己忍受的所有苦难和所犯的所有罪行而责怪自己。但是与此同时，作为人类种群的一个成员，他有理由敬佩并且赞扬这个总体安排的智慧与目的性。这样才有可能相互和解，并且有理由使常常遭到误解、显然自相矛盾的让·雅克·卢梭的主张相互协调。在其论文《关于科学的影响》和《关于人的不平等》中，他相当正确地展示了在文化和人类种族之间存在着不可避免的矛盾。人类每个个体是要完成各自使命的。在他的《爱弥儿》《社会契约论》和其他作品中，卢梭试图逐一地解决更加困难的问题，例如，文化应当采取什么样的动因才能确保人的能力适当地发展，才能确保与他们的目标保持一致，以便这个道德的目标不再与他作为自然种类的特性相矛盾。因为文化或许还没有真正地开始，更不要说完善了。它的发展与人作为人类和公民真正的教化原则相一致，上述矛盾是压迫人类生活的所有罪恶的来源，是使人类蒙羞的一切罪恶的来源。 [24]与此同时，那些被指责为恶行的原因的冲动本身是善的，是在发挥自然赋予的能力。但是，因为这些能力是适应于自然状态的，它们随着文化的发展受到了削弱，它们自身又削弱了文化，直到艺术达到完美，又一次成为自然为止，而这是人类道德命运的最高目标。

历史的终结

下面的一个阶段，人类开始从休闲和平时代转向到劳作不和谐时代，这成为社会整合的前奏。这里我们必须制造另一个飞跃，突然地让人类拥有家禽和庄稼，让他们能够为了繁衍而播种（《创世纪》，IV，2）。事实上，从野蛮的狩猎生活到田园生活，从挖树根摘野果到第二阶段的农耕状态，这个过程也可能是逐渐发生的。正是在这时，矛盾不可避免地出现在了那些一直和平共处的人们中间，结果是这些生活方式不一样的人们分开并分布到了全世界。田园生活不仅悠闲而且在人烟稀少的国度里，动物们也不缺乏草料。农业或者说种庄稼需要相当的劳作，而且因恶劣天气的影响而没有保障。农业也要求定居，拥有土地，要有足够的力量保护土地。然而，牧民们厌恶这样的财产权，因为这限制了他们放牧的自由。由于农业的这些特点，农民或许嫉妒牧民，认为牧民受到上帝的宠爱（《创世纪》，IV，4）。但是，事实上牧民给农民造成了诸多不便，只要牧民在邻里活动，吃草的动物也不会放过农民的庄稼。牧民很容易地赶着他的动物逃走，从而避免为造成的损失支付任何赔偿，因为他什么也没有留下，他能轻易地在另一个地方找到他所需要的。因此，农民毫无疑问地不得不采用武力避免受到侵犯，而他的对手并不认为侵入是非法的。由于如此的侵入不能完全得到杜绝，毫无疑问，他最终被迫尽可能地远离那些过着放牧生活的人们，除非他希望失去长时间辛勤努力的成果（《创世纪》，IV，16）。这种农民与牧民的分离标志着第三阶段的开始。

当人们依靠耕种土地谋生时（特别是种植树木），他们需要永久的住处，而保护这些财产免于被侵占需要一大群人相互帮助。因此，采取这种生活方式的人就不能分散居住，而是聚集在一起建立的村庄里（这被不太确切地称为城镇），以便保护他们的财产免遭野蛮的狩猎者或者游牧部落的破坏。生活模式的变化使得交换成为第一需要（《创世纪》，IV，20）。这使得文化和艺术起源不仅仅是一种消磨时光的手段，而且是一种职业（《创世纪》，21f）。但是首先这也意味着需要采取步骤建立一个市民宪法以及公开地监管公平。最初，这些事情毫无疑问仅仅关注大的暴力行为。而惩罚这种行为的权利现在不再像野蛮时代那样留给个人解决，而是指定给了一个能够服务并团结大众的合法政府，也就是，这样的一个政府，其本身不受暴力的统治（《创世纪》，IV，23f）。从这些最初的原始的开端开始，所有人类的天资现在渐渐地发展了，其中最为有益的是社会性和公众安全。人类能够繁衍，像蜂巢里的蜜蜂一样繁殖，从中心向各个方向输送经过文明教化的殖民者。这个时期还见证了人类不平等的开始；人类的不平等是种种罪恶之源，也是种种善行之源。此后不平等继续加深。

只要信奉上帝为主人的诺曼底的牧民继续成群地围着受一个人类主人或者公民权力的统治（《创世纪》，IV，4） [25]的城市居民和农民打转，并且宣称自己是所有土地拥有者的敌人，不友好地对待后者，同时也被后者憎恨，那么，这两者之间就会不停地陷入战争，或者至少是存在战争的危险。但是，作为敌对状态的一个结果，两国至少享受着内部自由这一无价财产（因为，即便是在现在，战争的危险也是唯一防止独裁统治的办法，因为一个国家必须有财富才会强大，没有自由就不能进行财富产生活动。一个穷国会用大量的努力来保持公共财富以补偿财富的缺乏，除非这个国家意识到这种努力只能够由人们自由创造，否则也是不可能的）。然而，随着时间的推移，城市居民的奢侈不断增长，特别是城市妇女充满诱惑力的艺术超过了原野上粗野的通奸，对于牧民一定是一个强大的诱惑，使他们与城市妇女建立关系，并使他们加入到城镇生活的悲惨中（《创世纪》，IV，2）。这两个以前敌对人群的最终融合结束了战争的危险，但是，也终结了自由。一方面，这导致了强大的暴政的毁灭，因为文化对于那些毫无灵魂的奢侈和最为卑鄙的奴隶制只是刚刚开始，并且掺杂着不文明国家的不道德行为。另一方面，人类也偏离了大自然为其设定好的事业，即不断培养自己向善的能力。人类的目标是统治地球而不是过着沉溺于粗鲁和奴役的生活，因此，这种状态根本与人类不匹配（《创世纪》，IV，17）。

结束语

善于思考的人们会感到不适，这种不适甚至可能导致道德沦丧。对于那些不思考的人来说，他们对这种不适全然不知。这种不适是因为考虑不周引起的，即对天意的不满，而作为一个整体世界的进程是由天意主宰的。当他们思考着如此严重压制人类的罪恶时，他们感受到了一种毫无希望改进的情绪。然而，最为重要的是我们应当对天意感到满足，尽管天意给我们在地球上铺就的道路是艰辛的。我们应当对天意感到满足，一方面为了让我们即使身处困难之中仍然具有勇气，一方面为了不让我们去责怪这些罪恶，从而也不让我们看到对罪恶应负的责任，因而失去提高自己以补救罪恶的机会。

我们不得不承认，压迫文明民族的最大罪恶是战争，不是过去或者现在的实际战争，而是不断增长的对未来战争的准备。国家的所有资源，所有应当用于进一步增进文化发展的成果都被用于为这一目的服务。自由在很多地区蒙难，国家本应当对于其每个成员进行母亲般的照料，却被粗暴的苛政所取代（尽管这种苛政是以害怕外部的危险为理由）。但是如果对战争的实时恐惧不能迫使一国之君表现出对人性的尊重的话，那么我们会达到现在的文明程度吗？会形成为了增进人们的福利而出现一个共同体内不同的社会阶层之间密切合作的局面吗？我们是不是仍遭遇同样的人们，遭遇即使有很严格的法律仍依然存在的那种程度的自由吗？我们只需要看看中国就明了了。中国的地理位置偶尔将其暴露在难以预料的侵入中，却不会让其受到一个强大的敌人所攻击。我们看到，由于这个原因，中国哪怕一点点的自由都被剥夺了。只要人类文明仍然保持在现阶段，战争就是使其发展的一个不可避免的手段。只有当文明达到其完全发展阶段——只有上帝知道这个阶段何时到来——永久的和平才能够实现并且惠及我们。与此相联，我们当然也只有为那些我们如此痛恨的罪恶而责怪自己。《圣经》相当公正地承认，如果在各民族间的文化还未融合之际，将各国融合为一个社会，使其能从外部危险中彻底解放，那么这样做只会阻碍文明的进一步发展，使社会衰退到不可补救的腐败中。

人类对大自然规律的另一个不满是生命的短暂。的确，任何一个人，如果不停地希望生命或许比它实际的长度要长，那他一定不欣赏生命的价值，因为延长生命仅仅是增加了由无休止的挣扎所组成的一部戏剧的长度。然而，我们或许应该原谅那些恐惧死亡而又不热爱生命的天真的看法，那些连每天对生存感到某种程度的满意都困难的人，却又总是对重复这一痛苦经历的日子过不够的人。但是如果我们停下来想一想寻求如何度过如此短暂一生的办法所受到的所有关照，还有强加在仅仅持续很短的一段时间的享乐之上的所有不公平，那么我们因此有理由得出结论说八百年或者更长的生命时长对我们没有好处。父亲们生活在害怕儿子的恐惧中；弟兄们生活在害怕弟兄的恐惧中；朋友们生活在害怕朋友们的恐惧中。如此长寿的一个种族可能达到这样的境地，它的命运不会好，倒不如让一场全球性的水灾将他们冲离地球（《创世纪》VI，12f）。

第三个愿望是回忆诗歌中高度赞扬的那一个黄金时代（这个愿望实际上是一个空洞的渴望，因为这个目标不会实现）。在那样的时代里，我们假定从所有想象的需求中解脱，我们满足于大自然提供的必需品，人与人之间有着完全的平等和永久的和平。一句话，有一种纯粹的无忧无虑的生活享受，在懒散的梦境和孩童般的天真玩耍中挥霍时间。这种渴望使得鲁宾逊·克鲁索的奇遇和南海各岛之行如此的富有魅力。但是，广义上说，它们是种表象，即善于思索的人们在愉悦中寻求价值时所感受到的文明生活的疲惫，还有一旦理智提醒他们应当通过行动给生命以意义的时候，则他们会退回到慵懒状态。这种渴望回归简单和无知的过去的愿望，其空虚和无聊已经在前面对于人类原始状态的描述中得到展现。我们看到人类不可能一直保持这种状态，因为这种状态不会使他满足。一旦离开这种状态，他就不会回去。结果是他必须继续将他现在的条件和困难归因于自己和自己的选择。

对于人类历史的描述对人有益，倘若这历史中有下面的内容，这也将指导和改进他的行为：这历史必须告诉他不要为压迫他的罪恶而责怪上苍，并且他没有权利把自己的错误归咎于前辈；例如，指责前辈把犯同样错误传递给了后代，因为没有什么武断的行动是可以遗传的。这部历史应当展示给他的是，他有理由感谢其先辈，并且对错误地运用理智而犯下的罪恶负责，因为他完全有能力意识到在同等条件下他会有同样的表现，并且他第一次运用理智会犯错误（即使大自然建议他不要那样做）。一旦关于道德罪恶的这一点得到正确理解，客观存在的罪恶就很难破坏成就与错误相互权衡的这一平衡。

因此，在哲学的帮助下，从描述人类最早历史的尝试中可以得出如下结论：我们应当对上帝和其对人类事务的整体安排感到满意。这个事业并不是始于善，然后走向恶，而是逐渐地由坏发展到更好。大自然感召每一个人尽其所能对这一进步的历程作出贡献。

[1]我今天（9月30日）在比兴9月13日的《每周消息》（Wöchentliche Nachrichten）上读到关于这个月《柏林月评》（Berlinische Monatsschrift）的一个通告。通告提到雅科布·路德维希·费利克斯·门德尔松·巴托尔迪（德国犹太裔作曲家——译者注）对我已经回答的同一个问题的回答。我还没有看到这本杂志，否则的话我会犹豫是否发表上述看法。我只想让他们发现两个个体的想法会碰巧一致。

[2]一个可继承的王国并不是一个可以被另一个国家继承的国家。只有统治这个国家的权力可以遗赠给另一个人。在这种情况下，国家需要一个统治者，但是这样的一个统治者（也就是，一个已经有另一个王国的人）并不拥有这个国家。

[3]迄今为止，人们仍在怀疑除了禁止性法律和劝诫性法律之外是否还有许可性法律。因为所有法律都包含一个客观的、实践中可行的因素作为某种行动的理由，而一个许可只靠实际的偶发事件。因此，一个许可性法律是强制某事，但这件事无法强迫人去做，如果这种法律的对象与许可的对象一致，那么矛盾就出现了。但是，上面第二条提到的许可性法律，最初的禁止仅适用于未来要求权利的模式（例如，继承），而禁止的例外情况（也就是，法律的许可性部分）适用于国家的政治财产。依据以自然权利为基础的许可性法律，当前的国家可以被许可保持平稳即使自然状态已经被公民社会所取代。即使当前的财产是不合法的，他们也是诚实的。一旦推定的财产被认定为推定的，则此财产是被禁止的，不仅在自然状态中而且在公民社会中也是如此（如果财物的状态是推定的）。如果是在公民社会中，继续占有是不被允许的，假定的占有物一旦被发现是非法占有，则必须立刻停止占有，因为这是一种侵权行为。
我这里的意图仅仅只是简要地向自然权利的鼓吹者指出许可性法律的概念。这个概念在理性的系统性分工中自动地展现了自己。它特别值得一提，因为它时常被用在国内法和成文法中，有一个不同就是法律中禁止的部分独立地存在，许可性部分作为限制性条件不包括法律条文本身，而是在附加的条款中以囊括个案。这样的法律通常表述为这个或那个是被禁止的，除非是在个案一、二、三以至无穷。许可性条款仅仅偶然地加在法律中，并不依据任何确定的原则，而是通过对某个个案的回顾附加到法律上。否则，限制性条款只得包括在禁止性法律中，它由此可能成为许可性条款。因此，那个由智慧而思路清晰的绅士温狄史格里兹伯爵提出的精巧但尚未解决的竞赛问题很快被放弃真是一种遗憾，因为它可能解决我们现在讨论的司法困境。找到一个像数学公式一样的世界性模式的可能性是对立法的一致性的真正考验。没有它，所谓的确切的法律必然仅仅是一个善良的愿望。否则，我们只能有一般的法（例如，在一般情况下有效的法），但是却没有普遍的法（即普遍有效的法律），而普遍的法这一概念是一部法律要求具有的。

[4]一般的假定是一个人不能对另一个人采取敌对性行为，除非他已经被他人伤害。如果双方都是在一个合法的公民状态时，这是完全正确的。一个人已经进入了这样一种状态，就给另一个人提供了保障，因为双方都服从同一个权威。但是，人（或者一个民族）在一个纯粹自然的状态中让我感觉不到这种安全。他和我共存的这种状态伤害了我。他或许没有主动地（事实上）伤害我，但是，他处于无法律约束的状态伤害了我，因为他对我是一种永久的威胁。我能够要求他或者与我一起进入一个共同的法治状态，或者离开我。下面所列条款依据的假设是所有相互影响的人必须遵循某种市民宪法。但是任何宪法，就生活在其下的人们而言，将归属于下面三种类型：
（1）依据一国内个人的公民权利的宪法； （2）依据国家间相互关系的国际权利的宪法； （3）依据世界性公民权利的宪法，个体和国家在一个相互影响的关系中共存，他们或许被看作是一个世界性国家的公民。这个分类，谈及永久和平的想法，并非随心所欲，而是必然的。即使一方能够影响另一方，而他自己却保持一种自然状态，这就会有战争危险。这正是上述条款所要禁止的。

[5]正当的（例如，外部的）自由，不能像通常所想的那样，定义为一个想做什么就做什么的授权令，除非它意味着对他人做不公平的事。授权令意味着什么？它意味着以某种方式行事的可能性，只要这种举动不会对别人造成不公平。因此，授权令的定义可以表述如下：自由是行动的可能性，其行动不会给他人造成不公平。也就是说，我们不做对别人不公平的事（不管我们实际上会做什么）。然而，这个定义是一个空洞的赘述。事实上，我的外部的、正当的自由应当被定义为一个授权令，除非我自己同意，否则我不遵守任何外部的法律。同样，一个国家内的外部的、正当的平等是公民之间没有人能够将他人置于法律责任之下而自己同时不被置于相同的法律责任之下（我们不需要界定司法依赖的原则，因为它总是隐含在一个政治性宪法的概念之中）。这些与生俱来、不可分割的权利的有效性，人类必然的属性，被一个原则所确认和强化，即人可能与更高层次的生物产生法律关系（如果他相信有后者的话）。因为他或许认为自己是先验世界的一个公民，同样的原则也适用于这个世界。至于我的自由，我甚至不承担神法规定给我的任何义务（我只能靠理性识别它们），除非我自己能够对它们表示我的同意，因为我能形成神法的观念也是基于自己理性的自由法则。至于我能想象到的、与最高贵的生物相联系的平等的原则，除上帝之外，如果我和这一高等生物都在我们自己的岗位上履行我们的职责，为什么是我有责任遵守法律而他享受命令的特权？这是没有道理的。但是，这一平等的原则（不像自由的原则）不能运用到我与上帝的关系中，因为上帝是唯一的生物，对他来说，责任的概念在其身上不再有效。
但是，关于作为主体所有公民的平等权利，我们或许要问一个世袭的贵族是否有资格享用。对这个问题的回答完全取决于哪一个更被看重，是国家授予的高级地位还是本人所取得的成就。现在很显然的是，如果等级是生而就被授予的，那么是否成就（在某人岗位上的技能和贡献）会与等级相伴而来则是非常不确定的。这相当于赋予一个得到偏爱的人领导地位而不管他是否在其岗位上取得成绩，在原始契约中，这不会被公众意愿所接受，毕竟这是所有权利背后的原则，因为一个贵族并不一定是一个高尚的人。至于一个掌权的贵族，例如，因为成绩所获得的地方高级治安官品级，品级对这个人而言不是附属的财产，而是这个人所占有的位置，这并不违反平等的原则。当一个人放弃了他的职位之后，他同时也辞去了他的品级而重新成为人民中的一员。

[6]许多人批评高调地授予统治者称号是奢侈的奉承，但是这对我来说是没有道理的事。因为让这片土地的统治者变得高傲倒不如让他们的心灵怀有谦卑。如果他是一个有知性的人（我们必须这样假定），他将会反思他接管了一个对人类而言太过巨大的办公室。这个办公室掌管着上帝在这个地球上最为神圣的机构即人的权利。他将始终活在惊恐中，害怕以什么方式伤害了上帝最为有价值的个人财产。

[7]马莱·迪·旁在他华丽而空洞的写作中吹嘘说，他根据多年的经验最终被大主教的名言所征服：“让蠢蛋们就政府的形式争论不休吧，管理最好的政府就是最好的。”如果这意味着管理最好的政府就是管理得最好的政府，那么他就打开了一个坚果（正如斯威福特所做的那样）而得到了一个虫子的奖赏。如果这意味着管理最好的政府也是最好类型的政府（也就是，最好的宪法），那就完全错了。好的政府并不能说明是好的类型的政府。的确，谁能比提图斯或者马可·奥勒留统治得要好，然而，一个将王位传给了多米提安，另一个传给了康茂德；这在有一部完善宪法的国家中是不会发生的，因为他们不适合统治者这个职位的事实早为人所知，他们的继任者也足够强大，能够把不称职者排除在继承的行列之外。

[8]一个保加利亚的王子对友善地提出用决斗解决纠纷的希腊皇帝说：“一个有钳子的铁匠不会用双手把滚烫的铁从炭火中取出。”

[9]当战争结束，当和平降临，一个民族在感恩节之后指定一天为赎罪日也不为过。上天会以国家的名义饶恕人类，饶恕他们不断犯下的大罪，因为国家就是不在国际关系中遵从一个有法律的体制。每个国家以独立而引以为豪，愿意采用野蛮的战争手段，尽管战争不能产生出国家所渴望的权利结果。在战争中每次胜利的感恩节，每次对万军之主（用以色列人的方式）哼唱的赞歌，都很明显地与人类之父的道德概念恰恰相反。因为除了展示国家在追求他们共同权利的方式上的冷漠之外，他们实际上还为毁灭数不清的人及其幸福的行为而高兴。

[10]如果我们希望给这个伟大的帝国起个名字，以它称呼自己的方式给它命名（例如，China，而非Sina或者任何其他的类似形式），我们只需借鉴一下吉奥尔基写的《藏语字母表》的第651页到654页。根据彼得堡的费舍教授所说，它实际上没有一个自己的固定名字。最为常见的一个名字是金，意思是金子（藏族人称它为Ser）。这就解释了为什么皇帝被称作黄金之王（世界上最辉煌之地）。这个字显然在中国发Chin的音，但是被意大利传教士读为Kin，是因为意大利人不会发喉音。同样也应当看到，罗马人称之为Ser的国家实际上就是中国。丝绸就是从中国途经大西藏到达欧洲的（或许穿过小西藏、布哈拉和波斯）。这引发了关于这个古老而特别的国家的众多猜测，将它与印度相比较，猜测它与西藏地区和日本的关系。但是相邻国家称之为Sina或者Tschina却没有什么道理。

或许古老但迄今为止奇怪的位于欧洲和西藏的群落可以解释为海西基记录的圣职者的呐喊。根据吉奥尔基的《藏语字母表》，Concioa一字的意思是上帝。这个字看上去像Konx，希腊人或许轻易地发音为pax。但是Om被拉·克洛泽翻译为“保佑”，如果说涉及神性的话就是有福之人的意思。当弗朗西斯科问西藏喇嘛他们如何看待上帝时，他总是得到这样的答案：“上帝是所有那些神圣的人的群体。”因此，神秘的Konx Ompax或许是“神圣上帝的智慧”的意思，即遍及世界的至高存在，也就是，自然人格化。我们最初的考虑应当有助于解释这个神秘的名字如何从西藏传到希腊。同样，这种影响可能是这样，即欧洲最早经西藏地区与中国发生了联系，或许比与印度交往更早。

[11]人是自然界的一部分。在自然界的机制中，其生存依靠某种基本的形式。我们只有将它归结为一个世界性的创造者事先决定了这一切，（大自然的）这种形式对我们来说才变得容易理解。我们把这种已定的影响称作上天的旨意，进一步定义为原始天意，因为它从远古时期延续。因为它根据有目的的宇宙法则延续自然的使命，我们称之为统治的天意。如果天意实现了某种目的，而人不能预示到其存在只能由结果猜测，这被称作指导性天意。最后，如果单个事件被看作是天意使然，我们便不再说是天意，而是一种特殊的施与。但是，如果有人宣称他能认识到这一点，那就是一种愚蠢的狂妄自大，因为这就意味着一个奇迹的诞生，即使发生的事件没有被特别地描述为奇迹性的话。因为不管它如何神奇或卑微，从一个单个事件中得出结论说，事件由一个特别的原则所左右，或者说事件本身是一个结果，不仅仅是另一个我们所全然不知的自然、机械的结果所导致，这是荒唐而自负的。同样，根据世界上的物体将天意分类，将它分为普遍的和特指的，就像文字记载中所提到的天意照看着各种各样的生物种类，但是也留下机会照顾个体，这样也是错误和自相矛盾的。说天意普遍存在的意思是没有哪一个个体应当被排除在外。然而，这种分类方式或许意味着表示天意由不同的方式实现。这也许是普遍性的（例如，每年出现的死亡和由于季节变化而产生的自然的复苏），或者是特殊性的（例如，海洋流将树木运送到北极海岸，而这种树在当地无法生长，从而给当地居民提供了生存资料）。后一种情况，我们能够解释某种现象的自然机制（例如，河床被森林覆盖，于是树可能掉入河里，被诸如墨西哥湾流的水流带走）。另一方面，我们必须不能忽视目的论（认为事物的发生和发展都是为了达到一定目的——译者注），它显示掌管自然的一个智慧的机构的前瞻性。但是，这个天佑和天意的概念，在当前的学术界，是过剩的。第一，试图给迥然不同的事物戴上挽具（如同给神话传说中的狮身鹰首兽戴上给马戴的挽具一样）是自相矛盾的，指出一个生物其本身是世界发展的完全动因就必须在世界性事件发生期间提供他自己的先决天意。例如，说医生作为上帝的助理治愈病人就是荒唐的。如果我们上升到那个最高的原始原因，上帝是医生及其所有药物的制造者，效果必须完全归因于他。这个原因理论上说我们理解不了。换句话说，它也可以完全上升到医生，只要我们把遭质疑的事件当作自然的规律对待，当作在地球上发生的事物的系列事件来解释。第二，如果我们采取这样的态度，我们就被剥夺了所有一定的原则，而我们通过这些原则评判效果。但是神的赞同概念是完全可以接受的，的确在道德和实践上是必要的，这是指玄奥的精神世界。例如，我们可以说我们不应当停止朝着善的方向努力，因为我们相信上帝会弥补我们所缺乏的正直，甚至是以我们所不能理解的方式，只要我们的态度足够诚恳。然而，没有人会用这样的论点去解释一个好的、被当作一个世俗事件的举动，因为这会假定玄奥的理论知识，我们如此宣称是很荒唐的。

[12]在所有的生活方式中，猎人的生活方式是与一个文明宪法最格格不入的。对于一个家庭来说，不得不分离地生活很快就会彼此成为陌生人，最终在广阔的森林中分散开来，彼此之间充满敌意，因为每个人都需要一大片区域以获得衣食。对诺亚提出的禁止食血的命令（《创世纪》VIIII，2—6）看上去不为别的，而是专为禁止猎人的生活方式而设立。这一定包括吃生肉，假如禁止吃生肉，食血就不可能了。这种禁忌常常被强调，后来被犹太基督教徒强加在新入教的异教徒身上，但是有着不同的意图（第15、20、21、25条）。

[13]下面的问题或许会被提出。如果大自然的意图是让这些寒冷的海岸无人居住，如果大自然不再给他们提供漂浮的树木，这种情况的确可能发生，那么会对当地居民产生怎样的影响？因为我们可以相信随着当地文化的进步，温带地区的居民会更好地利用生长在河岸两边的树木，不让这些树木倒入水中并漂流到大海里。我应当回答说：那些住在鄂毕河、叶尼塞河、勒拿河等沿岸的人会以贸易的方式提供，用树木换取动物产品。北冰洋岸边出产丰富的动物产品。他们只会在大自然迫使他们彼此和平地一起生活的时候才会这么做。

[14]宗教差别——一个古怪的表达！仿佛我们要谈论不同的道德观。当然有不同的历史信条，虽然这些与宗教本身没有关系，只是与深化宗教途径的办法相关，因此属于历史研究的范畴。或许有多种不同的宗教书，但是，只能有一个宗教对所有人在所有的时间内有效。因此，不同的信条只可能是宗教的工具。这些是偶发的，可能随着时间和地点的变化而变化。

[15]这些是理性的许可法。它允许一个公权利的国家持续存在，即使它受到了不公正的影响，直到导致一场彻底革命的一切条件成熟，或者是为一场和平方式的革命做好了准备。任何合法的体制，即使它仅仅是在小范围内属于合法的，也比什么都没有要好一些。不成熟的改革的命运即为无政府状态。因此，政治上的深谋远虑，正如目前情况所表明的，就是将进行适合公权利理想的改革作为一项任务。但是，当革命是被自然本身所引发的时候，就不能将革命当作进行更大压迫的理由，而应当将其看作是自然的召唤，召唤建立一个基于自由原则之上的合法体制，因为这样一个彻底的改革才是惟一能够持续下去的。

[16]人们或许会怀疑是否植根于人性中的与生俱来的邪恶影响了共同生活在一个国度的人们，因为一个人或许会引证他们尚未发展的文化（例如，他们的野蛮性）作为其想法的不合法因素的成因。但是，在国家间的外部关系中，这种邪恶是相当不加掩饰、无可辩驳地明显存在的。在每一个国家中，这种邪恶被体现在国内法中的高压政治所掩盖，因为公民间彼此动武的倾向被更加强大的力量——政府所抵消。这不仅仅使整体蒙上了一层道德的遮羞布，而且也终结了无法无天状况的爆发。它使得人们的道德能力发展为一种对权利的即时尊重变得容易了很多；因为每一个人都相信他能够保持权利概念的神圣并且忠诚地遵守它，但愿他能确定所有其他的人会做同样的事，并且政府又部分地能为他作出保障。这就向道德准则迈了一大步，向一个义务的概念得到承认的国家迈了一大步，不管能否有可能的收获作为回报。但是，由于每个个人，尽管自认为很好，却假设其他人不忠诚，人们因此彼此评价，结果是他们自己都没有多少价值，尽管“为什么是这样”的讨论没有意义，我们不能责怪人类作为一个自由生物的天性。对于权利概念的尊重，以及人类绝对没有能力拒绝权利概念的现实给以下理论一个最庄严的认可，即每个人都明白他自己必须遵循权利原则，不管其他人会如何表现。

[17]人们能在加尔费1788年的专著《关于道德与政治的结合》一书中找到类似准则的例证。这位值得尊敬的学者承认，从一开始他就无法针对这个问题给出一个令人满意的答案。但是宽恕如此的程序，同时承认一个人不能完全回答针对他们提出的反对意见的做法似乎对那些注定要滥用它的人是一个很大的让步，这种做法对任何人来说都是不可取的。

[18]那些，从女巫到吉卜赛人，既没有知识又不诚实的预言人被称作假先知。

[19]然而，这并不意味着一个有着君主宪法的民族因此能要求推翻它，或者是有一个秘密的愿望这样做。在欧洲占据一片延伸的领土的民族或许会感觉到君主制是惟一的一种体制能够在强大的邻国中保持自身的存在。如果臣民们抱怨，不是因为他们的内部政府，而是因为他们的政府对待外国公民的表现（例如，如果该国不鼓励国外的共和主义），这并不能证明人民对他们自己的体制不满意，而是他们非常地依赖这个体制，因为随着越来越多的民族成为共和国，该国逐渐变得更安全。然而，致力于扩大自身重要性的造谣的献媚者们试图把这些无害的政治谣言说成是革新主义、雅各宾主义和阴谋，构成对国家的危胁。但是，这种指控是没有丝毫道理的，特别是对一个远离革命中心一百英里的国家就更没有道理了。

[20]对于主张人的权利如此有热情，为什么没有统治者胆敢公开表明他不承认任何人民反对他的权利？或者说人民只把幸福寄托在政府的善行上，而任何臣民标榜自己有权利反对政府都是谎谬的、甚至会遭受惩罚，因为他们表明对于政府的抵抗是可以得到允许的。原因是任何公开的声明都会唤起民众对于统治者的反抗，即使他们像驯服的绵羊，喂得好，保护得好，并且由一个善良而善解人意的主人领着，不必因为缺乏福利而抱怨。被赋予了自由的生物不会仅仅满足于享受存在的舒适，这一点别人也会很好地提供（这里是由政府提供）。这完全依赖于控制这种舒适的原则。但是，福利没有任何统治原则，提供者和接受者也没有这样的原则，因为每个个体对此的定义不同。事实上，它依赖于这个愿望的物质方面，完全是经验性的，因此不可能成为一个普遍规则。被赋予了自由的一个生物，意识到其较之非理性动物所拥有的有利条件，能够并且必须遵循其意愿中正规的原则，要求他的人民不能缺乏政府。在政府中，人民是共同的立法者。换句话说，人要遵循的权利必须排在他们的康乐之上，因为人权是一项神圣的制度，超过所有功利主义的价值。不管政府如何乐善好施，它都不能背离人权。然而，这些权利总是一个理念。这个理念实现的条件是所采用的方法与道德相一致。这个限制条件必须不被人们所践踏，即通过革命实现他们的权利，这在任何时候都是不公平的。使一个民族遵守其体制的最好办法是自主地统治，同时用共和的形式管理，例如，用共和主义的精神统治，并以此类推。

[21]一项其特性无法直接预测的事业可以通过伴随它的效果来发现。什么是纯粹的君主？他是说战争将要爆发战争就会爆发的那个人。与此相反，什么样的君主是受限制的？他必须先询问人民是否应该有战争，如果人民说不应该有战争，那就不会有战争。在战争条件下，所有的国家权利都必须由国家元首处理。
现在，大不列颠的君主在没有征得人民同意的情况下发动了无数的战争。这个国王因此是一个不折不扣的君主，尽管根据宪法他不应当这么做。但是，他总是会忽视宪法，因为他总是确信只要控制着国家不同的力量，人民的代表们就会与他保持一致，因为他有权力嘉奖所有的权贵。这个腐朽的制度要想继续维持就自然不能曝光；它因此笼罩着一层神秘的面纱。

[22]人们都一致认为应当设计符合理智要求的政治体制（特别是在权利的问题上）。但是把它们严肃地提出是鲁莽的行为，而煽动人民抛弃现有的体制是要受到惩罚的。
柏拉图的《亚特兰蒂斯》、莫尔的《乌托邦》、哈林顿的《大洋国》、阿莱的《塞维亚姆比亚》相继问世，但是他们从没有在实践中检验过（克伦威尔试图建立专制共和国的失败尝试是个例外）。这些政治创造跟创造世界是一样的。没有人亲眼看到，也不可能有人亲眼看到，否则他就成为自身的创造者了。无论时光如何变化，在我们脑海中的这种政治产品某一天会变得完美仅仅是一个愉快的梦想。但是，我们会不断地接近这样的一种状态，只要它能与道德法取得一致，这就不仅仅是想象，这也是一国之君（不是公民）的责任。

[23]交流的冲动一定是孤独的人类向他们之外的其他动物宣告其存在的原始动力，特别是那些能发出可以模仿的声音的人们，这些声音后来成了名字。与这种冲动类似的效果现在还能在孩子们和智力低下的成年人身上看到。他们敲打、喊叫、唱歌、吹口哨，制造其他噪音（甚至常常是吵闹的宗教活动）打断人们的思考。他们这样做，除了在这大千世界宣告他们的存在，我看不出这些人还有其他的什么动机会这样做。

[24]下面的内容可能成为这一矛盾仅有的几个例子被引用。一方面是人对于道德目标的激情，另一方面是他本性中不变的对于法律的遵从和对于残酷环境的适应。
大自然有一个固定的时间表。就他们的要求和制造同类的能力而言，人类达到成熟大约是在十六岁或者是十七岁。这个年龄，在大自然界，是一个年轻人成为成人的年龄。这时他有能力照看自己，生育后代，照顾他的妻子和孩子。他需求的简单化使得这一切变得容易。但是，在一个文明的国家，为了实现这些功能，在技术和有利的外部环境方面他需要多种支持。在公民社会的语境下，相应的阶段因此要延长至少平均十年。然而，大自然没有更改进入青春期的年龄以适应社会的进步，而是固执地遵守其为了人类作为一个动物物种的生存而规定的法则。结果是，社会习俗对于自然的影响，或者是自然对社会习俗的影响明显存有偏见。在自然状态中达到一定年龄就已经成熟的人，在文明状态下却养活不了自己，更不要说抚养妻子和儿女，尽管按照自然的要求他有生育后代的冲动与能力。大自然当然没有赋予生物以本能和能力，为的是它能够压制他们。如此的能力不是为文明状态而设计，而是为人类作为一个动物品种的生存而设计。文明的状态因此与后者产生了矛盾，这个矛盾只有文明的最终目标——一个完善的公民体制才能够解决。与此同时，在自然状态和完美状态之间充满了邪恶及邪恶所带来的后果，也就是，以各种各样的形式呈现的人类悲剧。 另一个例子或许能够确认这样的事实，即大自然为了两个截然不同的目的赋予我们两种不同的能力：人作为一个动物物种以及人作为一个道德物种。例子就是希波克拉底所说的“生命短暂，艺术永恒”。当一个拥有才智的人通过长期实践和知识积累获得了必要的成熟的判断力的时候，艺术和科学就能够得到进一步的发展。只要这个人能够生存并在整个一代人的时间里保持他年轻的脑力，他发展艺术和科学的能量要比整整一代学者的能量大。如今，很明显大自然固定了人生的长度，意在终结而不是推动科学的进步。正当最幸运的思想家处于伟大发现的边缘时，暮年已至，他失去了洞察力，必须让下一代（下一代重新从ABC开始，不得不再次重走已经走过的整个路程）在文化的进步中走下一步。因此，人类实现使命的旅程显示出不断受到干扰，随时有倒退回原始野蛮状态的危险。希腊哲学家有这样的抱怨：“当我们开始认识到我们应当如何活时，我们却不得不面对死亡，这真是一个遗憾。” 第三个例子，我们可以引用人的不平等的例子——不是命运赋予人的自然天赋或者善行的不平等，而是从世界人权的角度出发，关于这一点，卢梭的抱怨是极具真实性的。然而，这种不平等与文明不可分割，只要文明毫无规划地发展（在相当长的一段时间内，情况就是这样）。但是，这种不平等当然不是大自然强加给人的，因为大自然给予他自由和理智。理智裁定这种自由受到其自身外部的、世界的法律的限制，这就是民权。人意图通过自己的努力上升到超越其自然能力的野蛮状态，但是，即使是超越野蛮也要小心不触犯它们。他期待在经过了许多次成功尝试之后获得这个技能。与此同时，人类由于自身缺乏经验而吃尽苦头，在罪恶的压迫下痛苦地呻吟。

[25]阿拉伯的贝都因人依然自认为是部落的创始人——前酋长的孩子们。但是，酋长毫无疑问不是他们的主人。他不能将自己的意愿强加在其臣民的身上。在一个游牧民族中，没有人拥有他带不走的固定资产，因此任何一个对自己部落不满意的家庭都能轻而易举地离开这个部落而加入其他的部落。

Perpetual Peace: A Philosophical Sketch

‘The Perpetual Peace’

A Dutch innkeeper once put this satirical inscription on his signboard, along with the picture of a graveyard. We shall not trouble to ask whether it applies to men in general, or particularly to heads of state（who can never have enough of war）, or only to the philosophers who blissfully dream of perpetual peace. The author of the present essay does, however, make one reservation in advance. The practical politician tends to look down with great complacency upon the political theorist as a mere academic. The theorist's abstract ideas, the practitioner believes, cannot endanger the state, since the state must be founded upon principles of experience; it thus seems safe to let him fire off his whole broadside, and the worldly-wise statesman need not turn a hair. It thus follows that if the practical politician is to be consistent, he must not claim, in the event of a dispute with the theorist, to scent any danger to the state in the opinions which the theorist has randomly uttered in public. By this saving clause, the author of this essay will consider himself expressly safeguarded, in correct and proper style, against all malicious interpretation.

FIRST SECTION
Which Contains the Preliminary Articles of a Perpetual Peace Between States

1.‘No conclusion of peace shall be considered valid as such if it was made with a secret reservation of the material for a future war.’

For if this were the case, it would be a mere truce, a suspension of hostilities, not a peace. Peace means an end to all hostilities, and to attach the adjective ‘perpetual’ to it is already suspiciously close to pleonasm. A conclusion of peace nullifies all existing reasons for a future war, even if these are not yet known to the contracting parties, and no matter how acutely and carefully they may later be pieced together out of old documents. It is possible that either party may make a mental reservation with a view to reviving its old pretensions in the future. Such reservations will not be mentioned explicitly, since both parties may simply be too exhausted to continue the war, although they may nonetheless possess sufficient ill will to seize the first favourable opportunity of attaining their end. But if we consider such reservations in themselves, they soon appear as Jesuitical casuistry; they are beneath the dignity of a ruler, just as it is beneath the dignity of a minister of state to comply with any reasoning of this kind.

But if, in accordance with ‘enlightened’ notions of political expediency, we believe that the true glory of a state consists in the constant increase of its power by any means whatsoever, the above judgement will certainly appear academic and pedantic.

2.‘No independently existing state, whether it be large or small, may be acquired by another state by inheritance, exchange, purchase or gift.’

For a state, unlike the ground on which it is based, is not a possession（patrimonium）. It is a society of men, which no one other than itself can command or dispose of. Like a tree, it has its own roots, and to graft it on to another state as if it were a shoot is to terminate its existence as a moral personality and make it into a commodity. This contradicts the idea of the original contract, without which the rights of a people are unthinkable.[1] Everyone knows what danger the supposed right of acquiring states in this way, even in our own times, has brought upon Europe（for this practice is unknown in other continents）. It has been thought that states can marry one another, and this has provided a new kind of industry by which power can be increased through family alliances, without expenditure of energy, while landed property can be extended at the same time. It is the same thing when the troops of one state are hired to another to fight an enemy who is not common to both; for the subjects are thereby used and misused as objects to be manipulated at will.

3.‘Standing armies（miles perpetuus） will gradually be abolished altogether.’

For they constantly threaten other states with war by the very fact that they are always prepared for it. They spur on the states to outdo one another in arming unlimited numbers of soldiers, and since the resultant costs eventually make peace more oppressive than a short war, the armies are themselves the cause of wars of aggression which set out to end burdensome military expenditure. Furthermore, the hiring of men to kill or to be killed seems to mean using them as mere machines and instruments in the hands of someone else（the state）, which cannot easily be reconciled with the rights of man in one's own person. It is quite a different matter if the citizens undertake voluntary military training from time to time in order to secure themselves and their fatherland against attacks from outside. But it would be just the same if wealth rather than soldiers were accumulated, for it would be seen by other states as a military threat; it might compel them to mount preventive attacks, for of the three powers within a state – the power of the army, the power of alliance and the power of money – the third is probably the most reliable instrument of war. It would lead more often to wars if it were not so difficult to discover the amount of wealth which another state possesses.

4.‘No national debt shall be contracted in connection with the external affairs of the state.’

There is no cause for suspicion if help for the national economy is sought inside or outside the state（e.g. for improvements to roads, new settlements, storage of foodstuffs for years of famine, etc.）. But a credit system, if used by the powers as an instrument of aggression against one another, shows the power of money in its most dangerous form. For while the debts thereby incurred are always secure against present demands（because not all the creditors will demand payment at the same time）, these debts go on growing indefinitely. This ingenious system, invented by a commercial people in the present century, provides a military fund which may exceed the resources of all the other states put together. It can only be exhausted by an eventual tax-deficit, which may be postponed for a considerable time by the commercial stimulus which industry and trade receive through the credit system. This ease in making war, coupled with the warlike inclination of those in power（which seems to be an integral feature of human nature）, is thus a great obstacle in the way of perpetual peace. Foreign debts must therefore be prohibited by a preliminary article of such a peace, otherwise national bankruptcy, inevitable in the long run, would necessarily involve various other states in the resultant loss without their having deserved it, thus inflicting upon them a public injury. Other states are therefore justified in allying themselves against such a state and its pretensions.

5. ‘No state shall forcibly interfere in the constitution and government of another state.’

For what could justify such interference? Surely not any sense of scandal or offence which a state arouses in the subjects of another state. It should rather serve as a warning to others, as an example of the great evils which a people has incurred by its lawlessness. And a bad example which one free person gives to another（as a scandalum acceptum） is not the same as an injury to the latter. But it would be a different matter if a state, through internal discord, were to split into two parts, each of which set itself up as a separate state and claimed authority over the whole. For it could not be reckoned as interference in another state's constitution if an external state were to lend support to one of them, because their condition is one of anarchy. But as long as this internal conflict is not yet decided, the interference of external powers would be a violation of the rights of an independent people which is merely struggling with its internal ills. Such interference would be an active offence and would make the autonomy of all other states insecure.

6.‘No state at war with another shall permit such acts of hostility as would make mutual confidence impossible during a future time of peace. Such acts would include the employment of assassins（percussores） or poisoners（venefici）, breach of agreements, the instigation of treason（perduellio）within the enemy state, etc.’

These are dishonourable stratagems. For it must still remain possible, even in wartime, to have some sort of trust in the attitude of the enemy, otherwise peace could not be concluded and the hostilities would turn into a war of extermination（bellum internecinum）. After all, war is only a regrettable expedient for asserting one's rights by force within a state of nature, where no court of justice is available to judge with legal authority. In such cases, neither party can be declared an unjust enemy, for this would already presuppose a judge's decision; only the outcome of the conflict, as in the case of a so-called ‘judgement of God’, can decide who is in the right. A war of punishment（bellum punitivum） between states is inconceivable, since there can be no relationship of superior to inferior among them. It thus follows that a war of extermination, in which both parties and right itself might all be simultaneously annihilated, would allow perpetual peace only on the vast graveyard of the human race. A war of this kind and the employment of all means which might bring it about must thus be absolutely prohibited. But the means listed above would inevitably lead to such a war, because these diabolical arts, besides being intrinsically despicable, would not long be confined to war alone if they were brought into use. This applies, for example, to the employment of spies（uti exploratoribus）, for it exploits only the dishonesty of others（which can never be completely eliminated）. Such practices will be carried over into peacetime and will thus completely vitiate its purpose.

All of the articles listed above, when regarded objectively or in relation to the intentions of those in power, are prohibitive laws（leges prohibitivae）. Yet some of them are of the strictest sort（leges strictae）, being valid irrespective of differing circumstances, and they require that the abuses they prohibit should be abolished immediately（Nos. 1, 5 and 6）. Others（Nos. 2, 3 and 4）, although they are not exceptions to the rule of justice, allow some subjective latitude according to the circumstances in which they are applied（leges latae）. The latter need not necessarily be executed at once, so long as their ultimate purpose（e.g. the restoration of freedom to certain states in accordance with the second article） is not lost sight of. But their execution may not be put off to a non-existent date（ad calendas graecas, as Augustus used to promise）, for any delay is permitted only as a means of avoiding a premature implementation which might frustrate the whole purpose of the article. For in the case of the second article, the prohibition relates only to the mode of acquisition, which is to be forbidden hereforth, but not to the present state of political possessions. For although this present state is not backed up by the requisite legal authority, it was considered lawful in the public opinion of every state at the time of the putative acquisition.[2]

SECOND SECTION
Which Contains the Definitive Articles of a Perpetual Peace Between States

A state of peace among men living together is not the same as the state of nature, which is rather a state of war. For even if it does not involve active hostilities, it involves a constant threat of their breaking out. Thus the state of peace must be formally instituted, for a suspension of hostilities is not in itself a guarantee of peace. And unless one neighbour gives a guarantee to the other at his request（which can happen only in a lawful state）, the latter may treat him as an enemy.[3]

First Definitive Article of a Perpetual Peace: The Civil Constitution of Every State shall be Republican

A republican constitution is founded upon three principles: firstly, the principle of freedom for all members of a society（as men）; secondly, the principle of the dependence of everyone upon a single common legislation（as subjects）; and thirdly, the principle of legal equality for everyone（as citizens）.[4] It is the only constitution which can be derived from the idea of an original contract, upon which all rightful legislation of a people must be founded. Thus as far as right is concerned, republicanism is in itself the original basis of every kind of civil constitution, and it only remains to ask whether it is the only constitution which can lead to a perpetual peace.

The republican constitution is not only pure in its origin（since it springs from the pure concept of right）; it also offers a prospect of attaining the desired result, i.e. a perpetual peace, and the reason for this is as follows. – If, as is inevitably the case under this constitution, the consent of the citizens is required to decide whether or not war is to be declared, it is very natural that they will have great hesitation in embarking on so dangerous an enterprise. For this would mean calling down on themselves all the miseries of war, such as doing the fighting themselves, supplying the costs of the war from their own resources, painfully making good the ensuing devastation, and, as the crowning evil, having to take upon themselves a burden of debt which will embitter peace itself and which can never be paid off on account of the constant threat of new wars. But under a constitution where the subject is not a citizen, and which is therefore not republican, it is the simplest thing in the world to go to war. For the head of state is not a fellow citizen, but the owner of the state, and a war will not force him to make the slightest sacrifice so far as his banquets, hunts, pleasure palaces and court festivals are concerned. He can thus decide on war, without any significant reason, as a kind of amusement, and unconcernedly leave it to the diplomatic corps（who are always ready for such purposes） to justify the war for the sake of propriety.

The following remarks are necessary to prevent the republican constitution from being confused with the democratic one, as commonly happens. The various forms of state（civitas）may be classified either according to the different persons who exercise supreme authority, or according to the way in which the nation is governed by its ruler, whoever he may be. The first classification goes by the form of sovereignty（forma imperii）, and only three such forms are possible, depending on whether the ruling power is in the hands of an individual, of several persons in association, or of all those who together constitute civil society（i.e. autocracy, aristocracy and democracy – the power of a prince, the power of a nobility, and the power of the people）. The second classification depends on the form of government（forma regiminis）, and relates to the way in which the state, setting out from its constitution（i.e. an act of the general will whereby the mass becomes a people）, makes use of its plenary power. The form of government, in this case, will be either republican or despotic. Republicanism is that political principle whereby the executive power（the government） is separated from the legislative power. Despotism prevails in a state if the laws are made and arbitrarily executed by one and the same power, and it reflects the will of the people only in so far as the ruler treats the will of the people as his own private will. Of the three forms of sovereignty, democracy, in the truest sense of the word, is necessarily a despotism, because it establishes an executive power through which all the citizens may make decisions about（and indeed against） the single individual without his consent, so that decisions are made by all the people and yet not by all the people; and this means that the general will is in contradiction with itself, and thus also with freedom.

For any form of government which is not representative is essentially an anomaly, because one and the same person cannot at the same time be both the legislator and the executor of his own will, just as the general proposition in logical reasoning cannot at the same time be a secondary proposition subsuming the particular within the general. And even if the other two political constitutions（i.e. autocracy and aristocracy） are always defective in as much as they leave room for a despotic form of government, it is at least possible that they will be associated with a form of government which accords with the spirit of a representative system. Thus Frederick Ⅱ at least said that he was merely the highest servant of the state,[5] while a democratic constitution makes this attitude impossible, because everyone under it wants to be a ruler. We can therefore say that the smaller the number of ruling persons in a state and the greater their powers of representation, the more the constitution will approximate to its republican potentiality, which it may hope to realize eventually by gradual reforms. For this reason, it is more difficult in an aristocracy than in a monarchy to reach this one and only perfectly lawful kind of constitution, while it is possible in a democracy only by means of violent revolution. But the people are immensely more concerned with the mode of government[6] than with the form of the constitution, although a great deal also depends on the degree to which the constitution fits the purpose of the government. But if the mode of government is to accord with the concept of right, it must be based on the representative system. This system alone makes possible a republican state, and without it, despotism and violence will result, no matter what kind of constitution is in force. None of the so-called ‘republics’ of antiquity employed such a system, and they thus inevitably ended in despotism, although this is still relatively bearable under the rule of a single individual.

Second Definitive Article of a Perpetual Peace: The Right of Nations shall be based on a Federation of Free States

Peoples who have grouped themselves into nation states may be judged in the same way as individual men living in a state of nature, independent of external laws; for they are a standing offence to one another by the very fact that they are neighbours. Each nation, for the sake of its own security, can and ought to demand of the others that they should enter along with it into a constitution, similar to the civil one, within which the rights of each could be secured. This would mean establishing a federation of peoples. But a federation of this sort would not be the same thing as an international state. For the idea of an international state is contradictory, since every state involves a relationship between a superior（the legislator） and an inferior（the people obeying the laws）, whereas a number of nations forming one state would constitute a single nation. And this contradicts our initial assumption, as we are here considering the right of nations in relation to one another in so far as they are a group of separate states which are not to be welded together as a unit.

We look with profound contempt upon the way in which savages cling to their lawless freedom. They would rather engage in incessant strife than submit to a legal constraint which they might impose upon themselves, for they prefer the freedom of folly to the freedom of reason. We regard this as barbarism, coarseness, and brutish debasement of humanity. We might thus expect that civilized peoples, each united within itself as a state, would hasten to abandon so degrading a condition as soon as possible. But instead of doing so, each state sees its own majesty（for it would be absurd to speak of the majesty of a people） precisely in not having to submit to any external legal constraint, and the glory of its ruler consists in his power to order thousands of people to immolate themselves for a cause which does not truly concern them, while he need not himself incur any danger whatsoever.[7] And the main difference between the savage nations of Europe and those of America is that while some American tribes have been entirely eaten up by their enemies, the Europeans know how to make better use of those they have defeated than merely by making a meal of them. They would rather use them to increase the number of their own subjects, thereby augmenting their stock of instruments for conducting even more extensive wars.

Although it is largely concealed by governmental constraints in law-governed civil society, the depravity of human nature is displayed without disguise in the unrestricted relations which obtain between the various nations. It is therefore to be wondered at that the word right has not been completely banished from military politics as superfluous pedantry, and that no state has been bold enough to declare itself publicly in favour of doing so. For Hugo Grotius, Pufendorf, Vattel and the rest（sorry comforters as they are） are still dutifully quoted in justification of military aggression, although their philosophically or diplomatically formulated codes do not and cannot have the slightest legal force, since states as such are not subject to a common external constraint. Yet there is no instance of a state ever having been moved to desist from its purpose by arguments supported by the testimonies of such notable men. This homage which every state pays（in words at least） to the concept of right proves that man possesses a greater moral capacity, still dormant at present, to overcome eventually the evil principle within him（for he cannot deny that it exists）, and to hope that others will do likewise. Otherwise the word right would never be used by states which intend to make war on one another, unless in a derisory sense, as when a certain Gallic prince declared:‘Nature has given to the strong the prerogative of making the weak obey them.’ The way in which states seek their rights can only be by war, since there is no external tribunal to put their claims to trial. But rights cannot be decided by military victory, and a peace treaty may put an end to the current war, but not to that general warlike condition within which pretexts can always be found for a new war. And indeed, such a state of affairs cannot be pronounced completely unjust, since it allows each party to act as judge in its own cause. Yet while natural right allows us to say of men living in a lawless condition that they ought to abandon it, the right of nations does not allow us to say the same of states. For as states, they already have a lawful internal constitution, and have thus outgrown the coercive right of others to subject them to a wider legal constitution in accordance with their conception of right. On the other hand, reason, as the highest legislative moral power, absolutely condemns war as a test of rights and sets up peace as an immediate duty. But peace can neither be inaugurated nor secured without a general agreement between the nations; thus a particular kind of league, which we might call a pacific federation（foedus pacificum）, is required. It would differ from a peace treaty（pactum pacis） in that the latter terminates one war, whereas the former would seek to end all wars for good. This federation does not aim to acquire any power like that of a state, but merely to preserve and secure the freedom of each state in itself, along with that of the other confederated states, although this does not mean that they need to submit to public laws and to a coercive power which enforces them, as do men in a state of nature. It can be shown that this idea of federalism, extending gradually to encompass all states and thus leading to perpetual peace, is practicable and has objective reality. For if by good fortune one powerful and enlightened nation can form a republic（which is by its nature inclined to seek perpetual peace）, this will provide a focal point for federal association among other states. These will join up with the first one, thus securing the freedom of each state in accordance with the idea of international right, and the whole will gradually spread further and further by a series of alliances of this kind.

It would be understandable for a people to say:‘There shall be no war among us; for we will form ourselves into a state, appointing for ourselves a supreme legislative, executive and juridical power to resolve our conflicts by peaceful means.’ But if this state says:‘There shall be no war between myself and other states, although I do not recognize any supreme legislative power which could secure my rights and whose rights I should in turn secure’, it is impossible to understand what justification I can have for placing any confidence in my rights, unless I can rely on some substitute for the union of civil society, i.e. on a free federation. If the concept of international right is to retain any meaning at all, reason must necessarily couple it with a federation of this kind.

The concept of international right becomes meaningless if interpreted as a right to go to war. For this would make it a right to determine what is lawful not by means of universally valid external laws, but by means of one-sided maxims backed up by physical force. It could be taken to mean that it is perfectly just for men who adopt this attitude to destroy one another, and thus to find perpetual peace in the vast grave where all the horrors of violence and those responsible for them would be buried. There is only one rational way in which states coexisting with other states can emerge from the lawless condition of pure warfare. Just like individual men, they must renounce their savage and lawless freedom, adapt themselves to public coercive laws, and thus form an international state（civitas gentium）, which would necessarily continue to grow until it embraced all the peoples of the earth. But since this is not the will of the nations, according to their present conception of international right（so that they reject in hypothesi what is true in thesi）, the positive idea of a world republic cannot be realized. If all is not to be lost, this can at best find a negative substitute in the shape of an enduring and gradually expanding federation likely to prevent war. The latter may check the current of man's inclination to defy the law and antagonize his fellows, although there will always be a risk of it bursting forth anew. Furor impius intus – fremit horridus ore cruento（Virgil） [‘Wicked Frenzy rages savagely with blood-stained mouth’].[8]

Third Definitive Article of a Perpetual Peace: Cosmopolitan Right shall be limited to Conditions of Universal Hospitality

As in the foregoing articles, we are here concerned not with philanthropy, but with right. In this context, hospitality means the right of a stranger not to be treated with hostility when he arrives on someone else's territory. He can indeed be turned away, if this can be done without causing his death, but he must not be treated with hostility, so long as he behaves in a peaceable manner in the place he happens to be in. The stranger cannot claim the right of a guest to be entertained, for this would require a special friendly agreement whereby he might become a member of the native household for a certain time. He may only claim a right of resort, for all men are entitled to present themselves in the society of others by virtue of their right to communal possession of the earth's surface. Since the earth is a globe, they cannot disperse over an infinite area, but must necessarily tolerate one another's company. And no one originally has any greater right than anyone else to occupy any particular portion of the earth. The community of man is divided by uninhabitable parts of the earth's surface such as oceans and deserts, but even then, the ship or the camel（the ship of the desert） make it possible for them to approach their fellows over these ownerless tracts, and to utilize as a means of social intercourse that right to the earth's surface which the human race shares in common. The inhospitable behaviour of coastal dwellers（as on the Barbary coast） in plundering ships on the adjoining seas or enslaving stranded seafarers, or that of inhabitants of the desert（as with the Arab Bedouins）, who regard their proximity to nomadic tribes as a justification for plundering them, is contrary to natural right. But this natural right of hospitality, i.e. the right of strangers, does not extend beyond those conditions which make it possible for them to attempt to enter into relations with the native inhabitants. In this way, continents distant from each other can enter into peaceful mutual relations which may eventually be regulated by public laws, thus bringing the human race nearer and nearer to a cosmopolitan constitution.

If we compare with this ultimate end the inhospitable conduct of the civilized states of our continent, especially the commercial states, the injustice which they display in visiting foreign countries and peoples（which in their case is the same as conquering them） seems appallingly great. America, the negro countries, the Spice Islands, the Cape, etc. were looked upon at the time of their discovery as ownerless territories; for the native inhabitants were counted as nothing. In East India（Hindustan）, foreign troops were brought in under the pretext of merely setting up trading posts. This led to oppression of the natives, incitement of the various Indian states to widespread wars, famine, insurrection, treachery and the whole litany of evils which can afflict the human race.

China[9] and Japan（Nippon）, having had experience of such guests, have wisely placed restrictions on them. China permits contact with her territories, but not entrance into them, while Japan only allows contact with a single European people, the Dutch, although they are still segregated from the native community like prisoners. The worst（or, from the point of view of moral judgements, the best） thing about all this is that the commercial states do not even benefit by their violence, for all their trading companies are on the point of collapse. The Sugar Islands, that stronghold of the cruellest and most calculated slavery, do not yield any real profit; they serve only the indirect（and not entirely laudable） purpose of training sailors for warships, thereby aiding the prosecution of wars in Europe. And all this is the work of powers who make endless ado about their piety, and who wish to be considered as chosen believers while they live on the fruits of iniquity.

The peoples of the earth have thus entered in varying degrees into a universal community, and it has developed to the point where a violation of rights in one part of the world is felt everywhere. The idea of a cosmopolitan right is therefore not fantastic and overstrained; it is a necessary complement to the unwritten code of political and international right, transforming it into a universal right of humanity. Only under this condition can we flatter ourselves that we are continually advancing towards a perpetual peace.

First Supplement: On the Guarantee of a Perpetual Peace

Perpetual peace is guaranteed by no less an authority than the great artist Nature herself（natura daedala rerum [Nature the contriver of things]）. The mechanical process of nature visibly exhibits the purposive plan of producing concord among men, even against their will and indeed by means of their very discord. This design, if we regard it as a compelling cause whose laws of operation are unknown to us, is called fate. But if we consider its purposive function within the world's development, whereby it appears as the underlying wisdom of a higher cause, showing the way towards the objective goal of the human race and predetermining the world's evolution, we call it providence.[10] We cannot actually observe such an agency in the artifices of nature, nor can we even infer its existence from them. But as with all relations between the form of things and their ultimate purposes, we can and must supply it mentally in order to conceive of its possibility by analogy with human artifices. Its relationship to and conformity with the end which reason directly prescribes to us（i.e. the end of morality） can only be conceived of as an idea. Yet while this idea is indeed far-fetched in theory, it does possess dogmatic validity and has a very real foundation in practice, as with the concept of perpetual peace, which makes it our duty to promote it by using the natural mechanism described above. But in contexts such as this, where we are concerned purely with theory and not with religion, we should also note that it is more in keeping with the limitations of human reason to speak of nature and not of providence, for reason, in dealing with cause and effect relationships, must keep within the bounds of possible experience. Modesty forbids us to speak of providence as something we can recognize, for this would mean donning the wings of Icarus and presuming to approach the mystery of its inscrutable intentions.

But before we define this guarantee more precisely, we must first examine the situation in which nature has placed the actors in her great spectacle, for it is this situation which ultimately demands the guarantee of peace. We may next inquire in what manner the guarantee is provided.

Nature's provisional arrangement is as follows. Firstly, she has taken care that human beings are able to live in all the areas where they are settled. Secondly, she has driven them in all directions by means of war, so that they inhabit even the most inhospitable regions. And thirdly, she has compelled them by the same means to enter into more or less legal relationships. It is in itself wonderful that moss can still grow in the cold wastes around the Arctic Ocean; the reindeer can scrape it out from beneath the snow, and can thus itself serve as nourishment or as a draft animal for the Ostiaks or Samoyeds. Similarly, the sandy salt deserts contain the camel, which seems as if it had been created for travelling over them in order that they might not be left unutilized. But evidence of design in nature emerges even more clearly when we realize that the shores of the Arctic Ocean are inhabited not only by fur-bearing animals, but also by seals, walruses and whales, whose flesh provides food and whose fat provides warmth for the native inhabitants. Nature's care arouses most admiration, however, by carrying driftwood to these treeless regions, without anyone knowing exactly where it comes from. For if they did not have this material, the natives would not be able to construct either boats or weapons, or dwellings in which to live. And they have enough to do making war on the animals to be able to live in peace among themselves. But it was probably nothing but war which drove them into these regions. And the first instrument of war among all the animals which man learned to domesticate in the course of peopling the earth was the horse. For the elephant belongs to that later age of luxury which began after states had been established. The same applies to the art of cultivating certain kinds of grasses known as cereals, whose original nature is now unknown to us, and to the production and refinement of various fruits by transplanting and grafting（in Europe, perhaps only two species were involved, the crab-apple and the wild pear）. Such arts could arise only within established states in which landed property was secure, after men had made the transition to an agricultural way of life, abandoning the lawless freedom they had enjoyed in their previous existence as hunters,[11] fishers and shepherds. Salt and iron were next discovered, and were perhaps the first articles of trade between nations to be in demand everywhere. In this way, nations first entered into peaceful relations with one another, and thus achieved mutual understanding, community of interests and peaceful relations, even with the most distant of their fellows.

In seeing to it that men could live everywhere on earth, nature has at the same time despotically willed that they should live everywhere, even against their own inclinations. And this obligation does not rest upon any concept of duty which might bind them to fulfil it in accordance with a moral law; on the contrary, nature has chosen war as a means of attaining this end.

We can observe nations which reveal the unity of their descent by the unity of their language. This is the case with the Samoyeds on the Arctic Ocean and another people with a similar language living two hundred miles away in the Altai Mountains; another people of Mongol extraction, given to horsemanship and hence to warlike pursuits, has pushed its way between them, thus driving the one part of the tribe far away from the other into the most inhospitable Arctic regions, where it would certainly not have gone by its own inclinations.[12] In the same way, the Finns in the northernmost region of Europe（where they are known as Lapps） are now far separated from the Hungarians, to whom they are linguistically related, by Gothic and Sarmatian peoples who have pushed their way in between them. And what else but war, nature's means of peopling the whole earth, can have driven the Eskimos so far North – for they are quite distinct from all other American races, and are perhaps descended from European adventurers of ancient times; the Pesherae have been driven South into Tierra del Fuego in the same manner. War itself, however, does not require any particular kind of motivation, for it seems to be ingrained in human nature, and even to be regarded as something noble to which man is inspired by his love of honour, without selfish motives. Thus warlike courage, with the American savages as with their European counterparts in medieval times, is held to be of great and immediate value–and not just in times of war（as might be expected）, but also in order that there may be war. Thus wars are often started merely to display this quality, so that war itself is invested with an inherent dignity; for even philosophers have eulogized it as a kind of ennobling influence on man, forgetting the Greek saying that ‘war is bad in that it produces more evil people than it destroys’. So much, then, for what nature does to further her own end with respect to the human race as an animal species.

We now come to the essential question regarding the prospect of perpetual peace. What does nature do in relation to the end which man's own reason prescribes to him as a duty, i.e. how does nature help to promote his moral purpose? And how does nature guarantee that what man ought to do by the laws of his freedom（but does not do） will in fact be done through nature's compulsion, without prejudice to the free agency of man? This question arises, moreover, in all three areas of public right–in political, international and cosmopolitan right. For if I say that nature wills that this or that should happen, this does not mean that nature imposes on us a duty to do it, for duties can only be imposed by practical reason, acting without any external constraint. On the contrary, nature does it herself, whether we are willing or not: fata volentem ducunt, nolentem trahunt [‘the fates lead him who is willing, but drag him who is unwilling’].

1. Even if people were not compelled by internal dissent to submit to the coercion of public laws, war would produce the same effect from outside. For in accordance with the natural arrangement described above, each people would find itself confronted by another neighbouring people pressing in upon it, thus forcing it to form itself internally into a state in order to encounter the other as an armed power. Now the republican constitution is the only one which does complete justice to the rights of man. But it is also the most difficult to establish, and even more so to preserve, so that many maintain that it would only be possible within a state of angels, since men, with their self-seeking inclinations, would be incapable of adhering to a constitution of so sublime a nature. But in fact, nature comes to the aid of the universal and rational human will, so admirable in itself but so impotent in practice, and makes use of precisely those self-seeking inclinations in order to do so. It only remains for men to create a good organization for the state, a task which is well within their capability, and to arrange it in such a way that their self-seeking energies are opposed to one another, each thereby neutralizing or eliminating the destructive effects of the rest. And as far as reason is concerned, the result is the same as if man's selfish tendencies were non-existent, so that man, even if he is not morally good in himself, is nevertheless compelled to be a good citizen. As hard as it may sound, the problem of setting up a state can be solved even by a nation of devils（so long as they possess understanding）. It may be stated as follows:‘In order to organize a group of rational beings who together require universal laws for their survival, but of whom each separate individual is secretly inclined to exempt himself from them, the constitution must be so designed that, although the citizens are opposed to one another in their private attitudes, these opposing views may inhibit one another in such a way that the public conduct of the citizens will be the same as if they did not have such evil attitudes.’ A problem of this kind must be soluble. For such a task does not involve the moral improvement of man; it only means finding out how the mechanism of nature can be applied to men in such a manner that the antagonism of their hostile attitudes will make them compel one another to submit to coercive laws, thereby producing a condition of peace within which the laws can be enforced. We can even see this principle at work among the actually existing（although as yet very imperfectly organized） states. For in their external relations, they have already approached what the idea of right prescribes, although the reason for this is certainly not their internal moral attitudes. In the same way, we cannot expect their moral attitudes to produce a good political constitution; on the contrary, it is only through the latter that the people can be expected to attain a good level of moral culture. Thus that mechanism of nature by which selfish inclinations are naturally opposed to one another in their external relations can be used by reason to facilitate the attainment of its own end, the reign of established right. Internal and external peace are thereby furthered and assured, so far as it lies within the power of the state itself to do so. We may therefore say that nature irresistibly wills that right should eventually gain the upper hand. What men have neglected to do will ultimately happen of its own accord, albeit with much inconvenience. As Bouterwek puts it:‘If the reed is bent too far, it breaks; and he who wants too much gets nothing.’

2. The idea of international right presupposes the separate existence of many independent adjoining states. And such a state of affairs is essentially a state of war, unless there is a federal union to prevent hostilities breaking out. But in the light of the idea of reason, this state is still to be preferred to an amalgamation of the separate nations under a single power which has overruled the rest and created a universal monarchy. For the laws progressively lose their impact as the government increases its range, and a soulless despotism, after crush-ing the germs of goodness, will finally lapse into anarchy. It is nonetheless the desire of every state（or its ruler） to achieve lasting peace by thus dominating the whole world, if at all possible. But nature wills it otherwise, and uses two means to separate the nations and prevent them from intermingling–linguistic and religious[13] differences. These may certainly occasion mutual hatred and provide pretexts for wars, but as culture grows and men gradually move towards greater agreement over their principles, they lead to mutual understanding and peace. And unlike that universal despotism which saps all man's energies and ends in the graveyard of freedom, this peace is created and guaranteed by an equilibrium of forces and a most vigorous rivalry.

3. Thus nature wisely separates the nations, although the will of each individual state, even basing its arguments on international right, would gladly unite them under its own sway by force or by cunning. On the other hand, nature also unites nations which the concept of cosmopolitan right would not have protected from violence and war, and does so by means of their mutual self-interest. For the spirit of commerce sooner or later takes hold of every people, and it cannot exist side by side with war. And of all the powers（or means） at the disposal of the power of the state, financial power can probably be relied on most. Thus states find themselves compelled to promote the noble cause of peace, though not exactly from motives of morality. And wherever in the world there is a threat of war breaking out, they will try to prevent it by mediation, just as if they had entered into a permanent league for this purpose; for by the very nature of things, large military alliances can only rarely be formed, and will even more rarely be successful.

In this way, nature guarantees perpetual peace by the actual mechanism of human inclinations. And while the likelihood of its being attained is not sufficient to enable us to prophesy the future theoretically, it is enough for practical purposes. It makes it our duty to work our way towards this goal, which is more than an empty chimera.

Second Supplement: Secret Article of a Perpetual Peace

In transactions involving public right, a secret article（regarded objectively or in terms of its content） is a contradiction. But in subjective terms, i.e. in relation to the sort of person who dictates it, an article may well contain a secret element, for the person concerned may consider it prejudicial to his own dignity to name himself publicly as its originator.

The only article of this kind is embodied in the following sentence: ‘The maxims of the philosophers on the conditions under which public peace is possible shall be consulted by states which are armed for war.’

Although it may seem humiliating for the legislative authority of a state, to which we must naturally attribute the highest degree of wisdom, to seek instruction from subjects（the philosophers） regarding the principles on which it should act in its relations with other states, it is nevertheless extremely advisable that it should do so. The state will therefore invite their help silently, making a secret of it. In other words, it will allow them to speak freely and publicly on the universal maxims of warfare and peace-making, and they will indeed do so of their own accord if no one forbids their discussions. And no special formal arrangement among the states is necessary to enable them to agree on this issue, for the agreement already lies in the obligations imposed by universal human reason in its capacity as a moral legislator. This does not, however, imply that the state must give the principles of the philosopher precedence over the pronouncements of the jurist（who represents the power of the state）, but only that the philosopher should be given a hearing. The jurist, who has taken as his symbol the scales of right and the sword of justice, usually uses the latter not merely to keep any extraneous influences away from the former, but will throw the sword into one of the scales if it refuses to sink（vae victis!）. Unless the jurist is at the same time a philosopher, at any rate in moral matters, he is under the greatest temptation to do this, for his business is merely to apply existing laws, and not to inquire whether they are in need of improvement. He acts as if this truly low rank of his faculty were in fact one of the higher ones, for the simple reason that it is accompanied by power（as is also the case with two of the other faculties）. But the philosophical faculty occupies a very low position in face of the combined power of the others. Thus we are told, for instance, that philosophy is the handmaid of theology, and something similar in relation to the others. But it is far from clear whether this handmaid bears the torch before her gracious lady, or carries the train behind.

It is not to be expected that kings will philosophize or that philosophers will become kings; nor is it to be desired, however, since the possession of power inevitably corrupts the free judgement of reason. Kings or sovereign peoples（i.e. those governing themselves by egalitarian laws） should not, however, force the class of philosophers to disappear or to remain silent, but should allow them to speak publicly. This is essential to both in order that light may be thrown on their affairs. And since the class of philosophers is by nature incapable of forming seditious factions or clubs, they cannot incur suspicion of disseminating propaganda.

————————————————————

[1] A hereditary kingdom is not a state which can be inherited by another state. Only the right to rule over it may be bequeathed to another physical person. In this case, the state acquires a ruler, but the ruler as such（i.e. as one who already has another kingdom） does not acquire the state.

[2] It has hitherto been doubted, not without justification, whether there can be permissive laws（leges permissivae） in addition to preceptive laws（leges praeceptivae） and prohibitive laws （leges prohibitivae）. For all laws embody an element of objective practical necessity as a reason for certain actions, whereas a permission depends only upon practical contingencies. Thus a permissive law would be a compulsion to do something which one cannot be compelled to do, and if the object of the law were the same as that of the permission, a contradiction would result. But in the permissive law contained in the second article above, the initial prohibition applies only to the mode of acquiring a right in the future（e.g. by inheritance）, whereas the exemption from this prohibition（i.e. the permissive part of the law） applies to the state of political possessions in the present. For in accordance with a permissive law of natural right, this present state can be allowed to remain even although the state of nature has been abandoned for that of civil society. And even if these present possessions are unlawful, they are nevertheless honest（possessio putativa）. A putative possession is prohibited, however, as soon as it has been recognized as such, both in the state of nature and after the subsequent transition to civil society（if the mode of acquisition is the same）. And continued possession could not be permitted if the supposed acquisition had been made in the state of civil society, for it would then have to end immediately, as an offence against right, as soon as its unlawfulness had been discovered.

My intention here was merely to point out briefly to exponents of natural right the concept of a permissive law, which automatically presents itself within the systematic divisions of reason. It is especially noteworthy since it is frequently used in civil or statutory law, with the one difference that the prohibitive part of the law exists independently, and the permissive part is not included within the law itself as a limiting condition（as it ought to be）, but added to cover exceptional cases. Such laws usually state that this or that is prohibited, except in cases 1, 2 or 3, and so on ad infinitum, for permissive clauses are only added to the law fortuitously, by a random review of particular cases, and not in accordance with any definite principle. Otherwise, the limiting conditions would have had to be included in the actual formula of the prohibitive law, whereby it would have become a permissive law in itself. It is therefore to be regretted that the ingenious but unsolved competition question submitted by that wise and clear-sighted gentleman, Count Windischgrätz, was so soon abandoned, for it might have solved the legal difficulty we are at present discussing. For the possibility of finding a universal formula like those of mathematics is the only true test of consistent legislation, and without it, the so-called ius certum must remain no more than a pious hope. Otherwise, we shall only have general laws（i.e. laws valid in general）, but no universal laws（i.e. laws which are generally valid） such as the concept of a law seems to demand.

[3] It is usually assumed that one cannot take hostile action against anyone unless one has already been actively injured by them. This is perfectly correct if both parties are living in a legal civil state. For the fact that the one has entered such a state gives the required guarantee to the other, since both are subject to the same authority. But man（or an individual people） in a mere state of nature robs me of any such security and injures me by virtue of this very state in which he coexists with me. He may not have injured me actively（facto）, but he does injure me by the very lawlessness of his state（statu iniusto）, for he is a permanent threat to me, and I can require him either to enter into a common lawful state along with me or to move away from my vicinity. Thus the postulate on which all the following articles are based is that all men who can at all influence one another must adhere to some kind of civil constitution. But any legal constitution, as far as the persons who live under it are concerned, will conform to one of the three following types:

（1） a constitution based on the civil right of individuals within a nation（ius civitatis）.

（2） a constitution based on the international right of states in their relationships with one another（ius gentium）.

（3） a constitution based on cosmopolitan right, in so far as individuals and states, coexisting in an external relationship of mutual influences, may be regarded as citizens of a universal state of mankind（ius cosmopoliticum）. This classification, with respect to the idea of a perpetual peace, is not arbitrary, but necessary. For if even one of the parties were able to influence the others physically and yet itself remained in a state of nature, there would be a risk of war, which it is precisely the aim of the above articles to prevent.

[4] Rightful（i.e. external） freedom cannot, as is usually thought, be defined as a warrant to do whatever one wishes unless it means doing injustice to others. For what is meant by a warrant? It means a possibility of acting in a certain way so long as this action does not do any injustice to others. Thus the definition would run as follows: freedom is the possibility of acting in ways which do no injustice to others. That is, we do no injustice to others（no matter what we may actually do） if we do no injustice to others. Thus the definition is an empty tautology. In fact, my external and rightful freedom should be defined as a warrant to obey no external laws except those to which I have been able to give my own consent. Similarly, external and rightful equality within a state is that relationship among the citizens whereby no one can put anyone else under a legal obligation without submitting simultaneously to a law which requires that he can himself be put under the same kind of obligation by the other person.（And we do not need to define the principle of legal dependence, since it is always implied in the concept of a political constitution.） The validity of these innate and inalienable rights, the necessary property of mankind, is confirmed and enhanced by the principle that man may have lawful relations even with higher beings（if he believes in the latter）. For he may consider himself as a citizen of a transcendental world, to which the same principles apply. And as regards my freedom, I am not under any obligation even to divine laws（which I can recognize by reason alone）, except in so far as I have been able to give my own consent to them; for I can form a conception of the divine will only in terms of the law of freedom of my own reason. As for the principle of equality in relation to the most exalted being I can conceive of, apart from God（e.g. a power such as Aeon）, there is no reason, if I and this higher being are both doing our duty in our own stations, why it should be my duty to obey while he should enjoy the right to command. But the reason why this principle of equality（unlike that of freedom） does not apply to a relationship towards God, is that God is the only being for whom the concept of duty ceases to be valid.

But as for the right of equality of all citizens as subjects, we may ask whether a hereditary aristocracy is admissible. The answer to this question will depend entirely on whether more importance is attached to the superior rank granted by the state to one subject over another than is attached to merit, or vice versa. Now it is obvious that if rank is conferred according to birth, it will be quite uncertain whether merit（skill and devotion within one's office） will accompany it; it will be tantamount to conferring a position of command upon a favoured individual without any merit on his part, and this could never be approved by the general will of the people in an original contract, which is, after all, the principle behind all rights. For it does not necessarily follow that a nobleman is also a noble man. And as for a nobility of office, i.e. the rank of a higher magistracy which can be attained by merit, the rank does not attach as a possession to the person, but to the post occupied by the person, and this does not violate the principle of equality. For when a person lays down his office, he simultaneously resigns his rank and again becomes one of the people.

[5] Many have criticized the high-sounding appellations which are often bestowed on a ruler（e.g.‘the divine anointed’, or‘the executor and representative of the divine will on earth’） as gross and extravagant flatteries, but it seems to me without reason. Far from making the ruler of the land arrogant, they ought rather to fill his soul with humility. For if he is a man of understanding（which we must certainly assume）, he will reflect that he has taken over an office which is too great for a human being, namely that of administering God's most sacred institution on earth, the rights of man; he will always live in fear of having in any way injured God's most valued possession.

[6] Mallet du Pan, in his flamboyant but hollow and empty style, boasts of having at last, after many years of experience, become convinced of the truth of Pope's famous saying:‘For forms of government let fools contest; Whate'er is best administered is best.’If this means that the best administered government is the best administered, he has cracked a nut（as Swift puts it） and been rewarded with a worm. But if it means that the best administered government is also the best kind of government（i.e. the best constitution）, it is completely false, for examples of good governments prove nothing whatsoever about kinds of government. Who, indeed, governed better than a Titus or a Marcus Aurelius, and yet the one left a Domitian as his successor, and the other a Commodus. And this could not have happened under a good constitution, since their unsuitability for the post of ruler was known early enough, and the power of their predecessors was great enough to have excluded them from the succession.

[7] Thus a Bulgarian prince, replying to the Greek Emperor who had kindly offered to settle his dispute with him by a duel, declared:‘A smith who possesses tongs will not lift the glowing iron out of the coals with his own hands.’

[8] At the end of a war, when peace is concluded, it would not be inappropriate for a people to appoint a day of atonement after the festival of thanksgiving. Heaven would be invoked in the name of the state to forgive the human race for the great sin of which it continues to be guilty, since it will not accommodate itself to a lawful constitution in international relations. Proud of its independence, each state prefers to employ the barbarous expedient of war, although war cannot produce the desired decision on the rights of particular states. The thanksgivings for individual victories during a war, the hymns which are sung（in the style of the Israelites） to the Lord of Hosts, contrast no less markedly with the moral conception of a father of mankind. For besides displaying indifference to the way in which nations pursue their mutual rights（deplorable though it is）, they actually rejoice at having annihilated numerous human beings or their happiness.

[9] If we wish to give this great empire the name by which it calls itself（i.e. China, not Sina or any similar form）, we need only consult Georgi's Alphabetum Tibetanum, pp. 651–654, note b in particular. According to Professor Fischer of Petersburg, it actually has no fixed name which it might apply to itself; the commonest one is still the word Kin, which means gold（the Tibetans, however, call this Ser）, which explains why the emperor is called King of Gold（i.e. of the fairest land in the world）. The word is apparently pronounced Chin in the land itself, but expressed as Kin by the Italian missionaries, who cannot pronounce the correct guttural sound. It can also be seen that what the Romans called the land of the people of Ser was in fact China, and silk was brought from there to Europe via Greater Tibet（probably crossing Lesser Tibet, Bukhara and Persia）. This led to numerous speculations on the antiquity of this extraordinary state as compared with that of Hindustan, and on its relations with Tibet as well as with Japan. But the name Sina or Tschina, which neighbouring countries allegedly use of it, leads nowhere.

Perhaps the ancient but hitherto obscure community between Europe and Tibet can be explained from what Hesychius has recorded of the hierophant's cryΚονζ'Ομπαζ（Konx Ompax） in the Eleusinian Mysteries（cf. Journey of the Younger Anacharsis, Part Ⅴ, p. 447 et seq.）. For according to Georgi's Alphabetum Tibetanum, the word Concioa means god, and it markedly resembles Konx, while Pahcio（ibid. p. 520）, which the Greeks might easily have pronounced pax, means promulgator legis, the divinity which pervades the whole of nature（also called Cencresi, p. 177）. But Om, which La Croze translates as benedictus（blessed）, can scarcely mean anything other than beatific if applied to the deity（p. 507）. When P. Francisco Orazio asked the Tibetan lamas how they conceived of god （Concioa）, he always received the answer:‘God is the community of all the holy ones’（i.e. the community of blessed souls, at last reunited in the deity by being reborn as lamas after numerous migrations through all kinds of bodies, and thereby transformed into beings worthy of adoration – p.223）. Thus the mysterious name Konx Ompax might designate that holy（Konx）, heavenly（Om） and wise（Pax） supreme being who pervades the whole world, i.e. nature personified. As used in the Greek mysteries, it may well have signified monotheism to the epopts, as distinct from the polytheism of the uninitiated mass, although it savoured of atheism to P. Orazio（loc. cit.）. Our earlier considerations should help to explain how this mysterious name reached the Greeks from Tibet; conversely, this influence makes it appear probable that Europe at an early date had contact with China by way of Tibet, perhaps even earlier than with India.

[10] In the mechanism of nature, of which man（as a sensory being） is a part, there is evident a fundamental form on which its very existence depends. This form becomes intelligible to us only if we attribute it to the design of a universal creator who has determined it in advance. We call this predetermining influence divine providence, and further define it as original providence in so far as it is active from the earliest times onwards（providentia conditrix; semel iussit, semper parent [As soon as he has given the command, they obey without fail] – Augustine）. In as much as it sustains the course of nature in accordance with purposive universal laws, we call it ruling providence（providentia gubernatrix）. If it realizes particular ends which man could not have foreseen and whose existence can only be guessed at from the results, it is termed guiding providence（providentia directrix）. And finally, if individual events are regarded as divinely intended, we no longer speak of providence but of a special dispensation（directio extraordinaria）. But it is foolish presumption for man to claim that he can recognize this as such, since it implies that a miracle has taken place, even if the events are not specifically described as miraculous. For however pious and humble it may sound, it is absurd and self-conceited for anyone to conclude from a single event that the efficient cause is governed by a special principle, or that the event in question is an end in itself and not just the natural and mechanical consequence of another end which is completely unknown to us. Similarly, it is false and self-contradictory to classify providence in terms of worldly objects（materialiter）, dividing it up into general and particular, as occurs in the doctrine that providence takes care to preserve the various species of creatures, but leaves chance to look after the individuals; for the whole point of saying that providence applies in general is that no single object should be excepted from it. This classification, however, was probably meant to indicate that the intentions of providence are carried out in different ways（formaliter）. These might be ordinary（e.g. the annual death and revival of nature with the changes of seasons） or extraordinary（e.g. the transporting of wood by Ocean currents to Arctic coasts where it cannot grow, thus providing for the native inhabitants, who could not live without it）. In the latter case, while we can well explain the physico-mechanical cause of the phenomena in question（e.g. by the fact that the riverbanks in temperate lands are covered in forests, so that the trees may fall into the rivers and be carried further a field by currents like the Gulf Stream）, we must not on the other hand overlook teleology, which indicates the foresight of a wise agency governing nature. But the conception, current in the academic world, of a divine participation or collaboration（concursus） in effects experienced in the world of the senses, is superfluous. For firstly, it is self-contradictory to try to harness disparates together（gryphes iungere equis [to harness griffins with horses]）, and to imply that a being who is himself the complete cause of the world's developments has to supplement his own predetermining providence during the course of world events（so that it must originally have been inadequate）; for example, it is absurd to say that after God, the doctor acted as an assistant in curing the patient – causa solitaria non invat [a single cause does not suffice]. God is the creator of the doctor and of all his medicaments, so that the effect must be ascribed entirely to him if we are to ascend to that supreme original cause which is theoretically beyond our comprehension. Alternatively, it can be ascribed entirely to the doctor, in so far as we treat the event in question as belonging to the order of nature and as capable of explanation within the causal series of earthly occurrences. And secondly, if we adopt such attitudes, we are deprived of all definite principles by which we might judge effects. But the concept of a divine concursus is completely acceptable and indeed necessary in the moral and practical sense, which refers exclusively to the transcendental world. For example, we may say that we should never cease to strive towards goodness, for we believe that God, even by means which we cannot comprehend, will make up for our own lack of righteousness so long as our attitude is sincere. It is, however, self-evident that no one should use such arguments to explain a good deed, regarded as a secular event, for this would presuppose theoretical knowledge of the transcendental, which it is absurd for us to claim.

[11] Of all ways of life, that of the hunter is undoubtedly most at odds with a civilized constitution. For families, having to live in separation, soon become strangers to each other, and subsequently, being scattered about in wide forests, they treat each other with hostility, since each requires a large area to provide itself with food and clothing. The command addressed to Noah forbidding the eating of blood（Genesis 9, 4–6） seems to have been originally nothing else but a prohibition of the hunter's way of life. For this must often involve eating uncooked meat, and if the latter is forbidden, the first is automatically ruled out too. This prohibition, often reiterated, was a condition later imposed by the Jewish Christians upon the newly accepted Christians of heathen origin, albeit with a different intention（Acts 15, 20 and 21, 25）.

[12] The following question might be raised. If nature intended that these frozen shores should not remain uninhabited, what will happen to their inhabitants if nature, as indeed may well happen, ceases to provide them with driftwood? For we may well believe that the natives of temperate zones, as their culture progresses, will make better use of the wood which grows on the banks of their rivers, and will not allow it to fall into them and be swept out to sea. I should reply that those who live on the Ob, the Yenisei, the Lena etc. will supply them with it commercially, bartering it for the animal products in which the Arctic coasts are so plentiful – but only after nature has compelled them to live in peace with one another.

[13] Religious differences – an odd expression! As if we were to speak of different moralities. There may certainly be different historical confessions, although these have nothing to do with religion itself but only with changes in the means used to further religion, and are thus the province of historical research. And there may be just as many different religious books（the Zend-Avesta, the Vedas, the Koran, etc.）. But there can only be one religion which is valid for all men and at all times. Thus the different confessions can scarcely be more than the vehicles of religion; these are fortuitous, and may vary with differences in time or place.

Appendix

I
On the Disagreement between Morals and Politics in Relation to Perpetual Peace

Morality, as a collection of absolutely binding laws by which our actions ought to be governed, belongs essentially, in an objective sense, to the practical sphere. And if we have once acknowledged the authority of this concept of duty, it is patently absurd to say that we cannot act as the moral laws require. For if this were the case, the concept of duty would automatically be dropped from morals（ultra posse nemo obligatur [no one is obliged to do anything he is incapable of doing]）. Hence there can be no conflict between politics, as an applied branch of right, and morality, as a theoretical branch of right（i.e. between theory and practice）; for such a conflict could occur only if morality were taken to mean a general doctrine of expediency, i.e. a theory of the maxims by which one might select the most useful means of furthering one's own advantage – and this would be tantamount to denying that morality exists.

If politics were to say: ‘Be ye therefore wise as serpents’, morality might add, by way of qualification: ‘and harmless as doves’. If these two precepts cannot exist together within a single commandment, then there is indeed a disagreement between politics and morality. But if the two are to be united, it is absurd to suppose that they are in opposition, and the question of how such a conflict could be resolved cannot even be posed as a mental exercise. It is true, alas, that the saying ‘Honesty is the best policy’ embodies a theory which is frequently contradicted by practice. Yet the equally theoretical proposition ‘Honesty is better than any policy’ infinitely transcends all objections, and it is indeed an indispensable condition of any policy whatsoever. The god of morality does not yield to Jupiter, the custodian of violence, for even Jupiter is still subject to fate. In short, reason is not sufficiently enlightened to discover the whole series of predetermining causes which would allow it to predict accurately the happy or unhappy consequences of human activities as dictated by the mechanism of nature; it can only hope that the result will meet with its wishes. But reason at all times shows us clearly enough what we have to do in order to remain on the paths of duty, as the rules of wisdom require, and thus shows us the way towards our ultimate goal.

But the man of practice, to whom morality is pure theory, coldly repudiates our well-intentioned hopes, even if he does concede that we can do what we ought to do. He bases his argument on the claim that we can tell in advance from human nature that man will never want to do what is necessary in order to attain the goal of eternal peace. It is perfectly true that the will of all individual men to live in accordance with principles of freedom within a lawful constitution（i.e. the distributive unity of the will of all） is not sufficient for this purpose. Before so difficult a problem can be solved, all men together（i.e. the collective unity of the combined will） must desire to attain this goal; only then can civil society exist as a single whole. Since an additional unifying cause must therefore overrule the differences in the particular wishes of all individuals before a common will can arise, and since no single individual can create it, the only conceivable way of executing the original idea in practice, and hence of inaugurating a state of right, is by force. On its coercive authority, public right will subsequently be based.

We can certainly expect in advance that there will be considerable deviations in actual experience from the original theoretical idea. For we cannot assume that the moral attitude of the legislator will be such that, after the disorderly mass has been united into a people, he will leave them to create a lawful constitution by their own common will.

It might thus be said that, once a person has the power in his own hands, he will not let the people prescribe laws for him. Similarly, a state which is self-governing and free from all external laws will not let itself become dependent on the judgement of other states in seeking to uphold its rights against them. And even a whole continent, if it feels itself in a superior position to another one, will not hesitate to plunder it or actually to extend its rule over it, irrespective of whether the other is in its way or not. In this way, all the plans which theory lays for political, international or cosmopolitan right dissolve into empty and impracticable ideals; but a practice which is based on empirical principles of human nature, and which does not consider it beneath its dignity to shape its maxims according to the way of the world, can alone hope to find a solid foundation for its system of political opportunism.

If, of course, there is neither freedom nor any moral law based on freedom, but only a state in which everything that happens or can happen simply obeys the mechanical workings of nature, politics would mean the art of utilizing nature for the government of men, and this would constitute the whole of practical wisdom; the concept of right would then be only an empty idea. But if we consider it absolutely necessary to couple the concept of right with politics, or even to make it a limiting condition of politics, it must be conceded that the two are compatible. And I can indeed imagine a moral politician, i.e. someone who conceives of the principles of political expediency in such a way that they can co-exist with morality, but I cannot imagine a political moralist, i.e. one who fashions his morality to suit his own advantage as a statesman.

The moral politician will make it a principle that, if any faults which could not have been prevented are discovered in the political constitution or in the relations between states, it is a duty, especially for heads of state, to see to it that they are corrected as soon as possible; it should be ensured that these political institutions are made to conform to natural right, which stands before us as a model in the idea of practical reason, and this should be done even if selfish interests have to be sacrificed. It would be contrary to all political expediency, which in this case agrees with morality, to destroy any of the existing bonds of political or cosmopolitan union before a better constitution has been prepared to take their place. And while it would be absurd to demand that their faults be repaired at once and by violent measures, it can still be required of the individual in power that he should be intimately aware of the maxim that changes for the better are necessary, in order that the constitution may constantly approach the optimum end prescribed by laws of right. A state may well govern itself in a republican way, even if its existing constitution provides for a despotic ruling power; and it will gradually come to the stage where the people can be influenced by the mere idea of the law's authority, just as if it were backed up by physical force, so that they will be able to create for themselves a legislation ultimately founded on right. If, however, a more lawful constitution were attained by unlawful means, i.e. by a violent revolution resulting from a previous bad constitution, it would then no longer be permissible to lead the people back to the original one, even although everyone who had interfered with the old constitution by violence or conspiracy would rightly have been subject to the penalties of rebellion during the revolution itself. But as for the external relationship between states, no state can be required to relinquish its constitution, even if the latter is despotic（and hence stronger in relation to external enemies）, so long as this state is in danger of being engulfed at any moment by other states; hence while plans must be made for political improvement, it must be permissible to delay their execution until a better opportunity arises.[14]

It may well be the case that despotic moralists, i.e. those who err in practice, frequently act contrary to political prudence by adopting or recommending premature measures, yet experience must gradually bring them out of their opposition to nature and make them adopt better ways. But moralizing politicians, for what they are worth, try to cover up political principles which are contrary to right, under the pretext that human nature is incapable of attaining the good which reason prescribes as an idea. They thereby make progress impossible, and eternalize the violation of right.

Instead of applying the correct practice they boast of, these worldly-wise politicians resort to despicable tricks, for they are only out to exploit the people（and if possible the whole world） by influencing the current ruling power in such a way as to ensure their own private advantage. They are just like lawyers（i.e. those for whom law is a profession, not a matter of legislation） who have found their way into politics. For since it is not their business to argue over legislation itself, but to fulfil the present instructions of the law of the land, they will always regard the existing legal constitution（or, if this is altered by a higher authority, the subsequent one） as the best, because everything in it will follow a proper mechanical order. But this skill in being all things to all men may give them the illusion that they can also pass judgement, in accordance with concepts of right（i.e. a priori, not empirically）, on the principles of any political constitution whatsoever. And they may boast that they know men（which is certainly to be expected, since they have to do with so many of them）, although they do not know man and his potentialities, for this requires a higher anthropological vantage-point.

Armed with concepts such as these, they proceed to take up political and international law as prescribed by reason. But they cannot take this step except in a spirit of chicanery, for they will follow their usual procedure of applying despotically formulated coercive laws in a mechanical manner, even in a sphere where the concepts of reason only allow for lawful coercion, in keeping with the principles of freedom, which alone make possible a rightfully established political constitution. The supposed practitioner believes he can solve this problem empirically, ignoring the idea of reason and drawing on experience of how the（largely unlawful） constitutions which have hitherto survived best were organized. And the maxims which he employs for this purpose, although he does not make them public, can roughly be expressed in the following sophistries:

1. Fac et excusa [Act first and justify your actions later]. Seize any favourable opportunity of arbitrarily expropriating a right which the state enjoys over its own or over a neighbouring people; the justification can be presented far more easily and elegantly and the use of violence can be glossed over far more readily after the fact than if one were to think out convincing reasons in advance and then wait for counter-arguments to be offered. This is particularly true of the first case, where the highest power in the state is also the legislative authority which must be obeyed without argument. Such audacity itself gives a certain appearance of inner conviction that the deed is right and just, and the god of success（bonus eventus） will then be the best of advocates.

2. Si fecisti, nega [If you are the perpetrator, deny it]. If you have committed a crime, for instance, in order to lead your people to desperation and thence to rebellion, deny that the guilt is yours. Maintain instead that it arose from the intransigence of the subjects; or if you have seized control of a neighbouring people, say that the very nature of man is responsible, for if he does not anticipate others in resorting to violence, he may count on it that they will anticipate and overpower him.

3. Divide et impera [Divide and rule]. That is, if there are certain privileged persons among the people who have chosen you for their ruler merely as primus inter pares [the chief among his peers], make sure to disunite them among themselves and set them at odds with the people. And if you back up the people with false promises of greater freedom, everything will be dependent on your absolute will. Or if you are dealing with foreign states, to stir up discord among them is a fairly certain method of subjugating them one by one while merely appearing to lend support to the weaker.

No one, it must be confessed, will be taken in by these political maxims, for they are all generally known. And it is not the case that men are ashamed of them, as if their injustice were all too obviously visible. For great powers are never embarrassed about how the common mass might judge them, but only about one another's opinions. And as for the principles listed above, the powers will feel no shame if they become publicly known, but only if they fail to succeed, for they are all agreed on the moral status of the maxims. They are left with political honour, on which they can always rely if they enlarge their power by whatever means they care to use.[15] From all these twists and turns of an immoral and opportunistic doctrine of how to create peace among men out of the warlike state of nature, this much at least is clear: men can as little escape the concept of right in their private relations as in their public ones, and they will not openly dare to base their politics on opportunistic machinations alone and thus to refuse altogether to obey any concept of public right（which is particularly remarkable in the case of international right）. Instead, they pay such concepts all the honour they deserve, even although they may also devise a hundred excuses and subterfuges to get out of observing them in practice and to pretend that brute force and cunning can possess that authority which is the source and unifying bond of all right.

In order to end this sophistry（if not the actual injustice which it covers over） and to make the false representatives of those who wield power on earth confess that they are advocating might instead of right（adopting as they do the tone of persons entitled to give orders）, it will be well to discover the ultimate principle from which the end of perpetual peace is derived, and thus to destroy the illusions with which men deceive themselves and others. It must likewise be demonstrated that all the evil which stands in the way of perpetual peace results from the fact that the political moralist starts out from the very point at which the moral politician rightly stops; he thus makes his principles subordinate to his end（i.e. puts the cart before the horse）, thereby defeating his own purpose of reconciling politics with morality.

To ensure that practical philosophy is at one with itself, it is first necessary to resolve the question of whether, in problems of practical reason, we should begin with its material principle, i.e. its end, as an object of the will, or with its formal principle, i.e. the principle which rests on man's freedom in his external relations and which states:‘Act in such a way that you can wish your maxim to become a universal law（irrespective of what the end in view may be）.’

The latter principle must undoubtedly take precedence. For as a principle of right, it has absolute necessity, whereas the former is necessary only if the empirical conditions which permit the proposed end to be realized can be assumed to exist. And if this end were also a duty, as with the end of perpetual peace, it would itself have to be deduced from the formal principle of the maxims governing external action. Now the former（i.e. material） principle is that of the political moralist, and it treats the problems of political, international and cosmopolitan right as mere technical tasks; but the latter（i.e. formal） principle is that of the moral politician, for whom it is a moral task, totally different in its execution from technical problems, to bring about perpetual peace, which is desirable not just as a physical good, but also as a state of affairs which must arise out of recognizing one's duty.

For the solution of the first problem（that of political expediency）, much knowledge of nature is required, so that one can use its mechanism to promote the intended end. Nevertheless, all this is uncertain so far as its repercussions on perpetual peace are concerned, no matter which of the three departments of public right one considers. For it is uncertain whether the obedience and prosperity of the people can be better maintained over a long period by strict discipline or by appeals to their vanity, by conferring supreme power upon a single individual or upon several united leaders, or perhaps merely by means of an aristocracy of office or by popular internal government. History offers examples of the opposite effect being produced by all forms of government, with the single exception of genuine republicanism, which, however, could be the object only of a moral politician. And it is even more uncertain in the case of an international right supposedly based on statutes worked out by ministers, for it is in fact a mere word with nothing behind it, since it depends upon treaties which contain in the very act of their conclusion the secret reservation that they may be violated. On the other hand, the solution of the second problem, that of political wisdom, presents itself as it were automatically; it is obvious to everyone, it defeats all artifices, and leads straight to its goal, so long as we prudently remember that it cannot be realized by violent and precipitate means, but must be steadily approached as favourable opportunities present themselves.

We may therefore offer the following advice:‘Seek ye first the kingdom of pure practical reason and its righteousness, and your object（the blessing of perpetual peace） will be added unto you.’ For morality, with regard to its principles of public right（hence in relation to a political code which can be known a priori）, has the peculiar feature that the less it makes its conduct depend upon the end it envisages（whether this be a physical or moral advantage）, the more it will in general harmonize with this end. And the reason for this is that it is precisely the general will as it is given a priori, within a single people or in the mutual relationships of various peoples, which alone determines what is right among men. But this union of the will of all, if only it is put into practice in a consistent way, can also, within the mechanism of nature, be the cause which leads to the intended result and gives effect to the concept of right. For example, it is a principle of moral politics that a people should combine to form a state in accordance with freedom and equality as its sole concepts of right, and this principle is based not on expediency, but on duty. Political moralists, on the other hand, do not deserve a hearing, however much they argue about the natural mechanism of a mass of people who enter into society, or claim that this mechanism would invalidate the above principles and frustrate their fulfilment, or try to prove their assertions by citing examples of badly organized constitutions of ancient and modern times（e.g. of democracies without a system of representation）. Such theories are particularly damaging, because they may themselves produce the very evil they predict. For they put man into the same class as other living machines, which only need to realize consciously that they are not free beings for them to become in their own eyes the most wretched of all earthly creatures.

The proverbial saying fiat iustitia, pereat mundus（i.e. let justice reign, even if all the rogues in the world must perish） may sound somewhat inflated, but it is nonetheless true. It is a sound principle of right, which blocks up all the devious paths followed by cunning or violence. But it must not be misunderstood, or taken, for example, as a permit to apply one's own rights with the utmost rigour（which would conflict with ethical duty）, but should be seen as an obligation of those in power not to deny or detract from the rights of anyone out of disfavour or sympathy for others. And this requires above all that the state should have an internal constitution organized in accordance with pure principles of right, and also that it unite with other neighbouring or even distant states to arrive at a lawful settlement of their differences by forming something analogous to a universal state. This proposition simply means that whatever the physical consequences may be, the political maxims adopted must not be influenced by the prospect of any benefit or happiness which might accrue to the state if it followed them, i.e. by the end which each state takes as the object of its will（as the highest empirical principle of political wisdom）; they should be influenced only by the pure concept of rightful duty, i.e. by an obligation whose principle is given a priori by pure reason. The world will certainly not come to an end if there are fewer bad men. Moral evil has by nature the inherent quality of being self-destructive and self-contradictory in its aims（especially in relations between persons of a like mind）, so that it makes way for the moral principle of goodness, even if such progress is slow.

Thus in objective or theoretical terms, there is no conflict whatsoever between morality and politics. In a subjective sense, however（i.e. in relation to the selfish disposition of man, which, since it is not based on maxims of reason, cannot however be called practice）, this conflict will and ought to remain active, since it serves as a whetstone of virtue. The true courage of virtue, according to the principle tu ne cede malis, sed contra audentior ito [‘You for your part must not give way to troubles, but confront them the more boldly’], does not so much consist, in the present case, in resolutely standing up to the evils and sacrifices which must be encountered, as in facing the evil principle within ourselves and overcoming its wiles. For this principle is far more dangerous, since it is deceitful, treacherous, and liable to exploit the weakness of human nature in order to justify any violation of justice.

The political moralist may indeed say that the ruler and people, or one people and another people, do no injustice to each other if they enter into mutual conflict through violence or cunning, although they act completely unjustly in refusing to respect the concept of right, which would alone be capable of establishing perpetual peace. For if one party violates his duty towards another who is just as lawlessly disposed towards him, that which actually happens to them in wearing each other out is perfectly just, and enough of their kind will always survive to keep this process going without interruption into the most distant future, so that later generations may take them as a warning example. Providence is justified in disposing the course of world events in this way; for the moral principle in man is never extinguished, and reason, which is pragmatically capable of applying the ideas of right according to this principle, constantly increases with the continuous progress of culture, while the guilt attending violations of right increases proportionately. If we suppose that mankind never can or will be in a better condition, it seems impossible to justify by any kind of theodicy the mere fact that such a race of corrupt beings could have been created on earth at all. But this kind of judgement is far too exalted for us; we cannot theoretically attribute our conception of wisdom to the supreme power whose nature is beyond our understanding.

Such are the desperate conclusions to which we are inevitably driven if we do not assume that the pure principles of right have an objective reality, i.e. that they can be applied in practice. And whatever empirical politics may say to the contrary, the people within the state, as well as the states in their relations with one another, must act accordingly. A true system of politics cannot therefore take a single step without first paying tribute to morality. And although politics in itself is a difficult art, no art is required to combine it with morality. For as soon as the two come into conflict, morality can cut through the knot which politics cannot untie.

The rights of man must be held sacred, however great a sacrifice the ruling power may have to make. There can be no half measures here; it is no use devising hybrid solutions such as a pragmatically conditioned right half-way between right and utility. For all politics must bend the knee before right, although politics may hope in return to arrive, however slowly, at a stage of lasting brilliance.

II
On the Agreement Between Politics and Morality According to the Transcendental Concept of Public Right

If, in considering public right as the jurists usually conceive of it, I abstract from all its material aspects（as determined by the various empirically given relationships of men within a state, or of states with one another）, I am left with the formal attribute of publicness. For every claim upon right potentially possesses this attribute, and without it, there can be no justice（which can only be conceived of as publicly knowable） and therefore no right, since right can only come from justice.

Every claim upon right must have this public quality, and since it is very easy to judge whether or not it is present in a particular instance, i.e. whether or not it can be combined with the principles of the agent concerned, it provides us with a readily applicable criterion which can be discovered a priori within reason itself. If it cannot be reconciled with the agent's principles, it enables us to recognize at once the falseness（i.e. unrightfulness） of the claim（praetensio iuris） in question, as if by an experiment of pure reason.

After we have abstracted in this way from all the empirical elements contained within the concept of political and international right（including that evil aspect of human nature which makes coercion necessary）, we may specify the following proposition as the transcendental formula of public right:‘All actions affecting the rights of other human beings are wrong if their maxim is not compatible with their being made public.’

This principle should be regarded not only as ethical（i.e. pertaining to the theory of virtue） but also as juridical（i.e. affecting the rights of man）.For a maxim which I may not declare openly without thereby frustrating my own intention, or which must at all costs be kept secret if it is to succeed, or which I cannot publicly acknowledge without thereby inevitably arousing the resistance of everyone to my plans, can only have stirred up this necessary and general（hence a priori foreseeable）opposition against me because it is itself unjust and thus constitutes a threat to everyone. Besides, this is a purely negative test, i.e. it serves only as a means of detecting what is not right in relation to others. Like any axiom, it is valid without demonstration, and besides, it is easy to apply, as can be seen from the following examples of public right.

1. In the internal right of a state（ius civitatis）, a question may arise which many people consider difficult to answer, although it can be resolved quite easily by means of the transcendental principle of publicness. It runs as follows:‘Is rebellion a rightful means for a people to use in order to overthrow the oppressive power of a so-called tyrant（non titulo, sed exercitio talis）?’ The rights of the people have been violated, and there can be no doubt that the tyrant would not be receiving unjust treatment if he were dethroned. Nevertheless, it is in the highest degree wrong if the subjects pursue their rights in this way, and they cannot in the least complain of injustice if they are defeated in the ensuing conflict and subsequently have to endure the most severe penalties.

Much can be said in arguments both for and against such a course of action if we try to settle the matter by dogmatic deduction of the principles of right. But the transcendental principle of publicness in questions of right can get round such long-winded discussion. According to this principle, the people, before establishing the civil contract, asks itself whether it dares to make public the maxim of its intention to rebel on certain occasions. It is easily seen that if one were to make it a condition of founding a political constitution that force might in certain eventualities be used against the head of state, the people would have to claim rightful authority over its ruler. But if this were so, the ruler would not be the head of state; or if both parties were given authority as a prior condition of establishing the state, the existence of the state itself, which it was the people's intention to establish, would become impossible. The injustice of rebellion is thus apparent from the fact that if the maxim upon which it would act were publicly acknowledged, it would defeat its own purpose. This maxim would therefore have to be kept secret.

But it would not be necessary for the head of state to conceal his intentions. He may say quite openly that he will punish any rebellion by putting the ringleaders to death, even if they believed that he was himself the first to infringe the fundamental law. For if he is aware that he possesses irresistible supreme power（and this must be assumed in any civil constitution, for a ruler who does not have sufficient power to protect each individual among the people against the others cannot have the right to give the people orders either）, he does not have to worry that his own aims might be frustrated if his maxim became generally known. And it is perfectly consistent with this argument that if the people were to rebel successfully, the head of state would revert to the position of a subject; but he would not be justified in starting a new rebellion to restore his former position, nor should he have to fear being called to account for his previous administration.

2. We now come to international right.– We can speak of international right only on the assumption that some kind of lawful condition exists, i.e. that external circum-stances are such that a man can genuinely be accorded his rights. For as a form of public right, it implies by definition that there is a general will which publicly assigns to each individual that which is his due. And this status iuridicus must be derived from some sort of contract, which, unlike that from which a state originates, must not be based on coercive laws, but may at most be a state of permanent and free association like the above-mentioned federation of different states. For without some kind of lawful condition which actively links together the various physical or moral persons（as is the case in the state of nature）, the only possible form of right is a private one. This again involves a conflict between politics and morality（the latter in the shape of a theory of right）. The criterion of publicness in the relevant maxims can, however, once again be easily applied, but only on condition that the contract binds the states for the single purpose of preserving peace amongst themselves and in relation to other states, and on no account with a view to military conquest. We can thus envisage the following instances of an antinomy between politics and morality, along with the appropriate solution in each case.

（a）‘If one of these states has promised something to another, whether it be assistance, cession of certain territories, subsidies, or the like, it may be asked whether this state, on occasions when its own welfare is at stake, may free itself from the obligation to keep its word, maintaining that it ought to be regarded as a dual person–on the one hand, as a sovereign who is not responsible to anyone within the state, and on the other, merely as the highest political official who is responsible to the state; and the conclusion to be drawn from this is that the state（or its ruler） can be exempted in the latter capacity from obligations it incurred in the first.’ But if the ruler of a state were to let it be known that this was his maxim, everyone else would naturally flee from him, or unite with others in order to resist his pretensions; which proves that such a system of politics, for all its cunning, would defeat its own purpose if it operated on a public footing, so that the above maxim must be wrong.

（b）‘If a neighbouring power which has grown to a formidable size（potentia tremenda） gives cause for anxiety, can one assume that it will wish to oppress other states because is is able to do so, and does this give the less powerful party a right to mount a concerted attack upon it, even if no offence has been offered?’ If a state were to let it be known that it affirmed this maxim, it would merely bring about more surely and more quickly the very evil it feared. For the greater power would anticipate the lesser ones, and the possibility that they might unite would be but a feeble reed against one who knew how to use the tactics of divide et impera. Thus this maxim of political expediency; if acknowledged publicly, necessarily defeats its own purpose and is consequently unjust.

（c）‘If a smaller state, by its geographical situation, constitutes a gap in the territory of a larger state, and this larger state requires the intrusive territory for its own preservation, is not the larger state justified in subjugating the smaller one and in annexing its territory?’ One can easily see that the larger state must on no account let it be known that it has adopted such a maxim. For the smaller states would either unite in good time, or other powerful states would quarrel over the proposed prey, so that the plan would be rendered impracticable if it were made public. This is a sign that it is unjust, and it would in fact be an injustice of very great magnitude; for the fact that the object of an injustice is small does not mean that the injustice done to it may not be very great.

3. As for cosmopolitan right, I pass over it here in silence, for its maxims are easy to formulate and assess on account of its analogy with international right.

In the principle that the maxims of international right may be incompatible with publicity, we thus have a good indication that politics and morality（in the sense of a theory of right） are not in agreement. But it is also necessary that we should know what the condition is under which its maxims will agree with international right. For we cannot simply conclude by a reverse process that all maxims which can be made public are therefore also just, because the person who has decisive supremacy has no need to conceal his maxims. The condition which must be fulfilled before any kind of international right is possible is that a lawful state must already be in existence. For without this, there can be no public right, and any right which can be conceived of outside it, i.e. in a state of nature, will be merely a private right. Now we have already seen above that a federative association of states whose sole intention is to eliminate war is the only lawful arrangement which can be reconciled with their freedom. Thus politics and morality can only be in agreement within a federal union, which is therefore necessary and given a priori through the principles of right. And the rightful basis of all political prudence is the founding of such a union in the most comprehensive form possible; for without this aim, all its reasonings are unwisdom and veiled injustice. This kind of false politics has its own casuistry to match that of the best Jesuit scholars. For it includes the reservatio mentalis whereby public contracts are formulated in terms which one can interpret to one's own advantage as required（for example, the distinction between the status quo of fact and the status quo of right）; it also includes the probabilismus, i.e. it tries to think out evil intentions which it might attribute to others, or uses the likelihood of their gaining predominance as a legal justification for undermining other peaceful states; and finally, it has the principle of the philosophical sin（peccatum philosophicum, peccatillum, or bagatelle）, whereby it can be regarded as a readily pardonable trifle to seize a small state if a much larger state gains in the process, to the supposed advantage of the world in general.[16]

All this is occasioned by the duplicity of politics in relation to morality, for it makes use of whatever branch of morality suits its purposes. But both aspects, philanthropy and respect for the rights of man, are obligatory. And while the former is only a conditional duty, the latter is an unconditional and absolutely imperative one; anyone must first be completely sure that he has not infringed it if he wishes to enjoy the sweet sense of having acted justly. Politics can easily be reconciled with morality in the former sense（i.e. as ethics）, for both demand that men should give up their rights to their rulers. But when it comes to morality in its second sense（i.e. as the theory of right）, which requires that politics should actively defer to it, politics finds it advisable not to enter into any contract at all, preferring to deny that the theory of right has any reality and to reduce all duties to mere acts of goodwill. This subterfuge of a secretive system of politics could, however, easily be defeated if philosophy were to make its maxims public, would it but dare to allow the philosopher to publicize his own maxims.

With this in mind, I now put forward another transcendental and affirmative principle of public right. It might be formulated as follows:‘All maxims which require publicity if they are not to fail in their purpose can be reconciled both with right and with politics.’

For if they can only attain their end by being publicized, they must conform to the universal aim of the public（which is happiness）, and it is the particular task of politics to remain in harmony with the aim of the public through making it satisfied with its condition. But if this end is to be attained only through publicity（i.e. by dispelling all distrust of the maxims employed）, the maxims in question must also be in harmony with public right; for only within this right is it possible to unite the ends of everyone. I must, however, postpone the further elaboration and discussion of this principle until another occasion, although it can already be seen that it is a transcendental formula if one removes all the empirical conditions relating to happiness, i.e. the substance of the law, and looks exclusively to the form of universal lawfulness.

If it is a duty to bring about in reality a state of public right（albeit by an infinite process of gradual approximation）, and if there are also good grounds for hoping that we shall succeed, then it is not just an empty idea that perpetual peace will eventually replace what have hitherto been wrongly called peace treaties（which are actually only truces）. On the contrary, it is a task which, as solutions are gradually found, constantly draws nearer fulfilment, for we may hope that the periods within which equal amounts of progress are made will become progressively shorter.

————————————————————

[14] These are permissive laws of reason, which allow a state of public right to continue, even if it is affected by injustice, until all is ripe for a complete revolution or has been prepared for it by peaceful means. For any legal constitution, even if it is only in small measure lawful, is better than none at all, and the fate of a premature reform would be anarchy. Thus political prudence, with things as they are at present, will make it a duty to carry out reforms appropriate to the ideal of public right. But where revolutions are brought about by nature alone, it will not use them as a good excuse for even greater oppression, but will treat them as a call of nature to create a lawful constitution based on the principles of freedom, for a thorough reform of this kind is the only one which will last.

[15] It might be doubted whether any inherent wickedness rooted in human nature influences men who live together within a single state, for one might instead（with some plausibility） adduce the deficiencies of their as yet underdeveloped culture（i.e. their barbarism） as the cause of the unlawful elements in their thinking. But in the external relationships between states, this wickedness is quite undisguisedly and irrefutably apparent. Within each individual state, it is concealed by the coercion embodied in the civil laws, for the citizens' inclination to do violence to one another is counteracted by a more powerful force – that of the government. This not only gives the whole a veneer of morality（causae non causae）, but by putting an end to outbreaks of lawless proclivities, it genuinely makes it much easier for the moral capacities of men to develop into an immediate respect for right. For each individual believes of himself that he would by all means maintain the sanctity of the concept of right and obey it faithfully, if only he could be certain that all the others would do likewise, and the government in part guarantees this for him; thus a great step is taken towards morality（although this is still not the same as a moral step）, towards a state where the concept of duty is recognized for its own sake, irrespective of any possible gain in return. But since each individual, despite his good opinion of himself, assumes bad faith in everyone else, men thereby pass judgement on one another to the effect that they are all in point of fact of little worth – although it is a moot point why this should be so, since we cannot blame it on the nature of man as a free being. Since, however, that respect for the concept of right which man is absolutely incapable of renouncing gives the most solemn sanction to the theory that man is also capable of conforming to this concept, everyone can see that he must himself act in accordance with it, no matter how others may behave.

[16] One can find examples of such maxims in Garve's treatise Über die Verbindung der Moral mit der Politik（On Combining Morality with Politics）, 1788. This estimable scholar admits from the very outset that he is unable to offer a satisfactory answer to this question. But to condone such procedures while admitting that one cannot fully answer the objections which can be raised against them seems to constitute a greater concession to those who are most inclined to misuse it than it is advisable for anyone to make.

A Renewed Attempt to Answer the Question:‘Is the Human Race Continually Improving?’

1
What Sort of Knowledge are we Looking For?

What we are seeking to know is a portion of human history. It is not a history of the past, however, but a history of future times, i.e. a predictive history. But if it is not discoverable from known laws of nature（as with eclipses of the sun and moon, which can be foretold by natural means） and can only be learnt through additional insight into the future supplied by supernatural revelation, it must be termed prognosticative or prophetic.[1] Besides, we are here concerned not with the natural history of mankind（as we should be if we asked, for example, whether new races of man might emerge in future times）, but with the history of civilization. And we are not dealing with any specific conception of mankind（singulorum）, but with the whole of humanity（universorum）, united in earthly society and distributed in national groups. All this is implied if we ask whether the human race（as a whole） is continually improving.

2
How can we Attain Such Knowledge?

We can obtain a prophetic historical narrative of things to come by depicting those events whose a priori possibility suggests that they will in fact happen. But how is it possible to have history a priori? The answer is that it is possible if the prophet himself occasions and produces the events he predicts.

It was all very well for the Jewish prophets to foretell that the state to which they belonged would sooner or later suffer not only decline, but also complete dissolution; for they were themselves the architects of their fate. As leaders of the people, they had loaded their constitution with so many ecclesiastical（and thence also civil） burdens that their state became completely unfit to exist in its own right, particularly in its relations with neighbouring nations. Thus the jeremiads of the priests naturally went unheeded, because these same priests stubbornly stuck to their belief in the untenable constitution they had themselves created, so that they were themselves able to foresee the consequences with infallible certainty.

Our politicians, so far as their influence extends, behave in exactly the same way, and they are just as successful in their prophecies. One must take men as they are, they tell us, and not as the world's uninformed pedants or good-natured dreamers fancy that they ought to be. But ‘as they are’ ought to read ‘as we have made them by unjust coercion, by treacherous designs which the government is in a good position to carry out’. For that is why they are intransigent and inclined to rebellion, and why regrettable consequences ensue if discipline is relaxed in the slightest. In this way, the prophecy of the supposedly clever statesmen is fulfilled.

Various divines also at times prophesy the complete decline of religion and the imminent appearance of the Antichrist, all the while doing the very things that are best calculated to create the state of affairs they describe. For they are not taking care to impress on the hearts of their congregation moral principles which would directly lead to an improvement. Instead, they see observances and historical beliefs as the essential duties, supposing that these will indirectly produce the same results; but although they may lead to mechanical conformity（as within a civil constitution）, they cannot produce conformity in moral attitudes. Nevertheless, these divines complain at the irreligion which they have themselves created, and which they could accordingly have foretold without any special gift of prophecy.

3
Subdivisions Within the Concept of what we Wish to Know of the Future

There are three possible forms which our prophecy might take. The human race is either continually regressing and deteriorating, continually progressing and improving, or at a permanent standstill, in relation to other created beings, at its present level of moral attainment（which is the same as continually revolving in a circle around a fixed point）.

The first statement might be designated moral terrorism, the second eudaemonism（which, if the goal of human progress were already visible from afar, might also be termed chiliasm）, while the third could be called abderitism. For in the latter case, since a genuine standstill is impossible in moral affairs, rises and falls of equal magnitude constantly alternate, in endless fluctuation, and produce no more effect than if the subject of them had remained stationary in one place.

a
The terroristic conception of human history

A process of deterioration in the human race cannot go on indefinitely, for mankind would wear itself out after a certain point had been reached. Consequently, when enormities go on piling up and up and the evils they produce continue to increase, we say:‘It can't get much worse now.’ It seems that the day of judgement is at hand, and the pious zealot already dreams of the rebirth of everything and of a world created anew after the present world has been destroyed by fire.

b
The eudaemonistic conception of human history

We may readily agree that the sum total of good and evil of which our nature is capable always remains unchanged, and can neither be augmented nor reduced within any one individual. And how could the quantity of good of which a person is capable possibly be increased? For it would have to be done by his own free agency as a subject, and before he could do it, he would in turn require a greater store of goodness than he already possessed in the first place. After all, no effects can exceed the capacity of their effective cause; and the quantity of goodness in man must therefore remain below a certain level in proportion to the amount of evil with which it is intermixed, so that man cannot work his way beyond a given limit and go on improving further. Thus eudaemonism, with its sanguine hopes, appears to be untenable. Its ideas of constant human progress and improvement would seem of little use to a prophetic history of mankind.

c
The hypothesis of abderitism in the human race as a definition of its future history

This point of view probably has the majority of subscribers on its side. To start off swiftly along the way of goodness without persevering on it, and instead, to reverse the plan of progress in order at all costs to avoid being tied to a single aim（even if only from a desire for variety）; to construct in order to demolish; to take upon ourselves the hopeless task of rolling the stone of Sisyphus uphill, only to let it roll back down again: such is the industrious folly which characterizes our race. In view of all this, it does not so much seem that the principle of evil within the natural character of mankind is amalgamated or fused with that of goodness, but rather that the one is neutralized by the other, with inactivity as the result（or a standstill, as in the case under discussion）. This empty activity of backward and forward motion, with good and evil continually alternating, would mean that all the interplay of members of our species on earth ought merely to be regarded as a farce. And in the eyes of reason, this cannot give any higher a value to mankind than to the other animal species, whose interaction takes place at less cost and without any conscious understanding.

4
The Problem of Progress Cannot be Solved Directly from Experience

Even if it were found that the human race as a whole had been moving forward and progressing for an indefinitely long time, no one could guarantee that its era of decline was not beginning at that very moment, by virtue of the physical character of our race. And conversely, if it is regressing and deteriorating at an accelerating pace, there are no grounds for giving up hope that we are just about to reach the turning point（punctum flexus contrarii） at which our affairs will take a turn for the better, by virtue of the moral character of our race. For we are dealing with freely acting beings to whom one can dictate in advance what they ought to do, but of whom one cannot predict what they actually will do, and who are capable, if things go really badly and they experience evils incurred through their own actions, of regarding these evils as a greater incentive to do better than they did in the past. But as the Abbé Coyer says:‘Poor mortals! Nothing is constant among you but inconstancy.’

Perhaps it is because we have chosen the wrong point of view from which to contemplate the course of human affairs that the latter seems so absurd to us. The planets, as seen from the earth, sometimes move backward, sometimes forward, and at other times remain motionless. But seen from the sun – the point of view of reason – they continually follow their regular paths as in the Copernican hypothesis. Yet some thinkers, otherwise not deficient in wisdom, prefer to stick firmly to their own interpretation of phenomena and to the point of view they originally adopted, even at the price of involving themselves to an absurd degree in Tychonic cycles and epicycles. It is our misfortune, however, that we are unable to adopt an absolute point of view when trying to predict free actions. For this, exalted above all human wisdom, would be the point of view of providence, which extends even to free human actions. And although man may see the latter, he cannot foresee them with certainty（a distinction which does not exist in the eyes of the divinity）; for while he needs to perceive a connection governed by natural laws before he can foresee anything, he must do without such hints or guidance when dealing with free actions in the future.

If it were possible to credit human beings with even a limited will of innate and unvarying goodness, we could certainly predict a general improvement of mankind, for this would involve events which man could himself control. But if man's natural endowments consist of a mixture of evil and goodness in unknown proportions, no one can tell what effects he should expect from his own actions.

5
A Prophetic History of the Human Race Must Nevertheless Start from Some Sort of Experience

In human affairs, there must be some experience or other which, as an event which has actually occurred, might suggest that man has the quality or power of being the cause and（since his actions are supposed to be those of a being endowed with freedom） the author of his own improvement. But an event can be predicted as the effect of a given cause only when the circumstances which help to shape it actually arise. And while it can well be predicted in general that these circumstances must arise at some time or another（as in calculating probabilities in games of chance）, it is impossible to determine whether this will happen during my lifetime, and whether I shall myself experience it and thus be able to confirm the original prediction.

We must therefore search for an event which would indicate that such a cause exists and that it is causally active within the human race, irrespective of the time at which it might actually operate; and it would have to be a cause which allowed us to conclude, as an inevitable consequence of its operation, that mankind is improving. This inference could then be extended to cover the history of former times so as to show that mankind has always been progressing, yet in such a way that the event originally chosen as an example would not in itself be regarded as the cause of progress in the past, but only as a rough indication or historical sign（signum rememorativum, demonstrativum, prognostikon）. It might then serve to prove the existence of a tendency within the human race as a whole, considered not as a series of individuals（for this would result in interminable enumerations and calculations） but as a body distributed over the earth in states and national groups.

6
An Occurrence in our Own Times Which Proves This Moral Tendency of the Human Race

The occurrence in question does not involve any of those momentous deeds or misdeeds of men which make small in their eyes what was formerly great or make great what was formerly small, and which cause ancient and illustrious states to vanish as if by magic, and others to arise in their place as if from the bowels of the earth. No, it has nothing to do with all this. We are here concerned only with the attitude of the onlookers as it reveals itself in public while the drama of great political changes is taking place: for they openly express universal yet disinterested sympathy for one set of protagonists against their adversaries, even at the risk that their partiality could be of great disadvantage to themselves. Their reaction（because of its universality） proves that mankind as a whole shares a certain character in common, and it also proves（because of its disinterestedness） that man has a moral character, or at least the makings of one. And this does not merely allow us to hope for human improvement; it is already a form of improvement in itself, in so far as its influence is strong enough for the present.

The revolution which we have seen taking place in our own times in a nation of gifted people may succeed, or it may fail. It may be so filled with misery and atrocities that no right-thinking man would ever decide to make the same experiment again at such a price, even if he could hope to carry it out successfully at the second attempt. But I maintain that this revolution has aroused in the hearts and desires of all spectators who are not themselves caught up in it a sympathy which borders almost on enthusiasm, although the very utterance of this sympathy was fraught with danger. It cannot therefore have been caused by anything other than a moral disposition within the human race.

The moral cause which is at work here is composed of two elements. Firstly, there is the right of every people to give itself a civil constitution of the kind that it sees fit, without interference from other powers. And secondly, once it is accepted that the only intrinsically rightful and morally good constitution which a people can have is by its very nature disposed to avoid wars of aggression（i.e. that the only possible constitution is a republican one, at least in its conception）,[2] there is the aim, which is also a duty, of submitting to those conditions by which war, the source of all evils and moral corruption, can be prevented. If this aim is recognized, the human race, for all its frailty, has a negative guarantee that it will progressively improve or at least that it will not be disturbed in its progress.

All this, along with the passion or enthusiasm with which men embrace the cause of goodness（although the former cannot be entirely applauded, since all passion as such is blameworthy）, gives historical support for the following assertion, which is of considerable anthropological significance: true enthusiasm is always directed exclusively towards the ideal, particularly towards that which is purely moral（such as the concept of right）, and it cannot be coupled with selfish interests. No pecuniary rewards could inspire the opponents of the revolutionaries with that zeal and greatness of soul which the concept of right could alone produce in them, and even the old military aristocracy's concept of honour（which is analogous to enthusiasm） vanished before the arms of those who had fixed their gaze on the rights of the people to which they belonged,[3] and who regarded themselves as its protectors. And then the external public of onlookers sympathized with their exaltation, without the slightest intention of actively participating in their affairs.

7
The Prophetic History of Mankind

In these principles, there must be something moral which reason recognizes not only as pure, but also（because of its great and epoch-making influence） as something to which the human soul manifestly acknowledges a duty. Moreover, it concerns the human race as a complete association of men（non singulorum, sed universorum [‘Not of individuals, but of mankind as a whole’]）, for they rejoice with universal and disinterested sympathy at its anticipated success and at all attempts to make it succeed.

The occurrence in question is not, however, a phenomenon of revolution, but（as Erhard puts it） of the evolution of a constitution governed by natural right. Such a constitution cannot itself be achieved by furious struggles – for civil and foreign wars will destroy whatever statutory order has hitherto prevailed – but it does lead us to strive for a constitution which would be incapable of bellicosity, i.e. a republican one. The actual form of the desired state might be republican, or alternatively, it might only be republican in its mode of government, in that the state would be administered by a single ruler（the monarch） acting by analogy with the laws which a people would give itself in conformity with universal principles of right.

Even without the mind of a seer, I now maintain that I can predict from the aspects and signs of our times that the human race will achieve this end, and that it will henceforth progressively improve without any more total reversals. For a phenomenon of this kind which has taken place in human history can never be forgotten, since it has revealed in human nature an aptitude and power for improvement of a kind which no politician could have thought up by examining the course of events in the past. Only nature and freedom, combined within mankind in accordance with principles of right, have enabled us to forecast it; but the precise time at which it will occur must remain indefinite and dependent upon chance.

But even if the intended object behind the occurrence we have described were not to be achieved for the present, or if a people's revolution or constitutional reform were ultimately to fail, or if, after the latter had lasted for a certain time, everything were to be brought back onto its original course（as politicians now claim to prophesy）, our own philosophical prediction still loses none of its force. For the occurrence in question is too momentous, too intimately interwoven with the interests of humanity and too widespread in its influence upon all parts of the world for nations not to be reminded of it when favourable circumstances present themselves, and to rise up and make renewed attempts of the same kind as before. After all, since it is such an important concern of the human race, the intended constitution must at some time or another finally reach that degree of stability which the lessons of repeated experience will not fail to instil into the hearts of everyone.

Thus the proposition that the human race has always been progressively improving and will continue to develop in the same way is not just a well-meant saying to be recommended for practical purposes. Whatever unbelievers may say, it is tenable within the most strictly theoretical context. And if one considers not only the events which may happen within a particular nation, but also their repercussions upon all the nations of the earth which might gradually begin to participate in them, a view opens up into the unbounded future. This would not be true, of course, if the first epoch of natural convulsions, which（according to Camper and Blumenbach） engulfed the animal and vegetable kingdoms before the era of man, were to be followed by a second in which the human race were given the same treatment so that other creatures might take the stage instead, etc. For man in turn is a mere trifle in relation to the omnipotence of nature, or rather to its inaccessible highest cause. But if the rulers of man's own species regard him as such and treat him accordingly, either by burdening him like a beast and using him as a mere instrument of their ends, or by setting him up to fight in their disputes and slaughter his fellows, it is not just a trifle but a reversal of the ultimate purpose of creation.

8
The Difficulty of Maxims Directed Towards the World's Progressive Improvement as Regards Their Publicity

Popular enlightenment is the public instruction of the people upon their duties and rights towards the state to which they belong. Since this concerns only natural rights and rights which can be derived from ordinary common sense, their obvious exponents and interpreters among the people will not be officials appointed by the state, but free teachers of right, i.e. the philosophers. The latter, on account of the very freedom which they allow themselves, are a stumbling-block to the state, whose only wish is to rule; they are accordingly given the appellation of‘enlighteners’, and decried as a menace to the state. And yet they do not address themselves in familiar tones to the people（who themselves take little or no notice of them and their writings）, but in respectful tones to the state, which is thereby implored to take the rightful needs of the people to heart. And if a whole people wishes to present its grievance（gravamen）, the only way in which this can be done is by publicity. A ban on publicity will therefore hinder a nation's progress, even with regard to the least of its claims, the claim for natural rights.

Another thing which is concealed（transparently enough） by legal measures from a certain people is the true nature of its constitution. It would be an affront to the majesty of the people of Great Britain to say that they lived under an absolute monarchy. Instead, it is said that their constitution is one which limits the will of the monarch through the two houses of parliament, acting as representatives of the people. Yet everyone knows very well that the influence of the monarch upon these represenatives is so great and so infallible that the afore-said houses make no decisions except those which His Majesty wishes and recommends through his minister. Now and again, the latter will certainly recommend decisions wherein he knows and indeed ensures that he will meet with contradiction（as with the abolition of the slave trade）, simply in order to furnish ostensible proof of parliamentary freedom. But this sort of approach has the insidious effect of discouraging people from looking for the true and rightfully established constitution, for they imagine they have discovered it in an instance which is already before them. Thus a mendacious form of publicity deceives the people with the illusion that the monarchy is limited[4] by a law which emanates from them, while their representatives, won over by bribery, secretly subject them to an absolute monarch.

All forms of state are based on the idea of a constitution which is compatible with the natural rights of man, so that those who obey the law should also act as a unified body of legislators. And if we accordingly think of the commonwealth in terms of concepts of pure reason, it may be called a Platonic ideal（respublica noumenon）, which is not an empty figment of the imagination, but the eternal norm for all civil constitutions whatsoever, and a means of ending all wars. A civil society organized in conformity with it and governed by laws of freedom is an example representing it in the world of experience（respublica phaenomenon）, and it can only be achieved by a laborious process, after innumerable wars and conflicts. But its constitution, once it has been attained as a whole, is the best qualified of all to keep out war, the destroyer of everything good. Thus it is our duty to enter into a constitution of this kind; and in the meantime, since it will be a considerable time before this takes place, it is the duty of monarchs to govern in a republican（not a democratic） manner, even although they may rule autocratically. In other words, they should treat the people in accordance with principles akin in spirit to the laws of freedom which a people of mature rational powers would prescribe for itself, even if the people is not literally asked for its consent.

9
What Profit will the Human Race Derive from Progressive Improvement?

The profit which will accrue to the human race as it works its way forward will not be an ever increasing quantity of morality in its attitudes. Instead, the legality of its attitudes will produce an increasing number of actions governed by duty, whatever the particular motive behind these actions may be. In other words, the profit will result from man's good deeds as they grow ever more numerous and successful, i.e. from the external phenomena of man's moral nature. For we have only empirical data（our experiences） on which to base this prediction – that is, we base it on the physical cause of our actions in so far as they actually take place as phenomena, not on the moral cause which contains the concept of duty as applied to what ought to happen, and which can be determined by processes of pure a priori thinking.

Violence will gradually become less on the part of those in power, and obedience towards the laws will increase. There will no doubt be more charity, less quarrels in legal actions, more reliability in keeping one's word, and so on in the commonwealth, partly from a love of honour, and partly from a lively awareness of where one's own advantage lies; and this will ultimately extend to the external relations between the various peoples, until a cosmopolitan society is created. Such developments do not mean, however, that the basic moral capacity of mankind will increase in the slightest, for this would require a kind of new creation or supernatural influence. For we must not expect too much of human beings in their progressive improvements, or else we shall merit the scorn of those politicians who would gladly treat man's hopes of progress as the fantasies of an overheated mind.[5]

10
What Sequence can Progress be Expected to Follow?

The answer is: not the usual sequence from the bottom upwards, but from the top downwards.

To expect that the education of young people in intellectual and moral culture, reinforced by the doctrines of religion, firstly through domestic instruction and then through a series of schools from the lowest to the highest grade, will eventually not only make them good citizens, but will also bring them up to practise a kind of goodness which can continually progress and maintain itself, is a plan which is scarcely likely to achieve the desired success. For on the one hand, the people believe that the expense of educating their children should be met not by them but by the state; and on the other, the state itself（as Büsching laments） has no money left over to pay qualified teachers who will carry out their duties with enthusiasm, since it needs it all for war. But apart from this, the whole mechanism of education as described above will be completely disjointed unless it is designed on the considered plan and intention of the highest authority in the state, then set in motion and constantly maintained in uniform operation thereafter. And this will mean that the state too will reform itself from time to time, pursuing evolution instead of revolution, and will thus make continuous progress. But those responsible for the desired education are also human beings who will therefore have to have had a suitable education themselves. And in view of the frailty of human nature and the fortuitous circumstances which can intensify its effects, we can expect man's hopes of progress to be fulfilled only under the positive condition of a higher wisdom（which, if it is invisible to us, is known as providence）; and in so far as human beings can themselves accomplish anything or anything can be expected of them, it can only be through their negative wisdom in furthering their own ends. In the latter event, they will find themselves compelled to ensure that war, the greatest obstacle to morality and the invariable enemy of progress, first becomes gradually more humane, then more infrequent, and finally disappears completely as a mode of aggression. They will thereby enter into a constitution based on genuine principles of right, which is by its very nature capable of constant progress and improvement without forfeiting its strength.

Conclusion

A doctor who used to console his patients from day to day with hopes of imminent recovery, telling one that his pulse was better, and others that their faeces or perspiration heralded an improvement, etc., received a visit from one of his friends. ‘How are you, my friend, and how is your illness?’ was the first question. ‘How do you think,’ was the reply. ‘I am dying of sheer recovery!’

I do not blame anyone if political evils make him begin to despair of the welfare and progress of mankind. But I have confidence in the heroic medicine to which Hume refers, for it ought to produce a speedy cure. ‘When I now see the nations engaged in war’, he says, ‘it is as if I witnessed two drunken wretches bludgeoning each other in a china-shop. For it is not just that the injuries they inflict on each other will be long in healing; they will also have to pay for all the damage they have caused.’ Sero sapiunt Phryges [‘The Phrygians learn wisdom too late’]. But the after-pains of the present war will force the political prophet to admit that the human race must soon take a turn for the better, and this turn is now already in sight.

————————————————————

[1] Those, from pythonesses to gypsies, who dabble in prophecy with neither knowledge nor honesty, are known as false prophets.

[2] This does not mean, however, that a people which has a monarchic constitution can thereby claim the right to alter it, or even nurse a secret desire to do so. For a people which occupies extended territories in Europe may feel that monarchy is the only kind of constitution which can enable it to preserve its own existence between powerful neighbours. And if the subjects should complain, not because of their internal government but because of their government's behaviour towards the citizens of foreign states（for example, if it were to discourage republicanism abroad）, this does not prove that the people are dissatisfied with their own constitution, but rather that they are profoundly attached to it; for it becomes progressively more secure from danger as more of the other nations become republics. Nevertheless, slanderous sycophants, bent on increasing their own importance, have tried to portray this innocuous political gossip as innovationism, Jacobinism and conspiracy, constituting a menace to the state. But there was never the slightest reason for such allegations, particularly in a country more than a hundred miles removed from the scene of the revolution.

[3] It may be said of such enthusiasm for asserting the rights of man: postquam ad arma Vulcania ventum est, – mortalis mucro glacies ceu futilis ictu dissiluit [Now that he was faced by Vulcan's arms, his mortal blade was shattered by the blow like brittle ice]. – Why has no ruler ever dared to say openly that he does not recognize any rights of the people against himself ? Or that the people owe their happiness only to the beneficence of a government which confers it upon them, and that any pretensions on the part of the subject that he has rights against the government are absurd or even punishable, since they imply that resistance to authority is permissible? The reason is that any such public declaration would rouse up all the subjects against the ruler, even although they had been like docile sheep, well fed, powerfully protected and led by a kind and understanding master, and had no lack of welfare to complain of. For beings endowed with freedom cannot be content merely to enjoy the comforts of existence, which may well be provided by others（in this case, by the government）; it all depends on the principle which governs the provision of such comforts. But welfare does not have any ruling principle, either for the recipient or for the one who provides it, for each individual will define it differently. It depends, in fact, upon the will's material aspect, which is empirical and thus incapable of becoming a universal rule. A being endowed with freedom, aware of the advantage he possesses over non-rational animals, can and must therefore follow the formal principle of his will and demand for the people to which he belongs nothing short of a government in which the people are co-legislators. In other words, the rights of men who are expected to obey must necessarily come before all considerations of their actual wellbeing, for they are a sacred institution, exalted above all utilitarian values; and no matter how benevolent a government is, it may not tamper with them. These rights, however, always remain an idea which can be fulfilled only on condition that the means employed to do so are compatible with morality. This limiting condition must not be overstepped by the people, who may not therefore pursue their rights by revolution, which is at all times unjust. The best way of making a nation content with its constitution is to rule autocratically and at the same time to govern in a republican manner, i.e. to govern in the spirit of republicanism and by analogy with it.

[4] A cause whose nature is not directly perceptible can be discovered through the effect which invariably accompanies it. What is an absolute monarch? He is one at whose command war at once begins when he says it shall do so. And conversely, what is a limited monarch? He is one who must first ask the people whether or not there is to be a war, and if the people say that there shall be no war, then there will be none. For war is a condition in which all the powers of the state must be at the head of state's disposal.

Now the monarch of Great Britain has waged numerous wars without asking the people's consent. This king is therefore an absolute monarch, although he should not be so according to the constitution. But he can always bypass the latter, since he can always be assured, by controlling the various powers of the state, that the people's representatives will agree with him; for he has the authority to award all offices and dignities. This corrupt system, however, must naturally be given no publicity if it is to succeed. It therefore remains under a very transparent veil of secrecy.

[5] It is certainly agreeable to think up political constitutions which meet the requirements of reason（particularly in matters of right）. But it is foolhardy to put them forward seriously, and punishable to incite the people to do away with the existing constitution.

Plato's Atlantis, More's Utopia, Harrington's Oceana and Allais' Severambia have successively made their appearance, but they have never（with the exception of Cromwell's abortive attempt to establish a despotic republic） been tried out in practice. It is the same with these political creations as with the creation of the world: no one was present at it, nor could anyone have been present, or else he would have been his own creator. It is a pleasant dream to hope that a political product of the sort we here have in mind will one day be brought to perfection, at however remote a date. But it is not merely conceivable that we can continually approach such a state; so long as it can be reconciled with the moral law, it is also the duty of the head of state（not of the citizens） to do so.

Conjectures on the Beginning of Human History

To introduce conjectures at various points in the course of a historical account in order to fill gaps in the record is surely permissible; for what comes before and after these gaps – i.e. the remote cause and the effect respectively – can enable us to discover the intermediate causes with reasonable certainty, thereby rendering the intervening process intelligible. But to base a historical account solely on conjectures would seem little better than drawing up a plan for a novel. Indeed, such an account could not be described as a conjectural history at all, but merely as a work of fiction. – Nevertheless, what it may be presumptuous to introduce in the course of a history of human actions may well be permissible with reference to the first beginning of that history, for if the beginning is a product of nature, it may be discoverable by conjectural means. In other words, it does not have to be invented but can be deduced from experience, assuming that what was experienced at the beginning of history was no better or worse than what is experienced now – an assumption which accords with the analogy of nature and which has nothing presumptuous about it. Thus, a history of the first development of freedom from its origins as a predisposition in human nature is something quite different from a history of its subsequent course, which must be based exclusively on historical records.

Nevertheless, conjectures should not make undue claims on our assent. On the contrary, they should not present themselves as a serious activity but merely as an exercise in which the imagination, supported by reason, may be allowed to indulge as a healthy mental recreation. Consequently, they cannot stand comparison with a historical account which is put forward and accepted as a genuine record of the same event, a record which is tested by criteria quite different from those derived merely from the philosophy of nature. For this very reason, and because the journey on which I am about to venture is no more than a pleasure trip, I may perhaps hope to be granted permission to employ a sacred document as my map, and at the same time to speculate that the journey which I shall make on the wings of imagination – although not without the guidance of experience as mediated by reason – will follow precisely the same course as that which the sacred text records as history. The reader will have the document in question before him（Genesis, Chapters Ⅱ–Ⅵ）, and may consult it at every step to see whether the route which philosophy follows with the help of concepts accords with that which the Bible story describes.

If we are not to indulge in wild conjectures, we must begin with something which human reason cannot deduce from prior natural causes – that is, with the existence of human beings. These human beings must also be fully developed, for they have no mother to support them, and they must be a pair in order that they may reproduce their kind. Besides, there must be only one couple if war is not to break out at once – as would happen if the people in question were close to one another yet strangers – and if nature is not to be accused of having failed, by permitting descent from different ancestors, to take the most appropriate measures to promote sociability as the principal end of human destiny; for the common descent of all human beings from a single family unit was undoubtedly the best means of attaining this end. I then place this couple in a setting secure from the attacks of wild beasts and amply pro-vided by nature with every means of sustenance – a garden, so to speak, in a climate of constant mildness. What is more, I imagine them not in their wholly primitive natural state, but only after they have made significant advances in the skilful use of their powers. For the reader might well find too many conjectures and too few probabilities if I were to try to fill this gap, which presumably occupied a considerable interval of time. The first human being could therefore stand and walk; he could speak（cf. Genesis Ⅱ. 20）[1] and indeed talk – i.e. speak with the help of coherent concepts（Ⅱ. 23） – and consequently think. These are all skills which he had to acquire for himself（for if they were innate, they would also be inherited, which does not tally with experience）; I assume, however, that he is already in possession of them, for I wish merely to consider the development of human behaviour from the ethical point of view, and this necessarily presupposes that the skills in question are already present.

Initially, the newcomer must have been guided solely by instinct, that voice of God which all animals obey. It permitted him to use some things as food and forbade him to use others（Ⅲ. 2–3）. – It is unnecessary, however, to assume for this purpose a particular instinct which has now been lost. It could simply have been the sense of smell and its affinity with the organ of taste, along with that sympathy which is known to exist between the latter and the digestive organs – in other words an ability, which is still in evidence today, to sense in advance whether a given food is suitable for consumption or not. We need not even assume that this sense was more acute in the first couple than it is now; for it is common knowledge that the perceptive powers of those who employ only their senses differ greatly from those of people who are also engaged in thought, and who accordingly pay less attention to their sensations.

So long as inexperienced man obeyed this call of nature, his lot was a happy one. But reason soon made its presence felt and sought to extend his knowledge of foodstuffs beyond the bounds of instinct; it did so by comparing his usual diet with anything which a sense other than that to which his instinct was tied – for example, the sense of sight – represented as similar in character（Ⅲ. 6）. Even if instinct did not recommend it, this experiment had a chance of succeeding so long as instinct did not contradict it. But it is a peculiarity of reason that it is able, with the help of the imagination, to invent desires which not only lack any corresponding natural impulse, but which are even at variance with the latter. Such desires, which are known primarily as lasciviousness, gradually engender a whole host of superfluous or even unnatural inclinations to which the term luxuriousness applies. The initial incentive to abandon natural impulses may have been quite trivial. But the outcome of that first experiment whereby man became conscious of his reason as a faculty which can extend beyond the limits to which all animals are confined was of great importance, and it influenced his way of life decisively. Thus, it may have been only a fruit which, because it looked similar to other agreeable fruits which he had previously tasted, encouraged him to make the experiment. There may also have been the example of an animal to which such food was naturally congenial, although it had an opposite and harmful effect on human beings, whose natural instinct was consequently opposed to it. Nevertheless, this was enough to give reason the initial inducement to quibble with the voice of nature（Ⅲ. 11）, and despite the latter's objections, to make the first experiment in free choice–an experiment which, since it was the first, probably did not turn out as expected. No matter how trivial the harm it did may have been, it was nevertheless enough to open man's eyes（Ⅲ. 7）. He discovered in himself an ability to choose his own way of life without being tied to any single one like the other animals. But the momentary gratification which this realization of his superiority may have afforded him was inevitably followed at once by anxiety and fear as to how he should employ his newly discovered ability, given that he did not yet know the hidden properties or remote effects of anything. He stood, as it were, on the edge of an abyss. For whereas instinct had hitherto directed him towards individual objects of his desire, an infinite range of objects now opened up, and he did not yet know how to choose between them. Yet now that he had tasted this state of freedom, it was impossible for him to return to a state of servitude under the rule of instinct.

Next to the instinct for food by which nature preserves each individual, the sexual instinct, by which nature ensures the survival of each species, is the most prominent. Once reason had awakened, it was not slow to make its influence felt in this area either. Man soon discovered that the sexual stimulus, which in the case of animals is based merely on a transient and largely periodic urge, could in his case be prolonged and even increased by means of the imagination. For although the imagination performs its function with greater moderation the further its object is withdrawn from the senses, it also functions more constantly and uniformly, thereby avoiding that satiety which follows the satisfaction of a purely animal desire. The fig-leaf was accordingly the product of a much stronger assertion of reason than had been evident in the first phase of its development. For to render an inclination more intense and lasting by withdrawing its object from the senses already displays a consciousness of some rational control over the impulses, and not just an ability, as in the first stage of rationality, to obey the impulses to a greater or lesser extent. Refusal was the device which invested purely sensuous stimuli with an ideal quality, and which gradually showed the way from purely animal desire to love, and so also from a feeling for the merely agreeable to a taste for beauty（initially only in human form, but subsequently also in nature）. Furthermore, the first incentive for man's development as a moral being came from his sense of decency, his inclination to inspire respect in others by good manners（i.e. by concealing all that might invite contempt） as the proper foundation of all true sociability. – A small beginning such as this, which nevertheless has epoch-making effects in imparting a wholly new direction to thought, is more important than the whole endless series of subsequent cultural developments.

The third step which reason took after its intervention in man's basic and immediately felt needs was to reflect in anticipation of the future. This ability not just to enjoy the present moment of life but also to visualize what is yet to come, often in the distant future, is the most decisive proof of man's advantage, in that he is able to prepare for remote objectives in keeping with his destiny. But this same ability is also the most inexhaustible source of cares and worries which an uncertain future evokes, and from which all animals are exempt（Ⅲ. 13–19）. The man who had to provide for himself, his wife, and his future children foresaw the increasing laboriousness of his work; the woman foresaw the hardships to which nature had subjected her sex, as well as those which the more powerful man would inflict upon her. Both foresaw with apprehension, at the end of a life of toil and as yet in the background of the picture, the fate which must befall all animals but which causes them no concern, namely death; and they seemed to reproach themselves for, and regard as a crime, that use of reason which had brought all these ills upon them. Perhaps the only comfort and reassurance they had was the prospect of living through their offspring, whose lot might be better than theirs or who might even, as members of one family, alleviate their parents' troubles（Ⅲ. 16–20）.

The fourth and last step which reason took, thereby raising man completely above animal society, was his（albeit obscure） realization that he is the true end of nature, and that nothing which lives on earth can compete with him in this respect. When he first said to the sheep‘the fleece which you wear was given to you by nature not for your own use, but for mine’ and took it from the sheep to wear it himself（Ⅲ. 21）, he became aware of a prerogative which, by his nature, he enjoyed over all the animals; and he now no longer regarded them as fellow creatures, but as means and instruments to be used at will for the attainment of whatever ends he pleased. This notion implies（if only obscurely） an awareness of the following distinction: man should not address other human beings in the same way as animals, but should regard them as having an equal share in the gifts of nature. This was a distant preparation for those restrictions which reason would in future impose on man's will in relation to his fellows, a preparation which is much more essential for the establishment of society than is inclination or love.

Thus, man had attained a position of equality with all rational beings, whatever their rank（Ⅲ. 22）, because he could claim to be an end in himself, to be accepted as such by all others, and not to be used by anyone else simply as a means to other ends. This, rather than reason considered merely as an instrument for the satisfaction of various inclinations, is the basis of man's unconditional equality even with higher beings; for even if the latter are incomparably superior to him in natural gifts, they do not have a right to use him as they please. Consequently, this fourth step of reason is also associated with man's release from the womb of nature, a change of status which undoubtedly does him honour, but is at the same time fraught with danger; for it expelled him from the harmless and secure condition of a protected childhood – from a garden, as it were, which provided for him without any effort on his part（Ⅲ. 23） – and thrust him out into the world at large, where so many cares, labours, and unknown evils awaited him. In the future, the hardships of life would often arouse in him the wish for a paradise created by his imagination, a paradise where he could dream or idle away his existence in quiet inactivity and everlasting peace. But restless reason, irresistibly driving him on to develop his innate capacities, stands between him and that imagined seat of bliss, and does not allow him to return to the state of rude simplicity from which it had originally extracted him（Ⅲ. 24）. It urges him to submit patiently to the labours he detests, to pursue the trivialities he despises, and to forget even his terror of death in favour of all those trifles whose loss he fears even more.

Note

From this account of the earliest history of man, the following conclusion can be drawn. Man's emergence from that paradise which reason represents to him as the first abode of his species was nothing other than his transition from a rude and purely animal existence to a state of humanity, from the leading-strings of instinct to the guidance of reason – in a word, from the guardianship of nature to the state of freedom. Whether he gained or lost through this change is no longer a question when we consider the destiny of his species, which consists quite simply in progress towards perfection, however flawed his first attempts to attain this end – even if they are followed by a long series of further attempts – may prove to be. – But while this course represents a progression from worse to better for the species as a whole, this is not so in the case of the individual. Before reason awoke, there were no commandments or prohibitions, so that violations of these were also impossible. But when reason began to function and, in all its weakness, came into conflict with animality in all its strength, evils necessarily ensued; and even worse, as reason grew more cultivated, vices emerged which were quite foreign to the state of ignorance and hence of innocence. From the moral point of view, therefore, the first step beyond this state was a fall; and from the physical point of view, this fall was a punishment, for it led to a host of hitherto unknown evils. Thus, the history of nature begins with goodness, for it is the work of God; but the history of freedom begins with evil, for it is the work of man. For the individual, who looks only to himself in the exercise of his freedom, a change of this kind represented a loss; for nature, whose end in relation to man concerns the species, it represented a gain. The individual therefore has cause to blame himself for all the ills which he endures and for all the evil which he perpetrates; but at the same time, as the member of a whole（of a species）, he has cause to admire and praise the wisdom and purposiveness of the overall arrangement. – In this way, it is possible to reconcile with each other and with reason the often misunderstood and apparently contradictory pronouncements of the celebrated J. J. Rousseau. In his esays On the Influence of the Sciences and On the Inequality of Man, he shows quite correctly that there is an inevitable conflict between culture and the nature of the human race as a physical species each of whose individual members is meant to fulfil his destiny completely. But in his Émile, his Social Contract, and other writings, he attempts in turn to solve the more difficult problem of what course culture should take in order to ensure the proper development, in keeping with their destiny, of man's capacities as a moral species, so that this [moral] destiny will no longer conflict with his character as a natural species. Since culture has perhaps not yet really begun – let alone completed – its development in accordance with the true principles of man's education as a human being and citizen, the above conflict is the source of all the genuine evils which oppress human life, and of all the vices which dishonour it.[2] At the same time, the very impulses which are blamed as the causes of vice are good in themselves, fulfilling their function as abilities implanted by nature. But since these abilities are adapted to the state of nature, they are undermined by the advance of culture and themselves undermine the latter in turn, until art, when it reaches perfection, once more becomes nature – and this is the ultimate goal of man's moral destiny.

The End of History

The following period began with man's transition from the age of leisure and peace to the age of labour and discord as the prelude to social union. Here, we must make another major leap and suddenly put him in possession of domestic animals and of crops which he can propagate himself for his own consumption by sowing and planting（Ⅳ. 2）. In fact, the transition from the savage life of the hunter to the former [pastoral] state, and from sporadic digging for roots or gathering of fruit to the second [agricultural] state, may have taken place very gradually. It was at this point that strife inevitably arose between those who had hitherto lived together in peace, with the result that those whose ways of life were different became separated and dispersed throughout the world. Pastoral life is not only leisurely, but also the most reliable means of support, for there is no lack of fodder for animals in a largely uninhabited country. Agriculture or the planting of crops, on the other hand, is extremely laborious, subject to the vagaries of climate, and consequently insecure; it also requires permanent settlements, ownership of land, and sufficient strength to defend the latter. The herdsman, however, abhors such property because it limits his freedom of pasture. As far as agriculture is concerned, the farmer may have seemed to envy the herdsman as someone more favoured by heaven（Ⅳ. 4）; but in fact, the herdsman caused him great inconvenience so long as he remained in the neighbourhood, for grazing animals do not spare the farmer's crops. It is also easy for the herdsman to move further afield with his animals, thus avoiding the need to make any restitution for the damage he has done, for he leaves nothing behind which he could not just as easily find elsewhere. Thus, the farmer no doubt had to use force to prevent these incursions, which were not considered unlawful by his adversary; and since the cause of such incursions could never be entirely eliminated, he was no doubt eventually compelled to distance himself as far as possible from those who lived a pastoral existence, unless he wished to lose the fruits of his long and diligent efforts（Ⅳ. 16）. This separation marks the beginning of the third epoch.

Where people depend for their livelihood on the cultivation of the soil（and on the planting of trees in particular）, they require permanent accommodation; and the defence of such property against all encroachment requires a large number of people who are prepared to assist one another. Hence those who adopted this way of life could no longer live in scattered family units, but had to stick together and set up village communities（incorrectly described as towns） in order to protect their property against savage hunters or tribes of pastoral nomads. The first essentials of life which a changed mode of living makes necessary（Ⅳ. 20） could now be acquired by mutual exchange. This inevitably gave rise to culture and the beginnings of art, both as a pastime and as an occupation（Ⅳ. 21f）; but first and foremost, it also meant that certain steps were taken to establish a civil constitution and the public administration of justice. Initially, the latter was no doubt concerned only with major acts of violence, the avenging of which was now no longer left to individuals as in the savage state, but assigned to a lawful authority which served to unite the whole – i.e. to a kind of government which was not itself subject to the rule of force（Ⅳ. 23f.）. – From these first crude beginnings, all human aptitudes could now gradually develop, the most beneficial of these being sociability and civil security. The human race could multiply and, like a beehive, send out colonists in all directions from the centre – colonists who were already civilized. This epoch also saw the beginning of human inequality, that abundant source of so much evil but also of everything good; this inequality continued to increase thereafter.

So long as the nations of nomadic herdsmen, who recognize only God as their master, continued to swarm around the town-dwellers and farmers, who are governed by a human master or civil authority（Ⅵ. 4）,[3] and, as declared enemies of all land ownership, treated the latter with hostility and were hated by them in turn, the two sides were continually at war, or at least at constant risk of war. But as a consequence, both nations could at least enjoy the priceless asset of internal freedom.（For even now, the risk of war is the only thing which keeps despotism in check, because a state must now have wealth before it can be powerful, and there can be no wealth-producing activity without freedom. In a poor nation, this lack of wealth must be compensated for by widespread efforts to preserve the commonwealth, and this is again impossible unless the nation feels that such efforts can be freely made.） – In the course of time, however, the growing luxury of the town-dwellers, and in particular the seductive arts in which the women of the towns surpassed the unkempt wenches of the wilderness, must have been a powerful temptation to the herdsmen to enter into relations with them and to let themselves be drawn into the glittering misery of the towns（Ⅵ. 2）. The consequent amalgamation of two formerly hostile populations put an end to the danger of war, but it also put an end to freedom. This led on the one hand to a despotism of powerful tyrants, and – since culture had only just begun – to soulless extravagance and the most abject slavery, combined with all the vices of the uncivilized state. On the other hand, the human race was irresistibly deflected from the course marked out for it by nature, namely the progressive cultivation of its capacities for goodness. It thus became unworthy of its very existence as a species whose destiny was to rule over the earth rather than to live in brutish indulgence and grovelling servitude（Ⅵ. 17）.

Concluding Note

Thinking people are subject to a malaise which may even turn into moral corruption, a malaise of which the unthinking are ignorant – namely discontent with that providence by which the course of the world as a whole is governed. They feel this sentiment when they contemplate the evils which so greatly oppress the human race, with no hope（as it seems） of any improvement. Yet it is of the utmost importance that we should be content with providence, even if the path it has laid out for us on earth is an arduous one. We should be content with it partly in order that we may take courage even in the midst of hardships, and partly in order that we should not blame all such evils on fate and fail to notice that we may ourselves be entirely responsible for them, thereby losing the chance to remedy them by improving ourselves.

We have to admit that the greatest evils which oppress civilized nations are the result of war – not so much of actual wars in the past or present as of the unremitting, indeed ever-increasing preparation for war in the future. All the resources of the state, and all the fruits of its culture which might be used to enhance that culture even further, are devoted to this purpose. Freedom suffers greatly in numerous areas, and the state's maternal care for its individual members is replaced by demands of implacable harshness（even if this harshness is justified by fear of external threats）. But if the constant fear of war did not compel even heads of state to show this respect for humanity, would we still encounter the same culture, or that close association of social classes within the commonwealth which promotes the well-being of all? Would we still encounter the same population, or even that degree of freedom which is still present in spite of highly restrictive laws? We need only look at China, whose position may expose it to occasional unforeseen incursions but not to attack by a powerful enemy, and we shall find that, for this very reason, it has been stripped of every vestige of freedom. – So long as human culture remains at its present stage, war is therefore an indispensable means of advancing it further; and only when culture has reached its full development – and only God knows when that will be – will perpetual peace become possible and of benefit to us. In this connection, therefore, we surely have only ourselves to blame for the evils which we so bitterly lament; and the Holy Scripture is quite justified in regarding the amalgamation of nations into one society, and their complete liberation from external danger at a time when their culture had scarcely emerged, as an obstacle to all further cultural progress and a descent into irremediable corruption.

The second source of man's dissatisfaction with the order of nature is the shortness of life. It is true that anyone who continues to wish that life might last longer than it actually does must have little appreciation of its value, for to prolong it would merely add to the length of a drama made up of endless struggles with adversity. Nevertheless, we may excuse those of childish judgement who fear death but have no love of life, and who find it hard to complete each day of their existence with some degree of contentment, yet can never have days enough in which to repeat this painful experience. But if we stop to think of all the care that afflicts us in our search for ways of passing a life as short as this, and of all the injustice that is done in the hope of a future enjoyment which will last for so short a time, it is reasonable to conclude that a life-expectancy of 800 years or more would not be to our advantage. Fathers would live in mortal fear of their sons, brothers of brothers, and friends of friends, and the vices of a human race of such longevity would necessarily reach such a pitch that it would deserve no better a fate than to be wiped from the face of the earth by a universal flood（Ⅵ. 12f.）.

The third wish（which is in fact an empty yearning, for it knows that its object can never be attained） is a reflection of that golden age which poets have praised so highly. In it, we are supposedly relieved of all those imaginary needs with which luxury encumbers us, we are content with the bare necessities of nature, and there is complete equality and perpetual peace among men – in a word, there is pure enjoyment of a carefree life, frittered away in idle dreams or childish play. It is yearnings such as these which make tales of Robinson Crusoe and voyages to the South Sea islands so attractive; but in a wider sense, they are symptoms of that weariness of civilized life which thinking people feel when they seek its value in pleasure alone, and when they resort to idleness as an antidote as soon as reason reminds them that they ought to give value to their life through their actions. The vacuity of this wish for a return to the past age of simplicity and innocence is adequately demonstrated by the foregoing account of man's original state. For as we have seen, man cannot remain in this state because it does not satisfy him, and he is even less inclined to go back to it once he has left it. Consequently, he must continue to ascribe his present condition and all its hardships to himself and his own choice.

An account of human history will be of benefit to man and will serve to instruct and improve him if it contains the following lessons. It must show him that he should not blame providence for the evils which oppress him, and that he is not entitled to ascribe his own misdemeanours to an original crime committed by his earliest ancestors, by alleging, for example, that a disposition to commit similar offences has been passed down to their descendants; for there can be nothing inherited about arbitrary actions. It should show him instead that he has every justification for acknowledging the action of his first ancestors as his own, and that he should hold himself wholly responsible for all the evils which spring from the misuse of his reason; for he is quite capable of realizing that, in the same circumstances, he would have behaved in exactly the same way, in that his first act in using reason would have been to misuse it（even if nature advised him otherwise）. Once this point concerning moral evils has been correctly understood, the strictly physical evils will scarcely tip the balance in our favour when merits and faults are weighed against each other.

The conclusion to be drawn from this attempt to describe the earliest history of mankind with the help of philosophy is therefore as follows. We should be content with providence and with the course of human affairs as a whole, which does not begin with good and then proceed to evil, but develops gradually from the worse to the better; and each individual is for his own part called upon by nature itself to contribute towards this progress to the best of his ability.

————————————————————

[1] The urge to communicate must have been the original motive for human beings who were still alone to announce their existence to living creatures outside themselves, especially to those which emit sounds which can be imitated and which can subsequently serve as a name. A similar effect of this urge can still be seen in children and thoughtless people who disturb the thinking section of the community by banging, shouting, whistling, singing and other noisy pastimes（and often even by noisy religious devotions）. For I can see no motive for such behaviour other than a desire on the part of those concerned to proclaim their existence to the world at large.

[2] The following may be cited as only a few examples of this conflict between man's aspiration towards his moral destiny on the one hand, and his unchanging obedience to laws inherent in his nature and appropriate to a crude and animal condition on the other.

Nature has fixed the time at which human beings reach maturity – in terms of their urge and ability to reproduce their kind – at the age of approximately sixteen or seventeen. This is the age at which, in the raw state of nature, a youth literally becomes a man; for he then has the capacity to look after himself, to reproduce his kind, and to look after his children as well as his wife. The simplicity of his needs makes this an easy task. But in a civilized state, he requires numerous means of support, in terms both of skill and of favourable external circumstances, in order to perform these functions. In the context of civil society, the corresponding stage is therefore postponed – at least on average – by a further ten years. Nevertheless, nature has not altered the age of puberty to match the progressive refinement of society, but sticks stubbornly to the law which it has imposed on the survival of the human race as an animal species. As a result, the effect of social customs on the end of nature – and vice versa – is inevitably prejudicial. For in the state of nature, a human being is already a man at an age when civilized man（who nevertheless still retains his character as natural man） is merely a youth, or even only a child; for we may well describe as a child someone who, in the civil state, is unable because of his age to support even himself, let alone others of his kind, despite having the urge and capacity to produce offspring as called upon by nature. For nature has certainly not endowed living creatures with instincts and capacities in order that they should resist and suppress them. Such abilities were consequently not designed for a state of civilization, but merely for the survival of the human race as an animal species; and the civilized state thus inevitably comes into conflict with the latter, a conflict which only a perfect civil constitution – the ultimate goal of culture – can resolve. Meanwhile, the intervening period [between the state of nature and the state of perfection] is filled as a rule with vices and their consequences, i.e. with human misery in its various forms.

A further example may confirm the truth of the proposition that nature has endowed us with two distinct abilities for two distinct purposes, namely that of man as an animal species and that of man as a moral species. The example in question is the saying of Hippocrates ‘ars longa, vita brevis’. The arts and sciences could be advanced much further by one individual with the appropriate talents, once he had attained the necessary maturity of judgement through long practice and the acquisition of knowledge, than by whole generations of scholars in succession, provided that this individual could live and retain his youthful mental capacities for the total lifetimes of the generations in question. Now it is evident that nature has fixed the length of human life with a view to ends other than that of the advancement of the sciences. For just when the most fortunate of thinkers is on the verge of the greatest discoveries which his skill and experience entitle him to expect, old age intervenes; he loses his acuteness and must leave it to the next generation（which starts once more from the ABC and must again traverse the entire distance which had already been covered） to take a further step in the progress of culture. Thus, the course which the human race follows on the way to fulfilling its destiny appears subject to incessant interruptions, with a constant risk of reverting to the original barbarism; and the Greek philosopher had some justification when he complained that it is a pity that we have to die just when we have begun to realize how we ought to have lived.

As a third example, we may cite the inequality of men – not their inequality in terms of natural gifts or goods bestowed on them by fortune, but it terms of universal human rights, about which Rousseau complains with a great deal of truth. Yet this inequality is inseparable from culture, so long as the latter proceeds, as it were, without a plan（and this is inevitably the case for a considerable period of time）. But it was surely not imposed on man by nature, for nature gave him both freedom and reason, and reason decreed that this freedom is subject to no other limits than those of its own universal and external legality, which is known as civil right. Man was meant to rise, by his own efforts, above the barbarism of his natural abilities, but to take care not to contravene them even as he rises above them. He can expect to attain this skill only at a late stage and after many unsuccessful attempts; and in the meantime, the human race groans under the evils which it inflicts on itself as a result of its own inexperience.

[3] The Bedouins of Arabia still describe themselves as children of a former sheikh, the founder of their tribe（such as Beni Haled and others）. But the sheikh is by no means their master, and he cannot force his will upon them as he chooses. For in a nation of herdsmen, no one has fixed property which he cannot take with him, so that any family which is discontented with its tribe can easily leave it and join forces with another.

导读

李耳（前571—前471），字聃，后世尊称为“老子”，楚国苦县厉乡曲仁里人（今河南省鹿邑县），春秋时期著名思想家，被尊奉为道家与道教的始祖。在《史记》等正统史料中对其身世经历的描述只有寥寥数语，野史杂传中则多为传说，不足全信，故而在今人眼中，老子是一位颇有着神秘色彩的仙风道骨式的人物。相传老子担任周王室管理藏书的官员，师从商容；之后治学传道，开创道家学派，被广为推崇。孔子还曾专程拜访老子问道问礼，但鉴于老子心中“自隐无名”的追求，故而始终不曾著书立说。之后，老子有感于周王朝衰微，于心不忍，故而决意西行离去，途中受函谷关令尹喜的诚意邀托，终于留下《道德经》五千言以讲道德之事，分上下两卷，之后便翩翩离去，隐匿于世。本书也即成为老子的唯一著述，更是道家学派和道教中至高无上的宝典圣经，是“三洞”之精华。关于老子之后的去向众说纷纭，自汉代开始，有传说认为老子携尹喜前往西域，教化胡人，创立佛教，此即为“老子化胡”说，不过这种说法并无确凿佐证。在道教神仙体系中，老子被神话为“三清”之一的“太清道德天尊”，也就是我们所熟知的“太上老君”。

《道德经》，又被称为《老子》《道德真经》《五千言》《老子五千文》等，这是因为在官方史料《史记》中并未正式提及其书名，而是后世根据其内容主旨附会而得。《道德经》分上下两卷，共五千多字，分八十一章，传世本上卷名为《道经》，讲述道之所传；下卷名为《德经》，讲述修养自身心意。《道德经》一书的文字，具有言简意赅、句式平整、音韵协调、修辞多样、字字珠玑、论点精辟、意蕴深远等特点，以五千的字量，囊括尽了老子一生的哲学智慧，可谓是哲学史、文学史与宗教史上的一部旷世经典，至今仍然流行于世界各个国家的读者群体之中。根据联合国教科文组织统计，《道德经》是除《圣经》之外被翻译成外国文字发行量最多的文化名著，其影响力可见一斑！

《道德经》可谓是东方式传统哲学的源起，即一种朴素的辩证思想与形而上学，在内容上既包藏对宇宙万象的探求，也蕴含对处世哲学的思索，真真正正称得上是一本“奇书”，无数能士贤圣哪怕穷尽一生却依然无法悉知一二。“道”在《道德经》中多次出现，是书的核心思想，同时也是一个不可言说的抽象概念，开篇第一句所谓“道可道，非常道；名可名，非常名”。“道”，是世界的究极本质，是万物的宗主；而且，“道生一，一生二，二生三，三生万物”的观念，更是将来源于“三易”中的世界观系统化，道出了万物的演变与世界的秩序。基于这种“人法地，地法天，天法道，道法自然”的世界观，更是逐渐孕育出了中国影响力与规模最大的本土宗教——道教。道教溯源于春秋道家，在汉末时初具规模，于南北朝时吸收“儒”“释”二家之长，终于在唐朝时最终确立宗教系统，其在华人社会中的地位更是与日俱增。除此之外，《道德经》中还蕴含着丰富的政治智慧及文学智慧，比如“无为而治”“小国寡民”等理念，我们不得不叹服数千年前古人思想的伟大。

作为道家学派的不朽代表，《道德经》的思想成就是众所周知、不容辩驳的，其影响力甚至早已超出中国乃至东亚范围，成为世界思想宝库中的一颗璀璨明珠。《道德经》生于春秋乱世，成于百家争鸣，流传千年至今依然熠熠生辉。今人重读《道德经》，无须再执着于究其全貌，更重要的是一字一句中受用一生的收获，切身体会这中华民族亘古流传的文化精髓。

柴尔

卷一

一章

道可道，非常道[1]；名可名，非常名[2]。无名天地之始，有名万物之母[3]。故常无，欲以观其妙[4]；常有，欲以观其徼[5]；此两者，同出而异名[6]，同谓之玄[7]。玄之又玄，众妙之门[8]。

译文：凡是可以言说的道，都不是永恒的自然之道；凡是可以命名的名，都不是永恒的名。天地之始原本无名，而万物却源于有名。所以，只有修养到“无”的境界，才能看到自然的奥妙，但必须要从“有”来观察，才能看到万物的边际。其实，“有”和“无”本质上相同，有着共同的起源，只是表现形式和名称不同罢了；因为是同体同源，所以都可称之为“玄”，它们幽深远大，是理解天地自然众多奥妙秘密的大门。

二章

天下皆知美之为美，斯恶矣[9]；皆知善之为善，斯不善矣。故有无相生，难易相成，长短相形，高下相倾，音声相和，前后相随[10]。是以圣人处无为之事[11]，行不言之教[12]。万物作焉而不辞，生而不有，为而不恃，功成而弗居[13]。夫唯弗居，是以不去[14]。

译文：如果天下的人都知道什么是美，那么丑就显露出来了；如果天下的人都知道什么是善，那么恶就显露出来了。所以，有与无在对应中相生互变，难与易在对应中互为成功的条件，长与短只是在对应中相互比较而言，高与下在对应中相互倾斜而归于平等，音与声在对应中相互构成自然界和谐的音律，前与后是在对应中相随而来去的。因此，圣人做事只是顺其自然；他用行为自然而然地影响人们，用不着发号令强行向人们灌输什么道理。他化生万物，但并不统治万物；他使万物生存，却不去占有万物；他慷慨赐予万物一切，而不以此为自己的功绩。正是因为他不居功，他的功绩才永远不会被抹杀。

三章

不尚贤[15]，使民不争[16]；不贵难得之货，使民不为盗[17]；不见可欲，使民心不乱[18]。是以圣人之治，虚其心，实其腹，弱其志，强其骨[19]；常使民无知无欲，使夫智者不敢为也。为无为，则无不治[20]。

译文：不标榜贤才，使人民不去争逐名位。不看重稀有难得的物品，使人民不去用非正常手段获得它们。不炫耀可以引起贪欲的事物，使民心不被扰乱。因此，圣人管理人民的方法是：净化他们的思想，满足他们的安饱需求，淡化他们的志向欲望，强健他们的筋骨肌肉。始终使人民无欺诈争盗的心智和欲念，处于返朴守淳的状态，这样一来，个别的“智者”也就不敢有所作为了。所有人的行为都顺其自然，也就没有什么不能治理的了。

四章

道冲，而用之或不盈[21]。渊兮，似万物之宗[22]。挫其锐，解其纷，和其光，同其尘[23]。湛兮，似或存[24]。吾不知谁之子，象帝之先[25]。

译文：道虚空而不满，但它却取之不尽、用之不竭。它渊深澄寂，就好像是天下万物的主宗一样。顿挫它的坚锐、化解它的纷扰、涵敛它的光芒、混同它于尘俗。它依然是澄澄湛湛，似无或存。我不知道它是谁的后代，它好像比能主宰万有的大帝要早。

五章

天地不仁[26]，以万物为刍狗[27]；圣人不仁[28]，以百姓为刍狗。天地之间，其犹橐籥乎[29]？虚而不屈[30]，动而愈出。多言数穷[31]，不如守中[32]。

译文：天地无所偏私、偏倚，它对万物同等看待，万物按春夏秋冬自然地生长和消亡，好像人们祭祀用的刍狗一样。圣人也无所偏爱、亲疏，他对所有人都同等看待，人们按照自然规律自作自息，好像人们祭祀用的刍狗一样。天地犹如一只嘘吸不已的大风箱，看似空虚，其实无穷，静而藏之，动而用之便有，越动越生生不已。圣人也应当与天地一样，持守中正虚静，不必对人对事多作肯定或否定，才能使人们生生不息。

六章

谷神不死[33]，是谓玄牝[34]。玄牝之门，是谓天地根[35]。绵绵若存[36]，用之不勤[37]。

译文：谷神虚空而奥妙无穷、永不失灭，可称为“微妙的母性”。微妙的母性是天地万物生命源泉的根本。它在时间的长河中，好像是绵绵不绝的存在，化育万物的功能，也是用之不尽的。

七章

天长地久。天地所以能长且久者，以其不自生[38]，故能长生[39]。是以圣人后其身而身先[40]，外其身而身存。非以其无私邪？故能成其私[41]。

译文：天是长在地是久存的。天地之所以能够长久存在，是因为天地不为自己的需要而生，因而能够长久存在。因此，圣人将自己的肉体生命价值放在众人之后，结果反而能使自己处于众人之先；将自己的肉体生命置之度外，结果反而能使生命长存。并非圣人没有私心，只是因为圣人彻悟了大道，所以才能够成就自己的生命长存。

八章

上善若水[42]。水善利万物而不争，处众人之所恶，故几于道[43]。居善地[44]，心善渊[45]，与善仁[46]，言善信，政善治[47]，事善能，动善时。夫唯不争，故无尤[48]。

译文：一个人如果要合乎道的意识、行为，就要做到如水一样。水有利于万物而不与万物相争，宁愿自居在众人所厌恶的低下、隐蔽的地方，所以，水具有非常接近于道的特性。一个人如果能做到如水一样，就要善于自处而甘居下地，心胸虚静深沉，与人与物宽厚仁慈，说话遵守诚信，为政精简清明，处事调剂融和，行动遵从恰当的天时节令。正是由于不与人相争、不与物相争，才能永无过患而安然处顺。

九章

持而盈之[49]，不如其已[50]；揣而棁之[51]，不可长保。金玉满堂，莫之能守。富贵而骄，自遗其咎[52]。功遂身退[53]，天之道[54]。

译文：物品装得太满必定会流失，不如不要装满；锤锻得太尖，尖端不可能长久保持。金玉财宝聚积了满屋满堂，未必能够守住；富贵之人若处处骄横，必定会给自己招来灾难。功成名就之后，主动隐身退后，这才符合自然规律。

十章

载营魄抱一[55]，能无离乎？专气致柔[56]，能如婴儿乎[57]？涤除玄览[58]，能无疵乎[59]？爱民治国，能无为乎？天门开阖，能为雌乎[60]？明白四达，能无知乎？生之畜之，生而不有，为而不恃，长而不宰，是谓玄德[61]。

译文：将灵魂和精神合抱为一，永不分离；专注于凝聚精气，达到平静柔和，好像无私无欲的婴儿一样；清除心灵中的任何邪念，心如明镜，照见万象；用无为的心态去爱护人民、治理国家；在心神与物相接之际恬然守静；不需要知识、智慧等人为地机巧，便能够明白与万物相通相识。生养万物，却不去占有万物；慷慨赐予万物一切，却不以此为功绩；化生万物，却不去统治万物；这就是玄妙的德行。

十一章

三十辐共一毂[62]，当其无，有车之用[63]。埏埴以为器[64]，当其无，有器之用。凿户牖以为室[65]，当其无，有室之用。故有之以为利，无之以为用[66]。

译文：车轮的三十根辐条汇集到车轮中心的毂上，中空无一物，却能合众辐条之力，使车轮旋转不息，实现车的功用。用黏土制作器皿，中间空空，才能装盛东西，达到使用的效果。建造一间房屋，必须开辟门窗，光线空气流通，才能住人。所以，“有”给人便利，“无”发挥了它的作用。

十二章

五色令人目盲[67]；五音令人耳聋[68]；五味令人口爽[69]；驰骋畋猎，令人心发狂[70]；难得之货，令人行妨[71]。是以圣人为腹不为目[72]，故去彼取此[73]。

译文：五色俱来，会使我们像盲人一样什么也看不清楚；五音同出，会使我们像聋子一样什么也听不清楚；五味一起品尝，只会损伤舌头的味觉功能。骑马驰骋、猎取野物，会使人心情狂乱；追求难得之物、稀有之物，会使人行为不端。因此，圣人只使用有限的物品来养育自己，而不会去占有过多的物品，但求恬淡安饱，而不以物役己追逐声色之愉。

十三章

宠辱若惊，贵大患若身[74]。何谓宠辱若惊？宠为下[75]，得之若惊，失之若惊，是谓宠辱若惊。何谓贵大患若身？吾所以有大患者，为吾有身；及吾无身[76]，吾有何患？故贵以身为天下[77]，若可寄天下；爱以身为天下，若可托天下[78]。

译文：得宠或受辱便感到惊恐，把荣辱这样的大患看得与自身生命一样珍贵。什么是得宠或受辱便感到惊恐呢？得宠者相对宠者往往是卑下的，得到宠爱就格外惊喜，失去宠爱就惊慌不安，这就叫作得宠或受辱便感到惊恐。什么是把荣辱这样的大患看得与自身生命一样珍贵呢？我之所以有重大的忧患，是因为我有血肉之躯；如果我没有血肉之躯，那么我还有什么值得忧患的事情呢？因此，看重自身是为了天下，这样的人就可以把天下寄交给他；爱护自身是为了天下，这样的人就可以把天下托付给他。

十四章

视之不见名曰夷[79]；听之不闻名曰希[80]；搏之不得名曰微[81]。此三者不可致诘[82]，故混而为一[83]。其上不皦，其下不昧[84]，绳绳兮不可名[85]，复归于无物。是谓无状之状，无物之象，是谓恍惚[86]。迎之不见其首；随之不见其后。执古之道，以御今之有[87]。能知古始，是谓道纪[88]。

译文：睁大眼睛看仍看不见的东西，称之为“夷”；仔细倾听仍听不到的东西，称之为“希”；认真摸索仍触不到的东西，称之为“微”。这三种东西无法追究推问到底，本来就是同一种东西。这种东西上不耀眼，下不昏暗，它纷绵不息无法描述，说它是一个具体的物质，它又不是物质。所以，它没有固定的形状，也不能用任何一种东西来比拟它的形象，只好称之为“恍惚”。迎面而来时看不到它的前部；跟随其后时看不见它的后部。遵循古老的“道”的规律，就可以驾驭今天的现实，也可以溯知远古万物的起源，这就是“道”的纲纪。

十五章

古之善为道者[89]，微妙玄通，深不可识。夫唯不可识，故强为之容[90]：豫兮若冬涉川[91]；犹兮若畏四邻[92]；俨兮其若客[93]；涣兮其若凌释[94]；敦兮其若朴[95]；旷兮其若谷[96]；混兮其若浊[97]；孰能浊以静之徐清？孰能安以久，动之徐生[98]？保此道者不欲盈[99]。夫唯不盈，故能蔽而新成[100]。

译文：古代修道之人，精微到妙不可言、无所不通的境界，一般人简直没有办法认识他。正是由于一般人没有办法认识他，所以，只好勉强地描述一些他的外在形象：他小心谨慎，时时像冬天过河；他待人恭敬，好像畏惧周围的人；他严肃拘谨，似乎总是在做客；他融和疏脱，像冰水消融一样；他敦厚朴素，像未经雕琢的木一样；他心胸开阔，像深幽的山谷一样；他浑然纯厚，像一潭浊水一样。谁能使混浊动荡的状态平静下来，然后慢慢变得澄清？又有谁能使平静的状态变动起来，然后慢慢显出生机？保持这个道的人不求盈满。正因为他不求盈自满，所以他能够使敝旧的事物转化为新的事物。

十六章

致虚极[101]，守静笃[102]。万物并作，吾以观复[103]。夫物芸芸[104]，各复归其根[105]。归根曰静，是谓复命[106]。复命曰常[107]，知常曰明[108]。不知常，妄作凶。知常容[109]，容乃公[110]，公乃王[111]，王乃天，天乃道，道乃久，没身不殆。

译文：心态达到极度的空明无欲，持守彻底的无为安静，才得以反复观察万物生长活动的循环规律。万物生长茂盛到极致，必渐枯靡，终归寂灭，回归到原本状态，这就是“归根”；归根也就是归于“静”，这就叫“复命”，复命叫“常”，体悟天地万物的“常道”，属于明智之人。没有体悟天地万物的“常道”，乱作妄为，必然大凶大害，没有好结果。认识到“常道”的人才能包容一切，具有宽容的心怀，才能处事公正；公正才能为天下之王，这样的王才符合天地自然法则，符合自然的“道”，符合自然的道才能长久，终生不会遭到危险。

十七章

太上，下知有之[112]；其次[113]，亲而誉之；其次，畏之；其次，侮之。信不足焉，有不信焉[114]。悠兮，其贵言[115]。功成事遂[116]，百姓皆谓：“我自然。”[117]

译文：最好的世代君主，人们只知道有他这么一个人而已；次一等的君主，人们亲近他，然后赞誉他；再次一等的君主，人们畏惧他；最次的君主，人们辱骂他。失信于民的君主，人们不信任服从他。君主悠然而不轻易发号施令，等事情成功之后，人们就说这本来就合于自然之道，没有什么好大惊小怪的。

十八章

大道废，有仁义；智慧出，有大伪[118]；六亲不和[119]，有孝慈；国家昏乱[120]，有忠臣。

译文：合乎自然规律的大道废弛了，便提出了仁义道德。智慧产生之后，世间便出现了虚伪和欺骗。父子、兄弟、夫妻不和，才产生所谓的孝慈。当国家昏乱的时候，便会有忠臣出现。

十九章

绝圣弃智[121]，民利百倍；绝仁弃义，民复孝慈；绝巧弃利，盗贼无有。此三者，以为文不足[122]，故令有所属[123]，见素抱朴[124]，少私寡欲。

译文：抛弃掉那些卖弄聪明才智的做法，人们的生活可以和平安静百倍；抛弃掉那些假仁假义的做法，人们自然会复归于孝慈；抛弃掉那些取巧获利的做法，自然不会有盗贼作奸犯科。圣智、仁义、巧利这三种东西都是巧饰，不足以治理天下。所以要使人有所归属，怀抱原始天然的朴素；随时保持纯净无杂，淡化欲望的思想观念。

二十章

绝学无忧[125]。唯之与阿[126]，相去几何？善之与恶，相去若何？人之所畏，不可不畏。荒兮其未央[127]哉！众人熙熙[128]，如享太牢[129]，如春登台[130]。我独泊兮其未兆[131]，如婴儿之未孩[132]；儽儽兮若无所归[133]。众人皆有余，而我独若遗[134]。我愚人之心也哉[135]，沌沌兮！俗人昭昭，我独昏昏[136]。俗人察察，我独闷闷[137]。澹兮其若海，飂兮若无止[138]。众人皆有以，而我独顽且鄙[139]。我独异于人，而贵食母[140]。

译文：不要一切学问，就会无忧无虑。唯唯诺诺与大声呵斥，两者之间有什么区别呢？善的事物与恶的事物，又有多大差别呢？众人所畏惧的，不能不畏惧。像荒原大沙漠一样广大无边，永无尽头！众人那么喜乐欢悦，有如在享受牛、羊、豕的祭奉一样，又好像春光明媚时登台眺望春色。我却独自如一潭清水，恬淡、宁静，不炫耀自己；又像一个还不懂事的婴儿，天真烂漫，无忧无虑；我平常的心疲惫闲散，好像是找不到归宿。众人都追求更多的财物显得富足有余，唯独我只取维持生命所需而显得贫困匮乏。我多么淳朴、浑厚！普通人对任何事情都非常明白，只有我昏昧不明；普通人对所有事情都精打细算，只有我混混沌沌。胸襟要像大海一样，宽阔无际；境界要像清风一样，清远徐吹。众人对人生都有目的，都要为世所用、为人所用、为己所用；唯独有我顽冥不化，表现很糟糕。我之所以与众人不同，是因为我看重的是吸取大道来滋养自身。

二十一章

孔德之容[141]，惟道是从。道之为物，惟恍惟惚[142]。惚兮恍兮，其中有象[143]；恍兮惚兮，其中有物；窈兮冥兮[144]，其中有精[145]；其精甚真，其中有信[146]。自今及古，其名不去，以阅众甫[147]。吾何以知众甫之状哉？以此[148]。

译文：大德的样态，随着道而转移。“道”这个东西，是模糊不清、似有似无的。在似有似无、模糊不清中，有它的形象；在模糊不清、似有似无中，有它的实物；在深远而不可测中，有它的精质；这种精质非常真切，有它的信验。从今天推及远古，“道”这个名称不能舍去，否则便不能认识万事万物。我凭什么知道万事万物起始的情况呢？就是依据于道。

二十二章

曲则全，枉则直，洼则盈，敝则新，少则得，多则惑[149]。是以圣人抱一为天下式[150]。不自见[151]，故明；不自是，故彰[152]；不自伐[153]，故有功；不自矜[154]，故长。夫唯不争，故天下莫能与之争。古之所谓“曲则全”者，岂虚言哉！诚全而归之。

译文：委曲可以保全，弯曲可以伸直，低洼的地方可以充盈，敝旧可以生新，求多需从求少开始，贪多反而令人迷惑，以致一无所获。因此，圣人以固守道作为天下人的榜样。不显露自己，才更为突出；不自以为是，才更为彰明；不自我夸耀，才会有更多的成功；不自我骄矜，才能更为长久。正是由于顺其自然，不人为地去争取，因此天下人都无法与他相争。古人所说“委曲可以保全”的道理，怎能是空话啊！实实在在走“委曲可以保全”的道路，才能够得上为天下之所归，众望之所属。

二十三章

希言自然[155]。故飘风不终朝[156]，骤雨不终日[157]。孰为此者？天地。天地尚不能久[158]，而况于人乎？故从事于道者，同于道；德者同于德；失者同于失[159]。同于道者，道亦乐得之；同于德者，德亦乐得之；同于失者，失亦乐得之。信不足焉，有不信焉[160]！

译文：“道”是不说话、不发号施令的，一切自然而然。狂风刮不过半天，暴雨下不过一日。这是谁做的事情呢？天地。天地尚不能持久，何况于人呢？因此，从事于道的人合于道；从事于德的人合于德；从事于天的人合于天。合于道的人，道也高兴地接受他；合于德的人，德也高兴地接受他；合于天的人，天也高兴地接受他。人要是诚信不足，就会有不信任的事情发生。

二十四章

企者不立[161]；跨者不行[162]。自见者不明；自是者不彰；自伐者无功；自矜者不长。其在道也，曰余食赘行[163]。物或恶之[164]，故有道者不处。

译文：踮起脚跟站者不能久立；跨大步走者不能远行。自逞己现者反而不突出；自以为是者反而不昭彰；自我夸耀者不会成功；自我骄矜者不会长久。这些行为，从道的观点来看，都是多余、无用的，因而也是有害的。对此，常人都会感到厌恶，所以有道的人不采取这些方式。

二十五章

有物混成[165]，先天地生。寂兮寥兮[166]，独立而不改[167]，周行而不殆[168]，可以为天地母[169]。吾不知其名，强字之曰道[170]，强为之名曰大[171]。大曰逝，逝曰远，远曰反[172]。故道大，天大，地大，人亦大。域中有四大[173]，而人居其一焉。人法地，地法天，天法道，道法自然[174]。

译文：有一个东西涌流长在、源源不断，先天地万物而存在。它没有形象、没有声音，独立存在，始终如一，不为一切外来势力的干扰而改变本性。它无所不在，运行不息，永远无穷无尽。可以称之为天地的母亲。我不知道它的名称，姑且称其为“道”；或者勉强称其为“大”。它无所不在、无所不包而运行不息，运行不息而无边无际，无边无际而循环往复。因此，道无所不包，天无所不包，地无所不包，人亦无所不包。宇宙中有四种无所不包的事物，而人占有其中之一。因此，人要效法大地，地要效法天，天要效法道，道本来就是自然。

二十六章

重为轻根，静为躁君[175]。是以圣人终日行不离辎重[176]，虽有荣观，燕处超然[177]。奈何万乘之主而以身轻天下[178]？轻则失根，躁则失君。

译文：重是轻的根源，静是躁的主宰。因此，圣人随时随地要有负重致远的精神，不忘济世救人的责任感，即便燕然安处在荣华富贵之中，也依然能超然物外，不为荣华富贵所累。为什么贵为万乘之主的君王，却轻举妄动，只图眼前攫取功利，不顾丧失生命的后果？轻则会丧失根基，躁则会丧失主宰。

二十七章

善行无辙迹[179]；善言无瑕谪[180]；善数不用筹策[181]；善闭无关楗而不可开[182]；善结无绳约而不可解[183]。是以圣人常善救人，故无弃人；常善救物，故无弃物。是谓袭明[184]。故善人者，不善人之师；不善人者，善人之资[185]。不贵其师，不爱其资，虽智大迷，是谓要妙[186]。

译文：真正善于行走的，不会留下痕迹；真正话说得好的人，不会留下话柄；真正善于计算的人，用不着计算的工具；真正善于关门的人，不用门栓却使人打不开。真正会打结的人，不结绳扣，也无法解开。事实上，圣人常常救助人，不抛弃任何人；圣人常常救助物，不抛弃任何事物。这可以说是将光明延伸出来。因此，善人是不善人的老师；不善人可以作为善人的借鉴。不崇拜老师，不爱惜可作借鉴的人，虽然各怀聪明，但还是最大的糊涂。这就是幽深而精妙的道理。

二十八章

知其雄[187]，守其雌，为天下溪[188]。为天下溪，常德不离[189]，复归于婴儿。知其白，守其黑，为天下式[190]。为天下式，常德不忒[191]，复归于无极。知其荣，守其辱，为天下谷[192]，为天下谷，常德乃足，复归于朴[193]。朴散则为器[194]，圣人用之[195]，则为官长[196]，故大制不割[197]。

译文：知道什么是强雄，却仍然要安守雌柔，甘愿为天下的溪涧。甘愿为天下的溪涧，才可以做到保有人的德行，重新回归到婴儿那样淳朴无邪的状态。知道什么是明亮，却仍然要安守昏黑，甘愿为天下的模式。甘愿为天下的模式，才不会偏离人的德行，才能够回归到大道。知道什么是荣乐，却仍然要安守卑辱，甘愿为天下的低谷。甘愿为天下的低谷，才能够充实人的德行，从而恢复人的本来面目。人没有了淳朴本性，就变成了器物工具，圣人懂得这个道理，则成为百官之长；因此，国家大法是不割舍人的本性的。

二十九章

将欲取天下而为之[198]，吾见其不得已[199]。天下神器[200]，不可为也。为者败之[201]，执者失之。夫物或行或随[202]，或歔或吹[203]，或强或羸[204]，或载或隳[205]。是以圣人去甚，去奢，去泰[206]。

译文：想要治理天下而强行去做，我看这种人是不会得逞的。天下这个东西，是一个神妙不可思议的东西，不可过分执着强力妄为。过分执着强力妄为必将遭遇失败。事实上，万物的前行和后随，急动或缓作，强壮或柔弱，安稳或危殆，都是自然而然的事情。因此，圣人会去除过分的行为，去除奢华的行为，去除极端的行为。

三十章

以道佐人主者[207]，不以兵强天下[208]，其事好还[209]。师之所处，荆棘生焉[210]。大军之后，必有凶年。善者果而已[211]，不敢以取强。果而勿矜[212]，果而勿伐[213]，果而勿骄，果而不得已，果而勿强。物壮则老[214]，是谓不道[215]，不道早已。

译文：用自然之道辅佐君主的人，不会赞成使用武力去侵略别人，每件事都必定有还报。军队所到的地方，荆棘就长满了；大战过后，一定会变成荒年。善用兵者，仅仅谋取胜利而已，没有必要继续逞强。胜利了不要自我骄矜，胜利了不要自我夸耀，胜利了不要自我骄傲；打仗只是为了保卫自己的生存，是不得已而为之，胜利了不能继续逞强好胜。少壮的事物伤害老弱，这不是自然之道，不遵从自然之道，只能加速自己的灭亡。

三十一章

夫兵者[216]，不祥之器，物或恶之，故有道者不处[217]。君子居则贵左，用兵则贵右[218]。兵者，不祥之器，非君子之器，不得已而用之，恬淡为上[219]。胜而不美，而美之者，是乐杀人。夫乐杀人者，则不可以得志于天下矣。吉事尚左，凶事尚右[220]。偏将军居左，上将军居右。言以丧礼处之。杀人之众，以哀悲泣之[221]，战胜，以丧礼处之。

译文：杀人的武器是不祥的工具，大家都厌恶它，因此有道之人不肯轻易使用它。君子平常生活工作时以左边为贵，用兵打仗时以右边为贵。武器是不祥的工具，不是君子的工具。万不得已时才会使用它，使用它时恬静平淡为上，胜利了也不要洋洋得意。胜利了洋洋得意的人，纯粹是以杀人为乐。那些以杀人为乐的人，终归是要失败的，不可能逞行于天下。吉祥的事情以左为上，凶丧的事情以右为上。偏将军在左边，上将军在右边。这就是按照办丧事的礼仪去处理。战争中若伤亡较多，应当以悲哀的心情为死伤者送葬。对于获胜归来的将士，要用丧礼来迎接他们。

三十二章

道常无名[222]，朴虽小[223]，天下莫能臣[224]。侯王若能守之，万物将自宾[225]。天地相合，以降甘露，民莫之令而自均[226]。始制有名[227]，名亦既有，夫亦将知止，知止可以不殆[228]。譬道之在天下，犹川谷之于江海。

译文：道本来无名，极其微妙，天下没有谁能主宰它。侯王如果能遵守自然之道，万物将会自动归附于他。就像天地间阴阳之气相合，自然会降下甘露一样，不用发布政令，人们自己就会平等地协调均匀。治理天下就要建立各种制度确定各种名分，各种制度、名分出来了，要知道适可而止，知道适可而止，就没有什么危险了。可以这样比喻，道对天下的作用，好像川溪汇聚成江海一样。

三十三章

知人者智，自知者明。胜人者有力，自胜者强[229]。知足者富，强行者有志[230]。不失其所者久，死而不亡者寿[231]。

译文：能够清楚认识别人的人，是有智慧的人；能够了解自己的人，是明白人。能够战胜别人，不过是有力量罢了；能够战胜自己，才称得上坚强。知足的人总是富有的，把做不到的事硬做到了，这叫作有志气。守住本分的人可以长久，精神不死的人可以永存。

三十四章

大道泛兮，其可左右[232]。万物恃之以生而不辞，功成不名有[233]。衣养万物而不为主[234]。常无欲，可名于小；万物归焉而不为主[235]，可名为大。以其终不自为大，故能成其大。

译文：大道广博，无往而不在。万物依赖它生长，而它却对万物不加干涉，它滋养万物生长却不以此为己功。它庇护着万物却并不想做万物的主人。它无欲无求，因此可以随便为它定名，称之为小。万物归附于它，它仍然不去主宰万物，包容了万物，这可以叫它为大。由于它始终没有自高自大，所以才能成为伟大。

三十五章

执大象，天下往[236]。往而不害，安平太[237]。乐与饵[238]，过客止。道之出口，淡乎其无味，视之不足见，听之不足闻，用之不足既[239]。

译文：持守自然之道的人，天下都将来归附。归附于道，不互相伤害，于是大家都永远平和安泰。动听的音乐和美味的佳肴，能够吸引住过往的客人。而“道”这个东西，讲起来平淡而无味，看也看不见，听也听不到，但万物都在用它而用之不尽。

三十六章

将欲歙之，必固张之[240]；将欲弱之，必固强之；将欲废之，必固兴之；将欲取之，必固与之[241]。是谓微明[242]。柔弱胜刚强。鱼不可脱于渊，国之利器不可以示人[243]。

译文：要想收敛一个东西，必须先扩张它。要想削弱它，必须先加强它。要想废弃它，必须先兴举它。要想夺取它，必须先给予它。这就是从微弱、渺小的地方看出大道理来。柔弱可以战胜刚强。就像鱼不能离开水一样，国家的生存命脉，也不能轻易展示给别人。

三十七章

道常无为而无不为[244]。侯王若能守之[245]，万物将自化。化而欲作[246]，吾将镇之以无名之朴[247]。无名之朴，夫亦将无欲[248]。不欲以静，天下将自定。

译文：永恒的大道始终无所作为，但是却能够取得无所不为的成果。侯王如果能持守自然之道，万物将自行调节转化。转化后如果又萌生欲望，我将用道来使他们安定。用道来使他们安定，人们又归于完全无欲的状态。处于无欲状态便会静守本分，天下就会自行进入安定状态。

卷二

三十八章

上德不德，是以有德；下德不失德，是以无德[249]。上德无为而无以为[250]；下德为之而有以为。上仁为之而无以为；上义为之而有以为[251]。上礼为之而莫之应，则攘臂而扔之[252]。故失道而后德，失德而后仁，失仁而后义，失义而后礼。夫礼者，忠信之薄，而乱之首[253]。前识者[254]，道之华，而愚之始[255]。是以大丈夫处其厚，不居其薄[256]；处其实，不居其华。故去彼取此[257]。

译文：有上品德行的人做善事很自然，不外在表现有德让别人知道，这才是真正有德行；达不到上品德行的人，做善事总要外在表现出不离德而让别人看出来，这已经不是真正有德行了。有上品德行的人顺应自然，无心作为却无所不为；达不到上品德行的人，行为有目的却不一定有成效。上仁之人的行为是自然无目的的；上义之人的行为是有人为目的的。上礼之人的行为如果没有人响应，他会卷起袖子强拉硬拽别人来赞同自己。因此，“道”渐行消失了以后，才产生了“德”，“德”消失了以后，才产生了“仁”；“仁”消失了之后，才产生了“义”；“义”消失了之后，才产生了“礼”。虚伪之礼是世风日下、忠信式微，乃至天下祸乱的根源。花巧之智是道的虚华，愚昧的开始。所以，君子淳厚，而不会陷入浇薄之境；或者，注重于朴实，而不至于被表面的虚华所欺骗。因此要舍弃虚华、浇薄而采取朴实、淳厚。

三十九章

昔之得一者[258]：天得一以清；地得一以宁；神得一以灵；谷得一以盈[259]；万物得一以生；侯王得一以为天下贞。其致之[260]，天无以清将恐裂；地无以宁将恐废[261]；神无以灵将恐歇[262]；谷无以盈将恐竭[263]；万物无以生将恐灭；侯王无以贞将恐蹶[264]。故贵以贱为本，高以下为基。是以侯王自称孤、寡、不谷[265]。此非以贱为本邪？非乎？故至数誉无誉。不欲琭琭如玉，珞珞如石。

译文：从前得到过道的：天得到道便可以清明；地得到道便可以安宁；神得到道便可以灵妙；河谷得到道便可以充盈；万物得到道便可以生存；侯王得到道便可以使天下安定。推而言之：天不清明恐怕会导致破裂；地不安宁恐怕会导致崩陷；神不灵异恐怕会导致消失；河谷不充盈恐怕会导致枯竭；万物不生存恐怕会导致毁灭；侯王不使天下安定恐怕会导致败亡。因此，贵以贱为根本，高以下为基础。侯王自称孤、寡、不谷。这不正是以贱为根本吗？不是吗？所以最高的荣誉无需赞美称誉。不求琭琭晶莹像宝玉，只愿珞珞坚硬像山石。

四十章

反者道之动[266]，弱者道之用[267]。天下万物生于有[268]，有生于无[269]。

译文：道的运动规律是循环往复的，道的作用是微妙、柔弱的。天下的万物产生于有，而有产生于无。

四十一章

上士闻道，勤而行之[270]；中士闻道，若存若亡；下士闻道，大笑之。不笑不足以为道。故建言有之[271]：明道若昧[272]；进道若退；夷道若颣[273]。上德若谷[274]；大白若辱；广德若不足；建德若偷[275]；质真若渝[276]。大方无隅[277]；大器晚成；大音希声[278]；大象无形；道隐无名[279]。夫唯道，善贷且成[280]。

译文：贤能之士听到道，会积极努力去修道；中等才德的人听到后，会有时去有时又不去；才德差的人听到后，会哈哈大笑。如果他们不嘲笑的话，那道也就称不上是道了。事实上，古语中已经阐明：光明的大道看起来似乎暗昧；进步的大道看起来似乎在退步；平坦的大道似乎崎岖不平。高尚的品德好像溪谷；纯洁的心灵能够忍辱；广博的德行总感到自我不足；强健的意志总显得怠惰懒散；质朴而纯真却好像含有污垢。特别大的四方形是没有边角的；特殊高明的器物往往是最后出现的；巨大的声音通常是听不见的；庞大的形象也是很难看得见的；道幽隐不可见而没有名称。但是，唯有道才最善于对万物施加影响，并促成万物的生成运转变化。

四十二章

道生一[281]，一生二[282]，二生三[283]，三生万物。万物负阴而抱阳[284]，冲气以为和[285]。人之所恶，唯孤、寡、不谷[286]，而王公以为称。故物或损之而益，或益之而损。人之所教，我亦教之：强梁者不得其死[287]。吾将以为教父[288]。

译文：道是独一无二的，道本身包含着阴阳二气，阴阳二气相交中和形成一种和谐状态，万物在这种状态中产生。万物背着阴而向着阳，阴阳二气互相交冲而成协调和谐的状态。人们最厌恶的就是“孤”、“寡”、“不谷”，但王公却用这些字来称呼自己。所以一切事物，如果减损它，它反而得到增益；如果增益它，它却反而受到减损。别人这样教导我，我也这样去教导别人：恃力强行的人不会有好下场。我把这个道理当作教育的最高原则。

四十三章

天下之至柔[289]，驰骋天下之至坚[290]。无有入无间[291]，吾是以知无为之有益。不言之教，无为之益，天下希及之[292]。

译文：天下最柔弱的东西，可以穿越天下最坚硬的东西；看不见形象的东西可以穿透没有间隙的东西。由此原理，我可以知道无为是一种有益的处世方法。我所提倡的不言之教、无为之益，天下很少有人能达到这个境界。

四十四章

名与身孰亲？身与货孰多[293]？得与亡孰病[294]？甚爱必大费[295]，多藏必厚亡[296]。知足不辱，知止不殆[297]，可以长久。

译文：名利与生命，我们更爱哪一个？生命与财物，哪个更重要？得到与失去它们之中的哪一个，对我们害处更大？过分珍爱某个事物，必然要为它耗费大量的精力；过于积敛财富，必定会招致惨重的损失。所以，懂得知足，就不会受到屈辱；懂得适可而止，就不会遇到危险，这样才可以保持长久的平安。

四十五章

大成若缺[298]，其用不弊[299]。大盈若冲[300]，其用不穷。大直若屈[301]，大巧若拙，大辩若讷[302]。躁胜寒[303]，静胜热。清静为天下正[304]。

译文：完美的东西好像是有缺陷的，但它的作用不会衰竭。充盈的东西好像是空虚的，但它的作用不会穷尽。直的东西好像是弯曲的，精巧的好像是笨拙的；卓越的辩才，仿佛有些口吃。清寒可以克服躁动，安静可以克服暑热。清静无为才能统治天下。

四十六章

天下有道，却走马以粪[305]；天下无道，戎马生于郊[306]。罪莫大于可欲，祸莫大于不知足，咎莫大于欲得[307]。故知足之足，常足矣[308]。

译文：天下的人奉行自然之道，战马都可以退还到田间用来耕种。天下的人背离自然之道，连怀胎的母马也要送上战场，产仔于战地的郊外。最大的罪过就是有太多的欲望，最大的祸害就是不知足，最大的过失就是想占有。所以，只有知足者才能够常常处于满足状态。

四十七章

不出户，知天下；不窥牖[309]，见天道。其出弥远，其知弥少。是以圣人不行而知，不见而明，不为而成。

译文：不出门就能知道天下的事情；不望窗外，就能知道日月星辰运行的自然规律。出门走得越远，反而知道的事情越少。所以，圣人不用出行便能推知天下的事情，不必亲自观看，便能明了日月星辰的运行情况及其规律，不妄为就能成就无所不为的功绩。

四十八章

为学日益[310]，为道日损[311]。损之又损，以至于无为，无为而无不为。取天下常以无事[312]，及其有事，不足以取天下。

译文：追求学问，知识一天比一天增加。遵循自然之道，欲望一天比一天减少。这样一天天地减少下去，最后便可以达到无为的境地，达到无为的境地便可以无所不为了。因此，治理天下，常常不是用谋略和手段的；用谋略和手段的，是不能治理天下的。

四十九章

圣人无常心[313]，以百姓心为心[314]。善者，吾善之；不善者，吾亦善之，德善[315]。信者，吾信之，不信者，吾亦信之，德信。圣人在天下歙歙[316]，为天下浑其心[317]。百姓皆注其耳目[318]，圣人皆孩之[319]。

译文：圣人没有私心，而是以百姓的心为自己的心。对于善良的人，我善待他；对于不善良的人，我也善待他；这样可使人人向善。对于守信的人，我信任他；对不守信的人，我也信任他，这样可使人人守信。圣人治理天下，收敛自己的意欲，使天下人归于浑厚朴素。人们都专注于自己的耳目，圣人使他们都回到婴孩般纯真质朴的状态。

五十章

出生入死[320]。生之徒十有三[321]；死之徒十有三[322]；人之生，动之于死地[323]，亦十有三。夫何故？以其生生之厚[324]。盖闻善摄生者[325]，陆行不遇兕虎[326]，入军不被甲兵[327]。兕无所投其角，虎无所措其爪，兵无所容其刃[328]。夫何故？以其无死地。

译文：从出生到死亡，属于长寿的占总数的十分之三，属于短寿的占总数的十分之三，人本来可以得生却走向了死路的，也占总数的十分之三。为什么呢？这是因为他们太放纵欲望而不懂得加以克制。据说，善于养护自己生命的人，在陆地行走不会遇到凶恶的犀牛和猛虎，在战争中也不会受到武器的伤害。犀牛的尖角触不到他，猛虎的利爪抓不到他，武器的利刃刺不到他。为什么会这样呢？因为他没有进入死亡的范围。

五十一章

道生之[329]，德畜之[330]，物形之，势成之[331]。是以万物莫不尊道而贵德。道之尊，德之贵，夫莫之命而常自然[332]。故道生之，德畜之，长之育之，亭之毒之[333]，养之覆之[334]。生而不有，为而不恃，长而不宰，是谓玄德。

译文：道赋予万物生命，用大道至玄德来养育万物，形成万物形象，完成万物的发展。因此，万物没有不尊敬道的，也没有不尊重德的。道之所以受到尊敬，德之所以受到尊重，并不是依靠什么命令，而是出于自然。因而，道化生万物之后，便用德来养育万物、成长万物、繁育万物，形成万物、成熟万物，抚养万物、保护万物。道化生万物却不去占有万物，赐予万物一切而不以此为自己的功绩，使万物生长而不去主宰万物；这就是玄妙的德行。

五十二章

天下有始[335]，以为天下母[336]。既得其母，以知其子[337]；既知其子，复守其母，没身不殆[338]。塞其兑，闭其门[339]，终身不勤[340]。开其兑，济其事[341]，终身不救。见小曰明[342]，守柔曰强。用其光，复归其明，无遗身殃[343]。是谓袭常[344]。

译文：天下万事万物都有本始，这个本始就是天地万物的根源。既然知道根源，就能认识万物。既然认识万物，又把握着万物的根本，那么终身都不会有危险。关门闭户，闭目塞听，不说不听，终身都可从容不迫。如果打开感官满足欲念，就会忙忙碌碌，终身都不可救药。能够察见到细微的，才称得上明白，能够持守柔弱的，才称得上坚强。运用光亮，返照自己，使视力、脑力、智慧恢复过来，不会给自己带来灾难。这就是透过大道认识了永恒的自然规律。

五十三章

使我介然有知[345]，行于大道[346]，唯施是畏[347]。大道甚夷[348]，而民好径[349]。朝甚除[350]，田甚芜[351]，仓甚虚[352]。服文彩，带利剑，厌饮食，财货有余，是谓盗夸[353]。非道也哉！

译文：假使我掌握知识，在大道上行走，唯一担心害怕的就是走了邪路。大道虽然平坦，但人却喜欢走邪径。朝廷腐败坏了，农田荒芜无人耕种，国库空虚，但有人却仍身着彩绣绸衣，佩带锋利的宝剑，饱餐美味佳肴，搜刮占有太多的财货，这就叫作强盗头子。多么的无道呀！

五十四章

善建者不拔，善抱者不脱，子孙以祭祀不辍[354]。修之于身，其德乃真；修之于家，其德乃余；修之于乡，其德乃长[355]；修之于国，其德乃丰[356]；修之于天下，其德乃普。故以身观身，以家观家，以乡观乡[357]，以国观国，以天下观天下。吾何以知天下然哉？以此。

译文：善于建树的人所建的东西永远不可能被拔掉，善于抱持的人抱住一个东西怎么也不会脱落，如果子孙能够遵循、守持这个道理，就可以世世代代祭祀，永不断绝。用这个道理陶冶自己的身心，他的品德便可以返璞归真；用这个道理治理家事，这一家人的品德便可高尚有余；用这个道理治理乡村，这个乡的影响就更大了；用这个道理治理国家，这个国家的德政会兴盛起来；用这个道理治理天下，高尚的道德便可以普及于天下。因此，从一个人可以推知其他人，从一个家庭可以观知其他家庭，从一个乡村可以观知其他乡村，从一个国家可以观知其他国家，从一个天下可以观知其他天下。我怎么会知道天下的情况之所以然呢？就是用以上的方法和道理。

五十五章

含德之厚，比于赤子。毒虫不螫[358]，猛兽不据[359]，攫鸟不搏[360]。骨弱筋柔而握固，未知牝牡之合而朘作[361]，精之至也。终日号而不嗄[362]，和之至也[363]。知和曰常，知常曰明，益生曰祥[364]，心使气曰强[365]。物壮则老[366]，谓之不道，不道早已。

译文：一个品德纯厚的人，好比初生的婴儿。毒虫不去螫他，猛兽也不伤害他，凶鸟不扑抓他。他的筋骨柔弱，但拳头却握得很牢固。他没有男女的欲念，但小生殖器却自动勃起，这是精气充足的缘故。他整天号哭不止，却不会哭哑声音，这是身体和谐造成的。认识和谐的道理叫作“常”。认识“常”叫作“明”。贪生纵欲就会遭殃；意志役使天地和谐，就是逞强。强壮的事物伤害老弱，是违背自然之道；违背自然之道，就会很快灭亡。

五十六章

知者不言，言者不知[367]。塞其兑，闭其门[368]；挫其锐，解其纷；和其光，同其尘[369]，是谓玄同[370]。故不可得而亲，不可得而疏；不可得而利，不可得而害；不可得而贵，不可得而贱[371]，故为天下贵。

译文：真正有智慧的人是不轻易说话的，轻易说话的人是没有智慧的。关门闭户，闭目塞听、不听不说；磨炼人们的锐气、化解他们的纷争、收敛他们的光芒、认同他们尘俗。这就是玄妙齐同的“道”。达到玄妙齐同境界的人，已经超脱亲疏、利害、贵贱的世俗范围，所以就为天下人所尊重。

五十七章

以正治国[372]，以奇用兵[373]，以无事取天下[374]。吾何以知其然哉？以此：天下多忌讳[375]，而民弥贫[376]；民多利器[377]，国家滋昏；人多伎巧[378]，奇物滋起[379]；法令滋彰[380]，盗贼多有。故圣人云：我无为而民自化[381]；我好静而民自正[382]；我无事而民自富；我无欲而民自朴[383]。

译文：治理国家要靠光明磊落，用兵打仗要靠奇巧谋略，治理天下要不搅扰人民。我怎么知道这个道理呢？是因为以下理由：天下的规则禁忌越多，人们就越贫穷；人们的利器越多，国家就越陷于混乱；人们的奇巧淫技越多，各种邪奇的事物也就越不断滋生；法规条令越多，盗贼的行为就越不断增加。因此，圣人说：“我无为，人们自然被感化；我静定，人们就自然端正；我无为而治，人们就自然生活富裕；我没有私欲，人们就自然淳朴。”

五十八章

其政闷闷[384]，其民淳淳[385]；其政察察[386]，其民缺缺[387]。祸兮，福之所倚[388]；福兮，祸之所伏[389]。孰知其极？其无正也。正复为奇，善复为妖[390]。人之迷，其日固久。是以圣人方而不割[391]，廉而不刿[392]，直而不肆[393]，光而不耀[394]。

译文：政治平和渐进，人民就淳朴安分；政治明察秋毫，人民就狡猾奸诈。灾祸，可能会转化为幸福；幸福，则可能隐藏着灾祸。谁能知道终极的结果呢？没有永远的正。正可以转化为邪，善可以转化为恶。可惜，世人迷惑于此，历时已经非常久远了。因此，有道的圣人方正而不伤害人，有棱角而不刺痛人，直率而不放肆，光明而不刺耀。

五十九章

治人事天，莫若啬[395]。夫唯啬，是谓早服[396]；早服谓之重积德[397]；重积德则无不克[398]；无不克则莫知其极[399]；莫知其极，可以有国；有国之母[400]，可以长久。是谓深根固柢[401]，长生久视之道[402]。

译文：治理人民、养护身心最好的办法莫过于节省了。只有节省精神和生命，才可以早早地把自己的生命功能保持住；早早地把自己的生命功能保持住就是不断积德；不断积德就没有什么不能攻克的；达到攻无不克的水平，别人便无法估量他的力量极限；具备了无法估量的力量，他就可以担负治理国家的重任。掌握治理国家的根本，便可以长治久安。这就是所谓的根深蒂固，做到根深蒂固，便可获得长久生存。

六十章

治大国若烹小鲜[403]。以道莅天下[404]，其鬼不神[405]；非其鬼不神，其神不伤人；非其神不伤人，圣人亦不伤人。夫两不相伤，故德交归焉。

译文：治理大国，好像用文火小心、慢慢地烹制小鱼。用道治理天下，鬼神便无法施展灵通；不是鬼神没有灵通，而是他们的灵通不会去伤害人。不但他们不会去伤害人，圣人也不会去伤害人。这样，鬼神和人彼此互不相伤，就可以让人民享受到德的恩泽。

六十一章

大国者下流[406]，天下之交[407]，天下之牝[408]。牝常以静胜牡，以静为下。故大国以下小国，则取小国；小国以下大国，则取大国[409]。故或下以取，或下而取[410]。大国不过欲兼畜人[411]，小国不过欲入事人。夫两者各得其所欲，大者宜为下。

译文：大国要像居于江河下游那样，使天下百川河流在这里交汇。天下各种事物的雌雄相交，雌柔往往以安静夺定而战胜雄强，这种安静夺定就是居于下流。因此，大国若谦下待小国，则可以争取小国的归附；小国若谦下待大国，则可以取得大国的容纳。因此，或者谦让而取得对方的信任，或者谦让而见容于对方。大国的欲望不过是接纳吸收别国加入自己的联盟，小国的欲望不过是加入别国的同盟。这样，双方都各得其所欲求的，因此大国还是以居于下流为好。

六十二章

道者，万物之奥[412]，善人之宝，不善人之所保[413]。美言可以市尊，美行可以加人[414]。人之不善，何弃之有？故立天子，置三公[415]。虽有拱璧以先驷马[416]，不如坐进此道[417]。古之所以贵此道者何？不曰：求以得[418]，有罪以免邪？故为天下贵。

译文：道是万物的庇荫，善良的人保护它、珍惜它，不善的人得到它的保护和救助。美丽动听的语言可以换来别人的尊敬，美好的行为可以获得别人的拥戴。即使是不善的人，道也不会抛弃他！因此，人们设立天子，配置三公。虽然有拱壁驷马这些价值连城的珍宝，但不如“道”重要。古人为什么把“道”看得那么珍贵？为什么不说：有要求就可以得到满足，犯了罪要求免罪就可以免吗？所以，道才是天下最崇高伟大、至高无上、至贵无上的。

六十三章

为无为[419]，事无事，味无味[420]。大小多少，抱怨以德[421]。图难于其易[422]，为大于其细。天下难事必作于易[423]；天下大事必作于细。是以圣人终不为大，故能成其大。夫轻诺必寡信[424]，多易必多难。是以圣人犹难之，故终无难矣。

译文：以无为的态度去有所作为，以不滋事的方法去处理事物，把恬淡无味当作有味。大生于小，多起于少，以恩德来报怨恨。解决难题，要从最容易的地方入手；实现远大，要从细微的地方入手。天下的难事一定要从容易的地方做起，天下的大事一定要从细小的地方做起。因此，圣人从来不企图做大事，却能够做成大事。凡是轻易允诺的人常常是不可信的，总把事情看得太容易的人必然会遇到很多的困难。因此，圣人总是重视天下事，所以才不会有困难了。

六十四章

其安易持[425]，其未兆易谋[426]，其脆易泮[427]，其微易散。为之于未有，治之于未乱。合抱之木，生于毫末[428]；九层之台[429]，起于累土[430]；千里之行，始于足下。为者败之，执者失之。是以圣人无为故无败，无执故无失。民之从事，常于几成而败之[431]。慎终如始，则无败事。是以圣人欲不欲，不贵难得之货[432]；学不学，复众人之所过[433]，以辅万物之自然而不敢为[434]。

译文：局面安定才容易保持长久，还没有出现混乱的征兆时容易谋求预防措施。脆弱的东西容易破碎，细微的东西容易失散。做事情要在还没开始之前就把基础都打好了；治理国政，要在天下未乱时就把乱根除掉。双手合抱的大树，生长于细小的嫩芽；九层的高台，是由一筐土一筐土堆筑起来的；千里的远行，是从脚下一步一步走出来的。有所作为的会招致失败，过于执着的会遭受失败。因此圣人无所作为而不致失败，不过于执着而不致失败。人们做事情，常常是在接近于成功时遭到失败。所以，做事情，在接近完成时也要像开始时那样慎重，就不至于失败。因此，圣人追求的是无所欲求，不看重难以得到的东西；做学问达到好像是没有学问的境界，恢复到比一般人还平凡，圣人只是辅助万物顺其自然而不妄为。

六十五章

古之善为道者，非以明民[435]，将以愚之[436]。民之难治，以其智多[437]。故以智治国，国之贼；不以智治国，国之福。知此两者亦稽式[438]。常知稽式，是谓玄德[439]。玄德深矣，远矣，与物反矣[440]，然后乃至大顺[441]。

译文：古代善于行道的人，不是教导人民知晓智巧伪诈，而是教导人民淳厚朴实。人民之所以难于统治，是因为他们的智巧心机太多。因此，用智巧心机治理国家，就必然会危害到国家，不用智巧心机治理国家，那才有益于国家。这两种都是治理国家的一个法则，时刻不忘这个法则，就叫作玄妙的德行。玄妙的德行真是太深妙了，太幽远了，它与具体的事物看起来是相反的，正因为相反，然后才能完全顺乎自然。

六十六章

江海之所以能为百谷王者[442]，以其善下之[443]，故能为百谷王。是以欲上民[444]，必以言下之；欲先民[445]，必以身后之。是以圣人处上而民不重[446]，处前而民不害[447]。是以天下乐推而不厌[448]。以其不争，故天下莫能与之争。

译文：江海所以能够成为百川河流所归往的地方，是因为江海能够居于低处，因而它能够成为百川汇集之处。所以，要想做居上位的人，言语态度一定要谦虚；要想领导人民，必须把自身的利益摆在后面。所以，圣人虽然地位居于人民之上，而人民并不感觉有重压，居于人民之前，而人民并不感觉受到妨害。天下人都乐意推举拥戴他而不感到厌倦。因为他不与人民相争，所以天下没有人能和他相争。

六十七章

天下皆谓我道大，似不肖[449]。夫唯大，故似不肖。若肖，久矣其细也夫。我有三宝，持而保之：一曰慈[450]，二曰俭[451]，三曰不敢为天下先。慈故能勇[452]，俭故能广[453]，不敢为天下先，故能成器长[454]。今舍慈且勇，舍俭且广，舍后且先，死矣。夫慈，以战则胜，以守则固。天将救之[455]，以慈卫之。

译文：天下的人都说我讲的“道”很大，它不像什么具体的事物。就是因为它很大，所以才不像具体的事物。如果像一个什么具体的事物，这个道就不伟大了。我有三件法宝执守而且保全它：第一件是仁慈；第二件是节俭；第三件是不敢居于天下人之先。有了仁慈才能有勇气；有了节俭才能广博；不敢居于天下人之先，才能成为万物的领导。现在丢弃仁慈而追求勇气；丢弃节俭而追求广大；舍弃居后而追求争先，结果是走向死亡。拥有仁慈之心，打仗就能够胜利，防守就能够巩固。天要救助谁，就用仁慈来保护他。

六十八章

善为士者不武[456]；善战者不怒[457]；善胜敌者不与[458]；善用人者为之下[459]。是谓不争之德，是谓用人之力，是谓配天古之极[460]。

译文：真正的勇武之士，不会有粗暴行为；善于打仗的人，不轻易动怒；善于战胜敌人的人，不与敌人正面冲突；善于用人的人，对人态度谦和。这就是不与人争的品德，这就叫作运用别人的能力，这就是与天一样伟大的古老而不变的原则。

六十九章

用兵有言：吾不敢为主而为客[461]；不敢进寸而退尺[462]。是谓行无行[463]，攘无臂[464]，扔无敌[465]，执无兵[466]。祸莫大于轻敌，轻敌几丧吾宝[467]。故抗兵相若[468]，哀者胜矣[469]。

译文：精通军事理论的人曾经说过：“带兵打仗，我不主动进攻，而采取被动防守；在双方交战时，我不轻易前进一寸，而宁肯后退一尺。”这就叫作有阵势却又不像有阵势，想奋臂打人却又不伸出臂膀，与敌对抗却没有敌手，使用兵器却像没拿兵器。最大的灾祸莫过于轻敌，一旦轻敌便丧失了我的“三宝”。当交战双方实力相当时，慈悲的一方可以获得胜利。

七十章

吾言甚易知，甚易行。天下莫能知，莫能行。言有宗[470]，事有君[471]。夫唯无知[472]，是以不我知。知我者希[473]，则我者贵[474]。是以圣人被褐而怀玉[475]。

译文：我说的话非常容易理解，也非常容易施行。可是天下却没有人能够真正理解，也没有人能够完全施行。其实，我说的话都有宗旨，我做的事都有根据。然而，由于人们不理解这个道理，因此也就无法理解我这个人。能够理解我的人就不多，而能够效法我的人就更难能可贵了。所以，真正得道的大圣人总是身着粗布衣服而怀揣无价美玉的。

七十一章

知不知，上[476]；不知知，病[477]。夫唯病病[478]，是以不病。圣人不病，以其病病，是以不病。

译文：知道很多东西，却认为自己知道不多的人，最好；不知道多少东西，却以为自己什么都知道了，这是人生的大病。只有知道这是一种病的人，才不会得这种病。圣人没有这种毛病，那是因为他把这种病看作病，所以才不会犯这种病。

七十二章

民不畏威，则大威至[479]。无狎其所居[480]，无厌其所生[481]。夫唯不厌，是以不厌[482]。是以圣人自知不自见[483]，自爱不自贵。故去彼取此[484]。

译文：当人民不畏惧权威的时候，可怕的祸乱就要到来。不要逼迫人民使他们不得安居，不要阻挡他们谋生的道路。只有为政者不压迫人民，人民才不厌恶统治者。所以，圣人有自知之明而不表现自己，有自爱之心而不自以为贵；也就是说，排除自我表现、自以为贵而保留自知之明、自爱之心。

七十三章

勇于敢则杀；勇于不敢则活。此两者，或利或害。天之所恶[485]，孰知其故？是以圣人犹难之。天之道，不争而善胜，不言而善应，不召而自来，然而善谋[486]。天网恢恢[487]，疏而不失[488]。

译文：有勇气并什么事情都敢干，难免招来杀身之祸；有勇气但谨慎不妄为，却可以平安地存活下来。这两种情况，结果是有利或者有害。上天为什么要厌恶前者？谁知道其中的缘故？这个问题圣人也难以回答。自然的规律是，不与物争、不与人争，然而却更精通如何取胜；无需言语却善于作出反应；不用召唤却会自动到来；看上去像一张网张开但其中却有谋略。天网宽广无边，尽管网眼稀疏，实际上却不会遗漏任何东西。

七十四章

民不畏死，奈何以死惧之[489]？若使民常畏死，而为奇者[490]，吾得执而杀之，孰敢[491]？常有司杀者杀[492]，夫代司杀者杀，是谓代大匠斫[493]。夫代大匠斫者，希有不伤其手者矣[494]。

译文：人民不畏惧死，那为什么要用死来吓唬他们呢？假如说人民真的都畏惧死，我们可以把少数邪恶之人抓来处死，谁还敢再为非作歹？天地间有专管生杀权的，只有它可以行使杀人的任务，但谁如果代替了专管杀人的人去杀人，就如同不懂木匠活的人却来代替高明的木匠去砍木头。凡是代替高明的木匠去砍木头的人，很少有不砍伤自己的手的。

七十五章

民之饥，以其上食税之多[495]，是以饥。民之难治，以其上之有为[496]，是以难治。民之轻死[497]，以其上求生之厚[498]，是以轻死。夫唯无以生为者[499]，是贤于贵生[500]。

译文：人民之所以遭受饥荒，是因为统治者吞吃赋税太多，所以人民才陷于饥饿。人民之所以难以统治，是因为统治者政令繁苛、喜欢有所作为，所以人民就难以统治。人民之所以把死看得那么轻，是因为统治者贪得无厌，只去满足自己奢侈的生活，而不顾及人民的死活，所以人民觉得死了也不算什么。只有不去追求生活享受的人，才比过分看重自己生命的人高明。

七十六章

人之生也柔弱[501]，其死也坚强[502]。草木之生也柔脆[503]，其死也枯槁[504]。故坚强者死之徒，柔弱者生之徒[505]。是以兵强则灭，木强则折。坚强处下，柔弱处上。

译文：人活着的时候身体是柔软的，死了以后身体就变得僵硬了。草木生长时是柔软脆弱的，死了以后就变得干枯了。所以坚强的东西属于死亡的一类，柔弱的东西属于生长的一类。因此，用兵逞强就会遭到灭亡，树木强大了就会遭到砍伐摧折。凡是强大的，总是处于下位，凡是柔弱的，反而居于上位。

七十七章

天之道[506]，其犹张弓与[507]？高者抑之，下者举之。有余者损之，不足者补之。天之道，损有余而补不足。人之道则不然[508]，损不足以奉有余。孰能有余以奉天下[509]？唯有道者。是以圣人为而不恃，功成而不处[510]，其不欲见贤[511]。

译文：自然的规律，不是很像张弓射箭吗？弓对准目标射，太高了就往下压一点，太低了就拉高一点，超出了就少拉满一点，不够远就多拉紧一点。自然的规律，是减少有余的补给不足的。可是人类社会的法则却不是这样，贫困不足的人民却还要拿出财物奉供侈奢有余的权贵。那么，谁能把自己有余的东西供献给天下的人呢？唯有得道之人。因此，圣人慷慨赐予万物一切，而不以此为自己的功绩。他是不愿意显示自己的贤能。

七十八章

天下莫柔弱于水，而攻坚强者莫之能胜[512]，以其无以易之[513]。弱之胜强，柔之胜刚，天下莫不知，莫能行。是以圣人云：受国之垢[514]，是谓社稷主；受国不祥[515]，是为天下王。正言若反。

译文：天下万物没有比水更柔弱的了，然而攻克坚强却没有什么东西能比得过水，因为没有什么东西能够代替水的地位。弱小的可以战胜强大的，柔弱的可以战胜刚强的；天下没有人不知道这个道理，但是却没有人能够做得到。所以圣人说：“能够承受全国的屈辱，才称得上是国家的君主；能够承担全国的灾难，才称得上是天下人的君王。”正面的话才是真话，可是往往做不到，就像是在说反话。

七十九章

和大怨，必有余怨，安可以为善？是以圣人执左契，而不责于人[516]。有德司契[517]，无德司彻[518]。天道无亲[519]，常与善人[520]。

译文：深重的怨恨和解以后，必然还会留有余怨；怎么样才是最妥善的办法呢？因此，要像圣人那样，只把握住大原则，不必苛责别人。有德的人就像圣人那样只把握住大原则，没有德的人处处设置规则。自然的规律对任何人都没有偏爱，永远帮助有德的善人。

八十章

小国寡民[521]。使有什伯之器而不用[522]；使民重死而不远徙[523]。虽有舟舆，无所乘之[524]；虽有甲兵，无所陈之[525]。使民复结绳而用之[526]。甘其食，美其服，安其居，乐其俗。邻国相望，鸡犬之声相闻[527]，民至老死不相往来。

译文：国土狭小人民稀少。即使拥有各种各样的器具也不使用；人民尊重生命而不向远方迁徙。尽管拥有船只车辆却不乘坐；虽然有武器装备，却没有必要去布阵打仗。使人民再回到远古结绳记事的早期原始状态之中。人民拥有自认为最甜美的食品，最美观的服装，最安适的居所，最欢乐自在的社会风俗。邻国之间可以互相望见，鸡犬的叫声都可以听得见，但人民从生到死，也不互相往来。

八十一章

信言不美，美言不信[528]。善者不辩，辩者不善[529]。知者不博，博者不知[530]。圣人不积[531]，既以为人己愈有[532]，既以与人己愈多[533]。天之道，利而不害。圣人之道，为而不争[534]。

译文：真实可信的话不漂亮，漂亮的话不真实可信。善良的人不太会说话，能说会道的人不善良。具有真知灼见的人不卖弄，卖弄的人不会有真知灼见。圣人不积聚财物，他尽力去帮助别人，自己反而拥有更多，尽力去奉献给别人，自己反而更为富有。自然的规律是让万事万物都得到好处，而不伤害它们。圣人的行为准则是，做什么事都尽力给予而不与人与物相争。

XIII

Favour and disgrace are things that startle;

High rank is, like one's body, a source of great trouble.

What is meant by saying that favour and disgrace are things that startle? Favour when it is bestowed on a subject serves to startle as much as when it is withdrawn. This is what is meant by saying that favour and disgrace are things that startle. What is meant by saying that high rank is, like one's body, a source of great trouble? The reason I have great trouble is that I have a body. When I no longer have a body, what trouble have I?

Hence he who values his body more than dominion over the empire can be entrusted with the empire. He who loves his body more than dominion over the empire can be given the custody of the empire.

XIV

What cannot be seen is called evanescent;

What cannot be heard is called rarefied;

What cannot be touched is called minute.

These three cannot be fathomed

And so they are confused and looked upon as one.

Its upper part is not dazzling;

Its lower part is not obscure.

Dimly visible, it cannot be named

And returns to that which is without substance.

This is called the shape that has no shape,

The image that is without substance.

This is called indistinct and shadowy.

Go up to it and you will not see its head;

Follow behind it and you will not see its rear.

Hold fast to the way of antiquity

In order to keep in control the realm of today.

The ability to know the beginning of antiquity

Is called the thread running through the way.

XX

Exterminate learning and there will no longer be worries.

Between yea and nay

How much difference is there?

Between good and evil

How great is the distance?

What others fear

One must also fear.

And wax without having reached the limit.

The multitude are joyous

As if partaking of the t'ai lao offering

Or going up to a terrace in spring.

I alone am inactive and reveal no signs,

Like a baby that has not yet learned to smile,

Listless as though with no home to go back to.

The multitude all have more than enough.

I alone seem to be in want.

My mind is that of a fool - how blank!

Vulgar people are clear.

I alone am drowsy.

Vulgar people are alert.

I alone am muddled.

Calm like the sea;

Like a high wind that never ceases.

The multitude all have a purpose.

I alone am foolish and uncouth.

I alone am different from others

And value being fed by the mother.

XXVIII

Know the male

But keep to the role of the female

And be a ravine to the empire.

If you are a ravine to the empire,

Then the constant virtue will not desert you

And you will again return to being a babe.

Know the white

But keep to the role of the black

And be a model to the empire.

If you are a model to the empire,

Then the constant virtue will not be wanting

And you will return to the infinite.

Know honour

But keep to the role of the disgraced

And be a valley to the empire.

If you are a valley to the empire,

Then the constant virtue will be sufficient

And you will return to being the uncarved block.

When the uncarved block shatters it becomes vessels.

The sage makes use of these and becomes the lord over the officials.

Hence the greatest cutting

Does not sever.

XXXI

It is because arms are instruments of ill omen and there are Things that detest them that one who has the way does not abide by their use. The gentleman gives pre-cedence to the left when at home, but to the right when he goes to war. Arms are instruments of ill omen, not the instruments of the gentleman. When one is compelled to use them, it is best to do so without relish. There is no glory in victory, and to glorify it despite this is to exult in the killing of men. One who exults in the killing of men will never have his way in the empire. On occasions of rejoicing precedence is given to the left; on occasions of mourning precedence is given to the right. A lieuten-ant's place is on the left; the general's place is on the right. This means that it is mourning rites that are observed. When great numbers of people are killed, one should weep over them with sorrow. When victorious in war, one should observe the rites of mourning.

XXXVIII

A man of the highest virtue does not keep to virtue and that is why he has virtue. A man of the lowest virtue never strays from virtue and that is why he is without virtue. The former never acts yet leaves nothing undone. The latter acts but there are things left undone. A man of the highest benevolence acts, but from no ulterior motive. A man of the highest rectitude acts, but from ulterior motive. A man most conversant in the rites acts, but when no one responds rolls up his sleeves and resorts to persuasion by force.

Hence when the way was lost there was virtue; when virtue was lost there was benevolence; when benevolence was lost there was rectitude; when rectitude was lost there were the rites.

The rites are the wearing thin of loyalty and good faith

And the beginning of disorder;

Foreknowledge is the flowery embellishment of the way

And the beginning of folly.

Hence the man of large mind abides in the thick not in the thin, in the fruit not in the flower.

Therefore he discards the one and takes the other.

LV

One who possesses virtue in abundance is comparable to a new born babe:

Poisonous insects will not sting it;

Ferocious animals will not pounce on it;

Predatory birds will not swoop down on it.

Its bones are weak and its sinews supple yet its hold is firm.

It does not know of the union of male and female yet its male member will stir:

This is because its virility is at its height.

It howls all day yet does not become hoarse:

This is because its harmony is at its height.

To know harmony is called the constant;

To know the constant is called discernment.

To try to add to one's vitality is called ill-omened;

For the mind to egg on the breath is called violent.

A creature in its prime doing harm to the old

Is known as going against the way.

That which goes against the way will come to an early end.

LXIII

Do that which consists in taking no action; pursue that which is not meddlesome; savour that which has no flavour.

Make the small big and the few many; do good to him who has done you an injury.

Lay plans for the accomplishment of the difficult before it becomes difficult; make something big by starting with it when small.

Difficult things in the world must needs have their beginnings in the easy; big things must needs have their beginnings in the small.

Therefore it is because the sage never attempts to be great that he succeeds in becoming great.

One who makes promises rashly rarely keeps good faith; one who is in the habit of considering things easy meets with frequent difficulties.

Therefore even the sage treats some things as difficult.

That is why in the end no difficulties can get the better of him.

LXIV

It is easy to maintain a situation while it is still secure;

It is easy to deal with a situation before symptoms develop;

It is easy to break a thing when it is yet brittle;

It is easy to dissolve a thing when it is yet minute.

Deal with a thing while it is still nothing;

Keep a thing in order before disorder sets in.

A tree that can fill the span of a man's arms

Grows from a downy tip;

A terrace nine storeys high

Rises from hodfuls of earth;

A journey of a thousand miles

Starts from beneath one's feet.

Whoever does anything to it will ruin it; whoever lays hold of it will lose it.

Therefore the sage, because he does nothing, never ruins anything; and, because he does not lay hold of anything, loses nothing.

In their enterprises the people

Always ruin them when on the verge of success.

Be as careful at the end as at the beginning

And there will be no ruined enterprises.

Therefore the sage desires not to desire

And does not value goods which are hard to come by;

Learns to be without learning

And makes good the mistakes of the multitude

In order to help the myriad creatures to be natural and to refrain from daring to act.

LXVII

The whole world says that my way is vast and resembles nothing. It is because it is vast that it resembles nothing. If it resembled anything, it would, long before now, have become small.

I have three treasures

Which I hold and cherish.

The first is known as compassion,

The second is known as frugality,

The third is known as not daring to take the lead in the empire;

Being compassionate one could afford to be courageous,

Being frugal one could afford to extend one's territory,

Not daring to take the lead in the empire one could afford to be lord over the vessels.

Now, to forsake compassion for courage, to forsake frugality for expansion, to forsake the rear for the lead, is sure to end in death.

Through compassion, one will triumph in attack and be impregnable in defence. What heaven succours it protects with the gift of compassion.

导读

尼采，全名弗里德里希·威廉·尼采（Friedrich Wilhelm Nietzsche，1844—1900），西方现代哲学的开创者。除了在哲学上的造诣，他还是语言学家、诗人、评论家和作曲家。尼采五岁丧父，家中的五个女人（母亲、妹妹、祖母、两个姑姑）便将所有的爱倾注于他。成长环境使然，他从小敏感而脆弱，早熟又孤僻。家庭对他来说，是幸福的港湾，但尼采心中始终有一个使命：探索人生的真谛。他自知在暖巢中得不到答案，便毅然舍弃这一切，在风雨飘摇的世界里四处漂泊。一生带着对真理的究极追求，最终以发疯去世谢幕，留下经典无数。他的一生，充满艺术。只需读几页他的书，你就能发现：想法标新立异的是他；言语充满辛辣讽刺的是他；抨击时不经意流露出自我沉醉的还是他。如柏拉图、阿里斯托芬一般，这些都是天才作家的“标配”。

据说，尼采的晚年，因受不了长期不被理解的孤独，在都灵大街发疯，失去了理智。本书的名字由此显得意味深长。他在书中说：“适合独立的人寥寥无几，那是强者的特权。”独立必然伴随着孤独，但孤独赠予了他深邃的思考、超脱的人格。初读《与孤独为伍》，像所有哲学书给人的体验一样，似是品一杯酒，晕晕乎乎、云里雾里。但在尼采制造的云雾缭绕背后，有一把尖刀，时刻替你剖开社会的本质、揭露内心的真实。它太过于真实，甚至有时你还想矢口否认，试图为自己留一层颜面。但他的语气太过于笃定和自信，让你羞愧过后不得不暗暗承认他的睿智和透彻。

他说：“要求别人爱自己是最大的傲慢。”“寻求机智的人没有机智。”他还说，“要明白普通人的行为就必须明白，他们很少花费精力去摆脱糟糕的境遇。”经典之所以为经典，正是在于这些针砭时弊的话语放到现代社会依然不会过时：那些渴望被爱的人，是否一直吝啬自己的爱？那些寻求捷径的人，是否有过踏实的付出？那些深陷困境的人，是否曾努力挣扎？求而不得的原因，尼采在十九世纪就给出了答案。

书中的讽刺浑然天成，犀利的话语夹裹在幽默中，抽打人的同时给予了最后一层颜面：“想成为榜样的人，必须给自己的德行添点愚蠢，这样别人就可以模仿并且超过模仿的对象——人们喜欢做这样的事。”“一知半解比彻底了解更受欢迎：事情在一知半解的人那里被简化，结果得到了更容易让人理解和信服的观点。”“视力不好的人，看到的东西往往比别人少一些；听力不好的人，听到的东西往往比别人多一些。”寥寥几句，思索良久。读者似乎在和尼采对话，更多的，则像是在辩论——和尼采辩论、和自己辩论。说服自己，又扳倒自己，渐渐陷入尼采构建的哲学世界，常常在看完几页后一抬头，世界都变得不真实了。

除了这些讽刺和批判，关于做人做事，他也有自己的见解和章法：“瀑布在跌落时，变得舒缓飘逸；实干家在行动时，将强烈的渴望化为彻底的冷静。”“某些人的本领看起来比实际小，是因为他们给自己安排的任务太庞大。”这些话，可以引起多少人的共鸣！他在幽默中不乏机敏的思考。不过，除了领略其中的智慧，现代人或许更需要批判的思维。阅读不是为了思想的膜拜和自我的否定，而是用清醒的头脑追寻自己的真理。有时，他会把人性看得过于深刻，甚至有些激进：“某人故去时，我们通常需要令人安慰的解释，与其说是平复痛苦，不如说是为自己的痛苦轻易得到平复寻找借口。”读这句话，仿佛可以看到尼采紧皱的眉头倔强地表达着对人类的不满。但有时，这些安慰的解释，只是悲伤流出的窗口，麻痹内心巨大的伤痛。不是为了忘记而惺惺作态，而是为了更好地铭记。人生的真相是残酷，但残酷的尽头也有温柔。书中后半段摘有尼采的诗，读起来更像是即兴而为，他说：我已找到的和正在寻找的——可曾在书里存在过？那么，亲爱的读者，你找到的和正在寻找的，是否也藏匿在尼采的文字和思想中呢？

何博文

三、自由精神

1.噢，神圣的单纯！人类生活在怎样的天真和虚妄中啊！一旦我们认识到这一点，就会对此连连称奇。我们是怎样将周遭的一切变得简单明了、自由随意！我们是如何让感觉对一切肤浅之物敞开大门，让思想耽溺于天马行空的联想和错误的推断！——我们是如何设法从一开始就保留无知，以享受生命那难以想象的磅礴恣肆、酣畅淋漓，亦即享受生命本身！而只有在无知那如花岗岩般坚实的地基上，知识才能巍然屹立；求知的意志是以更为强大的求无知、求不确定性、求不真实的意志为基础！不是作为后者的对立面，而是作为其升华！即便语言在此处就像在别处一样无法克服自身的粗鄙，将程度的不同和细微的差别说成对立，即便人类根深蒂固的伪善，扭曲了我们之中智者的话语，我们也能不时心领神会，然后抚掌大笑：正是最高妙的知识试图将我们束缚在这个被简化的，不自然的，伪造的和被扭曲的世界。它义无反顾地热爱错误，因为作为一个生命体，它热爱生活。

2.欢快的绪言之后是庄严的敬告：这是说给最严肃的人听的。要小心，哲学家和热爱知识的朋友们，警惕殉道者的做法！警惕“为真理之故”受苦，警惕为自己辩驳！它会损毁你良心全部的纯真和公正，使你无法容忍任何不同和反对的意见；它会使你在同危险、诽谤、猜忌、驱逐甚至更大的敌意作斗争时变得愚蠢、野蛮和无情，你不得不摆出人间真理守护人的姿态——仿佛“真理”如此幼稚、无能，以至于需要人守护！而你，我亲爱的无所事事的朋友和精神上的阴谋家，就成了众人中那个面露愁苦的骑士！毕竟你心里清楚，众人之中你自己正确与否根本不重要；你知道迄今为止没有哲学家能够被证明是正确的，而你在钟爱的词句和学说（有时是你自己）后面打上的每个问号，或许比你在控诉人和法庭面前作出的所有肃穆的手势和狡黠的答辩，都更为诚实和令人钦佩。不如避开！逃走，躲起来！运用你的面具和手腕，让自己受到误解或是别人的敬畏！别忘了花园，那个有着金色棚架的花园！接近那些像花园一样的人，或是那些让你想起黄昏时分水面上飘过的音乐的人。选择有益的独处，自由、随意、惬意的独处会让你在某种程度上保持美好！每一场漫长而隐秘的战争都会让人变得无比恶毒、狡猾和卑鄙！在时刻警惕敌人和可能的敌人中被拉伸的恐惧，让人变得富于攻击性！这些被社会驱逐的人，受到长期迫害和大力追捕的人，还有像斯宾诺莎[2]和乔尔丹诺·布鲁诺[3]那样被迫遁世的人，最终都会变成精明的复仇者和恶念的传播者，即便他们顶着最超凡脱俗的伪装，甚至于自己也蒙在鼓中（让我们揭示斯宾诺莎的伦理学和神学基础吧！）——更不用说道德义愤的愚蠢性，它准确无误地表明一个哲学家已经丧失其哲学式幽默。一个哲学家的殉道，他的“为真理之故牺牲”，暴露出他人格中潜藏的煽动者和演员的一面。如果到目前为止，我们只是出于艺术的好奇在审视他，结合众多哲学家的案例，很容易理解那种想偶尔瞥见堕落状态下的他（堕落成“殉道者”，堕落成在舞台和讲坛上豪言壮语的人）的危险欲望。只是有必要澄清我们将要看到的是什么：不过是一场“羊人剧”[4]，一出放在正剧结尾的闹剧，不过是再次证明那个真正的绵长的悲剧已经结束：假定每部哲学起初都是一部长长的悲剧的话。

3.每个优秀的人都会本能地寻求一座秘密堡垒，在那里他可以摆脱人群、民众和大多数；在那里，置身事外的他可以忘记人类的规则——除非，作为一名卓尔不群的博学之士，他会在更强大的本能驱使下，径直奔向这一规则。任何在和人打交道时没有流露出沮丧，表现出嫌恶、厌腻、怜悯、阴郁和孤单情绪的人，必定不具备精致的品位；但是如果他不去主动承担这份不快而是不断地规避它，坚持安静而骄傲地躲在自己的堡垒里，那么可以肯定：知识不适合他。否则总有一天，他会不得不对自己说：让我的品位见鬼去吧！规则比例外——比我这个例外本身，更有趣！他会选择走“下来”和走“进去”。哲学家对普通人的研究漫长而严肃，其中充斥着的掩饰、自我征服、亲昵和不良结交——和不相称的人结交都可以算作不良结交——构成了他人生经历中不可或缺的部分，并且可能是最令人不快、发狂和失望的部分。如果哲学家像知识最钟爱的孩子那样足够幸运，他就会遇见帮助他完成任务的捷径——即所谓的玩世不恭者，这些人早已看穿了自身的蒙昧、平庸和驯顺，却仍能保持在人前谈论自己的冲动——有时他们甚至在书中打滚，就像在自己的排泄物中一样。玩世不恭是普通人接近真诚的唯一形式；杰出的人必须在玩世不恭面前竖起耳朵，不论它是粗俗还是高雅；而在某个丑角或者科学“羊人”不知羞耻地夸夸其谈时，暗自感到庆幸。当然有时厌恶中会混合着着迷：因为某些不可知的原因，这些不知天高地厚的山羊和猴子有时颇具天分。比如加利亚尼神父[5]，这个思想无比深刻、目光无比犀利的人，同时也可能是他那个世纪最肮脏的人——他远比伏尔泰更深刻，因此也更沉默。科学的头颅经常被安到猴子身上，超凡的领悟力常被装配到平庸的灵魂上——这在物理学家和伦理生理学家中比比皆是。不论何时，如果有人以不含私怨、无伤大雅的方式将人类比喻成有两种需求的肚子和一种需求的头脑；不论何处，如果有人看到、寻求和想看到的只有食、色和虚荣，仿佛这些是人类行为真实和唯一的动机；总之，任何时候，如果有人对人类大加嘲讽但并非中伤诽谤时，热爱知识的人就应该认真倾听；只要有人不带情绪地说话，他就应该关注。那些处于激愤状态，不停地用牙齿撕扯自己（或者世界、上帝、社会）的人，从道德上讲，也许确实比那些哈哈大笑、洋洋自得的“羊人”站得更高，但在任何别的意义上，他都更加平庸、乏味和无益，而且愤怒的人比任何人说的谎都更多。

4.人们很难理解我们：尤其当你像急逝的恒河之水一样思考和生活，而周围的人却采取截然不同的方式：他们像乌龟一样缓慢，或者至多是“像青蛙那样蹦跳”——当然我这是在努力让自己难于被理解！——我们应该对旁人委婉善意的诠释表示由衷的感激。至于我们的“好友”，他们总是太懒惰，认为作为好友，他们有权好逸恶劳：如果我们从一开始就给他们一些误解的空间和自由会好得多——这样我们就可以对他们大加嘲笑；——或者索性摆脱掉这些好友，而仍然保持欢笑！

5.从一种语言翻译成另一种语言，最难传递的莫过于风格的节奏感，它源自于种族的个性，用生理学上的话说，就是“新陈代谢”的平均速度。有一些以忠实于原文为初衷的翻译，结果不自觉地将原文庸俗化，几乎成为歪曲，就是因为要同时翻译出勇敢而欢快的节奏（它跳跃着将一切事物和词语中暗含的危险抛在身后）是不可能的。德国人几乎无法用自己的语言快速说话，由此可以推断，他们对于表达自由、无拘无束的思想中那些最大胆、愉悦的情绪也大多无能为力。例如歌剧中的滑稽男低音和戏剧中的“羊人”，无论是在形体还是道德上都会令德国人感到陌生，所以阿里斯托芬[6]和佩特罗尼乌斯[7]对他们来说是不可翻译的。一切以静止、慵懒、肃穆、冗长和乏味为特征的风格，在德国蓬勃发展——请原谅我指出，即便是歌德的散文，融合了优雅与生硬，也不例外。它是其所属的那个“辉煌年代”的映象，是对“德国趣味”尚存的年代的一种德国式的表达：即道德和艺术上的洛可可式风格。莱辛是个例外，这要归功于他的历史性，他博古通今并且在很多方面造诣很高：他成为贝尔的译者并非偶然，他喜欢狄德罗和伏尔泰，更喜爱罗马喜剧家——在节奏感方面，莱辛崇尚无拘无束，竭力摆脱德国式的拘谨。但即便在他的散文中，德语也无法模仿马基雅维里的节奏感，后者的《君主论》让我们呼吸到佛罗伦萨的干爽空气，并且忍不住要将最严肃的事用最活泼、最轻快的方式表达。其中或许不无居心叵测的艺术家对反差效果的追求——一边是冗长、艰深、危险的思想，一边是飞驰的节奏和恣意的欢娱。谁会冒险用德文翻译佩特罗尼乌斯呢，他在创作、理念、词汇方面比迄今的任何一位音乐家都更深谙快板的精髓——如果我们能拥有他那风一样的轻盈步履，那样的气流和呼吸，那种风的解放性的藐视，以及风的那种让一切奔跑起来而获得健康的力量，所有那些邪恶病态世界中的沼泽，甚至“古代世界”中的沼泽又算得了什么？至于阿里斯托芬，由于他的贡献和补充，我们可以原谅希腊的存在（假定我们非常清楚需要原谅和改观的是什么）。临终前的柏拉图，枕下放的既不是《圣经》，也不是任何一本埃及的书，更不是毕达哥拉斯或柏拉图自己的著作，而是一本阿里斯托芬喜剧。没有什么比这个流传的轶事更能激发我对柏拉图那讳莫如深的行为方式和他那斯芬克斯式个性的思考。如果没有阿里斯托芬，即便是柏拉图，也无法忍受他的人生——那被他否定的希腊式人生！

6.适合独立的人寥寥无几——那是强者的特权。任何人，即便有充分的理由，只要不是迫于无奈而主动尝试独立，就证明他不但是个强者，而且大胆到近乎莽撞的地步。他会从此踏进一座迷宫，在这里，生活本身的危险被放大了一千倍，没有人清楚他是怎样和在哪里迷了路，变得孑然一身，最后被良心的牛头怪[8]撕成碎片。假使这样的人被摧毁，人们将难以理解、无法感受也不会寄予同情——而他则再也回不去！甚至连人们的怜悯也得不到！

7.当我们最了不起的见解，未经允许就出现在不喜欢它们和不适合听到它们的人的耳朵里时，听上去肯定会像是疯话，甚至是罪恶。哲学家们曾在希腊人、波斯人和穆斯林中分别进行“显白教诲”和“隐微教诲”，发现只要人们信仰等级秩序而非权利平等，二者的区分并不在于“显白教诲”是从外部而非内部观察、评价、估量和判断。其根本区别在于，“显白教诲”是从下面看事物，而“隐微教诲”是从上面看事物！在灵魂的某些高度上，连悲剧看起来也不可悲；即便集合世上所有的惨状，谁又敢确定它们一定会令我们心生怜悯，从而分外悲伤？……在高层次的人看来是营养品的东西，对于低层次和全然不同的人来说可能是毒药。普通人的美德在哲学家身上可能恰恰意味着恶习和缺陷；一个高层次的人可能只有在堕落和毁灭时，才会获得某些令俗世尊奉他为圣人的属性。同样的书，对于不同层次人的灵魂和健康，作用可能正好相反，要看读者究竟是低层次、生命力暗弱的人，还是高层次、生命力强悍的人。在前一种情形下，这些书是危险的，有可能导致人的崩溃和毁灭；在后一种情形下，它们会成为先驱的号角，激励勇者鼓起他们的勇气。给所有人读的书总是令人掩鼻：因为有渺小者的气味吸附在上面。凡是众人吃喝乃至敬拜的地方，都有臭味。谁要想呼吸纯净的空气，就不要去教堂。

8.人年轻时，无论是崇拜还是鄙视，都缺乏分寸，善于掌握分寸是生命最大的奖赏。我们必须为自己用简单的对错来评判人和事付出高昂的代价，也只有这样才算公平。在这段时期，最差的品位，即对于绝对的偏好，总是被残忍地滥用，出尽洋相，直到我们学会在感情中加入一点艺术，甚至冒险尝试一些刻意的东西：就像真正的生活艺术家做的那样。年轻人高涨的愤怒和虔敬，似乎一定要把人和事伪造成他们情感的宣泄对象方才罢休——在这一点上，年轻意味着伪造和欺骗。待年轻的灵魂被失望磨折，最终将怀疑的矛头指向自己，那处于自我怀疑和良心拷问中的自己，依然血性而野蛮。现在它是多么地痛恨自己，它是那么不耐烦地撕扯自己，它要为长期以来的自我欺骗狠狠地报复自己，仿佛这是有预谋的自我蒙蔽！在这一转变中，我们通过不信任自己的感情来惩罚自己；我们用怀疑来折磨自己的热情；事实上，连问心无愧也会被感到是种危险，仿佛这也是一种自我蒙蔽，是正义感开始变得倦怠的标志。最重要的是，我们开始划分阵营，并从原则上与年轻为敌。——十年以后，我们才知道，所有这些仍然是年轻的举动。

9.在人类历史中最漫长的一段时期——即所谓的史前时期——一件行为是否有价值，由它的结果来决定。行为本身及其动机并不在人们的考虑范围之内，就像在中国，儿女的荣辱直接反映到父母身上，人们通过追溯成败的根源来对行为作出肯定或否定的评价。让我们把这个时期叫作人类的道德前期：那时“了解你自己！”这句训诫尚不为人知。另一方面，地球上的某些地方在过去一万年中逐步改变认识，认为决定行为价值的不再是结果而是动机。总体上，这是一件大事，是视野和标准上精进的结果，体现了处于统治地位的贵族价值观和血统迷信所带来的影响，它标志着狭义上的道德时期的到来：这是人们自我认知的初步尝试。人们不再考虑结果而是动机：多么伟大的视角转换！这是在经历了长期挣扎和游移之后才取得的！当然，一种灾难性的新迷信，即狭隘的诠释从此成为主导：一件行为的动机被明确地诠释为意图的动机。人们达成共识，认为行为的价值即存在于其背后的意图的价值。意图被看作是行为的全部动机和背景——正是在这种偏见的左右下，人们进行道德上的褒贬、裁夺和哲学式推究直至今日。可是，伴随着人类新一轮自省和见解的深化，我们今天难道不是有必要再次作出价值颠覆和翻转的决定？我们难道不是应该站在一个被称为超道德时期（这个叫法起初有点贬义）的起点？今天，至少在我们这些“非道德者”中间，出现了一种猜测，即决定性的行为价值恰恰存在于它的非意图部分；而所有意图部分，所有可以被看见、了解和“感知”的部分，仍然停留于它的表层和皮毛——像所有的皮毛那样，它泄露出一些秘密，但隐藏的更多。简言之，我们认为意图只是一种有待诠释的符号，由于表征的对象太过丰富而致使本意丧失。传统意义上的道德，即意图的道德，是一种偏见，一种仓促、苟且之举，类似天文学、炼金术，无论如何都必须被征服。征服道德，某种意义上也是道德的自我征服，就让它作为灵魂的试金石，成为最敏锐、最诚挚和最恶毒的良心长期秘密劳作的代名词。

10.全心奉献、为他人牺牲自己，整套关于无私的伦理都缺乏确凿的论据支持，必须受到严厉的诘问和审判；同样还有宣扬“视角公正”的美学，它被今日的艺术解放运动用来装点门面，以令其心安理得。在“舍己为人”这类情感中存有太多的糖分和妖术，让人不得不起双倍的戒心，自问：“这些会不会是诱饵？”确实，这类情感能够取悦拥有这类情感的人、从中获益的人以及观众，但这并不能提供于其有利的论据，反而提醒我们要戒备。所以还是让我们小心些吧！

11.无论今日我们在哲学上采取何种立场，从任何角度看，这个世界的错误性是我们能见到的最确定无疑的东西——层出不穷的解释诱使我们认为“事物本质”就具有欺骗性。而自觉或不自觉的“上帝代言人”，认为我们的思考本身，即“理性”，要为世界的虚假性负责，这是他们在这个问题上选择的体面出路。他们认为这个世界，包括空间、时间、结构、运动在内的一切，都是一种错误的推断。这样的人有充分的理由对思考产生怀疑：不正是思考本身让我们蒙受更大的欺骗吗？谁能保证思考不会再犯同样的错误？说实在的，思想者们的天真令人感动并心生敬意，今天他们依然会走上前去请求意识给予他们诚实的回答，比如它是否是“真的”，比如为什么它坚决拒外部世界于千里之外，等等诸如此类的问题。对于“直接的确定性”的信仰是一种道德上的天真，是我们哲学家的光荣：但是，我们不应成为“仅仅是道德的”人！除去道德的层面，这种信仰是一种蠢行，没有给我们带来任何荣耀！在日常生活中，如果有人总是抱着怀疑的态度，会被看作是“不良个性”的表现，因此是不明智的。而我们这些人，既然超越了世俗世界及其是非评判，为什么不可以冒昧地说：哲学家，作为目前为止世上受骗最多的生物，有权拥有这个“不良个性”——他有义务抱持怀疑态度，从每个怀疑的深渊狞笑着向外窥探。——请大家务必原谅我用这副幽默的嘴脸来进行表述：长期以来，在对待欺骗和被欺骗的问题上，我学会采取与以往不同的方式进行思考和评判；对于某些盲目抗拒被欺骗的哲学家，我也准备了几句友善的提醒。为什么不呢？认为“真相比表象更有价值”，不过是道德上的偏见，甚至是世界上论证得最差的假定。让我们至少承认：如果没有全面的评估和表象作为基础，根本不会有生命；如果我们像某些哲学家那样，仅凭一腔热情就笨拙地想要废止整个“表象世界”，好吧，假设你可以这么做——但你的“真相”也会化为乌有！说实在的，是什么让我们认为在“真”与“假”之间存在着实质性的不同？难道承认存在清晰程度上的不同还不够吗，就好比外观上不同程度的深浅和色调，用画家的术语来说就是不同的值？为什么我们的世界不能是虚构的？有人反对道：可是所有虚构的东西都有作者。对此，我们何不简单地反问：为什么？这种“都有”不也是一种虚构吗？现在我们不可以对主语，也像对谓语和宾语那样感到一丝讽刺吗？难道哲学家不应当凌驾于对语法的信仰之上吗？家庭教师们请恕我冒昧，可是现在，不正是哲学同家庭教师们的信仰，决裂的时候了吗？

12.噢，伏尔泰！噢，人性！噢，愚钝！“真相”和关于真相的寻求需要注意。如果一个人以太人性的方式来寻求——“他找寻真相只是为了行善”——我敢打赌，他什么也找不到！

13.假设除我们的欲望和情感世界以外，没有东西“生来”是真的，假设我们不可能上升或下降到除了冲动以外的任何其他“现实”——因为思维只是这些冲动之间的相互联系。是不是可以尝试着这样提问：这种“生来”的东西是否足以提供对所谓客观（或者“物质”）世界的理解？我不是指贝克莱[9]、叔本华[10]口中的假象、“表象”或者“观念”，而是和我们的情感拥有相同真实程度的——一种形式更为原始的情感世界，这个世界中的一切仍然处于高度的统一中，然后在有机过程中实现分化和发展（自然也变得更脆弱和敏感），作为一种本能的生命，它的全部有机功能诸如自我调节、同化、吸收、排泄和新陈代谢，仍然被综合绑定在一起——犹如生命的早期形式？——最终，这个实验不仅被允许，而且受到方法的道义的驱策。不要设想有几种因果律，只要拿一种因果律进行尝试的实验还没有被推至极端（到荒唐的地步，如果可以这么说的话）。那是一种我们现在无法驳斥的方法的道义——它由“定义”而来，像数学家说的那样。最后，问题变成我们是否真的认为意志是有效的，我们是否相信意志的因果律。如果我们相信——从根本上说，对这一点的相信正是对因果律本身的相信——那么我们就必须试着假设意志的因果律为唯一的因果律。“意志”当然只能作用于“意志”——而不能作用于“物质”（不能作用于“神经”，比如说）。总而言之，我们必须冒险试一下那个假设，即只要发现“效果”的地方，意志就正在作用于意志——而一切机械现象，只要有力活跃于其中，都是意志的力量，意志的效果。——假设最终我们成功地将我们整个本能的生命解释为意志一种基本形式的发展和衍生——即我所提出的强力意志；——假设我们可以从一切有机过程中追溯到这个强力意志，并且能够在其中找到繁殖和营养问题——它们其实是同一个问题——的解决办法，我们就有权将一切有效力量毫不含糊地定义为：强力意志。从内部观察到的世界，根据其“悟性”描述和定义的世界——只能是“强力意志”而非任何别的东西。

14.“什么？说难听点不就是：上帝被驳倒了，而魔鬼没有？”正相反！正相反，我的朋友！见鬼，谁让你说得那么难听！

15.在我们这个时代发生的法国大革命是一场可怕的闹剧，从近处审视则会发现完全是多余的。然而全欧洲高尚而热情的观众，却远隔千里，长久而富于激情地用自己的义愤和狂喜诠释着这场革命，以至于文本在诠释之下消失了。这样，高尚的后代就可以再次误读整个过去，或许只有这样，历史的样貌才可以被忍受。还是说：这一切已经发生？我们自己是否就是那“高尚的后代”？根据我们的理解，这个过程岂不是在此刻已经完成？

16.没有人会因为一个学说仅仅有助于改善人的心情和品德，就认为它是真理。或许可爱的“理想主义者们”除外，这些人为一切真善美的事物激动不已，让各种五颜六色的一厢情愿在他们的池塘里游来游去。快乐和美德并不能令人信服。不过即便思维缜密的人也倾向于忘记，不快和邪恶同样是站不住脚的抗辩。有些事尽管极为有害和危险，却可能蕴含着真相。事实上，这或许是存在的基本特性，即获得关于它的全部真相，会毁掉一个人——因此，一个人精神力量的大小可以通过他所能接受的“真相”的多少来衡量，或者说，他需要“真相”在多大程度上被稀释、遮掩、粉饰、钝化和篡改。无疑，对于某些真相的发现，邪恶而不快乐的人处于更为有利的位置，成功的可能性更大。更不用说那些邪恶并快乐的人——对于这类人，道德学家们只能保持缄默。也许严酷和狡猾的个性在造就坚强、独立的人格和哲学家方面更有优势，而温和亲切、谦恭礼让、举重若轻这些品质在学者身上更受珍视，也更有意义。假设“哲学家”这个概念并不局限于写书的哲学家——或者更糟，就自己的哲学写书的哲学家！——司汤达为具有自由精神的哲学家的形象添上了这最后一笔，鉴于德国趣味，我不得不进行强调——因为它同德国趣味背道而驰。这位最后的伟大的心理学家说：要成为好的哲学家，必须眼光犀利透彻，不受幻象所左右。一个发迹的银行家，具有进行哲学发现的一个必备特质，那就是甄别事物本质的能力。

17.所有深刻的东西都喜欢面具。最深刻的东西甚至憎恶映像和比喻。难道上帝掩饰其羞耻的伪装不正应是某种同羞耻截然相反的东西吗？这是一个可疑的疑问，如果某些神秘主义者没有思考过这些事，反而是奇怪的。有些事情表述起来如此微妙，我们宁可粗鲁地进行掩饰，使其面目全非。有时在富于爱和慷慨的举动后，最明智的做法莫过于拿起棍棒，把目击者一顿好揍，以混淆其记忆。有些人懂得如何混淆和虐待自己的记忆，这样至少可以报复这个唯一的知情者——羞辱感是富于创造力的。令我们最感羞耻的并非是最糟糕的事：面具背后不只有欺瞒——狡猾中有诸多良善。我能想象有珍贵、脆弱之物需要守护的人，在生活中可能表现得粗枝大叶，好像一只陈旧、发绿，上着厚厚铁箍的酒桶——他精致的羞耻感使他不得不如此。一个有着深刻羞耻感的人，他与命运狭路相逢的地方人迹罕至，这种地方连他的至交和邻人也一无所知。他不让他们看到自己的致命之处，以及他重新获得的对生命的把握。这样一个深藏不露的人，本能地用言语掩饰沉默和隐瞒，想方设法规避交流，他需要一个面具代替他进入朋友的大脑和内心游荡，并确保它切实有效。假设有一天他不想再要这个面具，但他会发现面具已经在那儿了——而这是一件好事。每个深刻的人都需要一个面具：不但如此，在深刻思想的周围，面具会不断扩大，这要感谢那不停编织着的谎言，即对于他所说的每个词，走过的每一步，给出的每一个生命迹象的肤浅诠释。

18.我们必须考验自己是否适合独立和掌控；而且必须在合适的时间这样做。我们不应该规避这项考验，虽然它是一个人可能碰到的最危险的游戏，并且我们自己才是最终唯一的裁判。不要成为他人的附庸，即便是你最心爱的人——每个人都是监狱，也是庇护所；不要成为祖国的附庸，即便它正在遭受苦难，亟待援助——既然胜利的祖国很少令人牵挂；不要成为怜悯的附庸，即便怜悯的对象是大人物，我们只是碰巧撞见了他少有的磨难和无助；不要成为一门科学的附庸，即便它用最珍贵的发现作为诱饵，并且看似专为我们而预备；不要成为超脱的附庸，那种鸟类的超然绝尘，为了视野更开阔而越飞越高——这是飞行者的危险；不要变成自身美德的附庸，成为我们某个部分的牺牲品，比如“好客”的牺牲品，这是富有而高尚的人面临的危险中的危险，他们出手阔绰，几乎无动于衷，将慷慨这一美德推至不道德的境地。我们必须知道如何保重自己：这就是独立人格最严苛的考验。

19.一类新的哲学家正在出现：我冒昧地给这类哲学家起个不无危险的名字。根据我对他们的猜测，以及他们允许别人对他们的猜测——他们在本性上希望保留某些方面的神秘——这些未来的哲学家可以被正确地，但也许是错误地，描述为尝试者。这个名字本身也仅仅是个尝试，或者是个引诱，如果你愿意的话。

20.这些未来的哲学家是“真理”的新朋友吗？很可能是：因为迄今为止所有的哲学家都爱他们的真理。不过当然，他们不会成为独断论者。如果他们的真理成为所有人的真理，这对他们的骄傲和品味来说是个侮辱，而这恰恰是迄今为止所有独断论者的隐秘欲望和潜台词。“我的判断是我个人的判断：别人不能轻易拥有它”——一位未来的哲学家可能会这样说。我们必须改掉希望和多数人意见一致的坏毛病。当“善”从你邻居的口中说出时，“善”将不再是善。怎么可能存在一种“共同的善”？这个表述本身就是自相矛盾的，共同的东西从来就少有价值。最终还是和现在以及过去一直以来的情形一样：伟大的人收获伟大，深刻的人窥见深刻，讲究的人得到战栗和精致。总而言之，罕见的人得到罕见的东西。

21.说了上述这些话后，我觉得没必要再说明，这些未来的哲学家也会成为自由、非常自由的精灵——同样可以肯定，他们将超越自由精灵本身，变得更加高贵、伟大、卓尔不群，根本不会被误认为是任何别的东西。不过这么说了以后，我感到自己有责任——不仅对他们也对作为他们的前驱和先行者的我们，我们这些自由的精灵——从我们所有人身上消除一种古老而愚蠢的偏见和误解，长久以来它像雾霭一样遮蔽了“自由精神”这个概念。在现今的欧洲各国和美国，这个名词遭到一类非常狭隘、封闭和奴性的人滥用，他们想要的东西和我们的意图乃至本能截然相反——更不用说对于初露头角的新型哲学家们，他们就好比关上的窗、插上的门。简言之，他们令人遗憾地属于平均主义者，这些被错误地定名为“自由精灵”的人——是民主趣味及其“现代理念”伶牙俐齿、笔耕不辍的奴隶，这些人都没有孤独，没有属于自己的孤独，他们好心而笨拙，既不缺乏勇气也不缺乏令人尊敬的体面，只是他们不自由，肤浅得可笑，尤其是他们试图在现存的社会形态中找到所有人类失败和不幸的症结的固有倾向：而这正好颠倒了事实真相！他们努力奋斗的目标是绿色牧场上羊群的普遍幸福，即每个人都拥有稳定、放心、舒适和安逸的生活。他们最经常挂在嘴边的两句口号是“权利平等”和“同情一切受苦受难的人”——他们认为受苦本身是需要被废止的。我们，作为这一观点的反对者，在“人”这种植物究竟在哪里和怎样才能生长得最茁壮这个问题上，已经茅塞顿开。我们认为个人的成长总是发生在相反的情形下，他所处的境遇必须变得异常艰险，他的创造力和掩饰力（也就是他的“精神”）必须在长期的压力和约束下演化成精明和大胆，他的生命意志必须被强化为无条件的强力意志——我们认为街道上和内心里都存在的严酷、力量、奴性、危险，以及各色伪装、禁欲主义，实验艺术，各种恶行，人身上所有的邪恶、可怕、暴戾、凶残和恶毒的东西，都能像它们的反面一样，起到提升人类的作用——即便说了这么多，我们也没有说得完全。不管怎样，在我们就这一点发表和未发表的言论中，我们都站在所有现代意识形态和羊群急需品的另一端：或许与之截然对立？难怪我们这些“自由精灵”并不一定是最健谈的人，我们不想透露一丁点儿关于自由精灵享受的自由和受到的制约。至于那句危险的惯用语“超越善恶”，我们用它来避免自己的意思被曲解：我们是和这些可敬的“现代理念”代言人自称的“自由思想者”，或者诸如此类的称谓，不同的人。我们以自由精神的国度为家，或至少曾在那里做客；我们一次次逃离那些散发着霉味的舒适的庇护所；我们曾因偏好、偏见、年轻、出身、邂逅的人、读过的书，甚至流浪的疲惫而羁留于此。对于荣誉、金钱、地位、感官享受中的奴性诱惑，我们充满憎恶；对于悲苦和变化无常的疾病，我们心存感激，因为它们总能将我们从某些规则及其“偏见”中解放出来；我们对身体里的上帝、魔鬼、绵羊和蛀虫同样感念，我们好奇到堕落的地步，穷根究底到残忍的地步，拥有捉住难以捉摸事物的大胆手指，消化不易消化事物的牙齿和肠胃；多亏了“自由意志”的丰盈，我们作好准备从事一切要求敏锐洞察力的工作，以及参与一切冒险。我们拥有正、反两面灵魂，没有人能够轻易参透我们的最终意图，我们拥有前、后双重背景，没有人能穷尽它的边缘；藏在灯罩背后的我们是征服者，尽管我们一天到晚看上去像是继承人、浪荡子、收藏家和经办人，是自家财宝和橱柜的守财奴，在学习与遗忘之间精打细算，在设想上敢于创新，有时为各类数据洋洋自得，有时显得迂腐，有时甚至勤勉得像大白天里的夜猫子。是的，如果有必要，我们还是稻草人——而现在就有这个必要：我们生来就是自身最深沉、最黑暗、最明亮的孤独那宣了誓的、富于妒忌心的朋友——我们这些自由精灵，就是这样一类人！也许你们这些后来者，你们这些新型哲学家，也会有些类似之处？

四、来自高山：古抒情诗

噢，生命的正午！噢，节日！噢，夏日的花园！我在不安的狂喜中等待，我站立着，观望着，等候着——朋友们，你们在哪儿？我日夜殷勤等候的就是你们。现在来吧！是你们出现的时候了！

难道不是因为你，冰川在今日将它的灰白换成了玫瑰红？溪流追随着你，风和云朵不断爬上蓝天更高处，满怀热望地寻找你。

为了你，我在最高的高处摆好了筵席——和我一样，你生活的地方和星星相隔咫尺，或者说和深渊的深处相隔咫尺？我的帝国——可曾有帝国如此幅员辽阔？我的蜜汁——可曾有人尝到过它的甜蜜？

——朋友们，你们来了！——但是，哎呀，我不就是你们要拜访的那个人吗？你们踌躇着，瞪大眼睛——不，还是愤怒好了！我不再是——我了吗？我的手、步伐和面孔改变了吗？在你们眼里，我不是——我了吗？

我是另一个人吗？一个我自己的陌生人？从我自身里冒出来？一个经常打败自己的摔跤运动员？经常自己和自己过不去，被自己的胜利制约和伤害？

我曾寻找风刮得最猛烈的地方，学会在不毛之地生存，忘记祈祷和诅咒，忘记人和神，变成冰川之上飞掠而过的幽灵？

——老朋友们！你们看上去多么苍白，充满爱与惊恐！不——走吧！不要生气！在这里——你们不会感觉宾至如归：在这片坚冰与岩石的遥远国度，你必须成为一名猎手，并且喜欢阿尔卑斯山的山羊。

我变成了一名邪恶的猎手！——瞧瞧我的弓有多满，拉满这张弓的必定是男人中最强有力的那一个——可是那支箭，哎呀——啊，没有哪支箭比那一支更危险——闪开！快走！为了你们自己的性命！……

你转过脸来？——噢，心脏，你表现得很坚强，你的希望仍然强大：现在让你的心扉向新朋友敞开吧！不要抓住过去不放！不要抓住回忆不放！如果你曾经年轻，那么现在——你更加年轻！

曾经联结我们的东西，那由一个希望构成的纽带——谁还能读懂曾镌刻其上、如今业已模糊的爱的符号？它就像一张羊皮纸——褪色，枯黄——伸过去的手也会缩回来。

不再是朋友，可是——我该如何称呼他们？——他们是朋友的幽灵，暗夜里叩响我的心扉，注视着我说：“我们曾经是朋友吗？”——噢，褪色的词句，曾经如玫瑰一般芬芳！

噢，青春的憧憬，往往并不自知！那些我曾经仰慕和崇敬的人，变成了我的亲人——他们的老去成为他们被放逐的理由：只有那不断变化的人才保持着和我的相似。

噢，生命的正午！噢，第二次青春！噢，夏日的花园！我在不安的狂喜中等待，我站立着，观望着，等候着——我在等候朋友，新的朋友，不分日夜殷勤守候。现在来吧！是你们出现的时候了！

这首歌已经完成——欲望的甜蜜喊叫死在了嘴唇上：这是一个男巫干的，一个适时的朋友，正午之友——不！不要问他是谁——它在正午时发生，在正午时，一个人变成了两个……

现在，对胜利成竹在胸的我们，庆祝盛事中的盛事：我们的朋友查拉图斯特拉[11]来了，他是贵宾中的贵宾！既然全世界都在大笑，可怖的幕布被租来，婚礼之日迎来光明与黑暗……

[1]伊希斯是埃及古代宗教里的女神，被认为是贤妻良母的典范、自然和魔法的保护者，受到统治阶级和劳苦大众的一致欢迎，被尊奉为生育、魔法和丰产女神。

[2]巴鲁赫·斯宾诺莎，十七世纪荷兰哲学家。因怀有异端思想被犹太教会革除教籍、逐出社团，以磨镜片为生，在隐居中进行哲学研究。

[3]乔尔丹诺·布鲁诺，意大利文艺复兴时期的思想家和哲学家，因反对地心说、坚持日心说，被宗教裁判所囚禁八年，后被烧死在罗马鲜花广场。

[4]“羊人剧”，古希腊悲剧的雏形，由装扮成半人半兽的演员演出而得名。一般是轻松的短剧，在一个悲剧三联剧后上演，作为调剂和对悲剧的讽刺。

[5]费迪南多·加利亚尼，意大利经济学家。尼采曾称他为十八世纪“最精致、最挑剔的头脑”。

[6]阿里斯托芬，古希腊早期喜剧代表作家，相传写有四十四部喜剧，有“喜剧之父”之称。

[7]佩特罗尼乌斯，古罗马作家，暴君尼禄的廷臣，主管宫中娱乐，著有长篇讽刺小说《萨蒂利孔》。

[8]牛头怪（弥诺陶洛斯），古希腊神话中的人身牛头怪物，被禁闭在弥诺斯的迷宫中，吞食雅典进贡的童男童女。

[9]乔治·贝克莱，英国主观唯心主义哲学家、主教。他认为世界上只存在能进行思考的心灵，和不能进行思考、只存在于心灵之中的观念。

[10]亚瑟·叔本华，德国哲学家。他认为世界分为两部分：一方面是表象，一方面是控制表象世界的意志。

[11]查拉图斯特拉，公元前七到六世纪的古代波斯宗教改革者。尼采在其作品《查拉图斯特拉如是说》中假借他的名义说出自己的哲学思想。

1　Man Alone with Himself

1

Enemies of truth. Convictions are more dangerous enemies of truth than lies.

2

Topsy-turvy world. We criticize a thinker more sharply when he proposes a tenet that is disagreeable to us; and yet it would be more reasonable to do this when we find his tenet agreeable.

3

A person of character. It is much more common for a person to appear to have character because he always acts in accord with his temperament, rather than because he always acts in accord with his principles.

4

The one necessary thing. A person must have one or the other: either a disposition which is easygoing by nature, or else a disposition eased by art and knowledge.

5

Passion for things. He who directs his passion to things (the sciences, the national good, cultural interests, the arts) takes much of the fire out of his passion for people (even when they represent those things, as statesmen, philosophers, and artists represent their creations).

6

Calm in action. As a waterfall becomes slower and more floating as it plunges, so the great man of action will act with greater calm than could be expected from his violent desire before the deed.

7

Not too deep. People who comprehend a matter in all its depth seldom remain true to it forever. For they have brought its depths to the light; and then there is always much to see about it that is bad.

8

Idealists' delusion. All idealists imagine that the causes they serve are significantly better than the other causes in the world; they do not want to believe that if their cause is to flourish at all, it needs exactly the same foul-smelling manure that all other human undertakings require.

9

Self-observation. Man is very well defended against himself, against his own spying and sieges; usually he is able to make out no more of himself than his outer fortifications. The actual stronghold is inaccessible to him, even invisible, unless friends and enemies turn traitor and lead him there by a secret path.

10

The right profession. Men seldom endure a profession if they do not believe or persuade themselves that it is basically more important than all others. Women do the same with their lovers.

11

Nobility of mind. To a great degree, nobility of mind consists of good nature and lack of distrust, and thus contains precisely that which acquisitive and successful people so like to treat with superiority and scorn.

12

Destination and paths. Many people are obstinate about the path once it is taken, few people about the destination.

13

The infuriating thing about an individual way of living. People are always angry at anyone who chooses very individual standards for his life; because of the extraordinary treatment which that man grants to himself, they feel degraded, like ordinary beings.

14

Privilege of greatness. It is the privilege of greatness to grant supreme pleasure through trifling gifts.

15

Unwittingly noble. A man's behavior is unwittingly noble if he has grown accustomed never to want anything from men, and always to give to them.

16

Condition for being a hero. If a man wants to become a hero, the snake must first become a dragon: otherwise he is lacking his proper enemy.

17

Friend. Shared joy, not compassion, makes a friend.

18

Using high and low tides. For the purpose of knowledge, one must know how to use that inner current that draws us to a thing, and then the one that, after a time, draws us away from it.

19

Delight in oneself. 'Delight in an enterprise,' they say; but in truth it is delight in oneself, by means of an enterprise.

20

The modest one. He who is modest with people shows his arrogance all the more with things (the city, state, society, epoch, or mankind). That is his revenge.

21

Envy and jealousy. Envy and jealousy are the pudenda of the human soul. The comparison can perhaps be pursued further.

22

The most refined hypocrite. To speak about oneself not at all is a very refined form of hypocrisy.

23

Annoyance. Annoyance is a physical illness that is by no means ended simply by eliminating the cause of the annoyance.

24

Representatives of truth. The champions of truth are hardest to find, not when it is dangerous to tell it, but rather when it is boring.

25

More troublesome than enemies. When some reason (e.g., gratitude) obliges us to maintain the appearance of unqualified congeniality with people about whose own congenial behavior we are not entirely convinced, these people torment our imagination much more than do our enemies.

26

Out in nature. We like to be out in nature so much because it has no opinion about us.

27

Everyone superior in one thing. In civilized circumstances, everyone feels superior to everyone else in at least one way; this is the basis of the general goodwill, inasmuch as everyone is someone who, under certain conditions, can be of help, and need therefore feel no shame in allowing himself to be helped.

28

Reasons for consolation. When someone dies, we usually need reasons to be consoled, not so much to soften the force of our pain, as to excuse the fact that we feel consoled so easily.

29

Loyal to their convictions. The man who has a lot to do usually keeps his general views and opinions almost unchanged; as does each person who works in the service of an idea. He will never test the idea itself any more; he no longer has time for that. Indeed, it is contrary to his interest even to think it possible to discuss it.

30

Morality and quantity. One man's greater morality, in contrast to another's, often lies only in the fact that his goals are quantitatively larger. The other man is pulled down by occupying himself with small things, in a narrow sphere.

31

Life as the product of life. However far man may extend himself with his knowledge, however objective he may appear to himself - ultimately he reaps nothing but his own biography.

32

Iron necessity. Over the course of history, men learn that iron necessity is neither iron nor necessary.

33

From experience. That something is irrational is no argument against its existence, but rather a condition for it.

34

Truth. No one dies of fatal truths nowadays: there are too many antidotes.

35

Basic insight. There is no pre-established harmony between the furthering of truth and the good of mankind.

36

Human lot. Whoever thinks more deeply knows that he is always wrong, whatever his acts and judgments.

37

Truth as Circe. Error has turned animals into men; might truth be capable of turning man into an animal again?

38

Danger of our culture. We belong to a time in which culture is in danger of being destroyed by the means of culture.

39

Greatness means: to give a direction. No river is great and bounteous through itself alone, but rather because it takes up so many tributaries and carries them onwards: that makes it great. It is the same with all great minds. All that matters is that one man give the direction, which the many tributaries must then follow; it does not matter whether he is poorly or richly endowed in the beginning.

40

Weak conscience. Men who talk about their importance for mankind have a weak conscience about their common bourgeois honesty in keeping contracts or promises.

41

Wanting to be loved. The demand to be loved is the greatest kind of arrogance.

42

Contempt for people. The least ambiguous sign of a disdain for people is this: that one tolerates everyone else only as a means to his end, or not at all.

43

Disciples out of disagreement. Whoever has brought men to a state of rage against himself has always acquired a party in his favor, too.

44

Forgetting one's experiences. It is easy for a man who thinks a lot - and objectively - to forget his own experiences, but not the thoughts that were evoked by them.

45

Adhering to an opinion. One man adheres to an opinion because he prides himself on having come upon it by himself; another because he has learned it with effort, and is proud of having grasped it: thus both out of vanity.

46

Shunning the light. The good deed shuns the light as anxiously as the evil deed: the latter fears that, if it is known, pain (as punishment) will follow; the former fears that, if it is known, joy (that pure joy in oneself, which ceases as soon as it includes the satisfaction of one's vanity) will disappear.

47

The day's length. If a man has a great deal to put in them, a day will have a hundred pockets.

48

Tyrant-genius. If the soul stirs with an ungovernable desire to assert itself tyranically, and the fire is continually maintained, then even a slight talent (in politicians or artists) gradually becomes an almost irresistible force of nature.

49

The life of the enemy. Whoever lives for the sake of combating an enemy has an interest in the enemy's staying alive.

50

More important. The unexplained, obscure matter is taken as more important than the explained, clear one.

51

Evaluating services rendered. We evaluate services someone renders us according to the value that person places on them, not according to the value they have for us.

52

Unhappiness. The distinction that lies in being unhappy (as if to feel happy were a sign of shallowness, lack of ambition, ordinariness) is so great that when someone says, 'But how happy you must be!' we usually protest.

53

Fantasy of fear. The fantasy of fear is that malevolent, apelike goblin which jumps onto man's back just when he already has the most to bear.

54

Value of insipid opponents. Sometimes we remain true to a cause only because its opponents will not stop being insipid.

55

Value of a profession. A profession makes us thoughtless: therein lies its greatest blessing. For it is a bulwark, behind which we are allowed to withdraw when qualms and worries of a general kind attack us.

56

Talent. The talent of some men appears slighter than it is because they have always set themselves tasks that are too great.

57

Youth. The time of youth is disagreeable, for then it is not possible, or not reasonable, to be productive in any sense.

58

Goals too great. Who publicly sets himself great goals, and later realizes privately that he is too weak to accomplish them, does not usually have enough strength to revoke those goals publicly, either, and then inevitably becomes a hypocrite.

59

In the stream. Strong currents draw many stones and bushes along with them; strong minds many stupid and muddled heads.

60

Danger of intellectual liberation. When a man tries earnestly to liberate his intellect, his passions and desires secretly hope to benefit from it also.

61

Embodiment of the spirit. When a man thinks much and cleverly, not only his face, but also his body takes on a clever look.

62

Seeing poorly and hearing poorly. He who sees little, always sees less; he who hears poorly, always hears something more.

63

Self-enjoyment in vanity. The vain man wants not only to stand out, but also to feel outstanding, and therefore rejects no means to deceive and outwit himself. Not the opinion of others, but his opinion of their opinion is what he cares about.

64

Vain by way of an exception. When he is physically ill, the man who is usually self-sufficient is vain by way of an exception and responsive to fame and praise. In the proportion that he is losing himself, he must try to regain himself from the outside, using strangers' opinions.

65

The 'witty' ones. The man who seeks wit has no wit.

66

Hint for party chiefs. If we can force people to declare themselves publicly for something, we have usually also brought them to the point of declaring themselves for it privately; they want to continue to be perceived as consistent.

67

Contempt. Man is more sensitive to contempt from others than to contempt from himself.

68

Rope of gratitude. There are slavish souls who carry their thanks for favors so far that they actually strangle themselves with the rope of gratitude.

69

Trick of the prophet. In order to predict the behavior of ordinary men, we must assume that they always expend the least possible amount of intellect to free themselves from a disagreeable situation.

70

The only human right. He who strays from tradition becomes a sacrifice to the extraordinary; he who remains in tradition is its slave. Destruction follows in any case.

71

Lower than the animal. When man howls with laughter, he surpasses all animals by his coarseness.

72

Superficial knowledge. He who speaks a bit of a foreign language has more delight in it than he who speaks it well; pleasure goes along with superficial knowledge.

73

Dangerous helpfulness. There are people who want to make men's lives more difficult for no other reason than afterwards to offer them their prescriptions for making life easier - their Christianity, for example.

74

Industriousness and conscientiousness. Industriousness and conscientiousness are often antagonists, in that industriousness wants to take the fruits off the tree while still sour, but conscientiousness lets them hang too long, until they drop off the tree and come to nothing.

75

Suspicion. People whom we cannot tolerate, we try to make suspect.

76

Lacking the circumstances. Many men wait all their lives for the opportunity to be good in their way.

77

Want of friends. A want of friends points to envy or arrogance. Many a man owes his friends simply to the fortunate circumstance that he has no cause for envy.

78

Danger in multiplicity. With one talent the more, one often stands less secure than with one talent the less: as the table stands better on three legs than on four.

79

Model for others. He who wants to set a good example must add a grain of foolishness to his virtue; then others can imitate and, at the same time, rise above the one being imitated - something which people love.

80

Being a target. Often, other people's vicious talk about us is not actually aimed at us, but expresses their annoyance or ill humor arising from quite different reasons.

81

Easily resigned. A man suffers little from unfulfilled wishes if he has trained his imagination to think of the past as hateful.

82

In danger. When we have just gotten out of the way of a vehicle, we are most in danger of being run over.

83

The role according to the voice. He who is forced to speak more loudly than is his habit (as in front of someone hard of hearing, or before a large audience) generally exaggerates what he has to communicate.

Some people become conspirators, malicious slanderers, or schemers, merely because their voice is best suited to a whisper.

84

Love and hatred. Love and hatred are not blind, but are blinded by the fire they themselves carry with them.

85

Made an enemy to one's advantage. Men who are unable to make their merit completely clear to the world seek to awaken an intense enmity towards themselves. Then they have the comfort of thinking that this stands between their merit and its recognition - and that other people assume the same thing, which is of great advantage to their own importance.

86

Confession. We forget our guilt when we have confessed it to another, but usually the other person does not forget it.

87

Self-sufficiency. The golden fleece of self-sufficiency protects against thrashings, but not against pin-pricks.

88

Shadow in the flame. The flame is not so bright to itself as to those on whom it shines: so too the wise man.

89

Our own opinions. The first opinion that occurs to us when we are suddenly asked about a matter is usually not our own, but only the customary one, appropriate to our caste, position, or parentage; our own opinions seldom swim near the surface.

90

Origin of courage. The ordinary man is courageous and invulnerable like a hero when he does not see the danger, when he has no eyes for it. Conversely, the hero's one vulnerable spot is on his back; that is, where he has no eyes.

91

Danger in the doctor. A man is either born for his doctor, or else he perishes by his doctor.

92

Magical vanity. He who has boldly prophesied the weather three times and has been successful, believes a bit, at the bottom of his heart, in his own prophetic gift. We do not dispute what is magical or irrational when it flatters our self-esteem.

93

Profession. A profession is the backbone of life.

94

Danger of personal influence. He who feels that he exercises a great inner influence on another must leave him quite free rein, indeed must look with favor on his occasional resistance and even bring it about: otherwise he will inevitably make himself an enemy.

95

Giving the heir his due. Whoever has established something great with a selfless frame of mind takes care to bring up heirs. It is the sign of a tyrannical and ignoble nature to see one's opponents in all the possible heirs of one's work and to live in a state of self-defense against them.

96

A little knowledge. A little knowledge is more successful than complete knowledge: it conceives things as simpler than they are, thus resulting in opinions that are more comprehensible and persuasive.

97

Not suited to be a party member. He who thinks much is not suited to be a party member: too soon, he thinks himself through and beyond the party.

98

Bad memory. The advantage of a bad memory is that, several times over, one enjoys the same good things for the first time.

99

Causing oneself pain. Inconsiderate thinking is often the sign of a discordant inner state which craves numbness.

100

Martyr. The disciple of a martyr suffers more than the martyr.

101

Residual vanity. The vanity of some people, who should not need to be vain, is the left-over and full-grown habit stemming from that time when they still had no right to believe in themselves, and only acquired their belief from others, by begging it in small change.

102

Punctum saliens of passion. He who is about to fall into a state of anger or violent love reaches a point where his soul is full like a vessel; but it needs one more drop of water: the good will to passion (which is generally also called the bad will). Only this little point is necessary; then the vessel runs over.

103

Bad-tempered thought. People are like piles of charcoal in the woods. Only when young people have stopped glowing, and carbonized, as charcoal does, do they become useful. As long as they smolder and smoke they are perhaps more interesting, but useless, and all too often troublesome.

Mankind unsparingly uses every individual as material to heat its great machines; but what good are the machines when all individuals (that is, mankind) serve only to keep them going? Machines that are their own end - is that the umana commedia?

104

The hour-hand of life. Life consists of rare, isolated moments of the greatest significance, and of innumerably many intervals, during which at best the silhouettes of those moments hover about us. Love, springtime, every beautiful melody, mountains, the moon, the sea - all these speak completely to the heart but once, if in fact they ever do get a chance to speak completely. For many men do not have those moments at all, and are themselves intervals and intermissions in the symphony of real life.

105

To set against or set to work. We often make the mistake of actively opposing a direction, or party, or epoch, because we coincidentally get to see only its superficial side, its stunted aspect, or the inescapable 'faults of its virtues,' - perhaps because we ourselves have participated to a large degree in them. Then we turn our back on them and seek an opposite direction; but it would be better to look for the strong, good sides, or to develop them in ourselves. To be sure, it takes a stronger gaze and a better will to further that which is evolving and imperfect, rather than to penetrate its imperfection and reject it.

106

Modesty. True modesty (that is, the knowledge that we are not our own creations) does exist, and it well suits the great mind, because he particularly can comprehend the thought of his complete lack of responsibility (even for whatever good he creates). One does not hate the great man's immodesty because he is feeling his strength, but rather because he wants to feel it primarily by wounding others, treating them imperiously and watching to see how much they can stand. Most often, this actually proves that he lacks a secure sense of his strength, and makes men doubt his greatness. To this extent, cleverness would strongly advise against immodesty.

107

The first thought of the day. The best way to begin each day well is to think upon awakening whether we could not give at least one person pleasure on this day. If this practice could be accepted as a substitute for the religious habit of prayer, our fellow men would benefit by this change.

108

Arrogance as the last means of comfort. If a man accounts for a misfortune, or his intellectual inadequacies, or his illness by seeing them as his predetermined fate, his ordeal, or mysterious punishment for something he had done earlier, he is thereby making his own nature interesting, and imagining himself superior to his fellow men. The proud sinner is a familiar figure in all religious sects.

109

Growth of happiness. Near to the sorrow of the world, and often upon its volcanic earth, man has laid out his little gardens of happiness; whether he approaches life as one who wants only knowledge from existence, or as one who yields and resigns himself, or as one who rejoices in a difficulty overcome - everywhere he will find some happiness sprouting up next to the trouble. The more volcanic the earth, the greater the happiness will be - but it would be ludicrous to say that this happiness justified suffering per se.

110

The street of one's ancestors. It is reasonable to develop further the talent that one's father or grandfather worked hard at, and not switch to something entirely new; otherwise one is depriving himself of the chance to attain perfection in some one craft. Thus the saying: 'Which street should you take? - that of your ancestors.'

111

Vanity and ambition as educators. So long as a man has not yet become the instrument of the universal human good, ambition may torment him; but if he has achieved that goal, if of necessity he is working like a machine for the good of all, then vanity may enter; it will humanize him in small matters, make him more sociable, tolerable, considerate, once ambition has completed the rough work (of making him useful).

112

Philosophical novices. If we have just partaken of a philosopher's wisdom, we go through the streets feeling as if we had been transformed and had become great men; for we encounter only people who do not know this wisdom, and thus we have to deliver a new, unheard-of judgment about everything; because we have acknowledged a book of laws, we also think we now have to act like judges.

113

Pleasing by displeasing. People who prefer to be noticed, and thereby displease, desire the same thing as those who do not want to be noticed, and want to please, only to a much greater degree and indirectly, by means of a step that seems to be distancing them from their goal. Because they want to have influence and power, they display their superiority, even if it is felt as disagreeable: for they know that the man who has finally gained power pleases in almost everything he does and says, that even when he displeases, he seems nevertheless to be pleasing.

Both the free spirit and the true believer want power, too, in order to use it to please; if they are threatened because of their doctrines with a dire fate, persecution, prison, or execution, they rejoice at the thought that this will enable their doctrines to be engraved and branded upon mankind; although it is delayed acting, they accept it as a painful but potent means to attain power after all.

114

Casus belli and the like. The prince who discovers a casus belli for an earlier decision to wage war against his neighbor is like a father who imposes a mother upon his child, to be henceforth accepted as such. And are not almost all publicly announced motives for our actions such imposed mothers?

115

Passions and rights. No one speaks more passionately about his rights than the man who, at the bottom of his heart, doubts them. In drawing passion to his side, he wants to deaden reason and its doubts: he thus gains a good conscience, and, along with it, success with his fellow men.

116

The renouncing man's trick. He who protests against marriage, in the manner of Catholic priests, will seek to understand it in its lowest, most vulgar sense. Likewise, he who refuses the respect of his contemporaries will conceive it in a base way; he thus makes his renunciation of it and the fight against it easier for himself. Incidentally, he who denies himself much in large matters will easily indulge himself in small matters. It is conceivable that the man who is above the applause of his contemporaries is nevertheless unable to refuse himself the satisfaction of little vanities.

117

The age of arrogance. The true period of arrogance for talented men comes between their twenty-sixth and thirtieth year; it is the time of first ripeness, with a good bit of sourness still remaining. On the basis of what one feels inside himself, one demands from other people, who see little or nothing of it, respect and humility; and because these are not at first forthcoming, one takes vengeance with a glance, an arrogant gesture, or a tone of voice. This a fine ear and eye will recognize in all the products of those years, be they poems, philosophies, or paintings and music. Older, experienced men smile about it, and remember with emotion this beautiful time of life, in which one is angry at his lot of having to be so much and seem so little. Later, one really seems to be more - but the faith in being much has been lost, unless one remain throughout his life vanity's hopeless fool.

118

Deceptive and yet firm. When walking around the top of an abyss, or crossing a deep stream on a plank, we need a railing, not to hold on to (for it would collapse with us at once), but rather to achieve the visual image of security. Likewise, when we are young, we need people who unconsciously offer us the service of that railing; it is true that they would not help us if we really were in great danger and wanted to lean on them; but they give us the comforting sensation of protection nearby (for example, fathers, teachers, friends, as we generally know all three).

119

Learning to love. We must learn to love, learn to be kind, and this from earliest youth; if education or chance give us no opportunity to practice these feelings, our soul becomes dry and unsuited even to understanding the tender inventions of loving people. Likewise, hatred must be learned and nurtured, if one wishes to become a proficient hater: otherwise the germ for that, too, will gradually wither.

120

Ruins as decoration. People who go through many spiritual changes retain some views and habits from earlier stages, which then jut out into their new thinking and acting like a bit of inexplicable antiquity and gray stonework, often ornamenting the whole region.

121

Love and respect. Love desires; fear avoids. That is why it is impossible, at least in the same time span, to be loved and respected by the same person. For the man who respects another, acknowledges his power; that is, he fears it: his condition is one of awe. But love acknowledges no power, nothing that separates, differentiates, ranks higher or subordinates. Because the state of being loved carries with it no respect, ambitious men secretly or openly balk against it.

122

Prejudice in favor of cold people. People who catch fire rapidly quickly become cold, and are therefore by and large unreliable. Therefore, all those who are always cold, or act that way, benefit from the prejudice that they are especially trustworthy, reliable people: they are being confused with those others who catch fire slowly and burn for a long time.

123

What is dangerous about free opinions. The casual entertainment of free opinions is like an itch; giving in to it, one begins to rub the area; finally there is an open, aching wound; that is, the free opinion finally begins to disturb and torment us in our attitude to life, in our human relationships.

124

Desire for deep pain. When it has gone, passion leaves behind a dark longing for itself, and in disappearing throws us one last seductive glance. There must have been a kind of pleasure in having been beaten with her whip. In contrast, the more moderate feelings appear flat; apparently we still prefer a more violent displeasure to a weak pleasure.

125

Annoyance with others and the world. When, as happens so often, we let our annoyance out on others, while we are actually feeling it about ourselves, we are basically trying to cloud and delude our judgment; we want to motivate our annoyance a posteriori by the oversights and inadequacies of others, so we can lose sight of ourselves.

Religiously strict people, who judge themselves without mercy, are also those who have most often spoken ill of mankind in general. There has never been a saint who reserves sins to himself and virtues to others: he is as rare as the man who, following Buddha's precept, hides his goodness from people and lets them see of himself only what is bad.

126

Cause and effect confused. Unconsciously we seek out the principles and dogmas that are in keeping with our temperament, so that in the end it looks as if the principles and dogmas had created our character, given it stability and certainty, while precisely the opposite has occurred. It seems that our thinking and judging are to be made the cause of our nature after the fact, but actually our nature causes us to think and judge one way or the other.

And what decides us on this almost unconscious comedy? Laziness and convenience, and not least the vain desire to be considered consistent through and through, uniform both in character and thought: for this earns us respect, brings us trust and power.

127

Age and truth. Young people love what is interesting and odd, no matter how true or false it is. More mature minds love what is interesting and odd about truth. Fully mature intellects, finally, love truth, even when it appears plain and simple, boring to the ordinary person; for they have noticed that truth tends to reveal its highest wisdom in the guise of simplicity.

128

People as bad poets. Just as bad poets, in the second half of a line, look for a thought to fit their rhyme, so people in the second half of their lives, having become more anxious, look for the actions, attitudes, relationships that suit those of their earlier life, so that everything will harmonize outwardly. But then they no longer have any powerful thought to rule their life and determine it anew; rather, in its stead, comes the intention of finding a rhyme.

129

Boredom and play. Need forces us to do the work whose product will quiet the need; we are habituated to work by the ever-new awakening of needs. But in those intervals when our needs are quieted and seem to sleep, boredom overtakes us. What is that? It is the habit of working as such, which now asserts itself as a new, additional need; the need becomes the greater, the greater our habit of working, perhaps even the greater our suffering from our needs. To escape boredom, man works either beyond what his usual needs require, or else he invents play, that is, work that is designed to quiet no need other than that for working in general. He who is tired of play, and has no reason to work because of new needs, is sometimes overcome by the longing for a third state that relates to play as floating does to dancing, as dancing does to walking, a blissful, peaceful state of motion: it is the artist's and philosopher's vision of happiness.

130

Instruction from pictures. If we consider a series of pictures of ourselves from the time of childhood to that of manhood, we are agreeably surprised to find that the man resembles the child more than the adolescent: probably corresponding to this occurrence, then, there has been a temporary alienation from our basic character, now overcome again by the man's collected, concentrated strength. This perception agrees with the one that all those strong influences of our passions, our teachers, or political events, which pull us about in our adolescence, later seem to be reduced to a fixed measure. Certainly, they continue to live and act in us, but our basic feeling and basic thinking have the upper hand; these influences are used as sources of power, but no longer as regulators, as happens in our twenties. Thus man's thinking and feeling appear again more in accord with that of his childhood years - and this inner fact is expressed in the external one mentioned above.

131

Voice of the years. The tone adolescents use to speak, praise, blame, or invent displeases older people because it is too loud and yet at the same time muffled and unclear, like a tone in a vault, which gains resonance because of the emptiness. For most of what adolescents think has not flowed out of the fullness of their own nature, but rather harmonizes and echoes what is thought, spoken, praised, or blamed around them. But because the feelings (of inclination and disinclination) reverberate in them much more strongly than the reasons for these feelings, there arises, when they give voice to their feeling again, that muffled, ringing tone that indicates the absence or paucity of reasons. The tone of the more mature years is rigorous, sharply punctuated, moderately loud, but like everything clearly articulated, it carries very far. Finally, old age often brings a certain gentleness and indulgence to the sound and seems to sugar it: of course, in some cases it makes it sour, too.

132

Backward and anticipating people. The unpleasant personality who is full of mistrust, who reacts with envy to his competitors' and neighbors' successes, who flares up violently at divergent opinions, is showing that he belongs to an earlier stage of culture, and is thus a relic. For the way in which he interacts with people was proper and appropriate for the conditions of an age when rule by force prevailed: he is a backward person. A second personality, who shares profusely in others' joy, who wins friends everywhere, who is touched by everything that grows and evolves, who enjoys other people's honors and successes, and makes no claim to the privilege of alone knowing the truth, but instead is full of modest skepticism - he is an anticipator who is reaching ahead towards a higher human culture. The unpleasant personality grows out of times when the unhewn foundation of human intercourse had still to be laid; the other lives on its highest floors, as far away as possible from the wild animal that rages and howls locked up in the cellars, beneath the foundations of culture.

133

Comfort for hypochondriacs. When a great thinker is temporarily subjected to hypochondriacal self-torments, he may say to comfort himself: 'This parasite is feeding and growing from your great strength; if that strength were less, you would have less to suffer.' The statesman may speak likewise when his jealousy and vengeful feelings, in short, the mood of a bellum omnium contra omnes, for which he as a nation's representative must necessarily have a great gift, occasionally intrude into his personal relations and make his life difficult.

134

Alienated from the present. There are great advantages in for once removing ourselves distinctly from our time and letting ourselves be driven from its shore back into the ocean of former world views. Looking at the coast from that perspective, we survey for the first time its entire shape, and when we near it again, we have the advantage of understanding it better on the whole than do those who have never left it.

135

Sowing and reaping on personal inadequacies. People like Rousseau know how to use their weaknesses, deficiencies, or vices as if they were the fertilizer of their talent. When Rousseau laments the depravity and degeneration of society as the unpleasant consequence of culture, this is based on his personal experience, whose bitterness makes his general condemnation so sharp, and poisons the arrows he shoots. He is relieving himself first as an individual, and thinks that he is seeking a cure that will directly benefit society, but that will also indirectly, and by means of society, benefit him too.

136

A philosophical frame of mind. Generally we strive to acquire one emotional stance, one viewpoint for all life situations and events: we usually call that being of a philosophical frame of mind. But rather than making oneself uniform, we may find greater value for the enrichment of knowledge by listening to the soft voice of different life situations; each brings its own views with it. Thus we acknowledge and share the life and nature of many by not treating ourselves like rigid, invariable, single individuals.

137

In the fire of contempt. It is a new step towards independence, once a man dares to express opinions that bring disgrace on him if he entertains them; then even his friends and acquaintances begin to grow anxious. The man of talent must pass through this fire, too; afterwards he is much more his own person.

138

Sacrifice. If there is a choice, a great sacrifice will be preferred to a small one, because we compensate ourselves for a great sacrifice with self-admiration, and this is not possible with a small one.

139

Love as a device. Whoever wants really to get to know something new (be it a person, an event, or a book) does well to take up this new thing with all possible love, to avert his eye quickly from, even to forget, everything about it that he finds inimical, objectionable, or false. So, for example, we give the author of a book the greatest possible head start, and, as if at a race, virtually yearn with a pounding heart for him to reach his goal. By doing this, we penetrate into the heart of the new thing, into its motive center: and this is what it means to get to know it. Once we have got that far, reason then sets its limits; that overestimation, that occasional unhinging of the critical pendulum, was just a device to entice the soul of a matter out into the open.

140

To think too well or too ill of the world. Whether we think too well or too ill of things, we will always gain the advantage of reaping a greater pleasure: if our preconceived opinion is too good we are generally investing things (experiences) with more sweetness than they actually possess. If a preconceived opinion is overly negative, it leads to a pleasant disappointment: what was pleasurable in those things in and of themselves is increased through the pleasure of our surprise.

Incidentally, a morose temperament will experience the opposite in both cases.

141

Profound people. Those people whose strength lies in the profundity of their impressions (they are generally called 'profound people') are relatively controlled and decisive when anything sudden happens: for in the first moment the impression was still shallow; only later does it become profound. But long-foreseen, anticipated things or people excite such natures most, and make them almost incapable of maintaining presence of mind when their wait is over.

142

Traffic with one's higher self. Everyone has his good day, when he finds his higher self; and true humanity demands that we judge someone only when he is in this condition, and not in his workdays of bondage and servitude. We should, for example, assess and honor a painter according to the highest vision he was able to see and portray. But people themselves deal very differently with this, their higher self, and often act out the role of their own self, to the extent that they later keep imitating what they were in those moments. Some regard their ideal with shy humility and would like to deny it: they fear their higher self because, when it speaks, it speaks demandingly. In addition, it has a ghostly freedom of coming or staying away as it wishes; for that reason it is often called a gift of the gods, while actually everything else is a gift of the gods (of chance): this, however, is the man himself.

143

Solitary people. Some people are so used to solitude with themselves that they never compare themselves to others, but spin forth their monologue of a life in a calm, joyous mood, holding good conversations with themselves, even laughing. But if they are made to compare themselves with others, they tend to a brooding underestimation of their selves: so that they have to be forced to learn again from others to have a good, fair opinion of themselves. And even from this learned opinion they will always want to detract or reduce something.

Thus one must grant certain men their solitude, and not be silly enough, as often happens, to pity them for it.

144

Without melody. There are people for whom a constant inner repose and a harmonious ordering of all their capabilities is so characteristic that any goal-directed activity goes against their grain. They are like a piece of music consisting entirely of sustained harmonious chords, with no evidence of even the beginning of a structured, moving melody. At any movement from the outside, their boat at once gains a new equilibrium on the sea of harmonic euphony. Modern people are usually extremely impatient on meeting such natures, who do not become anything - though it may not be said that they are not anything. In certain moods, however, their presence evokes that rare question: why have melody at all? Why are we not satisfied when life mirrors itself peacefully in a deep lake?

The Middle Ages was richer in such natures than we are. How seldom do we now meet a person who can keep living so peacefully and cheerfully with himself even amidst the turmoil, saying to himself like Goethe: 'The best is the deep quiet in which I live and grow against the world, and harvest what they cannot take from me by fire or sword.'

145

Life and experience. If one notices how some individuals know how to treat their experiences (their insignificant everyday experiences) so that these become a plot of ground that bears fruit three times a year; while others (and how many of them!) are driven through the waves of the most exciting turns of fate, of the most varied currents of their time or nation, and yet always stay lightly on the surface, like cork: then one is finally tempted to divide mankind into a minority (minimality) of those people who know how to make much out of little and a majority of those who know how to make a little out of much; indeed, one meets those perverse wizards who, instead of creating the world out of nothing, create nothing out of the world.

146

Seriousness in play. At sunset in Genoa, I heard from a tower a long chiming of bells: it kept on and on, and over the noise of the back streets, as if insatiable for itself, it rang out into the evening sky and the sea air, so terrible and so childish at the same time, so melancholy. Then I thought of Plato's words and felt them suddenly in my heart: all in all, nothing human is worth taking very seriously; nevertheless ...

147

On convictions and justice. To carry out later, in coolness and sobriety, what a man promises or decides in passion: this demand is among the heaviest burdens oppressing mankind. To have to acknowledge for all duration the consequences of anger, of raging vengeance, of enthusiastic devotion - this can incite a bitterness against these feelings all the greater because everywhere, and especially by artists, precisely these feelings are the object of idol worship. Artists cultivate the esteem for the passions, and have always done so; to be sure, they also glorify the frightful satisfactions of passion, in which one indulges, the outbursts of revenge that have death, mutilation, or voluntary banishment as a consequence, and the resignation of the broken heart. In any event, they keep alive curiosity about the passions; it is as if they wished to say: without passions you have experienced nothing at all.

Because we have vowed to be faithful, even, perhaps, to a purely imaginary being, a God, for instance; because we have given our heart to a prince, a party, a woman, a priestly order, an artist, or a thinker, in the state of blind madness that enveloped us in rapture and let those beings appear worthy of every honor, every sacrifice: are we then inextricably bound? Were we not deceiving ourselves then? Was it not a conditional promise, under the assumption (unstated, to be sure) that those beings to whom we dedicated ourselves really are the beings they appeared to be in our imaginations? Are we obliged to be faithful to our errors, even if we perceive that by this faithfulness we do damage to our higher self?

No - there is no law, no obligation of that kind; we must become traitors, act unfaithfully, forsake our ideals again and again. We do not pass from one period of life to another without causing these pains of betrayal, and without suffering from them in turn. Should we have to guard ourselves against the upsurging of our feeling in order to avoid these pains? Would not the world then become too bleak, too ghostly for us? We want rather to ask ourselves whether these pains at a change of conviction are necessary, or whether they do not depend on an erroneous opinion and estimation. Why do we admire the man who remains faithful to his conviction and despise the one who changes it? I fear the answer must be that everyone assumes such a change is caused only by motives of baser advantage or personal fear. That is, we believe fundamentally that no one changes his opinions as long as they are advantageous to him, or at least as long as they do him no harm. But if that is the case, it bears bad testimony to the intellectual meaning of all convictions. Let us test how convictions come into being and observe whether they are not vastly overrated: in that way it will be revealed that the change of convictions too is in any case measured by false standards and that until now we have tended to suffer too much from such changes.

148

Conviction is the belief that in some point of knowledge one possesses absolute truth. Such a belief presumes, then, that absolute truths exist; likewise, that the perfect methods for arriving at them have been found; finally, that every man who has convictions makes use of these perfect methods. All three assertions prove at once that the man of convictions is not the man of scientific thinking; he stands before us still in the age of theoretical innocence, a child, however grown-up he might be otherwise. But throughout thousands of years, people have lived in such childlike assumptions, and from out of them mankind's mightiest sources of power have flowed. The countless people who sacrificed themselves for their convictions thought they were doing it for absolute truth. All of them were wrong: probably no man has ever sacrificed himself for truth; at least, the dogmatic expression of his belief will have been unscientific or half-scientific. But actually one wanted to be right because one thought he had to be right. To let his belief be torn from him meant perhaps to put his eternal happiness in question. With a matter of this extreme importance, the 'will' was all too audibly the intellect's prompter. Every believer of every persuasion assumed he could not be refuted; if the counterarguments proved very strong, he could still always malign reason in general and perhaps even raise as a banner of extreme fanaticism the 'credo quia absurdum est.' It is not the struggle of opinions that has made history so violent, but rather the struggle of belief in opinions, that is, the struggle of convictions. If only all those people who thought so highly of their conviction, who sacrificed all sorts of things to it and spared neither their honor, body nor life in its service, had devoted only half of their strength to investigating by what right they clung to this or that conviction, how they had arrived at it, then how peaceable the history of mankind would appear! How much more would be known! All the cruel scenes during the persecution of every kind of heretic would have been spared us for two reasons: first, because the inquisitors would above all have inquired within themselves, and got beyond the arrogant idea that they were defending the absolute truth; and second, because the heretics themselves would not have granted such poorly established tenets as those of all the sectarians and 'orthodox' any further attention, once they had investigated them.

149

Stemming from the time when people were accustomed to believe that they possessed absolute truth is a deep discomfort with all skeptical and relativistic positions on any questions of knowledge; usually we prefer to surrender unconditionally to a conviction held by people of authority (fathers, friends, teachers, princes), and we have a kind of troubled conscience if we do not do so. This inclination is understandable and its consequences do not entitle us to violent reproaches against the development of human reason. But eventually the scientific spirit in man must bring forth that virtue of cautious restraint, that wise moderation that is better known in the realm of practical life than in the realm of theoretical life, and that Goethe, for example, portrayed in his Antonio, as an object of animosity for all Tassos, that is, for those unscientific and also passive natures. The man of conviction has in himself a right not to understand the man of cautious thinking, the theoretical Antonio; the scientific man, on the other hand, has no right to scold him for this; he makes allowances for him and knows besides that, in certain cases, the man will cling to him as Tasso finally does to Antonio.

150

If one has not passed through various convictions, but remains caught in the net of his first belief, he is in all events, because of just this unchangeability, a representative of backward cultures; in accordance with this lack of education (which always presupposes educability), he is harsh, injudicious, unteachable, without gentleness, eternally suspect, a person lacking scruples, who reaches for any means to enforce his opinion because he simply cannot understand that there have to be other opinions. In this regard, he is perhaps a source of power, and even salutary in cultures grown too free and lax, but only because he powerfully incites opposition: for in that way the new culture's more delicate structure, which is forced to struggle with him, becomes strong itself.

151

Essentially, we are still the same people as those in the period of the Reformation - and how should it be otherwise? But we no longer allow ourselves certain means to gain victory for our opinion: this distinguishes us from that age and proves that we belong to a higher culture. These days, if a man still attacks and crushes opinions with suspicions and outbursts of rage, in the manner of men during the Reformation, he clearly betrays that he would have burnt his opponents, had he lived in other times, and that he would have taken recourse to all the means of the Inquisition, had he lived as an opponent of the Reformation. In its time, the Inquisition was reasonable, for it meant nothing other than the general martial law which had to be proclaimed over the whole domain of the church, and which, like every state of martial law, justified the use of the extremest means, namely under the assumption (which we no longer share with those people) that one possessed truth in the church and had to preserve it at any cost, with any sacrifice, for the salvation of mankind. But now we will no longer concede so easily that anyone has the truth; the rigorous methods of inquiry have spread sufficient distrust and caution, so that we experience every man who represents opinions violently in word and deed as any enemy of our present culture, or at least as a backward person. And in fact, the fervor about having the truth counts very little today in relation to that other fervor, more gentle and silent, to be sure, for seeking the truth, a search that does not tire of learning afresh and testing anew.

152

Incidentally, the methodical search for truth itself results from those times when convictions were feuding among themselves. If the individual had not cared about his 'truth,' that is, about his being right in the end, no method of inquiry would exist at all; but, given the eternal struggle of various individuals' claims to absolute truth, man proceeded step by step, in order to find irrefutable principles by which the justice of the claims could be tested and the argument settled. At first decisions were made according to authorities, later the ways and means with which the ostensible truth had been found were mutually criticized; in between, there was a period when the consequences of the opposing tenet were drawn and perhaps experienced as harmful and saddening; this was to result in everyone's judging that the opponent's conviction contained an error. Finally, the thinkers' personal struggle sharpened their methods so much that truths could really be discovered, and the aberrations of earlier methods were exposed to everyone's eye.

153

All in all, scientific methods are at least as important as any other result of inquiry; for the scientific spirit is based on the insight into methods, and were those methods to be lost, all the results of science could not prevent a renewed triumph of superstition and nonsense. Clever people may learn the results of science as much as they like, one still sees from their conversation, especially from their hypotheses in conversation, that they lack the scientific spirit. They do not have that instinctive mistrust of the wrong ways of thinking, a mistrust which, as a consequence of long practice, has put its roots deep into the soul of every scientific man. For them it is enough to find any one hypothesis about a matter; then they get fired up about it and think that puts an end to it. For them, to have an opinion means to get fanatical about it and cherish it in their hearts henceforth as a conviction. If a matter is unexplained, they become excited at the first notion resembling an explanation that enters their brain; this always has the worst consequences, especially in the realm of politics.

Therefore everyone should have come to know at least one science in its essentials; then he knows what method is, and how necessary is the most extreme circumspection. This advice should be given to women particularly, who are now the hopeless victims of all hypotheses, especially those which give the impression of being witty, thrilling, invigorating, or energizing. In fact, if one looks closer, one notices that the majority of all educated people still desire convictions and nothing but convictions from a thinker, and that only a slight minority want certainty. The former want to be forcibly carried away, in order to thus increase their own strength; the latter few have that matter-of-fact interest that ignores personal advantage, even the above-mentioned increase of strength. Wherever the thinker behaves like a genius, calling himself one, and looking down like a higher being who deserves authority, he is counting on the class in the overwhelming majority. To the extent that that kind of genius keeps up the heat of convictions and awakens distrust of the cautious and modest spirit of science, he is an enemy of truth, however much he may believe he is its suitor.

154

To be sure, there is also quite another category of genius, that of justice; and I can in no way see fit to esteem that kind lower than any philosophical, political, or artistic genius. It is its way to avoid with hearty indignation everything which blinds and confuses our judgment about things; thus it is an enemy of convictions, for it wants to give each thing its due, be it living or dead, real or fictive - and to do so it must apprehend it clearly. Therefore it places each thing in the best light and walks all around it with an attentive eye. Finally it will even give its due to its opponent, to blind or shortsighted 'conviction' (as men call it; women call it 'faith') - for the sake of truth.

155

Out of passions grow opinions; mental sloth lets these rigidify into convictions.

However, if one feels he is of a free, restlessly lively mind, he can prevent this rigidity through constant change; and if he is on the whole a veritable thinking snowball, then he will have no opinions at all in his head, but rather only certainties and precisely measured probabilities.

But we who are of a mixed nature, sometimes aglow with fire and sometimes chilled by intellect, we want to kneel down before justice, as the only goddess whom we recognize above us. Usually the fire in us makes us unjust, and in the sense of that goddess, impure; never may we touch her hand in this condition; never will the grave smile of her pleasure lie upon us. We honor her as our life's veiled Isis; ashamed, we offer her our pain as a penance and a sacrifice, when the fire burns us and tries to consume us. It is the intellect that saves us from turning utterly to burnt-out coals; here and there it pulls us away from justice's sacrificial altar, or wraps us in an asbestos cocoon. Redeemed from the fire, we then stride on, driven by the intellect, from opinion to opinion, through the change of sides, as noble traitors to all things that can ever be betrayed - and yet with no feeling of guilt.

156

The wanderer. He who has come only in part to a freedom of reason cannot feel on earth otherwise than as a wanderer - though not as a traveler towards a final goal, for this does not exist. But he does want to observe, and keep his eyes open for everything that actually occurs in the world; therefore he must not attach his heart too firmly to any individual thing; there must be something wandering within him, which takes its joy in change and transitoriness. To be sure, such a man will have bad nights, when he is tired and finds closed the gates to the city that should offer him rest; perhaps in addition, as in the Orient, the desert reaches up to the gate; predatory animals howl now near, now far; a strong wind stirs; robbers lead off his pack-animals. Then for him the frightful night sinks over the desert like a second desert, and his heart becomes tired of wandering. If the morning sun then rises, glowing like a divinity of wrath, and the city opens up, he sees in the faces of its inhabitants perhaps more of desert, dirt, deception, uncertainty, than outside the gates - and the day is almost worse than the night. So it may happen sometimes to the wanderer; but then, as recompense, come the ecstatic mornings of other regions and days. Then nearby in the dawning light he already sees the bands of muses dancing past him in the mist of the mountains. Afterwards, he strolls quietly in the equilibrium of his forenoon soul, under trees from whose tops and leafy corners only good and bright things are thrown down to him, the gifts of all those free spirits who are at home in mountain, wood, and solitude, and who are, like him, in their sometimes merry, sometimes contemplative way, wanderers and philosophers. Born out of the mysteries of the dawn, they ponder how the day can have such a pure, transparent, transfigured and cheerful face between the hours of ten and twelve - they seek the philosophy of the forenoon.

2　Among Friends: An Epilogue

1

Fine, with one another silent,

Finer, with one another laughing -

Under heaven's silky cloth

Leaning over books and moss

With friends lightly, loudly laughing

Each one showing white teeth shining.

If I did well, let us be silent,

If I did badly, let us laugh

And do it bad again by half,

More badly done, more badly laugh,

Until the grave, when down we climb.

Friends! Well! What do you say?

Amen! Until we meet again!

2

Don't excuse it! Don't forgive!

You happy, heart-free people, give

This unreasonable book of mine

Ear and heart and sheltering!

Truly, friends, my own unreason

Did not grow to earn a curse!

What I find, what I am seeking -

Was that ever in a book?

Honor one from the fools' legion!

Learn from out of this fool's book

How reason can be brought - 'to reason'!

So then, friends, what do you say?

Amen! Until we meet again.

3　The Free Spirit

1

Osancta simplicitas! What strange simplification and falsification mankind lives in! One can never cease to marvel once one has acquired eyes for this marvel! How we have made everything around us bright and free and easy and simple! How we have known how to bestow on our senses a passport to everything superficial, on our thoughts a divine desire for wanton gambolling and false conclusions! - how we have from the very beginning understood how to retain our ignorance so as to enjoy an almost inconceivable freedom, frivolity, impetuosity, bravery, cheerfulness of life, so as to enjoy life! And only on this now firm and granite basis of ignorance has knowledge hitherto been able to rise up, the will to knowledge on the basis of a far more powerful will, the will to non-knowledge, to the uncertain, to the untrue! Not as its antithesis but - as its refinement! For even if, here as elsewhere, language cannot get over its coarseness and continues to speak of antitheses where there are only degrees and many subtleties of gradation; even if likewise the incarnate tartuffery of morals which is now part of our invincible 'flesh and blood' twists the words in the mouths even of us men of knowledge: here and there we grasp that fact and laugh at how it is precisely the best knowledge that wants most to hold us in this simplified, altogether artificial, fabricated, falsified world, how it is willy-nilly in love with error because, as a living being, it is - in love with life!

2

After so cheerful an exordium a serious word would like to be heard: it addresses itself to the most serious. Take care, philosophers and friends of knowledge, and beware of martyrdom! Of suffering 'for the sake of truth'! Even of defending yourselves! It spoils all the innocence and fine neutrality of your conscience, it makes you obstinate against rebuffs and red rags, it makes you stupid, brutal and bullish if in the struggle with danger, slander, suspicion, casting out and even grosser consequences of hostility you finally even have to act as defenders of truth on earth - as if 'truth' were so innocuous and inept a person she stood in need of defending! And precisely by you, you knights of most sorrowful countenance, you idlers and cobweb-spinners of the spirit! After all, you know well enough that it cannot matter in the least whether precisely you are in the right, just as no philosopher hitherto has been in the right, and that a more praiseworthy veracity may lie in every little question-mark placed after your favourite words and favourite theories (and occasionally after yourselves) than in all your solemn gesticulations and smart answers before courts and accusers! Better to step aside! Flee away and conceal yourselves! And have your masks and subtlety, so that you may be misunderstood! Or feared a little! And do not forget the garden, the garden with golden trellis-work. And have about you people who are like a garden - or like music on the waters in the evening, when the day is already becoming a memory; - choose the good solitude, the free, wanton, easy solitude which gives you too a right to remain in some sense good! How poisonous, how cunning, how bad every protracted war makes one when it cannot be waged with open force! How personal a protracted fear makes one, a protracted keeping watch for enemies, for possible enemies! These outcasts of society, long persecuted and sorely hunted - also the enforced recluses, the Spinozas and Giordano Brunos - in the end always become refined vengeance-seekers and brewers of poison, even if they do so under the most spiritual masquerade and perhaps without being themselves aware of it (just dig up the foundation of Spinoza's ethics and theology!) - not to speak of the stupidity of moral indignation, which is in the philosopher an unfailing sign that he has lost his philosophical sense of humour. The martyrdom of the philosopher, his 'sacrifice for truth', brings to light what there has been in him of agitator and actor; and if one has hitherto regarded him only with artistic curiosity, in the case of many a philosopher it is easy to understand the dangerous desire to see him for once in his degeneration(degenerated into 'martyr', into stageand platform ranter). But if one does harbour such a desire, one has to be clear what it is one will get to see-merely a satyr play, merely a farcical after-piece, merely a continuing proof that the long tragedy has come to an end: supposing that every philosophy was in its inception a long tragedy. -

3

Every superior human being will instinctively aspire after a secret citadel where he is set free from the crowd, the many, the majority, where, as its exception, he may forget the rule 'man' - except in the one case in which, as a man of knowledge in the great and exceptional sense, he will be impelled by an even stronger instinct to make straight for this rule. He who, when trafficking with men, does not occasionally glisten with all the shades of distress, green and grey with disgust, satiety, sympathy, gloom and loneliness, is certainly not a man of an elevated taste; but if he does not voluntarily assume this burden and displeasure, if he continually avoids it and, as aforesaid, remains hidden quietly and proudly away in his citadel, then one thing is sure: he is not made, not predestined for knowledge. For if he were, he would one day have to say to himself: 'The devil can take my good taste! the rule is more interesting than the exception - than I, the exception!' - and would go down, would above all 'go in'. The study of the average human being, protracted, serious, and with much dissembling, self-overcoming, intimacy, bad company - all company is bad company except the company of one's equals -: this constitutes a necessary part of the life story of every philosopher, perhaps the most unpleasant and malodorous part and the part most full of disappointments. If he is lucky, however, as a favourite child of knowledge ought to be, he will encounter means of facilitating and cutting short his task - I mean so-called cynics, that is to say people who recognize the animal, the commonness, the 'rule' in themselves and yet still possess a degree of spirituality and appetite which constrains them to speak of themselves and their kind before witnesses - sometimes they even wallow in books as in their own dung. Cynicism is the only form in which common souls come close to honesty; and the higher man must prick up his ears at every cynicism, whether coarse or refined, and congratulate himself whenever a buffoon without shame or a scientific satyr speaks out in his presence. There are even cases in which fascination mingles with the disgust: namely where, by a caprice of nature, such an indiscreet goat and monkey is touched with genius, as in the case of the Abbé Galiani, the profoundest, most sharp-sighted and perhaps also dirtiest man of his century - he was far more profound than Voltaire and consequently also a good deal more silent. It is more often the case that, as already indicated, a scientific head is set on a monkey's body, a refined exceptional understanding on a common soul - no rare occurrence, for instance, among physicians and moral physiologists. And whenever anyone speaks, without bitterness, rather innocuously, of man as a belly with two needs and a head with one; wherever anyone sees, seeks and wants to see only hunger, sexual desire, and vanity, as though these were the actual and sole motives of human actions; in brief, whenever anyone speaks 'badly' of man - but does not speak ill of him - the lover of knowledge should listen carefully and with diligence, and he should in general lend an ear whenever anyone speaks without indignation. For the indignant man, and whoever is continually tearing and rending himself with his teeth (or, instead of himself, the world, or God, or society) may indeed morally speaking stand higher than the laughing and self-satisfied satyr, but in every other sense he is the more commonplace, less interesting, less instructive case. And no one lies so much as the indignant man.

4

It is hard to be understood: especially when one thinks and lives gangasrotogati among men who think and live otherwise, namely kurmagati or at best 'as the frog goes', mandeikagati - I am certainly doing everything I can to be hard to understand myself! - and one ought to be heartily grateful even for the will to some subtlety in interpretation. As regards one's 'good friends', however, who are always too indolent and think that because they are one's friends they have a right to indolence: one does well to allow them from the first some room and latitude for misunderstanding - thus one can laugh at their expense; - or get rid of them altogether, these good friends and still laugh!

5

That which translates worst from one language into another is the tempo of its style, which has its origin in the character of the race, or, expressed more physiologically, in the average tempo of its 'metabolism'. There are honestly meant translations which, as involuntary vulgarizations of the original, are almost falsifications simply because it was not possible to translate also its brave and happy tempo, which leaps over and puts behind it all that is perilous in things and words. The German is virtually incapable of presto in his language: thus, it may be fairly concluded, also of many of the most daring and delightful nuances of free, free-spirited thought. Just as the buffo and the satyr is strange to him, in his body and in his conscience, so Aristophanes and Petronius are untranslatable for him. Everything staid, sluggish, ponderously solemn, all long-winded and boring species of style have been developed in profuse multiplicity among the Germans - pardon me for the fact that even Goethe's prose is, in its blend of elegance and stiffness, no exception: it is a reflection of the 'good old days', to which it belongs, and an expression of the German taste of a time when there still was a 'German taste': it was rococo in moribus et artibus. Lessing constitutes an exception, thanks to his histrionic nature, which was versed in and understood much: he, who was not for nothing the translator of Bayle and liked to flee to the neighbourhood of Diderot and Voltaire and even more to that of the Roman writers of comedy - in tempo too Lessing loved freespiritedness, escape from Germany. But how could the German language, even in the prose of a Lessing, imitate the tempo of Machiavelli, who in his Principe lets us breathe the subtle dry air of Florence and cannot help presenting the most serious affairs in a boisterous allegrissimo: not perhaps without a malicious artist's sense of the contrast he is risking - thoughts protracted, difficult, hard, dangerous and the tempo of the gallop and the most wanton good humour. Who, finally, would venture a German translation of Petronius, who was, to a greater degree than any great musician has hitherto been, a master of presto in invention, ideas, words - what do all the swamps of the sick wicked world, even of the 'antique world', matter when one has, like him, the feet of a wind, the blast and breath, the liberating scorn of a wind that makes everything healthy by making everything run! And as for Aristophanes, that transfiguring, complementary spirit for whose sake one excuses all Greece for having existed, assuming one has grasped in all its profundity what there is to be excused and transfigured here - I know of nothing that has led me to reflect more on Plato's concealment and sphinx nature than that happily preserved petit fait that under the pillow of his death-bed there was discovered no 'Bible', nothing Egyptian, Pythagorean, Platonic-but Aristophanes. How could even a Plato have endured life - a Greek life which he had denied - without an Aristophanes!

6

Few are made for independence - it is a privilege of the strong. And he who attempts it, having the completest right to it but without being compelled to, thereby proves that he is probably not only strong but also daring to the point of recklessness. He ventures into a labyrinth, he multiplies by a thousand the dangers which life as such already brings with it, not the smallest of which is that no one can behold how and where he goes astray, is cut off from others, and is torn to pieces limb from limb by some cave-minotaur of conscience. If such a one is destroyed, it takes place so far from the understanding of men that they neither feel it nor sympathize - and he can no longer go back! He can no longer go back even to the pity of men!

7

Our supreme insights must - and should! - sound like follies, in certain cases like crimes, when they come impermissibly to the ears of those who are not predisposed and predestined for them. The exoteric and the esoteric as philosophers formerly distinguished them, among the Indians as among the Greeks, Persians and Moslems, in short wherever one believed in an order of rank and not in equality and equal rights - differ one from another not so much in that the exoteric stands outside and sees, evaluates, measures, judges from the outside, not from the inside: what is more essential is that this class sees things from below - but the esoteric sees them from above! There are heights of the soul seen from which even tragedy ceases to be tragic; and, taking all the woe of the world together, who could venture to assert that the sight of it would have to seduce and compel us to pity and thus to a doubling of that woe? ... What serves the higher type of man as food or refreshment must to a very different and inferior type be almost poison. The virtues of the common man would perhaps indicate vice and weakness in a philosopher; it may be possible that if a lofty type of man degenerated and perished, he would only thus acquire qualities on whose account it would prove necessary in the lower world into which he had sunk henceforth to venerate him as a saint. There are books which possess an opposite value for soul and health depending on whether the lower soul, the lower vitality, or the higher and more powerful avails itself of them: in the former case they are dangerous, disintegrative books, which produces dissolution, in the latter they are herald calls challenging the most courageous to their courage. Books for everybody are always malodorous books: the smell of petty people clings to them. Where the people eats and drinks, even where it worships, there is usually a stink. One should not go into churches if one wants to breathe pure air.

8

In our youthful years we respect and despise without that art of nuance which constitutes the best thing we gain from life, and, as is only fair, we have to pay dearly for having assailed men and things with Yes and No in such a fashion. Everything is so regulated that the worst of all tastes, the taste for the unconditional, is cruelly misused and made a fool of until a man learns to introduce a little art into his feelings and even to venture trying the artificial: as genuine artists of life do. The anger and reverence characteristic of youth seem to allow themselves no peace until they have falsified men and things in such a way that they can vent themselves on them - youth as such is something that falsifies and deceives. Later, when the youthful soul, tormented by disappointments, finally turns suspiciously on itself, still hot and savage even in its suspicion and pangs of conscience: how angry it is with itself now, how it impatiently rends itself, how it takes revenge for its long self-delusion, as if it had blinded itself deliberately! During this transition one punishes oneself by distrusting one's feelings; one tortures one's enthusiasm with doubts, indeed one feels that even a good conscience is a danger, as though a good conscience were a screening of oneself and a sign that one's subtler honesty had grown weary; and above all one takes sides, takes sides on principle, against 'youth'. - A decade later: and one grasps that all this too - was still youth!

9

Throughout the longest part of human history - it is called prehistoric times - the value or non-value of an action was derived from its consequences: the action itself came as little into consideration as did its origin, but, in much the same way as today in China a distinction or disgrace reflects back from the child onto its parents, so it was the retroactive force of success or failure which led men to think well or ill of an action. Let us call this period the pre-moral period of mankind: the imperative 'know thyself!' was then still unknown. Over the past ten thousand years, on the other hand, one has in a few large tracts of the earth come step by step to the point at which it is no longer the consequences but the origin of the action which determines its value: a great event, taken as a whole, a considerable refinement of vision and standard, the unconscious after-effect of the sovereignty of aristocratic values and of belief in 'origins', the sign of a period which may be called the moral in the narrower sense: the first attempt at self-knowledge has been made. Instead of the consequences, the origin: what an inversion of perspectives! And certainly one achieved only after protracted struggles and vacillations! To be sure, a fateful new superstition, a peculiar narrowness of interpretation therewith became dominant: men interpreted the origin of an action in the most definite sense as origin in an intention; men became unanimous in the belief that the value of an action resided in the value of the intention behind it. The intention as the whole origin and prehistory of an action: it is under the sway of this prejudice that one has morally praised, blamed, judged and philosophized on earth almost to the present day. - But ought we not today to have arrived at the necessity of once again determining upon an inversion and shift of values, thanks to another self-examination and deepening on the part of man - ought we not to stand on the threshold of a period which should be called, negatively at first, the extra-moral: today, when among us immoralists at least the suspicion has arisen that the decisive value of an action resides in precisely that which is not intentional in it, and that all that in it which is intentional, all of it that can be seen, known, 'conscious', still belongs to its surface and skin - which, like every skin, betrays something but conceals still more? In brief, we believe that the intention is only a sign and symptom that needs interpreting, and a sign, moreover, that signifies too many things and which thus taken by itself signifies practically nothing - that morality in the sense in which it has been understood hitherto, that is to say the morality of intentions, has been a prejudice, a precipitancy, perhaps something provisional and precursory, perhaps something of the order of astronomy and alchemy, but in any event something that must be overcome. The overcoming of morality, in a certain sense even the self-overcoming of morality: let this be the name for that protracted secret labour which has been reserved for the subtlest, most honest and also most malicious consciences as living touchstones of the soul.

10

There is nothing for it: the feelings of devotion, self-sacrifice for one's neighbour, the entire morality of self-renunciation must be taken mercilessly to task and brought to court: likewise the aesthetics of 'disinterested contemplation' through which the emasculation of art today tries, seductively enough, to give itself a good conscience. There is much too much sugar and sorcery in those feelings of 'for others', of 'not for me', for one not to have to become doubly distrustful here and to ask: 'are they not perhaps - seductions?' That they give pleasure - to him who has them and to him who enjoys their fruits, also to the mere spectator - does not yet furnish an argument in their favour, but urges us rather to caution. So let us be cautious!

11

Whatever standpoint of philosophy we may adopt today: from every point of view the erroneousness of the world in which we believe we live is the surest and firmest thing we can get our eyes on - we find endless grounds for it which would like to lure us to suppose a deceptive principle in the 'nature of things'. But he who makes our thinking itself, that is to say 'the mind', responsible for the falsity of the world - an honourable way out taken by every conscious or unconscious advocatus dei - : he who takes this world, together with space, time, form, motion, to be the result of a false conclusion: such a one would have good cause, to say the least, to learn finally to mistrust thinking itself: would it not have played on us the biggest hoax ever? and what guarantee would there be that it would not go on doing what it has always done? In all seriousness: the innocence of thinkers has something touching and inspiring of reverence in it which permits them even today to go up to consciousness and ask it to give them honest answers: whether it is 'real', for example, and why it really keeps the external world so resolutely at a distance, and other questions of the sort. The belief in 'immediate certainties' is a piece of moral naivety which does honour to us philosophers: but - we ought not to be 'merely moral' men! Apart from the moral aspect, that belief is a piece of stupidity which does us little honour! In civil life an ever-ready mistrustfulness may count as a sign of 'bad character' and thus be an imprudent thing to have: here among us, beyond the civil world and its Yes and No - what is there to stop us from being imprudent and saying: the philosopher, as the creature which has hitherto always been most fooled on earth, has by now a right to 'bad character' - he has today the duty to be distrustful, to squint wickedly up out of every abyss of suspicion. - You must forgive me this humorous expression and grimace: for I have long since learned to think differently, to judge differently on the subject of deceiving and being deceived, and I keep in readiness at least a couple of jabs in the ribs for the blind rage with which philosophers resist being deceived. Why not? It is no more than a moral prejudice that truth is worth more than appearance; it is even the worst-proved assumption that exists. Let us concede at least this much: there would be no life at all if not on the basis of perspective evaluations and appearances; and if, with the virtuous enthusiasm and awkwardness exhibited by some philosophers, one wanted to abolish the 'apparent world' altogether, well, assuming you could do that - at any rate nothing would remain of your 'truth' either! Indeed, what compels us to assume there exists any essential antithesis between 'true' and 'false'? Is it not enough to suppose grades of apparentness and as it were lighter and darker shades and tones of appearance - different valeurs, to speak in the language of painters? Why could the world which is of any concern to us - not be a fiction? And he who then objects: 'but to the fiction there belongs an author?' - could he not be met with the round retort: why? Does this 'belongs' perhaps not also belong to the fiction? Are we not permitted to be a little ironical now about the subject as we are about the predicate and object? Ought the philosopher not to rise above the belief in grammar? All due respect to governesses: but is it not time that philosophy renounced the beliefs of governesses?

12

Oh Voltaire! Oh humanity! Oh imbecility! There is some point to 'truth', to the search for truth; and if a human being goes about it too humanely - 'il ne cherche le vrai que pour faire le bien' - I wager he finds nothing!

13

Granted that nothing is 'given' as real except our world of desires and passions, that we can rise or sink to no other 'reality' than the reality of our drives - for thinking is only the relationship of these drives to one another - : is it not permitted to make the experiment and ask the question whether this which is given does not suffice for an understanding even of the so-called mechanical (or 'material') world? I do not mean as a deception, an 'appearance', an 'idea' (in the Berkeleyan and Schopenhaueran sense), but as possessing the same degree of reality as our emotions themselves - as a more primitive form of the world of emotions in which everything still lies locked in mighty unity and then branches out and develops in the organic process (also, as is only fair, is made weaker and more sensitive), as a kind of instinctual life in which all organic functions, together with self-regulation, assimilation, nourishment, excretion, metabolism, are still synthetically bound together - as an antecedent form of life? - In the end, it is not merely permitted to make this experiment: it is commanded by the conscience of method. Not to assume several kinds of causality so long as the experiment of getting along with one has not been taken to its ultimate limits (- to the point of nonsense, if I may say so): that is a morality of method which one may not repudiate nowadays - it follows 'from its definition', as a mathematician would say. In the end, the question is whether we really recognize will as efficient, whether we believe in the causality of will: if we do so - and fundamentally belief in this is precisely our belief in causality itself - then we have to make the experiment of positing causality of will hypothetically as the only one. 'Will' can of course operate only on 'will' - and not on 'matter' (not on 'nerves', for example -): enough, one must venture the hypothesis that wherever 'effects' are recognized, will is operating upon will - and that all mechanical occurrences, in so far as a force is active in them, are force of will, effects of will. - Granted finally that one succeeded in explaining our entire instinctual life as the development and ramification of one basic form of will - as will to power, as is my theory -; granted that one could trace all organic functions back to this will to power and could also find in it the solution to the problem of procreation and nourishment - they are one problem - one would have acquired the right to define all efficient force unequivocally as: will to power. The world seen from within, the world described and defined according to its 'intelligible character' - it would be 'will to power' and nothing else.

14

'What? Does that, to speak vulgarly, not mean: God is refuted but the devil is not -?' On the contrary! On the contrary, my friends! And who the devil compels you to speak vulgarly! -

15

As happened lately, in all the clarity of modern times, with the French Revolution, that gruesome and, closely considered, superfluous farce, into which, however, noble and enthusiastic spectators all over Europe interpeted from a distance their own indignations and raptures so long and so passionately that the text disappeared beneath the interpretation: so a noble posterity could once again misunderstand the entire past and only thus perhaps make the sight of it endurable. - Or rather: has this not already happened? have we ourselves not been this 'noble posterity'? And, in so far as we comprehend this, is it not at this moment - done with?

16

No one is likely to consider a doctrine true merely because it makes happy or makes virtuous: excepting perhaps the dear 'idealists', who rapturize over the good, the true and the beautiful and let all kinds of colourful, clumsy and good-natured desiderata swim about together in their pond. Happiness and virtue are no arguments. But even thoughtful spirits like to forget that making unhappy and making evil are just as little counter-arguments. Something might be true although at the same time harmful and dangerous in the highest degree; indeed, it could pertain to the fundamental nature of existence that a complete knowledge of it would destroy one - so that the strength of a spirit could be measured by how much 'truth' it could take, more clearly, to what degree it needed it attenuated, veiled, sweetened, blunted, and falsified. But there can be no doubt that for the discovery of certain parts of truth the wicked and unhappy are in a more favourable position and are more likely to succeed; not to speak of the wicked who are happy - a species about whom the moralists are silent. Perhaps severity and cunning provide more favourable conditions for the formation of the strong, independent spirit and philosopher than does that gentle, sweet, yielding good-naturedness and art of taking things lightly which is prized in a scholar and rightly prized. Supposing in advance that the concept 'philosopher' is not limited to the philosopher who writes books - or, worse, writes books of his philosophy! - A final trait in the image of the free-spirited philosopher is provided by Stendhal, and in view of what German taste is I do not want to fail to emphasize it - for it goes against German taste. 'Pour être bon philosophe', said this last great psychologist, 'il faut être sec, clair, sans illusion. Un banquier, qui a fait fortune, a une partie du caractère requis pour faire des découvertes en philosophic, c'est-à-dire pour voir clair dans ce qui est.'

17

Everything profound loves the mask; the profoundest things of all hate even image and parable. Should not nothing less than the opposite be the proper disguise under which the shame of a god goes abroad? A questionable question: it would be strange if some mystic or other had not already ventured to meditate some such thing. There are occurrences of so delicate a description that one does well to bury them and make them unrecognizable with a piece of coarseness; there are acts of love and extravagant magnanimity after which nothing is more advisable than to take a stick and give the eyewitness a thrashing and so confuse his memory. Some know how to confuse and mistreat their own memory, so as to take revenge at least on this sole confidant - shame is inventive. It is not the worst things of which one is most ashamed: there is not only deceit behind a mask - there is so much goodness in cunning. I could believe that a man who had something fragile and valuable to conceal might roll through life thick and round as an old, green, thick-hooped wine barrel: the refinement of his shame would have it so. A man whose shame has depth encounters his destinies and delicate decisions too on paths which very few ever reach and of whose existence his intimates and neighbours may not know: his mortal danger is concealed from their eyes, as is the fact that he has regained his sureness of life. Such a hidden man, who instinctively uses speech for silence and concealment and is inexhaustible in evading communication, wants a mask of him to roam the heads and hearts of his friends in his stead, and he makes sure that it does so; and supposing he does not want it, he will one day come to see that a mask is there in spite of that - and that that is a good thing. Every profound spirit needs a mask: more, around every profound spirit a mask is continually growing, thanks to the constantly false, that is to say shallow interpretation of every word he speaks, every step he takes, every sign of life he gives.

18

One must test oneself to see whether one is destined for independence and command; and one must do so at the proper time. One should not avoid one's tests, although they are perhaps the most dangerous game one could play and are in the end tests which are taken before ourselves and before no other judge. Not to cleave to another person, though he be the one you love most - every person is a prison, also a nook and corner. Not to cleave to a fatherland, though it be the most suffering and in need of help - it is already easier to sever your heart from a victorious fatherland. Not to cleave to a feeling of pity, though it be for higher men into whose rare torment and helplessness chance allowed us to look. Not to cleave to a science, though it lures one with the most precious discoveries seemingly reserved precisely for us. Not to cleave to one's own detachment, to that voluptuous remoteness and strangeness of the bird which flies higher and higher so as to see more and more beneath it - the danger which threatens the flier. Not to cleave to our own virtues and become as a whole the victim of some part of us, of our 'hospitality' for example, which is the danger of dangers for rich and noble souls who expend themselves prodigally, almost indifferently, and take the virtue of liberality to the point where it becomes a vice. One must know how to conserve oneself: the sternest test of independence.

19

A new species of philosopher is appearing: I venture to baptize these philosophers with a name not without danger in it. As I divine them, as they let themselves be divined - for it pertains to their nature to want to remain a riddle in some respects - these philosophers of the future might rightly, but perhaps also wrongly, be described as attempters. This name itself is in the end only an attempt and, if you will, a temptation.

20

Are they new friends of 'truth', these coming philosophers? In all probability: for all philosophers have hitherto loved their truths. But certainly they will not be dogmatists. It must offend their pride, and also their taste, if their truth is supposed to be a truth for everyman, which has hitherto been the secret desire and hidden sense of all dogmatic endeavours. 'My judgement is my judgement: another cannot easily acquire a right to it' - such a philosopher of the future may perhaps say. One has to get rid of the bad taste of wanting to be in agreement with many. 'Good' is no longer good when your neighbour takes it into his mouth. And how could there exist a 'common good'! The expression is a self-contradiction: what can be common has ever but little value. In the end it must be as it is and has always been: great things are for the great, abysses for the profound, shudders and delicacies for the refined, and, in sum, all rare things for the rare.

21

After all this do I still need to say that they too will be free, very free spirits, these philosophers of the future - just as surely as they will not be merely free spirits, but something more, higher, greater and thoroughly different that does not want to be misunderstood or taken for what it is not. But in saying this I feel I have a duty, almost as much towards them as towards us, their heralds and precursors, us free spirits! - to blow away from all of us an ancient and stupid prejudice and misunderstanding which has all too long obscured the concept 'free spirit' like a fog. In all the countries of Europe and likewise in America there exists at present something that misuses this name, a very narrow, enclosed, chained-up species of spirits who desire practically the opposite of that which informs our aims and instincts - not to mention the fact that in regard to those new philosophers appearing they must certainly be closed windows and bolted doors. They belong, in short and regrettably, among the levellers, these falsely named 'free spirits' - eloquent and tirelessly scribbling slaves of the democratic taste and its 'modern ideas', men without solitude one and all, without their own solitude, good clumsy fellows who, while they cannot be denied courage and moral respectability, are unfree and ludicrously superficial, above all in their fundamental inclination to see in the forms of existing society the cause of practically all human failure and misery: which is to stand the truth happily on its head! What with all their might they would like to strive after is the universal green pasture happiness of the herd, with security, safety, comfort and an easier life for all; their two most oft-recited doctrines and ditties are 'equality of rights' and 'sympathy for all that suffers' - and suffering itself they take for something that has to be abolished. We, who are the opposite of this, and have opened our eyes and our conscience to the question where and how the plant 'man' has hitherto grown up most vigorously, we think that this has always happened under the opposite conditions, that the perilousness of his situation had first to become tremendous, his powers of invention and dissimulation (his 'spirit' - ) had, under protracted pressure and constraint, to evolve into subtlety and daring, his will to life had to be intensified into unconditional will to power - we think that severity, force, slavery, peril in the street and in the heart, concealment, stoicism, the art of experiment and devilry of every kind, that everything evil, dreadful, tyrannical, beast of prey and serpent in man serves to enhance the species 'man' just as much as does its opposite - we do not say enough when we say even that much, and at any rate we are, in what we say and do not say on this point, at the other end from all modern ideology and herd desiderata: at its antipodes perhaps? Is it any wonder we 'free spirits' are not precisely the most communicative of spirits? that we do not want to betray in every respect from what a spirit can free itself and to what it is then perhaps driven? And as for the dangerous formula 'beyond good and evil' with which we at any rate guard against being taken for what we are not: we are something different from 'libres-penseurs', 'liberi pensatori', 'Freidenker', or whatever else all these worthy advocates of 'modern ideas' like to call themselves. At home in many countries of the spirit, or at least having been guests there; having again and again eluded the agreeable musty nooks and corners into which predilection and prejudice, youth, origin, the accidents of people and books, or even weariness from wandering seemed to have consigned us; full of malice towards the lures of dependence which reside in honours, or money, or offices, or raptures of the senses; grateful even to distress and changeful illness because it has always liberated us from some rule and its 'prejudice', grateful to the god, devil, sheep and worm in us, curious to the point of vice, investigators to the point of cruelty, with rash fingers for the ungraspable, with teeth and stomach for the most indigestible, ready for every task that demands acuteness and sharp senses, ready for every venture thanks to a superfluity of 'free will', with fore- and back-souls into whose ultimate intentions no one can easily see, with fore- and backgrounds to whose end no foot may go, hidden under mantles of light, conquerors even though we look like heirs and prodigals, collectors and arrangers from morn till night, misers of our riches and our full-crammed cupboards, thrifty in learning and forgetting, inventive in schemata, sometimes proud of tables of categories, sometimes pedants, sometimes night owls of labour even in broad daylight; yes, even scarecrows when we need to be - and today we need to be: in so far, that is, as we are born, sworn, jealous friends of solitude, of our own deepest, most midnight, most midday solitude - such a type of man are we, we free spirits! and perhaps you too are something of the same type, you coming men? you new philosophers?

4　From High Mountains: Epode

Oh life's midday! Oh festival! Oh garden of summer! I wait in restless ecstasy, I stand and watch and wait - where are you, friends? It is you I await, in readiness day and night. Come now! It is time you were here!

Was it not for you the glacier today exchanged its grey for roses? The brook seeks you; and wind and clouds press higher in the blue, longingly they crowd aloft to look for you.

For you have I prepared my table in the highest height - who lives so near the stars as I, or who so near the depths of the abyss? My empire - has an empire ever reached so far? And my honey - who has tasted the sweetness of it?

- And there you are, friends! - But, alas, am I not he you came to visit? You hesitate, you stare - no, be angry, rather! Is it no longer - I? Are hand, step, face transformed? And what I am, to you friends - I am not?

Am I another? A stranger to myself? Sprung from myself? A wrestler who subdued himself too often? Turned his own strength against himself too often, checked and wounded by his own victory?

Did I seek where the wind bites keenest, learn to live where no one lives, in the desert where only the polar bear lives, unlearn to pray and curse, unlearn man and god, become a ghost flitting across the glaciers?

- Old friends! how pale you look, how full of love and terror! No - be gone! Be not angry! Here - you could not be at home: here in this far domain of ice and rocks - here you must be a huntsman, and like the Alpine goat.

A wicked huntsman is what I have become! - See how bent my bow! He who drew that bow, surely he was the mightiest of men - : but the arrow, alas - ah, no arrow is dangerous as that arrow is dangerous - away! be gone! For your own preservation! ...

You turn away? - O heart, you have borne up well, your hopes stayed strong: now keep your door open to new friends! Let the old go! Let memories go! If once you were young, now - you are younger!

What once united us, the bond of one hope - who still can read the signs love once inscribed therein, now faint and faded? It is like a parchment - discoloured, scorched - from which the hand shrinks back.

No longer friends, but - what shall I call them? - they are the ghosts of friends which at my heart and window knock at night, which gaze on me and say: 'were we once friends?' - oh faded word, once fragrant as the rose!

Oh longing of youth, which did not know itself! Those I longed for, those I deemed changed into kin of mine - that they have aged is what has banished them: only he who changes remains akin to me.

Oh life's midday! Oh second youth! Oh garden of summer! I wait in restless ecstasy, I stand and watch and wait - it is friends I await, in readiness day and night, new friends. Come now! It is time you were here!

This song is done - desire's sweet cry died on the lips: a sorcerer did it, the timely friend, the midday friend - no! ask not who he is - at midday it happened, at midday one became two ...

Now, sure of victory together, we celebrate the feast of feasts: friend Zarathrustra has come, the guest of guests! Now the world is laughing, the dread curtain is rent, the wedding day has come for light and darkness...

译者导读

查尔斯·麦基（Charles Mackay）生于1812年3月26日，卒于1889年12月24日，苏格兰诗人、作家、小说家和歌曲作家，以其文集《大众的迷茫与狂热》（Extraordinary Popular Delusions and the Madness of Crowds）而闻名于世。本书所选4篇作品即出自此文集。

《流行在大都市里的荒唐语》讲述了一些毫无意义的表达在都市坊间毫无缘由的起落兴衰；《南海泡沫危机》讲述了南海公司兴起到衰落的全过程，展示了泡沫膨胀时的斑斓和破灭时的黯淡，重现了当年金融市场的疯狂和荒谬；《郁金香狂热》描述了人们如何仅仅为了一棵球形的根茎而倾家荡产，举国上下如何为了这羸弱的花朵而陷入一片混乱；《疯狂的慢性投毒犯》揭露了那些天良尽失之人如何残害朋友和至亲，恶贯满盈之人如何从戕害人命中谋取暴利。

这4篇文章所讲述的故事截然不同，然而，却揭露了人类这个貌似智慧的动物，一不小心就极容易滑进去的一种状态——丧失理智的狂癫状。处于这种状态的所谓人类，已然没有了任何的思考能力和意识，犹如风中柳絮，或飘扬高空，或陷入泥潭，所有一切皆由外力主使。伦敦的市民张口闭口“阔斯”的时候，从来没有去想为什么这个音节具有如此丰富的含义和如此巨大的威力；所有南海公司和一系列泡沫公司的狂热股民，从来没有去想那些难以置信的事实如何产生高额的利润；荷兰的上上下下，也没有一个人去想一个类似洋葱的花根如何可以和祖产画上等号；那些把毒药坦然放进至亲的食物中的人，一样没有去想，亲人死后，人类良心和法律是否会允许他的“坦然”一直持续下去。

这种理智尽失的狂癫状只有两个结局：一种是始于狂癫、终于无形的“善始善终”，比如盲目热爱一个个表达的伦敦市民，只是在使用中过瘾，而从不去想每一个表达何去何从。而另一种结局便是从狂癫的顶峰跌入现实的谷底，或身败名裂，或粉身碎骨。泡沫公司的股民和股东们不得不面临泡沫破灭的现实，变得一贫如洗，甚至锒铛入狱；郁金香的追随者不得不面临一个“洋葱般根茎”回归本位的现实，家产尽失，血本无归；而那些将至亲置于死地的狂徒必然得接受人间道德和法律的惩罚，被斩首示众，甚至被挫骨扬灰。

文章和文章所讲述的故事都已成为遥远的历史，但是，它们所蕴含的深刻含义，对于今天我们这个充斥着各种欲望的社会，仍旧具有十分深远的教育和警醒意义。那些追求时尚、钟爱名牌、豪掷半年工资买一个名牌包的美女们；那些为求偶像一个签名而心甘情愿排数小时长队的追星族们；那些梦想一夜暴富而倾其所有的炒股迷们；那些所有、所有在迷恋着某种东西的人们，是否应该把文中的这些人作为自己的一面镜子，停下脚步，抓住一丝理智的光芒，照亮自己那因过分迷恋而变得茫然和晦暗的内心，在自我的所作所为中，追寻一下“意义”的痕迹。

在翻译的过程中，一面心中琢磨着久远的文字，一面脑海中闪现着当今社会的一幕幕。这大概就是经典的魅力吧：喻古讽今。而经典的丰富和深刻也绝非译者几句粗浅的解释可以涵盖。相信聪慧的读者在品读的过程中，定会发现另一番洞天。

流行在大都市里的荒唐语

啦！发兮咚呔——啦！发兮咚咚，

万岁！啦！发兮咚呔！

——贝朗热[1]

在大城市中，有一种诙谐无处不在。对于那些富有同情心和包容心的人，这种诙谐是他们永不枯竭的消遣源泉。这些人高贵而优雅，但他们从不会嘲笑酗酒技工的愚笨或怪癖，不会对肮脏的乞丐和恶作剧的顽童嗤之以鼻，也不会对充满大都市大街小巷的游手好闲者、粗鲁莽撞者和人云亦云者趾高气昂。有一种人，他走过了大都市，却发现诸多让人悲泣之事。对于这种人，或许，每一个角落都足以让他们心如刀绞。但是，让这些人带着悲伤独自前行吧——我们绝不会和他结伴。这些人挖出人类的苦难，只是为了表达他们对这些苦难的悲伤，而这对于减轻人类的痛苦毫无益处。这些哭泣的哲学家用心中的悲伤毁掉了他们的视力，人也在眼泪中变得无能。对于那些他们为之痛哭不已的罪恶，他们束手无策。于是，人们发现不流泪的人才是真正的慈善家。他就像一个杰出的医师，无论所面对的病例如何糟糕，他总可以做到带着微笑去乐观面对。

苦难已被无数次地挖掘，罪恶已引得群情激愤，乌合之众的愚蠢也已被无数次地口诛笔伐。所以，我们在这里的写作不再为之“锦上添花”，至少在这一章不会。我们目前的任务没有那么惹人厌烦，就是信步穿过大城市中的人群聚集地，在其中寻求普通大众的乐趣，并且在经过的时候，记下穷人那些无伤大雅的愚蠢行为和奇思怪想。

在此，我们首先要讲的是，无论我们走到哪里，我们总是会听到一个表达被城市中形形色色的人群反复使用。重复这个表达的人总是喜形于色，听到的人总是忍俊不禁。你看不管是那蓬头垢面、老茧满手的男人，粗鲁的屠夫，跑腿的听差，淫荡的女人，赶出租马车的车夫，抑或是在街头的角落里游手好闲的懒虫，所有的人无不如此。这个表达总是具有一触即发的威力，只要有人说起，听者无不捧腹大笑。这个措辞适用于任何一种环境，它是可以回答所有问题的万能答案；简而言之，它是时下最受人欢迎的具有俚语性质的表达。在它如昙花一现般短暂的流行季节里，这个表达给贫穷卑微者，给收入微薄者的生活投了一缕欢乐的亮光，加了一丝嬉戏的乐趣，从而让他们找到了和他们身居高位的同胞一样开怀大笑的理由。

伦敦尤其盛产这种表达。不知在什么地方，一夜之间不期而至；也不知以何种方式，几小时内妇孺皆知。多年以前，人们最爱的一个表达是“阔斯”（虽然只是个单音节词，但它本身足以算作一个表达方式）。这个奇怪的词语在群众中的受欢迎程度无与伦比，迅即便获得了近乎无限的含义。当平民百姓要表达不相信的态度，并且同时想博人一笑时，这个流行的俚语是绝对的不二词选。当一个人被要求施与恩惠，又不打算给予的时候，他总可以大喊一声：“阔斯！”在这一声大喊中，他对请求者极端鲁莽行为的态度表露无遗。当一个喜爱恶作剧的顽童想激怒路人并取悦他的密友的时候，他会直勾勾地盯着他的脸，然后脱口而出：“阔斯！”对于他所期望的效果，这个“阔斯”没有一次不灵验。当一个辩手要表达对对手论点的真实性的怀疑时，当他要尽快摆脱他无法推翻的论点时，他选择“阔斯”，带着口不择言的神态，噘起他轻蔑的嘴唇，耸起他不耐烦的肩膀。这个万能的单音节词传达了他所有的意图。他不仅告诉对手他知道他撒谎了，而且，如果他认为人们会愚蠢到去相信他的地步的话，他就不折不扣地错了。每个酒馆里都回响着“阔斯”，每个街角都喧嚣着“阔斯”，几英里范围内的墙壁上无不涂鸦着“阔斯”。

但是，像世间万物一样，“阔斯”虽盛，却也只能盛极一时。它来得迅猛，去得突然，而且，再也没有享受人们曾经给它的溺爱和崇拜。新来者把它赶跑了，毫无争辩地代替了它的统治地位；而这个新来者也注定在独领一段风骚之后，被它的继任者抛下万人瞩目的宝座。

下一个接踵而至的流行语是：“多么糟糕透顶的帽子啊！”这个表达一流行开来，就有成千上万只看似漫无目的，实则敏锐异常的眼睛四处搜寻戴着旧帽子的过客，不管他帽子露旧的痕迹是多么微乎其微。顷刻间，一呼百应，震耳欲聋的噪音极具印第安人的尖叫特色。如若发现自己身处众人关注的中心，最明智的做法莫过于以逆来顺受的方式来保持自己的尊严。如果对于投向自己帽子的责难表露出一点点的厌恶，那只能是加倍的自取其辱。这群乌合之众马上就会发现一个人是否易怒，而且，如果这个人和他们是一个阶层的，他们就会拿他取乐。在这个表达流行的日子里，如果这样的一个人，戴着这样的一顶帽子走过人群拥挤的邻近社区，如果他的烦恼仅限于这些乌合之众的大呼小叫，他应该意识到他已经很幸运了。然而，事实是这顶倒霉催的帽子经常会被人从他的头顶上一把抓下来，被肆无忌惮的恶作剧者扔到排水沟中，然后，再拿起来，带着淤泥挂到一根棍子上。他们以此来取悦那些旁观者。这些看客们乐得笑弯了腰，在欢笑的间隙大声喊着：“噢！多么糟糕透顶的帽子啊！”“多么糟糕透顶的帽子啊！”有多少可怜的人为此变得紧张兮兮！因此，只要他们的钱包还可以节约出这部分开支，必会在陷入这种窘境之前为自己买顶新帽子。

这个独特的说辞在连续几个月的时间内为伦敦带来了欢乐。然而，和“阔斯”以及其他出身不明的习语不同，它的来历明明白白。南华克区[2]曾经有一场竞争激烈的竞选，竞选人之一是一名著名的帽商。这位绅士为了拉选票，利用职业之便，以巧妙的方式来赢得选民的好感。这种方式就是贿赂选民，却让他们浑然不觉。每当他去拜访或碰见一个选民，而这个选民的帽子不是最好的材料，或者，虽然是最好的材料却早已不再流行时，他总是会不失时机地说：“你戴的帽子多么的糟糕透顶啊！给我的商店打电话，你会得到一顶崭新的帽子！”在竞选当天，这个场景被对手所利用。在这位尊敬的候选人对着选民讲话的时候，他的对手煽动群众不断地大声叫喊：“多么糟糕透顶的帽子啊！”这个习语从南华克区传遍整个伦敦，并一度成为最为流行的俚语。

曾一度备受宠爱的“钩子行者”起源于一个流行民谣的副歌。像“阔斯”一样，它也曾是回答所有问题的万能答案。随着时间的推移，仅仅第二个词为人们所专爱，并且这个词的第一个字的发音被特别地拉长，第二个字的音节则急转直下。如果一个可爱的女仆被一个她所不喜欢的人强吻，她一准儿会翘起她的小鼻子，叫道：“行者。”如果一个清洁工问他的朋友借一先令，而他的朋友不能或不愿借给他，他得到的答复极有可能是：“行者！”如果一个醉鬼在街上踉跄而行时，一个小男孩会去拽他的衣服后摆，或者有人会把他的帽子敲到他的眼上取笑他，而无论是哪种玩笑，必会伴着一声“行者！”2到3个月后，“行者”退出了历史舞台，而且，再也没有重新成为那代人或后来人的消遣用语。

下一个流行习语是最荒谬可笑的。谁发明了它？它是如何流行起来的？人们又是在哪里第一次听到了它？所有的这一切都无从得知。有关它的事情，没有一件可以确定。但是，连续几个月，它一直是伦敦人心中首屈一指的流行语。从它身上，伦敦人获得了巨大的满足感。根据所指对象性别的不同，这句习语是：“她/他走时她/他的眼睛都出来了。”那段时间，这个习语在所有熟悉这个城市的人当中口口相传。事实是，这个无厘头的习语给粗俗之人带来了多少欢乐，就给清醒之人带来了多少困惑。智慧的人觉得它很愚蠢，而很多人觉得它很有趣。游手好闲者用粉笔把它写在墙上或者涂在纪念碑上以自娱自乐。但是，“所有的明亮都终将黯淡”，习语也毫不例外。人们终于厌倦了他们的嗜好，随之，“他走时眼睛都出来了”这句习语再也没有在它曾经盛极一时的流行地听到过。

紧随其后的习语很奇怪，流行空间也很有限。这个习语的形式是鲁莽而有些不得体的询问：“你妈把她的轧布机卖了吗？”然而，它的流行程度并不像以前的流行语那样给人带来喧闹的气氛和兴奋的心情，所以，它很快就失宠了。阻碍它流行程度和延续时间的原因是这个习语显然不能用在老人身上。自然而然，它的热度匆匆而逝，随即，被人们抛入遗忘的深渊。相比之下，它的继任者所享盛名要久得多。它的根基是那样的深厚，以至于无论岁月多么久远，时尚如何变迁都无法消除它的痕迹。这个习语是“烧起来啦！”直到今天，它仍是被广泛应用的口语表达。它源于改革暴动时期，那时，愤怒的人们把布里斯托尔烧了将近一半。据说火焰在这个完全陷入暴乱的城市里呼呼乱窜。很难猜测这个习语的流行是因为它的几个词具有美妙的发音，还是因为包含了隽永的涵义。然而，无论原因是什么，事实是确定的，那就是它有力地刺激了大众的幻想，并在刺激中给了他们快感，并且把它之前的习语赶出了流行地带。走遍伦敦，人们听到的只有“烧起来啦！”它回答了所有的问题，解决了所有的争端，适用于所有人、所有事以及所有的场合。它突然间成为英语这个语言中最包罗万象的表达。一个人说话不得体，人们会说他“烧起来了”；一个人过分频繁地去杜松子酒馆，并因此堕落下去，人们也会说他“烧起来了”；让自己陷入深情无法自拔、在深夜出门寻欢、惊扰周围的人们并且制造骚乱，所有的这一切都是当事者“烧起来了”。恋人争吵时“烧起来了”，街上两个恶棍的斗殴也是用的这个表达。那些煽动革命和动乱的传教士让英国像法国一样烧了起来。人们是如此钟爱这个表达，以至于人们重复它就是为了它的声音。很显然，听到他们的器官发出这个声音就足以让他们感到欣欣然。当没有人倾听并回应他们的呼声时，东区的劳工会用这个著名的、常常让西区的贵族感到震惊的习语回应他们。甚至在万物沉寂的深夜，那些值夜班的和无法入睡的人们也总能听到这个声音。蹒跚回家的醉鬼在打嗝儿的间隙叫一声“烧起来了”，以此表明他还属于人类，还是个公民。酒醉让他丧失了整理其他思想的能力，他的智商降到了畜生的水平，但是，他的这声呼喊让他抓住了他和人类的最后一丝联系。他只要能够大声喊出这个声音，他就有权利做英国人，他就不会像狗一样睡在排水沟里。他大喊大叫着继续前行，惊扰了安静的街道，惊醒了熟睡的人们，直到筋疲力尽一头栽倒在路上。这时，很及时地，一个警察碰巧发现了他，这位治安的捍卫者把灯光照到他脸上，随后惊呼一声：“这儿有一个可怜的家伙烧起来了！”然后，有人抬来担架，将这位酩酊大醉者送到哨所，扔进一个肮脏的小屋。在那儿，一群和他一样喝得大醉的倒霉鬼用一个大声的、拉长音的“烧起来啦！”来欢迎他们这个新同志。

这个习语是这样的万能且貌似经久不衰，以至于一位并不了解俚语易逝特性的投机者以此习语为名创办了一个新闻周刊。然而，就像把房屋建在沙地上的人一样，他的地基最终还是坍塌了。那个习语和他所创办的报纸一起被冲进了历史的汪洋。人们最终厌倦了这个单调的“烧起来啦”，这个说法甚至在他们当中也成为粗俗之语。渐渐地，只有不谙世事的小男孩喜欢它，然后，随着时间的流逝，最终被人们完全遗忘了。这个表达已经不是常用的习语，但仍旧用来指突发的火灾、骚乱或恶行。

下一个集万千宠爱的表达不太简洁，它起初的用途是指责早熟的年轻人。他们未成年，却又总是装出一副男子汉十足的气概来。“你妈知道你出来了吗？”是个让人发怒的质问。它用于质问那些吹牛离了谱的，在街上抽烟的，带着假胡子看起来不可一世的年轻人。我们很是见过一些逞能的家伙，只要有女士从他们面前经过，他们必定直勾勾地一直把人家看到惊慌失措；但是，只要对他们一说这句话，他们就立马原形毕露，卑微之极。盛装出行的学徒和伙计对这个习语深恶痛绝，每每听到，必会一脸愤怒。总体而言，这个习语应用的效果是好的，它无数次地告诉那些浮夸的年轻人，他们并非像自己想象的那样优美、动人。然而，除了这个正面效果之外，这个表达所暗含的对对方自制能力的怀疑赋予了它挑衅的特性。一句“你妈知道你出来了吗？”的询问包含了假装的关心和担忧；言下之意便是这么年轻、对大城市这么没有经验的人竟然在没有父母的陪同下独自出来乱逛，实在令人遗憾和揪心。由此，那些即将成年的年轻人一旦成为被询问的对象，必会马上勃然大怒。甚至，年岁大一点的人也不喜欢这个习语。如果一个车夫在不知道客人显赫身份的情况下，对一个公爵领地或勇士封号的继承人说了这句话，对方必会对这种公然的侮辱怒发冲冠，并一定会和这个胆大妄为的冒犯者对簿公堂。车夫解释说他本来是想跟这位老爷要双倍的钱，结果被拒，所以，他对之施以“你妈知道你出来了吗”的侮辱。迅即，在场的所有车夫都开始大呼小叫着“你妈知道你出来了吗”，然后，这位老爷只好在尽量不失尊严的前提下落荒而逃。公堂之上，车夫求情说他不知道他的客人是个老爷，然而，被冒犯的正义让他为自己的过错付出了代价。

这个习语气数用尽之后，像它的先辈们一样销声匿迹了。随后，“你是谁？”代替了它的统治地位。这个新宠像蘑菇，仿佛一夜之间即可破土而出，迅猛生长；又像齐普赛街上的青蛙，随一阵急雨从天而降。前一天，它还没有被听说、被知晓，甚至没有被发明；后一天，它就已经遍及了整个伦敦。每一条小路都回响着它，每一条大路上都有它的余音萦绕，

街头巷尾，四处传诵

这不变的呼喊。

这个习语的说法很迅捷，第一个词和最后一个词的读音都以喷薄之势而出，中间一个词的读音轻如气息。像它所有可以被广泛应用的同仁一样，这个习语也可以用于几乎各种不同的场合。喜欢对平实的问题作出平实回答的人绝对不会喜欢它。傲慢无礼者用它去冒犯别人；无知者用它去遮掩自己的贫乏；恶作剧者用它来取笑。每一个进入酒吧间的新人都会被人毫不客气地问一句：“你是谁？”如果他呆头呆脑地抓耳挠腮，不知如何应答，人群里肯定会爆发一阵狂笑。面对这一问，再权威的辩论者也只能张口结舌，再无礼的傲慢也只能偃旗息鼓。在这个习语盛行之时，一个绅士感到有贼在掏他的衣兜，他突然转身，把那个人逮个现形，然后大呼一声：“你是谁？”周围的看客必定会随之欢呼，并且认为这是他们听到的最棒的笑话了——堪称智慧的顶峰和幽默的精髓。另一个类似的场景给这个习语增添了额外的趣味，在它即将淡出之时，为它注入了新的生命和活力。这一幕发生在大不列颠王国的刑事大法庭上。一个犯人在接受公开审问，被控告之罪已被证实，他的律师不是为他作无罪辩护，而是请求法庭从轻发落，理由是他以前是个品端行正的好人。“那么你的证人们呢？”尊敬的主持法官问道。这时，旁听席中传来一个粗鲁的声音：“求你了，长官！我认识这个受审的犯人，他是有史以来最诚实的人了。”一时间，法庭上的官员们惊得目瞪口呆，那些陌生人压抑不住地咯咯直笑。这时，法官突然抬起头，冷静而威严地说：“你是谁？”整个法庭都被震惊了，咯咯窃笑变成了捧腹大笑，几分钟后才重新恢复安静和秩序。引领员平静情绪之后，开始寻找那个胆敢亵渎法庭的家伙，但是却无果而终。没有人认识他，也没有人见过他。一段时间之后，法庭又恢复了正常的审讯。紧接着受审的罪犯对自己的前景十分乐观，因为他得知那张代表正义的、庄严的嘴巴竟然能说出这么草根的习语，仿佛他曾亲身体验，并且很欣赏这个说法。他由此推断，这样的一个法官绝对不会过分严厉。他的心和劳苦大众在一起，他理解他们的语言和做事的方式，所以，对于他们受到诱惑而犯罪这件事，必然能够尽可能地体谅。从后来的事实判断，无数的罪犯都这么想，最后，这个博学的法官突然间受到了大众的极度欢迎，他的智慧被人们到处传颂。就这样，“你是谁？”获得了新生，又接着被大众宠爱了一段时间。

但是，如果你认为两个前后相继的习语之间是没有休止符的你方唱罢我登场的模式，那你就大错特错了。这些习语的兴起并非绵延不断的一条单线，而是在赢得大众青睐的过程中，与歌曲平分秋色。情形如下：当人们沉浸在音乐之中时，习语再怎么高声呼喊，也只能是徒劳无益；而当人们心向习语时，音乐再甜美，他们也是充耳不闻。大约20年前，整个伦敦回响着一首让所有人神魂颠倒的歌曲。男孩儿、女孩儿、小伙子、老大爷、少女、少妇以及寡妇，所有的人都步调一致地喜欢起了音乐。人们对于歌唱的狂热无与伦比，然而，最糟糕的是，就像传奇小说《修道院》（The Monastery）中的好神父菲利普一样，他们的曲调绝对一成不变。整个城里那些游手好闲的人整齐划一地唱着：“樱桃熟了！”“樱桃熟了！”每一个歌唱的声音都是那样的不协调，每一把小提琴的演奏都让人疯狂，每一个笛子的演奏都让人崩溃，每一个管乐的演奏都犹如病态的喘息，街道上所有的乐器都在演奏这同样的旋律。最后，那些努力勤学的人和偏爱安静的人不得不绝望地堵上耳朵，甚至，跑到数英里之外的田野里或树林里去寻找安静。这个瘟疫一般无处不在又折磨人的歌曲存在了一年，直到樱桃这个词在这片土地上成为人们厌恶的对象。最终，激情消减了，钟爱的浪潮又朝着新的方向前进。下一个宠儿是一首歌还是一个俚语，现在确定还为时尚早，但是，可以肯定的是，马上，人们又开始对一个戏剧的主题开始痴迷，无论你走到哪儿，总能听到“汤姆和杰米”。仅仅以言语的形式来取悦大众的时间已经很久了，所以，在后来的消遣中，人们开始更加注重实际的行动。城里每一个青年的心中都充斥着要脱颖而出的强烈愿望，而实现这个愿望的方式真是多种多样。他们会选择打倒“查理一家”，整夜被关在拘留所里，在淫荡的女人中间起哄，或者和一群粗鄙的人同被关在圣吉斯大教堂的地穴里。那些小男孩模仿这些年轻人的行动，并且企图在类似的事情上和他们一比高低。这种情形一直持续到这个毫无价值的激情像其他的愚蠢行为一样，走到它生命的尽头。整个城市又开始沉醉于下一个流行时尚。紧接着，把拇指尖放到鼻子尖上，并且在空中迅速转动4个手指成为回答所有问题的方式。在粗俗之人中，这种方式被认为是顶级智慧的象征。如果一个人想侮辱或者激怒另外一个人，他只需使用这个神秘的具有象征意义的手势，即可达到目的。在每一个有人群聚集的街角，如果一个过路者觉得好奇要停下来观察他们的行动，两分钟之内，他必定可以看到其中有人把手指放到他们的鼻子上，以此来表示他们对这个观察者的怀疑、吃惊、拒绝，或者嘲笑。今天，人们仍能看到这个荒谬习俗的遗留痕迹，但是，不同的是，现在它被认为是低级的行为，甚至在粗俗人群中也不例外。

大约16年之前，伦敦城又毫无道理地迷上了音乐。大众在高声赞扬“海洋，海洋！”的歌声里，喊哑了嗓子。如果一个不知情的陌生人（而且是个哲学家）步行穿过伦敦时听到了这个在全城传唱的歌谣，他一定会建立一个有趣的理论，来阐述英国人对海的喜爱和我们众所周知的海洋霸权地位之间的关系。他可能会说，“毫无疑问，这个民族在海上不可战胜。他们对海洋的热爱渗入了他们的日常思维：他们甚至在市场这种地方赞美海洋，他们的路边歌手通过歌颂海洋来祈求施舍；身份不分贵贱，年龄不分长幼，性别不分男女，所有的人都在歌颂‘啊！海洋！’”在这个热爱战争的民族的歌谣里，爱情不是钟爱的主题——酒神巴斯（Bacchus）不是他们的神；他们的思维模式严厉而冷峻，他们只想着“海洋，海洋！”，以及征服海洋的方式。

如果耳朵是这个哲学家判断事物的唯一依据的话，毫无疑问，这些歌声会给他留下这样的印象。唉！那些日子里，那些真正懂得欣赏音乐的高雅的耳朵们啊！当不和谐的旋律演奏起这个让人震惊的圣歌，当成千上万个不同的曲调随声附和，他们在无处可逃的处境中忍受了多么巨大的折磨啊！萨伏伊的流浪歌手听到了这个旋律，开始在伦敦幽静的长街上大声歌唱，直到最深、最偏僻处的屋子里都回响着他的声音。那些优雅之人不得不忍受着魔鬼般的长嚎，这首歌持续了6个月之久。他们疲惫而绝望，甚至在陆地上开始有海里晕船的感觉。

几首其他歌曲在随后的不同时期相继盛行，但是，除了“都围着我的帽子”这首歌外，其他几首都没有获得特别的宠爱，直到一个美国男演员引入了一首名字叫作“黑人，杰姆·克劳”的低俗歌曲。歌手穿着很应景的服装，摆着奇怪的手势，而且每当歌曲结束的时候总会突然旋转他的身体。这种风格迅疾抓住了全城人的口味，结果，那些规矩之人的耳朵不得不连续几个月忍受这首毫无意义的歌谣所带来的惊吓：

转啊，摇啊，

就这么做吧——

转啊，摇啊，

跳吧，黑人，杰姆·克劳！

街头的流浪歌手为了增加歌曲的效果，涂黑了他们的脸庞；那些失去父亲的、不得不在偷盗和卖唱这两种谋生方式之间作出选择的流浪儿毫不犹豫地选择了后者，因为这个方式看起来似乎更能赚钱，当然，前提是公众的口味保持这个风格不变。在任何大街的夜市上，都可以看到这首歌的伴舞，把粗野笨拙演绎到了无以复加的地步；而这首歌的歌词，刺透人流的喧嚣，高高飘在空中。在这首打油诗的流行时期，那个安静的旁观者，

坐在公路旁

身上布满夏日的灰尘，看着人流

匆忙地来往

众人犹如黄昏光线下的蠓虫儿

此时此刻的他，可能会像雪莱一样高呼：

成千上万的人在狂歌乱舞

如痴如醉

那个曾经自言自语英国人的国民性格，并且认为这个民族对海洋歌曲情有独钟的哲学理论家会对这种现象作何感想呢？如果再次造访伦敦，他一定会得出另一个貌似真实的理论来说明我们对废除奴隶制所作出的不懈努力。“仁慈的民众啊！”他一定会说，“你们的同情心是多么无限啊！你们不幸的非洲同胞们，他们只是在肤色上和你们不同，但对你们是多么友好啊。你们也毫不吝惜你们为他们贡献的2000万，你们想永远纪念他们。杰姆·克劳是那个受伤害民族的代表，也是你们这个民族的大众偶像！看他们如何赞扬他！——他们如何模仿他的特色！——他们如何在闲暇和放松的时刻重复他的名字！他们甚至把他的形象雕刻出来，用以装饰他们的壁炉！他的事业和他的苦难永远不会被忘记！噢，博爱的英格兰啊！——噢，文化的先锋！”

这些就是伦敦民众的特色，此时此刻，没有动乱、行刑、谋杀、麻烦来打乱他们平静的思绪。这些就是普通民众的奇思怪想——这些毫无恶意的愚蠢行为无形中减轻了生存的压力。对于那些智者，虽然，他们会有点嘲笑这些愚蠢的言行，但是绝对不会毫无同情心。他们一定会说：“如果他们愿意，就让他们尽情享受那些俚语式的表达和歌谣吧；如果他们无法幸福，至少，让他们快活吧。”对于英国人，就像对贝朗热歌中所唱到的法国人一样，在小小的一首歌中蕴含着一些安慰。我们和他一样，共同拥有：

那些忧郁的人们啊，

能够给予他们快乐的，

恰恰是这些没有意义的话语！

啊，他们渡过忧伤之河的渡口啊！

就在这些没有意义的表达里。

南海泡沫危机

最后，腐败，犹如洪水，

铺天盖地、淹没一切，而，贪婪

于不知不觉中，蔓延、伸展，

像低空的雾，遮光蔽日。

政客和爱国者一起孜孜不倦地炒着股票，

贵妇和男仆在交易所里齐头并肩；

法官做着经纪人，主教侵吞民脂民膏，

位高权重的公爵耍尽手段，

却只为，蝇头小利：

整个不列颠陷入了利欲熏心的魔咒里。

——蒲伯

南海公司由声望很高的牛津伯爵哈利（Harley, Earl of Oxford）创建于1711年，其目的是恢复辉格党下台以来一直境遇不佳的政府声誉，清偿国家流动债务中高达近1000万英镑的海陆军的信用债券及其他债券。这个由商人创建的、在那个时候尚未命名的公司主动承担了政府的这些债务。政府保证在一个时期内向他们提供6%的年利率。按此利率计算，政府每年须向他们支付高达60万的利息，为此，政府永久性免收他们所进口的葡萄酒、醋、印度商品、丝织品、烟草、鲸鱼鳍，以及其他一些商品的关税。同时，他们还获得了南海地区的贸易垄断权，从此，通过国会法案组建的这个公司就以“南海”闻名于世了。伯爵大人因为在事务办理中的贡献而赢得了很高的荣誉，而这项计划总是被那些阿谀奉承者称为“牛津伯爵的杰作”。

即便是在公司建立的早期，公司和公众就对南美西岸的巨大财富形成了极具梦幻色彩的想象。每个人都听说过秘鲁和墨西哥的金矿、银矿；每个人都认为那里的矿藏取之不尽；只要把英国的产品运到那里的海岸，当地居民就会拿上百倍的金锭、银锭来给予回报。有一则消息被人孜孜不倦地传播着：西班牙将让出智利和秘鲁海岸上的4个港口，以便为英国的船只提供交通便利。这则消息大大增强了公众对于南海公司的信心，连续好几年，它的股票炙手可热。

但是，西班牙的菲利普五世从来没有打算让英国在美洲的西班牙殖民地港口享受自由贸易。双方曾经着手谈判，但谈判的结果只是签订奴隶贸易特许条约。条约允许英国垄断美洲西班牙属殖民地的奴隶贸易30年；同时，允许英国每年有一艘商船和墨西哥、西班牙及秘鲁进行贸易，商船的吨位和货物价值都有严格的限定。后一个条款的实现须满足一条刚性条件，那就是西班牙国王享有1/4的利润，同时，对于剩下3/4的利润收取5%的所得税。这个结果让牛津伯爵和他的政党大失所望，这让他们想起“大山临盆，老鼠出世”[3]的故事，现实和希望的巨大落差让他们心灰意冷。但是，公众对南海公司的信心并未动摇。牛津伯爵随后宣布，除合约中规定的每年一艘的船舶外，西班牙允许第一年再加两艘商船；同时，还印发了沿途海岸所有港口的名单，并且高调宣布这些港口统统对大不列颠开放贸易。实际上，合约中规定的每年一次的商船直到1717年才进行第一次航行，而第二年的航行就因为和西班牙决裂而取消了。

国王在1717年议会的开幕式演讲中很明显地暗示了让人担忧的政府信用状态，并且提议采取适当的措施来减少国债。南海公司和英格兰银行这两个金融巨头紧接着在5月20号就对议会提出了建议。南海公司保证他们换购国债的股本可以通过认购或其他方式由1000万增加到1200万；而且，他们同意将年利率由6%降到5%。英格兰银行给出的有利条件也相当诱人。众议院争论了一段时间之后，出台了3个法案，分别是《南海公司法案》、《英格兰银行法案》和《通用基金法案》。在第一个法案中，议会接受了南海公司的提议，而公司也准备好预付增加的200万英镑以清偿安妮女王（Queen Anne）就任第9年和第10年所发行的4个奖券基金的本息。通过第二法案，英格兰同意降低政府欠它的1775027英镑15先令的利息；同意取消多达200万英镑的国库券；同意政府按5%的利率，每年向他们支付10万英镑的年金。同时，在一年期内，这些债券可由政府赎回。除此之外，政府还要求他们在急需的情况下以5%的利率预付不超过2500万英镑的债券，债券可由议会赎回。《通用基金法案》列举了几点缺陷，这些缺陷由前述的资源来完善。

南海公司的名字就是这样不断地出现在公众的视野中。虽然，他们和南美国家的贸易几乎甚至可以说根本没有提高他们的年收入；但是，这并不妨碍它作为一个金融公司继续蓬勃发展。公众对于公司股票的需求空前高涨。董事们受这种胜利景象的鼓舞，甚至开始考虑扩大他们影响的新方式。约翰·劳（John Law）那个曾经让法国人神魂颠倒的密西西比计划[4]给了他们灵感，他们认为在英国也可以玩同样的把戏。他们预料到约翰·劳必定失败的结局，却并没有因此而改变他们自己的计划。他们认为自己的计划足够聪明，可以避免约翰的错误，将这个计划永远进行下去，把信用的弦拉到极限，而且这根弦绝不会突然崩断。

约翰·劳的计划获得了大众极度的欢迎，成千上万的人蜂拥到甘康普瓦大街[5]上，用狂热亲手将自己毁灭。恰在此时，南海公司向议会提出他们著名的清偿国债计划。在欧洲两个最著名的国家，人们想象着无尽的财富在他们迷醉的眼前漂来浮去。英国人的挥霍事业开始的要比法国人晚，但是这种狂热一旦抓住了他们，就注定其程度的不可超越。1720年1月22日，下议院转组为全院委员会来讨论国王在议会开幕式上涉及国债的演讲，以及南海公司有关偿还国债的提议。提议由几个董事制定，详细地阐述了有关国债的计划。根据提议，公司愿意以每年5%的利率承担30981712英镑的国债直到1727年。1727年之后，国债可由立法机构根据自己的意愿择时赎回，并且利率降到4%。这个提议很受欢迎；但是，英格兰银行在下议院中有很多的朋友，他们希望这个公司也可以在这些有可能产生的利益中分一杯羹。这些朋友代表这个公司，作了如下陈述：英格兰银行在国家处于危难时，曾作出了卓著的贡献，所以，如果这种性质的政府交易可以带来利益的话，相比于一个对国家无所作为的公司，他们至少应该优先受到青睐。对于事态的进一步商议因此推迟了5天。同时，银行的管理层起草了一份计划。因为害怕英格兰银行会给政府提供更优惠的条件，南海公司重新考虑了他们之前的提议，对它作了一些修改，并希望修改后的提议更容易让政府接受。一个重要的变化是，规定政府可以在4年后赎回债券，而非刚开始提出的7年。在这场非凡的竞拍中，银行也不甘服输，管理层又重新考虑了他们最初的提议并提交了更新版本。

这样，在每个公司提交了两份提议后，议院开始仔细考虑。罗伯特·沃波尔（Robert Walpole）是英格兰银行的主要拥护者，而财政大臣艾斯拉比（Aislabie）极力支持南海公司。2月2日，经讨论决定，后者的提议对国家更有利。南海公司的提议被通过了，同时，根据他们的提议，追加了相关法案。

交易所里热情高涨。公司的股票前一天还是130英镑，今天已稳步升到300英镑，然后在所追加法案的讨论期，以惊人的速度一路飙升。沃波尔先生几乎是议院中唯一大胆持反对意见的政府官员。他以极其严肃和富有说服力的语言警告他们可能随之而来的犯罪。他说，这个计划纵容了“股票行业的危险操作，它让国家精英不再专心从事贸易和工业。它抛出了一个危险的诱饵，让毫无警戒心的人们用他们的劳动所得去换取想象中的财富，从而引诱他们走向毁灭。这个计划的原则可谓恶贯满盈。它通过唤起民众对财富的迷恋心理，以及根本没有足够的本金来保证的红利来人为地增加股票的面值”。他预言：如果计划成功了，公司董事将成为政府的主人，在王国形成全新的贵族统治，并控制立法机构。如果正如他所确信的那样，这个计划失败了，它将在全体民众中产生不满，并给整个国家带来伤害。这是所有人的一场幻梦。当厄运如期而至，人们终将如大梦初醒，不禁自问这一切是否是真的。他为这件事所费的口舌都是徒劳的。他被看成是虚伪的预言家，甚至被比喻成声音嘶哑难听的乌鸦，象征恶兆的嘎嘎叫声让人讨厌。而他的朋友却把他比作希腊神话中的凶事预言家卡珊德拉[6]：只有当不幸登门造访，在人们的家里和他们四目相对的时候，他们才会相信他的预言。虽然议院对他的一字一句都曾洗耳恭听，但是，当议员得知他要谈论南海公司的问题时，立即人去席空。

这个法案在下议院经历了两个月的讨论。在此期间，公司董事和他们的朋友们，尤其是董事会主席，著名的约翰·布朗特（John Blunt）爵士都不遗余力地想方设法提升股票价格。有关英国和西班牙之间签订一系列协议的荒谬流言史无前例地四处流传：西班牙赋予英国它所有殖民地的自由贸易权，波托西——拉——巴兹丰富的银矿将被源源不断地运送到英国，直到英国的银矿和铁一样丰富。墨西哥的居民将为我们倾空他们的金矿，因为我们将为他们提供丰富的棉花和羊毛产品。和南太平洋各国做生意的这个商人公司将成为有史以来最富有的公司，而对于它的股票持有人来说，他们所投资的每100英镑，每年都可以为他们带来几百甚至上千的利润。最后，股票的价格通过这种方式升到了近400英镑，波动了一段时间之后，稳定在330英镑，直到法案在众议院以172票赞成55票反对的比例通过。

法案在上议院以史无前例的速度通过了评审的各个阶段：4月4日第一次宣读，5日第二次宣读，6日交付委员会，7日第三次宣读并通过。

在上议院的讨论中，几位议员强烈反对这个计划，但是人们对他们的警告置若罔闻。一种对投机的狂热迷住了众多议员和普通民众的心。诺斯（North）勋爵和格雷（Grey）说，这个计划旨令少数人富有、陷多数人于贫困，在性质上是不公平的，必然会导致致命的后果。沃顿（Wharton）公爵随后也发了言；但是，因为他只不过是口若悬河地二手兜售沃波尔在下议院提出的观点，他所得到的关注还不及诺斯勋爵和格雷得到的多。考珀（Cowper）伯爵也持同样的立场，他把这个法案比作围攻特洛伊时那匹举世闻名的木马。就像那匹木马一样，人们欢呼雀跃着以无比华丽的场面迎接它，但是，它所带来的却只有背叛和毁灭。桑德兰（Sunderland）伯爵努力回应所有的异议；法案一经提出，只有17名议员持反对意见，83名完全赞成这个计划。就在这个计划在上议院通过的当天，它获得了皇室的同意，成为这个岛国的法律。

顷刻间，全民都成为了股票经纪人。股票交易所天天人满为患，康希尔也被数不清的马车挤得水泄不通。每个人都来购买股票。“每个傻瓜都梦想升级为流氓。”这是当时出版的一个民谣的歌词，在大街小巷里到处传唱：

明星和嘉德勋位获得者

混迹于乌合之众；

他们疯狂地买卖着股票，

还对犹太人和异族人的争吵

喜闻乐见。

最高贵的贵妇也闻风而来，

不辞辛苦，天天乘着马车奔忙，

或者忍痛割爱，把珠宝典当，

原来是为购得股票才这般疯狂。

社会各阶层在对赚钱近乎病态的渴望中备受煎熬。即使在南海公司内部，发财的欲望也同样不可遏制。一系列史上最令人眼花缭乱的阴谋诡计在南海公司一一出炉了。股市行情表被迅速地填满，一笔笔交易在不断地进行；与此同时，南海公司不择手段地哄抬这些股票的市场价格，使其达到一个虚高的水平。

与众人的期望背道而驰，在法案获得皇室的同意后，南海公司的股票价格开始下跌。4月7日的报价是310英镑，第二天就降到了290英镑。董事们已经尝到他们计划的甜头了，所以，他们不可能坐视股票降到它真实的水平而无动于衷。顷刻间，他们的使者们开始奔忙。每一个希望计划成功的人都在他的周围召集一群听众，对他们详细讲述南美各个海洋国家的丰富宝藏。股票交易所里挤满了侧耳倾听的人们。一个谎言，仅仅是因为它以极度自信的方式被讲述出来，便对股票市场产生了立竿见影的影响。据说斯坦霍普（Stanhope）伯爵在法国已经收到了西班牙政府的提议，提议的内容是：为了扩张英国在南太平洋地区的贸易并保证其安全，西班牙政府愿意用直布罗陀海峡和马翁港来交换秘鲁海岸的一些地方。一年只能有一艘贸易船只到那些港口，并允许西班牙国王抽取利润的25%的日子一去不复返了。南海公司可以随心所欲地造船、租船，而且无需向任何外国君主交付任何比例的利润。“人们幻想着元宝在眼前飞舞”，股市一路攀升。4月12日，在上议院通过此法案的第五天，公司管理层以300%的溢价发行了100万新股，每股面值100英镑，售价300英镑。社会各阶层人士蜂拥而至，以至于第一次的股票认购数量就达200多万原始股。对于每股面值为100英镑的原始股，他们可以分5次付款，每次60英镑。几天之内，股票又飙升到340英镑，认购股票以2倍于首次认购的价格售出。为了进一步提升股票的价格，董事常设会议于4月21日宣布，凡认购仲夏季节发行股票的股民，均可享受10%的红利。这些决议达到了预设的目的，随后，为进一步提高有钱人购买股票的欲望，公司管理层决定以400%的溢价再发行100万股。每一个阶层的人们对这笔资金是如此地热望，以至于几小时内150多万股就被以上述价格认购一空。

同时，数不清的股份公司在各地纷纷成立。这些公司迅即获得了“泡沫”的称号，这是人类想象力所能找到的最合适的词语了。公众总是对使用绰号情有独钟。没有哪个词能比“泡沫”更适合了。有些公司持续了一周，有些两周，然后就音信全无了；而其他的甚至连这个时间长度也持续不了。每天晚上都有新的计划，每天早上都有新的项目。对于利润的狂热追求，贵族的最高层丝毫不亚于康希尔最单调乏味的股票经纪人。威尔士的王子成了一个公司的管理者，并且，据说他通过投机买卖净赚4万英镑。布里奇沃特公爵开启了一个改善伦敦和威斯敏斯特的项目，尚多斯公爵开办了另一个项目。大约有100个不同的项目，一个比一个夸张，一个比一个具有欺骗性。用官方的语言说，这些项目“由狡猾的流氓开办并推销，由贪婪而愚蠢的乌合之众追捧，最终的结果只是证明它们看起来正如它们那个粗俗的称谓所表示的那样——泡沫和欺骗”。据计算，在这些不正当的操作中，有150万英镑被赚取和亏损；一群傻瓜变得一贫如洗，一群流氓变得腰缠万贯。

这些计划中有一些看起来似乎还是可行的。如果人们是在头脑没有发热的情况下进行这些计划，或许参与的各方都会有收益。但是，这些计划设立的目的仅仅是为了增加市场上的股票。这些公司的发起人运用第一次发迹的机会将股票一卖而空；然后，第二天，计划迅即结束。梅特兰（Maitland）在他的《伦敦史》（History of London）中很严肃地告诉我们，一个受到极大鼓励的计划实际上是要建立一个“用木屑做廉价木板”的公司。这无疑是一个笑话；但是，有足够的证据证明，许许多多的、一点都不合理的计划，昙花一现般消失了，并且在它们消失之前毁掉了成百上千的人。在众多的计划当中，有一个是生产永动轮的——资本金为100万；另一个是“鼓励在英国喂马，改善教会或教堂的土地，修缮并重建牧师住所”。本来应该对后者感兴趣的牧师却对前者青睐有加。对于这个现象的解释只能是：这个计划是由曾经在英国很常见的一群热衷于猎狐的教区牧师设计的。这个公司的股票很快就被认购了。在所有开设的公司中，最荒谬的、最可笑的、最能将人们的极度疯狂暴露无遗的是一个由一位不知名的冒险者开办的，名为“进行获取暴利事业的公司，但没有人知道它是什么”。如果不是有许多目击者确实可靠的陈述，很难有人相信竟然会有人被这样的项目欺骗。这位大胆而成功地利用了公众易骗性的天才只是在他的创办计划书中说所需本金是50万英镑；为此，他们发行5000股面值100英镑的股票，每份股票的保证金是2英镑，每一个认购者在付保证金之后，每年每股可获得100英镑的利润。这笔巨大的利润是如何获得的，那时，他没有屈尊告诉公众；但是他许诺说，1个月以后将披露所有的细节，并且要求补交未支付的98英镑。第二天一早9点钟，这位天才在康希尔开设了办公室。成群的人围在他的门口，下午3点打烊的时候，他发现有3000多股票被认购，而且保证金已付。这样，在5小时内，他赚了2000英镑。他对自己的冒险事业十分满意，并且，很明智地当天晚上就去了欧洲。从此，杳无音信。

斯威夫特（Swift）把股票交易所比作南太平洋里的一个海湾，他高呼道：

认购者成千上万地漂浮在这里

你推我挤

每个人都奋力划着漏船

他们来钓金子，结果却被淹死

一会儿，被深深地淹在下面，

一会儿，又冲上云霄，

他们来来回回，步履蹒跚，

几乎丧失了理智，就像醉鬼一样

同时，在加罗伟的悬崖峭壁上，安然地，

躺着一个以遇难船只为生的野蛮民族，

他们等待着，破漏的小船来临，

等待着，掠夺死难者的财物。

另一个成功的骗局是一种叫作“环球许可证”的东西。这些许可证只不过是方形的扑克牌，牌上有蜡质的印章，印章上刻有位于交易所大街附近的环球酒馆的符号以及“帆布许可证”这几个文字。许可证的拥有者仅仅是享有未来某个时刻认购一个新的帆布工厂股票的权利。有关工厂的创办者，当时只知道是个很有钱的人；但是，后来这个人卷入了南海公司董事贪污和被罚的案件。就是这些许可证竟然在交易所售得60基尼[7]。

人们陷在这些泡沫里四处奔忙，不分贵贱，无论男女。先生们走进酒馆和咖啡馆约见他们的股票经纪人；女士们为了同样的目的穿梭于各个帽子店。但是，实际上这些人并不是都相信他们认购股票的项目的可行性；他们的目的就是他们的股票可以通过股票经营的技巧增值，然后，再把这些股票以最快的速度卖给那些真正轻信的人；对于他们来说，这一个目的就足够了。股票交易所里的人群是如此混乱，以至于同一个泡沫公司的股票在同一时间，在交易所一端的售价比另一端要高10%。理智的人们悲悯而惊恐地看着人们这种非同寻常的迷恋。议会内外都曾有人清晰地预言行将发生的毁灭。沃波尔先生一直没有停止他悲观的预感。他的担忧为少数几个还能理智思考的人所共有，而且，这份担忧深刻地影响了政府的决策。在6月11日议会休会之日，国王发布公告，宣布所有这些不合法公司都严重妨害了公众利益，所以，应对其提起公诉；同时，禁止任何股票经纪人从这些公司再买卖股票，否则罚款500英镑。但是，那些无耻的投机者无视公告的颁布，一如既往地进行他们的罪恶活动，那些被蒙蔽的人们也依旧在推波助澜。7月12日，聚集在枢密院的上议院法官们发布了一条命令，命令拒绝所有专利和特许权的申请，并解散所有的泡沫公司。法官命令的副本包括了所有这些不法公司的名单。在人人都着迷股票的今天，这个命令也不是毫无趣味的：

1720年7月12日，在白厅会议室里，

与会的诸位上议院大法官阁下提出。

与会的诸位上议院大法官阁下对这些公司给公众带来的诸多麻烦进行了仔细的考量。这些公司为了不同的目的，以股份制的形式成立，为了让公众和他们并肩作战，他们向公众保证他们对专利和特许权的申请肯定能获得批准；国王的臣民们就是被这种虚假的保证所骗，而后和他们的金钱诀别。为了阻止这种欺骗行动，诸位阁下命令把提到的几份申请，以及申请之后商业局和国王的律师及副检察长的报告，一同放到他们面前进行讨论。经过深思熟虑，根据国王枢密院的建议，诸位阁下决定拒绝所有提到的申请，这些申请具体如下：

1.几个人的申请：以“大不列颠宏大渔业”的名义申请进行渔业贸易的专利特许证。

2.“英格兰皇家渔业公司的申请”：申请有利于进一步发展所谓渔业的权力的专利特许证。

3.乔治·詹姆斯的申请，代表他自己及其他涉猎渔业的不同名流：申请能够让他们组建公司，同时进行贸易的专利特许证。

4.几名商人及几位署名者的申请：申请为了恢复并发展格陵兰岛及其他地方的捕鲸业而成立公司。

5.约翰·兰伯特及其他几位署名人士的申请，代表他们自己及其他为数不少的商人：申请为了发展格陵兰岛贸易，尤其发展戴维斯海峡的捕鲸业，成立公司。

6.另外一个有关格陵兰贸易的申请。

7.几位商人、绅士和市民的申请：申请为购买、建造用于出租或货运的轮船而成立公司。

8.塞缪尔·安特里姆和其他几人的申请：申请种植大麻和亚麻的专利特许证。

9.几位商人、轮船主、航海者，及帆布制造商的申请：申请成立公司的特许权，以便让他们能够以股份制的形式继续发展和促进上述制造业。

10.托马斯·柏一德、几百位商人、轮船主、航海者、织工，及其他商业人员的申请：申请成立公司的特许权，特许他们为了生产帆布、优质荷兰亚麻布购地筹资。

11.对已故威廉国王和玛丽王后所批准的特权有兴趣的几位人士的申请：为了制造亚麻布和帆布，政府不得给予任何人——无论身份和地位——特许权，保证他们现在拥有的权利，而且还应再赋予他们棉以及棉丝制品的生产权。

12.几位市民、商人、伦敦经商者，以及英国股票的认购者和其他一些人的申请：为了避免在英国任何一个地方发生火灾，申请成立公司。

13.伦敦及大不列颠其他地方的几位对国王忠心耿耿的臣民的申请：为避免在英国国内因火灾而造成的损失，申请成立公司。

14.托马斯·伯吉斯，以及其他署名的国王臣民，代表他们自己以及其他认购120万英镑基金的人们的申请：为了开展国王在他的德国领土上的贸易，以哈尔伯公司的名义申请成立公司。

15.一个木材经销商，爱德华·琼斯代表他自己及其他人的申请：申请为了从德国进口木材而组建公司。

16.几个伦敦商人的申请：为开展盐业，申请公司经营特许权。

17.兼做商人的伦敦麦克菲迪斯上尉，代表他自己以及几位商人、呢绒商、帽商、染布商的申请：申请公司经营特许权，以便让他们能够募集足够的资金买地，种植培育一种叫作茜草的植物，供染布商使用。

18.伦敦鼻烟制造商约瑟夫·加仑多的申请：为他所发明的如何在弗吉尼亚以及国王所有的领土上，让弗吉尼亚烟草变得适合制成鼻烟的方法申请专利。

泡沫名单

在同一条法令中，下面的泡沫公司被宣布为非法并予以取缔：

1.瑞典铁进口公司。

2.为伦敦提供海运煤炭的公司。资本金：300万。

3.在全英国新建以及重修房屋公司。资本金：300万。

4.棉布制作公司。

5.发展并提高英国铝制品公司。

6.开发布兰科和萨尔·塔哥塔斯岛定居点的公司。

7.给迪尔镇提供淡水资源的公司。

8.进口弗兰德斯花边的公司。

9.改善大不列颠土地状况的公司。资本金：400万。

10.鼓励在英国养马、改善教堂和教会土地质量、新建以及重修牧师住宅公司。

11.大不列颠钢铁制造公司。

12.改善弗林特郡土地状况公司。资本金：100万。

13.购买土地用来建造房屋的公司。资本金：200万。

14.毛发贸易公司。

15.在霍利岛建立盐制品公司。资本金：200万。

16.房地产买卖，以及按揭贷款公司。

17.进行一项十分盈利的事业，但没人知道是什么的公司。

18.铺设伦敦街道公司。资本金：200万。

19.在大不列颠任何一个地方提供葬礼的公司。

20.土地买卖及有息贷款公司。资本金：500万。

21.大不列颠皇家渔业公司。资本金：1000万。

22.确保海员工资安全公司。

23.为需要帮助的人建立贷款办公室，并鼓励勤勉者的公司。资本金：200万。

24.购买并改善可出租土地公司。资本金：400万。

25.从大不列颠北部及美国进口沥青、柏油，及其他松脂制品的公司。

26.服饰、毡布及波形瓦贸易公司。

27.购买并改善埃塞克斯的一个庄园并获得其矿藏开采权的公司。

28.马匹保险公司。资本金：200万。

29.出口羊毛制品，并进口铜、黄铜以及铁的公司。资本金：400万。

30.建立一个宏伟的救治站的公司。资本金：300万。

31.建立工厂，并购买铅矿的公司。资本金：200万。

32.改进肥皂制造技术公司。

33.有关在圣克鲁兹岛定居事业的公司。

34.在德比郡挖矿井，以及精炼铅矿的公司。

35.制作玻璃瓶子及其他玻璃制品的公司。

36.生产永动轮的公司。资本金：100万。

37.改善花园公司。

38.保证并提高儿童的财富的公司。

39.在海关装货以及为商人协商贸易的公司。

40.在英格兰北部进行羊毛生产的公司。

41.从弗吉尼亚进口胡桃树的公司，资本金：200万。

42.用线和棉花制作有曼彻斯特特色材料的公司。

43.制造具有雅法[8]和卡斯提尔[9]特色的肥皂的公司。

44.改善这个王国的钢铁制造业的公司。资本金：400万。

45.进行花边、荷兰麻布、麻纱，以及细麻等交易的公司。资本金：200万。

46.负责这个王国生产的某些商品的交易和改善以及其他方面的公司。资本金：300万。

47.为伦敦市场提供牲畜的公司。

48.制作穿衣镜、马车镜以及其他种类镜子的公司。资本金：200万。

49.在康沃尔和德比郡加工锡矿和铅矿的公司。

50.生产油菜油的公司。

51.进口海狸皮的公司。资本金：200万。

52.生产厚纸板和包装纸的公司。

53.进口在羊毛制造业中所需要的油及其他材料的公司。

54.改进丝织业并提高产量的公司。

55.以股票、养老金、记账以及其他的方式借钱的公司。

56.以小额折扣，向寡妇及其他人发放津贴的公司。资本金：200万。

57.改进麦芽酒公司。资本金：400万。

58.建立宏伟的美国渔业公司。

59.购买并改善林肯郡沼泽地的公司。资本金：200万。

60.改进大不列颠纸制造业的公司。

61.冒险借贷公司。

62.用热空气烘干麦芽的公司。

63.要在奥鲁诺克河上进行贸易的公司。

64.在科尔切斯特及大不列颠的其他地方，更有效地制作粗呢的公司。

65.购买松脂制品、提供粮食，并为工人发工资的公司。

66.雇佣贫穷的技工，为商人及其他人提供保镖的公司。

67.提高耕作质量，改善牲畜品种的公司。

68.另一个改善马匹育种的公司。

69.又一个为马投保的公司。

70.开展大不列颠谷物贸易的公司。

71.为所有的佣人可能给男女主人带来的损失投保的公司。资本金：300万。

72.建立房屋和医院，接收和抚养私生子的公司。资本金：200万。

73.不用火，不用损失材料的粗糖漂白公司。

74.在大不列颠建立收费关卡和收费码头的公司。

75.针对盗窃和抢劫的保险公司。

76.从铅中提取银的公司。

77.制作瓷器和荷兰代夫特陶器的公司。资本金：100万。

78.进口烟草，然后，再把它出口到瑞典和北欧的公司。资本金：400万。

79.用煤矿井制铁的公司。

80.给伦敦和威斯敏斯特提供干草和稻草的公司，资本金：300万。

81.在爱尔兰制作帆布和包装布的公司。

82.生产压舱物的公司。

83.购买并装配镇压海盗的船只的公司。

84.从威尔士进口木材的公司。资本金：200万。

85.岩盐制作公司。

86.把水银转换成可锻造的纯金属的公司。

除了这些泡沫公司外，天天都有大批新的公司涌现，政府的指责和理智者的嘲弄都丝毫不起作用。印刷所里满是对这些铺天盖地的蠢事的讽刺画，报纸上也都是极具讽刺意味的名言警句。有一个天才的扑克牌制造商发行了一套南海公司的扑克牌，这种扑克牌现在已经很少见了。每一张牌上除了通常的数字外，在一个角上，有一个小尺寸的泡沫公司的讽刺画，并且在讽刺画的下面配有相应的诗句。生产圆形和方形炮弹和子弹的帕扣机器公司完全颠覆了战争的形式，是著名的泡沫公司之一。它迎合公众口味的虚伪和做作言行在黑桃8这张牌上，做了如下总结：

稀世发明，毁灭了

国内的傻瓜，而不是国外的。

但是，我的朋友不要担心，

这个可恶的机器，

只有在这个机器上有股份的人才会受到伤害。

红心9是讽刺英国黄铜公司的漫画，并配有下面的警句：

那个鲁莽的傻瓜，想做金银交易，

却换来了英国的黄铜，

在交易所里，他的愚蠢会被证明，

用贵重的金属换来掺假的烂铜。

方块8用下面的打油诗讽刺殖民阿卡迪亚的公司：

有个愚蠢的富人想一掷千金，

挥霍之地选在北美；

让他去认购股票吧！

只有傻瓜才不会将他耻笑！

每副扑克牌以类似的方式揭露那些欺诈的计划，并嘲笑那些上当受骗的人。据计算，进行这些计划的总资金应超过3亿英镑。

然而，是时候回到之前的话题，继续讲讲吞没了成千上万贪婪者与轻信者的财富的南海公司。5月29日，股价上升到500英镑，2/3的领取政府养老金的人把国债券换成了南海公司的股票。整个5月份，股价持续上升，28号的报价是550英镑。4天之后，股价惊人地从550英镑飙升到890英镑。此时此刻，公众普遍认为股价不会继续上升，所以，许多人利用这个机会卖出，以期实现他们的利润。坐在火车里陪国王去汉诺威的许多贵族及其他人也都急于卖出。6月3日在交易所里，卖家蜂拥而至，买家屈指可数。就这样，股价一下子从890降到了640。董事们震惊了，命令他们的代理人去购买。他们的努力成功了。傍晚时分，信心回升，股价又升到了750英镑。随后股价稳定下来，仅有小幅波动，直到公司于6月22日休市。

没有必要也没有趣味去详细描述董事们用于提升股价的不同技巧。根据8月初的报价，股票的价格最终抬升至原来的10倍，阐明这一点便足以说明一切。泡沫涨到了极限，开始了破裂前的颤抖和摇晃。

许多领取政府年金的人表达了对董事们的不满，指责他们在股票认购的同时列示股份清单的做法。当公众得知董事长约翰·布朗特爵士已经全部卖出的时候，更大的不安发生了。整个8月，股价一直下跌，到9月2日，报价只有700英镑。

情况变得十分令人担忧。为了防止公众对他们的事业完全丧失信心，董事们于9月8日在泰勒商人大厅召开全公司参加的常规会议。上午九点钟，房间人满为患。齐普赛街上挤满了无法进入房间的人，人群里的激动情绪无法抑制。董事们和他们的朋友们群集在那里。副董事长约翰·弗罗斯爵士被叫到了董事的位置。他向公众解释了他们开会的原因，宣读了董事会的几项决定，并陈述了他们的计划：他们要收回可赎回及不可赎回基金，以及以现金认购股票。秘书长克莱格斯作了简短的演讲，在演讲中他肯定了董事们的做法，并且强调说内部团结是完善计划最有效的方式。演讲结束时，他表达了对董事会的谢意。感谢他们谨慎而有技巧的管理，并希望他们继续以这种方式管理公司以达到公司利益最大化。代表南海公司利益的亨格福德先生在下议院出尽了风头；人们认为他知道卖出股票的正确时机，是个不折不扣的赢家；因此，在今天这个场合，他不免夸夸其谈。他说他见过大风大浪，许多集团沉浮起落；但是，在他看来，没有任何一个团体能像南海公司那样，在那么短的时间内将事情做得那么完美。他们的所作所为超过了王室、教会和法院。他们把所有不同团体的利益统一起来；虽然没有做到完全消灭，但是他们平息了这个民族所有的人与人之间的矛盾和敌意。在他们的股票增长的过程中，有钱人的财富急剧增长；乡绅看到他们土地的价值在他们的手里双倍甚至三倍地增长。同时，他们的事业也让教堂受益匪浅，很多尊敬的牧师也通过这个计划得到了大笔财富。总之，他们让整个国家都富了起来；此外，他还说他希望这些人不要忘了同时也让自己富有起来。在此番演讲的后半部分，人群中发出不屑一顾的嘶嘶声，无疑是对这种过度赞扬的讽刺。但是，董事们和他们的朋友们，以及在这间屋子里的所有的赢利者都给予了热烈的掌声。波特兰公爵也随声附和，并且对于有些人不满意这个事实表达出极大的震惊。当然他通过投机赚了钱，这种情形简直就是重现了那个老掉牙的笑话：一个胖议员在酒足饭饱之后总是习惯把手放在自己的大肚子上，然后对天下竟然还有饥荒表示出极大的怀疑。

会上通过了几项决议，但是这些决议都对公众毫无影响。在同一天晚上，股票跌到了650；翌日，跌到了540。它的股票就这样一天天跌下去，直到400。9月13日，国会议员布罗德里克先生写给米德尔顿大法官一封信，这封信后来在考克斯沃波尔出版社发表。信中，国会议员说：“有关为什么南海公司的董事们那么早就笼罩在破产的阴云的猜想各式各样。我可以肯定的是，只要是他们觉得有利可图的事，他们肯定会去做。他们对信用的过度使用超出了它的承受范围，最终，信用状况极度恶化，储备货币已难以支撑。最举足轻重的人退出了，保证了自己资金的安全；而那些被欺骗的头脑简单的大众却全都血本无归。这些人的思想被贪欲控制，他们希望金钱的小土丘可以变成高耸入云的大山。成千上万的家庭沦为赤贫。惊愕无法表达，愤怒难以名状。整个事情让人绝望透顶。我从来没有见过专门为转嫁危机而制定计划，所以，我不得不猜测下一步要做什么。”10天之后，股价持续下跌，他写道：“公司还没有作出决定，因为他们身处丛林之中，不知何去何从。通过最近来镇上的几位绅士，我观察到‘南海公司人’这个名字本身在各个国家已经为人们深恶痛绝。很多金匠已经被迫逃跑了，而且每天都继续有更多的人在逃跑。我怀疑他们当中是否有1/3，不，1/4的人能够经受得住这场灾难。从一开始，我对整个事态的判断建立在那个毫无疑问的原则基础之上，即，1000万现金（这个数字已经远远超过经济运行中的实际现金总额）难以支撑2000万的实体经济正常运转，否则，纸币的信用状况就会恶化。所以，无论何时，只要这一点变得不确定，无论原因如何，我们尊贵的国家机器必会摔得粉身碎骨。”

9月12日，在秘书长克莱格斯的恳求下，南海公司的董事们和银行的董事们举行了几次会议。据传，英国银行同意购买南海公司600万债券，这一消息导致股票急升到670；但是，在下午，人们得知这个消息并不靠谱；于是，股票又跌到了580，第二天570，然后渐渐跌到了400。[10]

政府内阁对事态的发展极为震惊。人们诅咒出现在街头的每一个公司董事，以宣泄心中的愤怒，政府担心时刻都有爆发动乱的危险。特使被派到汉诺威急请国王返回。南海公司派人去请当时在乡间别墅休假的沃波尔先生，希望他利用自己在英格兰银行的董事中的影响力，劝说他们接受为南海公司发行一些债券的建议。

英格兰银行十分不情愿搅进南海公司这摊浑水，因为它害怕让自己陷入无法逃脱的灾难；因此，对于收到的所有提议，它明确表示了自己不情愿的态度；但是，全国上下一致呼吁它出手相救。所有的商界名人都被召来商议如何应对眼下的紧急情况。最后，由沃波尔先生草拟合同作为进一步协商的基础。至此，公众的惊慌才稍微有所平息。

第二天，也就是9月20日，南海公司在泰勒商人大厅召开股东大会，会议作出了几项决定。决定授权董事们与英格兰银行或其他人，就发行公司债券一事达成协议；或者，和银行达成他们认为合适的其他协议。一位叫普尔特尼的先生说，最让人震惊的就是笼罩人们的极度恐慌情绪。人们在惊慌和恐惧中来回奔走，他们的想象中充满了灾难，而这个灾难的形式和规模却无人知晓：

像夜晚，漆黑无边——

像怒火，熊熊燃烧——

像地狱，让人毛骨悚然。

两天后，英国银行举行了股东大会。会上，董事长通知了有关南海公司事件的几次会议的内容，并且指出，董事们还未就此事达成一致意见。会上提出一项决议，并获得一致通过。决议授权董事们与南海公司达成协议，为其发行债券。发行的数量、条件和时间由银行董事们自行掌握。

这样，双方都得以按照他们认为对公众最有利的方式行事。为恢复政府信誉，英格兰银行以15%的定金、3%的保险费和5%的利息认购300万英镑南海公司债券。一大早，人们带着钱急切地赶到广场上，人数之多让人认为债券会被一抢而空。但是，中午前，形势逆转。尽管为防止股票继续下跌作出了所有的努力，但是，南海公司的股票还是急剧下降。他们的债券已没有任何信誉。一些有名的金匠和银行家担心以南海公司股票的形式贷出的巨大款项无法变现，现在不得不关门避债，溜之大吉。南海公司一直以来的承兑商剑锋公司也停止付款。然而，这仅仅是不幸的开端。银行也挤满了兑现的人群，付钱的速度远远快于它上午发售债券时收钱的速度。因为接下来的一天是休息日（9月29日），银行才有稍作喘息的机会。英格兰银行勇敢地面对风暴，但是，他们的前对手南海公司，却被这场暴风雨摧毁了。他们的股票降到了150；而且，渐渐地，几经波动之后，降到了135。

银行发现他们无法恢复公众的信念，也无法阻止毁灭的潮流；所以，为了避免和他们意欲救助的对象一起被彻底毁灭的风险，他们拒绝实施他们本已开始介入的协议。他们没有任何义务，因为，所谓的银行合同只不过是草拟的协议而已。协议中的几项重要细节尚未确定，而且，协议条款中没有针对银行退出行为的惩罚项。杂志《议会历史》这样形容当时的情形：“就这样，在8个月的时间内，人们目睹了这个庞然大物的崛起、兴盛和倒塌。它由一根上足发条的神秘弹簧带到令人炫目的高空，吸引了整个欧洲的眼球和期待；但是，它的地基建立在欺骗、幻觉、轻信和痴迷之上，这就决定了董事们的阴谋诡计一旦暴露，整座建筑必定顷刻坍塌。”

在南海计划如日中天的时候，在这个危险的欺骗进行的过程中，全国上下礼义廉耻顿失。议会着手调查行为不轨者，以揭露恶行的真相；而这，无论是对于犯罪者的道德标准，还是对于滋生恶行的人的智力水平，都是一种侮辱。探讨恶果是一项很有趣的研究。就像人一样，一个国家如果成为了孤注一掷的赌徒，它必会受到惩罚，惩罚的到来只不过是或迟或早的事而已。一位享有盛名的作家斯莫利特说：“这是一个不讨历史学家喜欢的年代。这些交易的细节不能给那些多情而充满想象力的读者带来任何激情或兴趣；因为，这些交易里没有温暖、没有色彩，也没有装饰。这些细节所展示的无非是一幅充满没滋没味的恶行和卑鄙低劣的堕落的单调画卷。”然而，他说错了，事实恰恰相反。如果斯莫利特曾经身临其境的话，他一定会发现这一点——这个主题对于人们兴趣的激发甚至能够满足小说家的渴望。在被掠夺的人的绝望里，难道没有温暖吗？在由成千上万个因此变得赤贫，并被毁灭的家庭的苦难绘就的画卷里，没有生机和活力吗？昨日膏粱，今日乞丐；昨日位高权重，今日流浪街头；每一个角落里都回响着自责和诅咒之声。所有的这一切都毫无生机可言吗？一个民族突然间全体摆脱了理智的束缚，向着一个金灿灿的前景狂奔，并且固执地拒绝承认这个前景是不存在的；直到，就像一只追逐鬼火的小鹿一样，陷入沼泽地，无法自拔。这个场景很枯燥，很没有教育意义吗？然而，历史就是在这种错误思想的指导下写就的。历史学家绞尽脑汁、极尽巧言之能事，一遍遍描述不称职的朝臣使用伎俩获得更不称职的国王的欢心；或者，不厌其烦地重复战斗围攻的凶残场面；而那些真正深刻影响人们的道德行为和生活福祉的事情，却被他们忽略了。这些事情只被当作枯燥无趣，没有任何温暖和色彩的材料搁置脑后了。

在这个举世闻名的泡沫经济时代，英国呈现出了一幅非同寻常的景象。公众的头脑处于病态的高涨状态。人们不再满足于通过脚踏实地的辛勤劳动去获得稳定的利益。对于明天无尽财富的希望让今天的他们变得这样没头没脑和骄奢淫逸。伴随前所未闻的奢华而来的是道德的放纵。那些由赌博获胜而一夜暴富的文盲摆出一副不可一世的样子。这让那些无论思想还是举止都极具绅士风度的人感到很羞耻，因为他突然意识到黄金竟然可以让身份卑微、品性恶劣之人骤然变得貌似尊贵。理查德·斯蒂尔爵士称这群人为“精打细算的平民”。他们的傲慢在霉运来临之时成为对自己不利的因素。在议会调查的过程中，董事们往往因其傲慢而非侵吞公款，受到惩罚。在这些愚蠢之极的富人当中，有一个曾经以不可一世的傲慢神情说他要拿金子喂他的马，结果却沦落到了只能拿水和面包勉强充饥的地步。每一个傲慢的表情和每一番盛气凌人的言谈都被毫不留情地压制下去，还之以百倍的贫穷和侮辱。

全国的事态让人惊恐不已。乔治一世不得不提前结束了在汉诺威的访问，匆匆赶回英国。他11月11日到达，议会于12月8日召开。同时，公众集会在全国所有的重要城镇召开。会议通过了人们请立法机构惩罚南海公司董事的请求，原因是这些董事用欺诈行为将整个国家带到了毁灭的边缘。没有人会想到国家本身和南海公司的罪责其实相同；没有人去指责大众的轻信和贪婪——这个让人堕落的获取欲吞噬了国民性格中所有的高贵品质；也没有人去指责大众的痴迷，这种痴迷情绪让他们义无反顾地、疯狂而急切地一头扎进诡计多端的谋划者为他们准备好的网。这些因素从未被人提起。所有的故事只是，民众是淳朴的、朴实的、勤勉的；他们被一伙强盗毁灭了；所以，这伙强盗要毫不留情地被绞死、被开膛破肚、被车裂。

这种感觉几乎笼罩了全国上上下下所有的人。议会两院并没有作出比公众更理智的判断。在南海公司董事的罪责明确之前，惩罚是唯一能够听得到的呐喊。国王登上御座发表庄重的演讲，他希望找到走出苦难的出路并马上付诸实施；而做到这一点，必须要谨慎小心、冷静沉着并且坚决果断。在回应国王讲话的辩论中，几位发言人对设计南海计划的董事们极尽辱骂之能事。莫尔斯沃思勋爵的言辞尤其激烈，“有人说没有法律来惩罚那些制造国家灾难的南海公司的董事。在他看来，在这件事情的处理上，他们应该效法古罗马。在古罗马，没有惩罚弑父杀母罪的法律，因为立法者不相信会有让罪恶之手沾满父亲鲜血的不孝之子。当这个罪行出现的时候，他们立即制定了相关法律来惩罚这种滔天罪行。他们把这个十恶不赦的罪恶之子放在扎紧口的麻袋里，然后，把他活活扔进台伯河。他认为罪恶的南海计划的策划者和执行者就是国家的杀父仇人，他必要亲眼看到他们以同样的方式被装进麻袋，扔进泰晤士河，方解心头之恨。其他人员的讲话一样没有节制且缺乏考虑。沃波尔先生的讲话要理智得多。他建议说当务之急是恢复政府信誉：“如果伦敦着火了，所有的聪明人肯定都是先急着救火，以防止火势蔓延，然后再去找纵火犯。政府信誉已经被刺得遍体鳞伤，鲜血淋漓，所以，人们应该尽快地给予治疗。惩罚刺客的事情稍后进行，时间完全来得及。”12月9日，就回应国王演讲的请愿陈词，人们达成了一致意见。陈词中特别补充并强调了如下内容：众议院不仅要寻求治愈国家灾难的良方，更要惩罚始作俑者。

调查进展迅速。众议院勒令董事们详细交代他们计划进程的每一个细节，最终，达成了一致意见并作出决定，即，灾难的产生源于股票经纪人卑鄙下流的手段，制定法律来阻止这种龌龊行为的再次发生是恢复政府信誉的最佳途径。这时，沃波尔先生起身说，正像他先前暗示的那样，他花了一些时间来研究恢复政府信誉的计划，但是这个计划的成功实施必须以一个条件作为基础。他认为，在他公布计划之前，他还是要首先确定他是否有这个可以依赖的基础条件。这个条件就是：在当前情况下，原来和南海公司签署的国债申购单、不动产申购单、货币申购单以及其他相关合约是否仍旧具有法律效力？这个问题引起了激烈的讨论。最后，以259比117的比例通过决议——这些合同仍旧有效，只有在以解脱持有者为目的的情况下，可以由南海公司董事会更改，或者通过法定程序撤销。第二天，沃波尔先生就向众议院展示了他恢复政府信誉的计划。他的计划的本质就是在一定的条件下把南海公司900万的股票转给英格兰银行，把同样数目的股票转给东印度公司。这个计划得到了众议院的一致赞成。几乎毫无异议，众议院要求两大公司对此事作出回应并拿出具体计划。它们都不愿伸出援助之手，在以商讨此事为目的召集的董事会上，援助计划遭遇了比较激烈的反对，但是反对无效。他们最终同意了发行南海公司债券的计划。他们的报告一经呈现给委员会，相应法案立即成立；在沃波尔先生的监督下，法案在议会两院顺利通过。

同时，委员会还提交了一项法案。法案禁止南海公司的董事、董事长、副董事长、财政主管、出纳员以及所有职员在12个月内离开英国；另外，法案还规定查明他们的房产和财产以防他们将其转移或转让。众议院最有影响的议员均支持本项法案。希彭先生相信克莱格斯部长和南海公司事件有染的传闻；所以，当他看到克莱格斯部长先生在他的座位上的时候，就决定要触其要害。他说他很高兴看到大不列颠众议院又恢复了往日的精神和元气，又可以全体一心一意地为公众福祉服务了。限制南海公司董事和官员并收押财产是必要的，“但是，”他补充道，“身居高位的其他人和南海公司的董事们一样罪孽深重，而他会在合适的时候直言不讳地指出这个人的名字。”克莱格斯先生怒不可遏，他站起来说如果这种冷嘲热讽之语是针对他而言，他将给质问他的人以满意的答复，无论是在议院内还是议院外。恢复秩序的呼声顿时从每一个角落响起。在这阵喧嚣声中，莫尔斯沃思站了起来并表示他很惊讶于克莱格斯竟然有如此胆量来挑战整个众议院。年过60的莫尔斯沃思确实有点老了，但是，在议会内他仍旧会回应克莱格斯先生，不管需要他说的是什么；而在议会外，他相信有足够多的年轻人会和他站在一边，毫无畏惧地直视克莱格斯先生。恢复秩序的声音又从四周响起，所有议员同时站起，似乎所有的人都同时在大呼小叫。试图恢复秩序的人只能在那里徒劳地呼喊。混乱持续了几分钟；在此期间，几乎只有莫尔斯沃思爵士和克莱格斯先生坐在自己的位置上。最后，针对克莱格斯先生的呼声变得异常激烈，这使他不得不意识到顺应众议院的普遍民意才是比较明智的选择；所以，他随后解释了自己不合时宜的表达。他解释道，他所说的让众议院中怀疑他行为的人满意，不是指他要和人打架，而是说他要解释他的行为。这件事情到此结束。众议院继续商议他们应该以什么样的方式对南海公司事件进行调查：是常设委员会还是特别委员会。最后，由13人组成的特别委员会成立，拥有调遣人员、文件和记录的权力。

上下两院的议员们都激愤难平、心如刀绞。罗切斯特主教说这项计划就像一场瘟疫。沃顿公爵说众议院无需再去考虑尊重当事人的问题。如果是他，即便是最好的朋友参与了此项计划，他也会毫不留情地把他抛弃。整个国家都陷入了羞愧难当、愤愤不平的状态，如果他可以像人一样做事，他对犯罪者的惩罚必定像其他人一样，绝不姑息。斯坦霍普勋爵说，罪犯拥有的每一分钱都应该充公以弥补公众的损失，无论这个人是否是董事。

在此期间，公众情绪一直处于高涨状态。我们从考克斯的沃波尔得知南海公司董事这个名字已经成为欺骗和罪恶的代名词。来自全国各郡、市、区的请愿书纷至沓来，无不呼吁还受伤的民族以正义，给挪用公款的罪犯以惩罚。那些在惩罚罪犯方面态度中立而不愿走极端的人被控告为同谋。在无尽的侮辱和恶意的谩骂中，这些人被匿名信或公开信控告，成为这个受伤的民族急速复仇的牺牲品。控告财政大臣艾斯拉比先生以及财政部另一官员克莱格斯先生的呼声如此强烈，以至于上议院决定立即着手对他们进行调查。1月21日，政府命令所有和南海公司计划有关的经纪人须将他们自1719年米迦勒节以来为财政部官员买卖、认购或代管的股票记录悉数呈给众议院。根据上交记录，大量的股票被转到艾斯拉比先生名下。包括著名历史学家[11]的祖父爱德华·吉本先生在内的5位南海公司董事被上院的黑杖侍卫拘留看管。经斯坦霍普伯爵示意，及全体一致同意，议会作出如下决定：在增加或减少股票面值时，凡没有实际支付与受益价值相等的利润的行为；南海公司的董事或经纪人，凡在南海公司法案在议会尚未通过期间，为任何政府官员或国会议员购买股票的行为，均被认为是情节严重、影响恶劣的腐败行为。几天后，通过了另一项决议，内容是几名公司董事或官员秘密地将他们的股票贩卖给公司，犯下了欺骗罪和失信罪。他们的行为导致了整个事态转向不利于政府信誉的方向。艾斯拉比先生辞去财政大臣的职位，直到立法机关正式调查他的个人罪行，他才再次在议会露面。

同时，知晓公司不轨董事所有危险秘密的公司财务主管奈特把所有的书籍和文件打包后逃离了英国。他乔装打扮上了河上的一只小船，驶向专门租用的一艘大船，之后安全抵达法国加来。保密委员会通知了众议院这个情况，众人当即决定应该给国王递交两个申请：第一个申请希望国王发表声明，悬赏缉拿奈特；第二个申请是国王须立即下令封锁所有港口，并依法监管所有海岸，以防奈特之流或其他南海公司官员逃出英国。申请上的字迹尚未干透，就由众议院专门委派的梅修恩先生送到了国王手里。当天晚上国王即发布了皇家声明，悬赏2000英镑缉拿奈特。众议院议员命令紧锁众议院大门并把钥匙放在桌子上。保密委员会的成员之一罗斯将军告诉大家说他们已经发现了一系列只有恶魔能想到的、用来毁灭一个国家的、最为罪孽深重的邪恶和欺骗行为。在适当的时候，他们会将之公布给众议院。同时，为了进一步发现真相，保密委员会认为很有必要拘留南海公司的一些董事和重要官员并查封他们的资料。此示意一经提出，便得到全体同意并立即执行。众议院议员罗伯特·卓别林爵士、希欧多尔·詹森爵士、索布里奇先生、弗·艾尔斯先生和南海公司的董事们被传唤到位，并要求对他们的腐败行为作出解释。希欧多尔·詹森爵士和索布里奇先生在被传唤时，努力为自己辩解。众议院耐心倾听他们的解释，然后命令他们退出。随即，一项提议提出并马上获得全体一致通过。提议内容为：他们犯有尽人皆知的违反信托罪，这一罪行让国王的许多臣民们损失惨重，让政府信誉蒙羞。因为他们的罪行，众议院随即下达命令，将他们驱逐出众议院并由武装士兵关押。4天后，罗伯特·卓别林爵士和艾尔斯先生在出席议会时，同样被驱逐出众议院。同时，众议院决定请求国王给驻外大使下令，命令他们如果发现奈特逃往他们所在的国家，一定要将他交给英国政府。国王立即同意，当夜，使节们就被派往了欧洲大陆的各个国家。

在被关押的董事当中有约翰·布朗特爵士，人们普遍认为是他一手设计并实施了南海计划。蒲伯在写给巴瑟斯特的勋爵艾伦的信中说，此人自称是个伟大的信徒，行动上也极其符合宗教规范，但实际上却是个不折不扣的异教徒。他总是猛烈抨击这个时代的奢华和腐败、议会的偏袒不公和党派的软弱。在贬斥身份显赫的贵族的贪婪时，他的抨击尤其猛烈。起初，他只是个抄写员，后来不仅成了南海公司的董事，而且成为公司最活跃的管理人。他是否是在这个职位上开始抨击权贵们的贪婪，我们不得而知。可以肯定的是，他所看到的贪婪行为足以证实他这些最严厉的诅咒绝对不失公允。但是，如果这位批判者本人没有犯下他所控诉的那些罪行的话，他的高谈阔论或许会取得更好的效果。在关押期间，他被带到上议院的法庭，并经历了长时间的审查。在此期间，他拒绝回答几个重要的问题。他说他已经被众议院的某个委员会调查过了，并且已经不记得他的回答内容了，为了避免自相矛盾，他拒绝在另一个法庭上回答同样的问题。此番言论即是犯罪的间接证明，在上议院引起了一阵喧闹。当上议院又一次以强硬的态度问及他是否曾将部分股票卖给政府或议会两院的议员以加速法案的通过时，他再次拒绝回答。他说，他对上议院诚惶诚恐，但是，被迫指控自己，他很难做到。几番让他恢复记忆的尝试失败后，议会命令他退下。随后，内阁的支持者和反对者之间进行了一场激烈的讨论。有人声称，政府对约翰·布朗特爵士这种得心应手的沉默早已见怪不怪。沃顿公爵把矛头指向了斯坦霍普伯爵，这令后者异常气愤。伯爵说话时情绪高涨，这种过分激烈的情绪导致他大脑充血。他感觉十分糟糕，不得不离开议院大厅到他自己的房间内休息。人们立即使用吸杯为他放血，第二天早晨继续放血，但是收效甚微。人们对这个致命的结果始料未及。傍晚时分，他开始昏迷，然后就仰面朝天，与世长辞了。这位政治家的突然死亡让全国上下陷入极大的悲痛之中。乔治一世极为伤感，他把自己关在房间里，为失去这位伟大的人物伤心不已。

公司的财务主管奈特在列日附近的蒂利蒙，被居住在布鲁塞尔的英国人里斯先生的一个秘书抓捕，随后被关在安特卫普城堡内。英国政府多次向奥地利政府申请将他押送回国，但都没有成功。奈特将自己置于布拉班特领地的保护之下，并要求在此地受审。《皇家条目》（Joyeuse Entrée [12]）的条款授予布拉班特领地的特权规定：在此地逮捕的罪犯应该就地审判。领地坚持他们的特权并拒绝把奈特交给英国政府。英国政府不停地诉求。在此期间，奈特从城堡逃跑了。

2月16日，保密委员会向众议院递交了他们的第一份调查报告。在报告中，他们表示他们的调查遇到了很多的困难和挫折。他们所努力调查的每一个人都尽自己最大努力不让法官达到目的。在他们调查的一些账目中，虚假款项被伪造；而在另外一些账目中，有款项，却无股票持有者姓名。在一些账目中有很多擦除和修改的痕迹；在另一些中，有的页面被撕掉。他们还发现一些重要的账目已经被悉数销毁，一些被撕掉或隐藏。在调查之初，他们发现交给他们的事情范围广大，种类繁多。在执行法律的过程中，许多人被分配了不同的任务。在处理成千上万的人高达上百万甚至上千万的财产时，他们不得不借法律之名，以并不合法的方式进行。他们发现在南海法案通过之前，南海公司账面价值1259325英镑已经贬为以股票计价的市场价值574500英镑。经调查，这些股票均为蓄意伪造，其操作目的是为了加速法案的通过。根据标记，这些股票在不同时间，以150%到325%的溢价售出。这么一大笔交易发生在授权公司增股之前，这让委员会十分震惊；因此，他们决定要十分仔细地考察整个交易过程。董事长、副董事长和几位董事都被带到委员会面前加以严格审问。他们发现，这些账目被制作的时候，公司并没有相当数量的股票，他们所拥有的只是最多不超过3万英镑的一小笔资金。在进一步调查的过程中，他们发现，这些股票被公司伪装成的购买商购买，同时，股票交易中没有任何形式的双方协议、现金支付、保证金或证券。他们的如意算盘是，如果法案没有通过，股票如预期的那样下跌，公司自然不用承担任何损失。相反，如果股价上升（计划成功后，事实确实如此），由股价上升带来的利润必然使他们收益。按照这个思路，在法案通过之后，根据奈特的指示，公司设立并调整了股票账户。那些假定的购买者由于股价的上升，从南海公司得到了收益。这些伪造的股票主要由约翰·布朗特爵士、吉本先生和奈特先生处理；他们以行贿的方式，将这些股票赠送给政府的几名官员及其亲属，以求加速法案的通过。在这些股票中，桑德兰伯爵得到5万英镑，肯德尔公爵夫人得到1万英镑，普拉滕伯爵夫人得到1万英镑，她的两个侄子得到1万英镑，克莱格斯秘书长得到3万英镑，查尔斯·斯坦霍普先生（财政部秘书之一）得到1万英镑，剑锋公司得到5万英镑。在调查的过程中，他们还发现斯坦霍普先生从特纳卡斯沃尔公司收到了25万英镑的股票差价收益，但是，他的名字被从账簿上删除，后改为斯坦盖普。财政大臣艾斯拉比获利的方式更加让人厌恶。他在特纳卡斯沃尔公司开立了一个高达794451英镑的股票账户。此外，他还建议公司在没有任何担保的情况下，自行将第二批新股认购金额由100万英镑提高到150万英镑。第三次发行的方式尤其可耻。艾斯拉比名下7万英镑，克莱格斯先生名下65.9万英镑，桑德兰伯爵16万英镑，斯坦霍普先生4.7万英镑。这个报告完成之后，又有6个其他不太重要的报告。在最后一个报告的末尾，委员会宣布因为没有找到在此案中负有重要责任的奈特，他们的调查无法再继续。

委员会命令，在第三天将第一份报告印刷出来并进行讨论。经过愤怒而激烈的讨论，达成了一系列协议，协议谴责董事、议会成员及与之相关的行政官员的行为。通过协议，委员会宣布这些人中的每一个都应该用他们自己的财产去弥补他们给公众造成的损失和伤害。他们的所作所为被定性为腐败、无耻和危险的行为。为了解除不幸者的痛苦，委员会命令引入一项法案。

查尔斯·斯坦霍普参与了这些交易并第一个受到了质问。在他的自我辩解中，他强调，在过去的几年里，他把他所拥有的所有钱都寄存到了奈特先生那里，所以，无论奈特先生为他买了多少股票，他已经提前付清了所需的款项。至于特纳卡斯沃尔公司为他所买的股票，他本人一无所知，这件事情中所做的一切都未经过他的授权，所以，他不可能为其负责。特纳公司承担了第二件事情的责任。但是，每一个怀着公正之心的人都知晓这不光彩的事实：斯坦霍普先生得到了25万英镑，并且，以他的名义放在南海公司的账户上。但是，最后以超过3票的微弱优势，他被无罪释放了。友人不遗余力地袒护他，切斯特菲尔德伯爵的儿子，斯坦霍普勋爵在态度摇摆的议员之间游说。他用自己的三寸不烂之舌劝说他们投票释放他或者不出席议会。许多优柔寡断的乡绅被他说服并改变了主意，由此产生了上述结果。无罪释放斯坦霍普的消息在全国引起了极大的不满。气势汹汹的大众聚集在伦敦各处。人们对于发生暴乱的恐惧与日俱增。当许多人认为，对于一个更大的罪犯的审讯很可能会是类似斯坦霍普的结局时，这种担心就更加严重了。即便当地的规则不健全，身居高位、肩负重任的艾斯拉比先生本应以诚实为本；但是，他却被认为是不折不扣的最大的罪犯。释放斯坦霍普先生的第二天，对他的案件的调查正式开始。众议院的大厅里和通道上挤满了人，人人都迫不及待地想知道调查的结果。辩论持续了整整一天。艾斯拉比几乎找不到支持者。他的罪过昭然若揭，而且让人深恶痛绝，没有人有勇气和他站到一边。最后议会达成一致意见：艾斯拉比先生为了获得非法利益，怂恿并推进了损害国家和公众利益的南海公司计划的执行；在这些损人利己的犯罪行为中，他和南海公司的董事们同流合污，损害了国家的贸易和声誉；因为他所犯下的无耻罪行，他被逐出众议院，收监伦敦塔，并被严密监视；一年之内或直到下次议会召开，他不得出国；他应该清算他所有的财产，用以解救那些因为他的恶行而惨遭损失的人。

这个裁决让人欢欣雀跃。虽然消息在半夜12点半公布，却迅即传遍了全城。几家人张灯结彩以示他们的欢乐。第二天，当艾斯拉比先生被送到伦敦塔的时候，大众聚集在塔山上，准备向他大呼大叫并投掷石块。结果，他们的这个愿望没有实现，于是，他们就点起了一大堆篝火，围着它在无法言说的欢乐里狂舞。几堆篝火在其他的地方也点了起来。伦敦呈现出一派节日景象，全城人共同庆祝，宛如刚刚逃离了一场巨大的灾难。释放斯坦霍普的决定让人们怒不可遏，如果对艾斯拉比先生的裁决也是类似的纵容，很难想象这愤怒将会发展到何种程度。

为了让公众更加满意，任职于特纳卡斯沃尔公司的乔治·卡斯沃尔爵士第二天也被驱逐出议会，囚禁伦敦塔并要求退还25万英镑。

下一步审查的是保密委员会的报告中和桑德兰伯爵有关的部分。为了使他尊贵的身份免受罪责的损害，他的同党作了不遗余力的努力。当不利于他的事实主要来源于约翰·布朗特爵士的口供时，他们费尽心机制造假象，让人觉得约翰爵士的话并不可信，尤其是当这些话指向身居高位的枢密顾问时。众所周知，如果对他作出有罪的判决，那么权力就会落到托利党手中；因此，内阁中所有的朋友都聚集在他的周围，极力保护他的安全。最终，他以233票赞成，172票反对的结果被释放；但是，整个国家对于他的罪行深信不疑。愤怒席卷了每一个角落，气势汹汹的大众又一次聚集在伦敦。所幸，这一次没有暴乱发生。

这一天克莱格斯命丧黄泉。第二天本应是他受审的日子。人们普遍认为他是服毒自尽。但让他痛苦不堪、备受折磨的似乎是5周之前他在财政部任职的儿子死于天花的事实。为了这个宝贝儿子，他聚集了大量的财富。他不停地赚钱，但方式却不正当。为了儿子的利益，他不惜牺牲他的荣誉和名声；然而，儿子却不复存在了。对于事实真相进一步被揭露的恐惧加剧了他内心的苦痛，最终，他在中风痉挛中一命呜呼。他留下了150万英镑的财产。这些财产被充公，用以安抚那些因为他曾不遗余力地创造的那个幻境而惨遭损失的人们。

公司董事一个接一个受到了审查。从他们的财产中共拿出214万英镑充公以弥补他们所造成的伤害。同时，根据每个人的行为和处境，法律允许每个人保留一部分财产以便他们洗心革面，重新做人。在约翰·布朗特爵士多达18.3万英镑的财产中，允许他保留0.5万英镑；约翰·菲罗斯爵士的总财产为24.3万英镑，允许保留1万英镑；希欧多尔·詹森爵士的总财产为24.3万英镑，允许保留5万英镑；爱德华·吉本先生的总财产为10.6万英镑，允许保留1万英镑；约翰·兰伯特爵士的总财产为7.2万英镑，允许保留0.5万英镑。对于其他在本案中参与不多的人的处理方式更加宽松。历史学家吉本的祖父爱德华·吉本先生受到了严重的处罚。这位历史学家在他的《回忆录和写作》中绘声绘色地描述了当时议会的进程。他坦言他并不是一个没有偏见的目击者；但是，凡是对当时灾难之年的进程有所描述的作家都不可避免地对这些受审者带有偏见，而他们的偏见和吉本的观点正好针锋相对；所以，这位历史学家的描述具有特殊的价值。仅仅根据听取双方证词的原则，他的观点是应当被考虑的。他说：“在1716年，我的祖父被选为南海公司的董事之一。他的记录表明在他接受这个致命的职位之前，他已经获得了6万英镑的财产。但是，他的财产在1720年的海难中被淹没。30年的劳动所得在一天内化为乌有。对于他们是利用还是滥用了南海公司计划的分辨，对于我祖父及他的董事同仁们是罪过或是清白的判断，我既不是一个称职的法官也做不到毫无偏袒，但是，现代的公正必须谴责那些充满暴力和武断的审判程序。这些程序足以让正义的事业蒙羞，让不公正的行为更加面目可憎。整个民族刚刚从它的黄金梦中醒来，全体民众，甚至议会就开始为他们的愤怒寻找出气筒。但是，所有的人都承认，无论董事们的罪过有多大，他们都未触及这个国家的现有法律。莫尔斯沃思勋爵处罚当事人的理念十分偏激，议会并没有按照他的理念行事；但是，一个刑罚法案被制定——这是一条追溯法令，用以惩罚在犯罪之时尚未存在的罪行。立法机关拘禁了各位董事，认为他们的出现不利于治安，给他们的人格加上了与生俱来的耻辱的烙印。他们被迫宣誓交出他们所有的财产，并且禁止转移或转让他们财产中的任何部分。每一个公民都有在法庭上通过他的律师申诉的权利，但是，这个刑罚法案显然违反了这一条。他们请求申诉，但是，他们的请求被拒绝了。他们的压迫者不需要证据，当然也不会听取辩护。最初有人提议诸位董事可以保留各自财产的1/8以支撑他们将来的生活。但是，有人坚决主张，由于每个人的富有程度和犯罪程度的不同，这个比例对于许多人来说过轻，而对于一些人来说则又过重。所以，每一个人的情况和行为应该单独考量。但是，33个英国人的财产和荣誉并没有在法庭上得到冷静而严肃的审判；相反，他们成为草率谈话的主题，成为当时大部分人无法无天行为的娱乐对象。委员会最不道德的人用恶言相向或弃权票来发泄他们心中的公愤或私怨。侮辱加重了伤害，玩笑又让侮辱更加痛苦。平均每人20英镑的津贴被随随便便地取消了。有一个捕风捉影的消息说一个董事以前参与过另一个项目，这个项目让一群不知名的人丢掉了他们的钱，而这则消息竟成为给他定罪的实证。一个人惨遭灭顶之灾只是因为他愚蠢而狂放地说他要让他的马以金子为食；另一个遭殃的人，则是因为某一天，生性高傲的他在财政部拒绝礼貌地回答一个地位远远高于他的人的问话。没有出席法庭，没有经过申诉，然后就被谴责，被武断地处以罚金，充公财产，所有相关人都难逃此劫。他们绝大部分的财富就这样被一扫而空。这样无耻而大胆的压迫几乎得不到万能的议会的庇护。我的祖父和他的同伴一样，没有受到任何礼遇。他所秉承的托利党的理念和周围托利党的人脉关系已经让统治者对他厌恶至极。他的名字在一个疑点颇多的秘密报告中出现。他尽人皆知的能力不能成为他不知情或犯错的借口。在最初对南海公司董事的诉讼中，吉本先生成为第一批被拘禁的人之一。在最终宣判时，对他的罚金数额表明了他的罪大恶极。他承诺，除去继承的祖产外，他交付给众议院的总金额高达106543英镑5先令6便士。议会许诺给他1.5万英镑或1万英镑作为生活补贴；但是，经过考虑，议会一致决定给他数额较小的津贴。在这种糟糕的情景中，我的祖父，以偌大的年龄，以议会不能从他那里夺走的技巧和信誉，建起了一座新的财富大厦。16年的辛苦付出终于有了回报。所以，我有理由相信，第二个财富大厦不会比第一个低级。”

完成对董事的处罚之后，立法机构下一步考虑的就是如何恢复政府信誉。事实证明，沃波尔的计划收效甚微，而且声誉不佳。在1720年年底，人们清算了南海公司的股金总额。结果发现，南海公司的股金总额为3780万英镑；而其中为股东所持有的仅为2450万英镑。剩下的1330万英镑为公司以法人形式所有，这一部分是他们利用全民痴迷所赚取的利润。从这一笔钱中抽出了800多万英镑，以100英镑获利33英镑6先令8便士的年息分给了股东和认购者。这极大地缓解了当时的形势。同时，议会进一步下达命令，规定那些从南海公司以股票的形式借钱，同时又将这些钱转给公司或抵押给公司，为公司所用的人，只要付出所借总额的10%，就可以免于其他的要求。当股价飞升之时，南海公司以这种方式借出了1100万；现在，当股价降到了正常水平，他们收回了110万。

但是，政府信誉在很久以后才得以恢复。就像伊卡洛斯[13]一样，人们的信心飞升得太高，融化了他蜡质的翅膀；然后，像伊卡洛斯那样跌进了海里；在海浪中挣扎的时候，他意识到他真正的位置是在坚实的地上。从此，他再也不敢尝试飞那么高了。

自此之后，在商业繁荣的伟大时代，又差点发生几次过度投机的事件。一个计划的成功往往会产生其他几个类似的计划。在一个充满商业交易的国度里，民众的模仿能力总是能够抓住这些成功的典范，然后，把利益的狂热追求者拉进万劫不复的深渊。1825年的泡沫公司，就像南海公司所产生的那些泡沫公司一样，在这个恐慌之年昙花一现后就消失了。这个事件和1720年的事件如出一辙：欺诈之行从贪婪之心那里收获了巨大的利益；但是，当最后的审判日来临之时，双方的损失一样惨重。1836年的计划曾经差点引起灭顶之灾；但是，灾难被及时避免了。[14]

疯狂的慢性投毒犯

佩斯卡拉：我从来没听说过类似的事情。

斯特凡诺：在我看来，如果人们仅仅是听别人讲这个故事，肯定会认为这是最不可能发生的荒谬之事。

佩斯卡拉：确实如此。我将尽可能简单地告诉你他们是如何疯狂到这个地步的。

米兰公爵

投毒罪行从古到今一直存在，并且曾一度形成整套的方法。投毒方式是利用毒药发挥作用过程较慢，让普通的观察者认为受害者是死于身体的逐步衰弱。对此事感兴趣者可以参阅贝克曼有关秘密毒药的著作——《发明史》。在这本书里，他收集了希腊和罗马作家所描写的几个有关事例。16世纪早期，此罪行开始逐渐增多；到了17世纪，它就像一场瘟疫一样，蔓延到了整个欧洲。投毒操作通常由假扮的女巫师或男巫师完成。后来，这个技巧在那些声称具有魔力或超自然力量的人中，成为一个专门的学科。亨利八世21年时通过了一项法案，将此投毒行为定性为严重危害国家罪：犯罪者将被沸水煮死。

在时间上，史无前例；在残暴程度上，亦无出其右者的此类投毒案件是对托马斯·奥弗伯里爵士的谋杀。这件事情发生在1613年，成为当时詹姆斯一世王廷的耻辱。对这件事情的梗概稍作描述，恰好可以让人们对50年后在法国和意大利流行的投毒狂潮略知一二。

苏格兰青年罗伯特·克尔很早就引起了詹姆斯一世的注意；并且，尽人皆知，这个人仅仅凭借他的美貌就享尽了荣耀。即便是在当时，人们也怀疑詹姆斯一世沉迷于最让人鄙视的不轨行为；而在今天，我们越是研究他的历史，这个怀疑就越是强烈。无论这个被怀疑的行为是什么，这位帅气十足的克尔在大庭广众之下让他的皇帝主子亲吻他光滑的脸颊，以这种恶心的方式迅速得宠。1613年他成为苏格兰的王室财政大臣；同时，他还以罗切斯特子爵的身份在英格兰担任同样的官职。不仅如此，无数的荣耀在未来的日子里源源不断地向他涌来。

在他飞黄腾达的过程中，并非无友相助。从国王大臣托马斯·奥弗伯里爵士本人信中的某些线索看，他只是一味地迎合国王的恶习，而且详细了解他秘密从事的所有危险行为。就是他本人竭尽所能，促进克尔的晋升；当然，他从后者那里得到了相应的回报。奥弗伯里对克尔的友谊并不仅限于此，如果这样的两个人之间真的有什么友谊可言的话。他还担当中间人的角色，帮助罗切斯特和埃塞克斯伯爵的妻子弗朗西丝·霍华德夫人通奸。这是一个激情富有到狂野，而羞耻感却无分毫的女人。她的丈夫妨碍了她和罗切斯特的通奸，为了摆脱他，她启动了诉讼离婚程序，离婚的理由是但凡存有些微谦卑或优雅之心的女人宁死也不愿意说出的。她见不得人的诉讼成功了。判决刚刚执行，她和罗切斯特大人规模盛大的婚礼就已准备就绪。

托马斯·奥弗伯里爵士曾经全心全意地帮助他的财神爷和埃塞克斯伯爵夫人私通；而现在，他似乎又认为和这样一个品质下贱的女人结婚将会成为他仕途继续前进的障碍。因此，他便竭尽所能地劝阻克尔选择这个婚姻。但是罗切斯特十分倾心这个结合，他的热情和伯爵夫人的热情一样强烈。一天，当奥弗伯里和罗切斯特子爵在白厅的画廊里散步的时候，有人听见奥弗伯里说：“尊贵的大人，如果您娶了那个卑贱的女人为妻，你将彻底地毁掉你的荣誉和你自己。请听取我的建议，坚决不要这样做。如果你做了，只怕你官位难保，所以，你最好小心为妙。”罗切斯特愤怒地扬袖而去，并且大声发誓道：“这件事情，我会和你算账的！”这些话成为倒霉的奥弗伯里的死刑执行令。他暗示罗切斯特，他可以影响国王，并降低国王对罗的喜欢程度。他努力想阻止一个人熊熊燃烧的激情，而这个人又是这样的没心没肺、放荡不羁，且无所顾忌。这一切致命地打击了罗切斯特的自尊心。

奥弗伯里不知天高地厚的规劝传到了伯爵夫人那里。从那一刻起，她就发誓她一定要给他最致命的报复。但是，因为他们极端的虚伪，两位都隐藏了他们的实际意图。在罗切斯特的请求下，奥弗伯里成为被派往俄罗斯王廷的大使。这个表面上的举荐却是未来深不可测的致命阴谋的第一步。罗切斯特装作十分关心奥弗伯里的利益的样子，建议他拒绝出使这个任务，并且说这只不过是清除他的一个计谋。同时，他许诺他会对付由奥弗伯里的拒绝所带来的一切不良后果。奥弗伯里就这样中了圈套，拒绝了作为使节出使的任务。詹姆斯国王被激怒了，立即将他囚禁到伦敦塔。

现在，他完完全全地被看管着，他的敌人终于有机会开始他们的复仇行动。罗切斯特所做的第一件事情就是通过他在宫廷里的影响，解雇伦敦塔的副主管，并委派他的傀儡杰维斯·艾尔维斯来填补这个空位。这个人只是个工具；为完成复仇计划，另外一个人必不可少，那就是曾经做过药店伙计的理查德·韦斯顿。他被安排在副看守的职位上，直接看管奥弗伯里。至此为止，所有的一切都为阴谋家的计划作好了准备。

同时，阴险狡诈的罗切斯特以最贴心的文字给奥弗伯里写信，信中要他耐心忍受他的不幸，并且许诺他被囚禁的时间不会很长，因为他的朋友们正在竭尽所能平息国王的不快情绪。他照旧装作极度同情他的样子，因此，随信附上了油酥点心和其他的美味作为礼物，而这些东西在伦敦塔里都是得不到的。送给他的这些点心都被下了毒。偶尔，在没有信的时候，也会有类似的礼物送给杰维斯·艾尔维斯，其目的是让人认为这些东西是没有毒的；但是，那位不幸的囚犯却从没有尝过这些没有毒的事物。一个叫作特纳的女人被雇来去获得这些毒药。她曾经有一所声名狼藉的房子，并且不止一次地把它借给罗切斯特和埃塞克斯女士，让他们在那里进行罪恶的通奸勾当。这些药都由假装成朗伯斯区算命先生的福尔曼医生负责准备，协助他准备的是一个叫富兰克林的药剂师。这两个人都知道这些毒药的使用目的。他们巧妙地把毒药混合在油酥点心和其他的食品里，混合的量要小，以便能够渐渐消耗受害人的体质。特纳夫人定期将放了毒药的食品送给副看管，然后，副看管再把他们放在奥弗伯里面前。不仅他的食物被投毒，他的饮料也被投了毒。砒霜和他所吃的盐混合，斑蝥和胡椒混合。就这样，在这段时间内，他的健康状况明显下降了。他一天天变得虚弱下来。他的胃口极其奇怪，十分钟情于糖果和果冻。罗切斯特继续安慰他，并且满足他在这方面所有的需要，给他送丰富的油酥点心，偶尔送些松鸡和其他的野味，或者送些乳猪。在这些肉食的调味汁里，特纳夫人混合了一些斑蝥，并且用硝酸银给猪排下毒。就像在审判中所陈述的那样，奥弗伯里以这种方式服下的毒药总量足以毒死20个成年男人；但是，因为他的体质强壮，所以，仍旧可以苟延残喘。药剂师富兰克林承认说他和福尔曼医生准备了7种不同种类的毒药。它们是：硝酸、砒霜、水银、钻石粉、硝酸银、大蜘蛛和斑蝥。奥弗伯里坚持的时间太长了，这让罗切斯特有点不耐烦。在他写给埃塞克斯女士的一封信中，他说事情的解决没有他预料得那么快。埃塞克斯女士立即命令看门人马上处理掉受害人。在这段时间内，虽然奥弗伯里看起来对投毒之事一无所知，他也并非没有怀疑到罗切斯特对他的背叛。他只是怀疑他要被终身囚禁，他们只是让国王更加厌恶他。他在一封信中威胁罗切斯特说，如果他不被立即释放，他就要将他的流氓行为公之于世。他说：“不久后，你和我都将以另一性质的审判面对公众……不要将我逼上绝路，以免我说出让你和我都后悔不已的话……无论我活着还是死了，你的羞耻罪行都不会消失，它们会永远地留在这个世界上，让你成为有史以来最面目可憎的人……令我惊讶的是，你竟然忽视了一个知晓你所有秘密勾当的人……它们是普通的秘密和普通的危险吗？它们会带来什么样的后果？”

与罗切斯特大人这样不计后果的人打交道时，所有这些警告和掌握危险秘密的暗示都只能成为对自己的不利因素：它们更有可能导致奥弗伯里的死亡而不是救赎。罗切斯特的所想和所为似乎是一致的。他毫不犹豫地采取了谋杀者的理论，即，“人死则死无对证”。就这样，在他收到写有这些话语的信之后，他对他的情人抱怨事情的延迟。他们督促韦斯顿赶紧完成这个罪行。所有人的耐心都耗尽了，终于，1613年10月，一剂氯化汞放到了他的食物里。在这些人的魔爪下被痛苦地囚禁6个月之后，他的生命结束了。就在他断气当天，尸骨未寒之时，他就被匆匆地裹进一个床单，没有举行葬礼，草草地埋在了伦敦塔附近的一个深坑里。

在《詹姆斯一世王廷和人物》一书当中，安东尼·韦尔登爵士对这个悲剧结局的描写和上述内容有些许不同。他说：“富兰克林和韦斯顿来到奥弗伯里的囚室，发现他处于极端的痛苦折磨之中。很显然，是生命本能的力量在和毒药作斗争。看起来很有可能生命的本能要赢得这场争斗，因为奥弗伯里长出了疮、疹斑和水疱。他们害怕医生的检查会让他们的恶行大白于天下。于是，他们都同意用床单将他勒死；然后，就这样做了。就这样，他们结束了他悲惨的生命，并让阴谋者相信他是死于毒药。除了这两个谋杀者之外，其他人不会想到这种方式。”

突然的死亡——过分仓促的埋葬，以及没有进行尸检的事实，都加剧了浮在人们心头的怀疑。传闻，从偷偷泄露转为四处流传；死者的亲眷公开表示他们认为他们的亲人是死于谋杀。但是，罗切斯特在宫廷中的权力依旧如日中天，没有人敢发表哪怕一句对他不利的言论。不久后，他和埃塞克斯伯爵夫人的婚礼在前所未有的豪华气势中进行。国王亲自参加了仪式。

奥弗伯里对詹姆斯性格的了解似乎比罗切斯特所认为的还要深。当他预言罗切斯特的婚姻将疏远国王和他的关系时，他真是不折不扣的预言家。此时，罗切斯特所受的恩宠却比以往任何时候都高；但是，好景不长——良心，这个忙碌的监视器，开始起作用了。流言的传播从来没有停止过；一直心存内疚的罗切斯特最终变得憔悴不堪。他的脸颊没有了色彩——他的目光黯淡、脾气暴躁、神情恍惚、情绪低沉。看到他的这幅光景，国王终于对他的陪伴不再感兴趣，而后，开始四处寻找新欢。机智、帅气而又放荡不羁的白金汉公爵乔治·维利尔斯正合了国王的心意，仅仅后两个品质就足以让詹姆斯喜欢上他。罗切斯特的影响日渐削弱，白金汉公爵的权力与日俱增。一个失宠之人是没有朋友的。对罗切斯特不利的流言比以往任何时候都更加强烈、更加坚决。这位新宠也不遗余力地落井下石，以加速这位旧爱的堕落。因为急于想彻底毁掉这位享受皇帝宠爱的前任，白金汉怂恿托马斯·奥弗伯里的家人依法质询他们亲人的离奇死亡。

詹姆斯惩罚那些他没有亲自参与的罪行时，绝对足够严厉。此外，他对于自己发现秘密之迅捷十分自以为豪。托马斯·奥弗伯里的案件正中他的下怀。他的行动从逮捕杰维斯·艾尔维斯爵士开始。在诉讼的早期阶段，詹姆斯看上去并不知道罗切斯特在这件事中的纠缠之深。凶残的慢性投毒的全过程让国王感到十分恐怖，为此，他请来了所有的法官。安东尼·威尔顿爵士跪在他们中间说：“尊敬的法官大人们，最近，我听说你们正在调查一起投毒案件。上帝啊！如果餐桌变成了陷阱，连吃饭都要危及到每个人的生命，如果我们把意大利的这个恶俗引进到我们这里，那么，这个王国（世上唯一以热情好客著称的民族）将会处于怎样悲惨的境地啊！所以，各位长官，我命令你们对此事严查，没有算计，没有私情，也没有偏袒。在庄严而又令人生畏的宣判日，你们给出此事的答案。如果你姑息了这个犯罪案件中的任何一个罪犯，你和你的后代子孙都将受到上帝的诅咒！如果我姑息了任何罪犯，上帝将会永远诅咒我和我的子孙后代！”

这个诅咒在忠于斯图亚特王朝的家族里完全应验。庄重的誓言被打破了，上帝的诅咒不偏不倚地落在了他和他的子孙后代的头上。

在杰维斯·艾尔韦斯爵士之后，被捕的第二个人是副看守韦斯顿，然后是富兰克林和特纳夫人，最后是萨默赛特郡伯爵及其夫人，也就是罗切斯特。奥弗伯里死后，他荣升到了这个尊贵的位置。

第一个受审的是韦斯顿。公众的好奇心空前强烈，这件事情成为人们口中唯一的话题。审判那一天，法庭被挤得水泄不通。在法庭审判报告上，最高法院首席法官库克向陪审团揭露了投毒者卑鄙和猥琐的行为。面对他们秘密的企图，人的生命没有丝毫的自我保护和防御措施。在英国听说投毒是多么罕见的事情啊！在我们的国民看来，这是多么地让人憎恨啊！但是，魔鬼教会这些胆大妄为之徒诡谲之道，他们能够游刃有余地给人们投毒，让受害者按照他们的意愿在1个月、2个月、3个月或更长的时间段内，慢慢消耗掉生命的精华。他们让受害者中毒的方式有4种，即：闻、饮、尝、触。

当起诉书宣读完毕，韦斯顿唯一的反应就是：“主啊！可怜可怜我吧！主啊！可怜可怜我吧！”当被问及他将如何被审判时，他拒绝把自己交给国家的陪审团，并且宣布他只选择接受上帝的审判。他的这种态度持续了一段时间。后来，由于害怕受到藐视法庭罪责[19]的惩罚，他最终屈服，请求“无罪”辩护，并且以应有法律程序接受审判。

他所有的罪证都被完全证实，他被宣判有罪并且在泰伯恩刑场处死。特纳夫人、富兰克林和杰维斯·艾尔维斯爵士也受到了审判。宣判有罪后，于1615年10月19日到12月4日之间被处死。而对萨默赛特伯爵和伯爵夫人的重要审判直到次年5月份才进行。

在审判杰维斯·艾尔维斯的过程中，案件的细节被披露。通过这些细节，人们得知萨默赛特夫人的叔叔，北安普敦公爵和放鹰首领托马斯·孟勋爵士也参与了投毒。前者已经死去，法庭逮捕并审讯了托马斯·孟勋爵士。出人意料的是，这个人似乎太危险了，因而，并不能把他带上绞刑台。他知道詹姆斯一世太多见不得人的秘密，他的临终演讲很可能会揭露对国王不利的信息。对旧罪过的掩盖必然导致新的过错：对托马斯·孟勋爵士的审讯戛然而止；随即，他被释放。

詹姆斯已经违背了他的誓言。他开始害怕他对于投毒者的惩罚过分草率和疯狂。毫无疑问，萨默赛特将被宣判有罪，而国王也十分明白他必会祈求宽恕和赦免。被囚禁在伦敦塔里的时候，萨默赛特十分自信地肯定詹姆斯不敢审判他。在这一点上，他彻底地错了；但是，詹姆斯确实很痛苦。如今，他们之间的秘密无从确认；但是，猜测可以通过猜测略知一二。一些人认为秘密就是国王所沉迷的恶习；而另外一些人确认这个秘密和亨利王子的死有关。亨利王子是一个善良的年轻人，却深受萨默赛特的厌恶。王子早亡，但是他的父亲并没有为此感到悲伤。据坊间流传，王子为萨默赛特投毒谋杀。或许，国王因担心某个罪行而心情沉重；他不能放心地将他的同谋萨默赛特在公众面前处决。所以，当国王发现他的最爱深陷奥弗伯里谋杀案时，他的痛苦折磨难以言状。备受痛苦煎熬的国王想尽一切办法，让罪犯的精神处于不会胡言乱语的所谓的安全状态。有人悄悄地建议他先认罪，并相信国王的宅心仁厚。同样的建议也传给了伯爵夫人。国王命令培根起草一份包括所有对萨默赛特“有利”的事实的文件，而这些事实须以犯罪证据为基础。有人再次建议萨默赛特认罪，并许诺不祥之事不会降临到他的头上。

伯爵夫人首先被审判。在宣读起诉书的过程中，她浑身颤抖地流着泪，低声认罪。当被问及她为什么不该被处以死刑的时候，她胆怯地回答说：“我已犯了众怒，我知道没有什么能减轻我的罪过；但是，我渴望得到宽恕，希望各位长官为我向国王求情。”最终，她被宣判死刑。

第二天，伯爵受审。他似乎并未相信詹姆斯的承诺，所以拒绝认罪。可能，根据他对国王性格的了解，他对自己感到自信。他泰然自若地对目击证人进行严厉的交叉询问。经过他顽固的辩解和持续长达11小时的审讯之后，他被证明犯有重罪，并被宣判死刑。

无论罪犯和国王之间的秘密可能是什么，事实是，后者全然不顾他曾经发过的庄重誓言，根本不敢签署死刑执行令。很可能，这个执行令本应该是他自己的。伯爵和伯爵夫人被囚禁伦敦塔，时长将近5年之久。最后，让公众震惊、气愤，让他们的最高长官蒙羞的是，这两个人得到了王室的原谅，只是被命令居住在远离宫廷的地方而已。因为犯有重罪，伯爵的房产被充公；但是詹姆斯从这些充公房产的收入中，每年拿出4000英镑给这位伯爵大人！真是无耻之极！

对这两个罪犯后来的生活，人们不得而知。只是知道他们对彼此曾经的爱变成了厌恶；他们在同一个屋檐下生活了几个月，但是却从未说过一句话。

对于他们暴行的揭露并没有制止投毒的罪行。恰恰相反，就像我们在后面要看到的，真相的揭露引起了疯狂的模仿，而模仿恰是人性中很奇怪的一个特点。有人猜测詹姆斯本人就极有可能成为了投毒的牺牲品。在对哈里斯的《詹姆斯一世的生活和写作》的注释中，就有很多有关这个话题的信息。白金汉的罪名虽然没有完全成立，但是，其疑点足以送成百上千个人上绞刑架。他的犯罪动机是报复国王在统治后期对他的冷淡态度。他害怕詹姆斯要降低他的级别；同时，他又希望他可以通过对皇位继承人思想的影响，在新的统治时期继续保持他在宫廷里的权威，而做到这一点，就必须及时结束旧的统治。

在《哈利父子杂录》第二卷中，有一本名为《复仇先驱》的小册子。这本小册子由医学博士乔治·伊格利沙曼撰写，他是詹姆斯国王的医师之一。在引用这个册子的时候，哈里斯说它的内容充满了仇恨和偏见。册子内容显然有夸大其词之嫌，但是，它绝对是证据链上的一环。伊格利沙曼说：“国王得了疟疾，公爵就利用了这个机会。当国王的所有医生都在用餐时，他让国王服下了一种白色的粉末。刚开始，国王拒绝了很长时间；但是，在他极尽谄媚的强烈要求下，国王用酒服下。迅即，身体状况开始越来越糟。他多次昏厥，浑身疼痛，疯狂地拉肚子。在重重的折磨中，国王大声喊出了那个白色的粉末，‘上帝啊！我真不应该服下它啊！’”然后，他又告诉我们：“白金汉伯爵夫人（公爵的母亲）用石膏粉涂在国王的心脏上和胸上。从此，他变得虚弱、呼吸短促、痛苦不堪。医生们惊呼国王中毒了；白金汉公爵命令他们出去，并把他们之中的一个囚禁到他自己的房间内，把另一个从宫廷赶走。国王死后，他的身体和头都极其肿胀，头发和头皮都粘到了枕头上，他的手指甲和脚趾甲都已经松动。”克拉兰敦是公爵的党羽，他所给出的詹姆斯的死因完全不同。他说：“国王死于疟疾。这本是痛风后的一点不适，但是，在一个已经58岁，而且身体肥胖又笨重的人身上，这个病有点变本加厉；在经历了四五次晕厥之后，国王离开了这个世界。国王死后，毫无根据的流言四起。这些极尽刻薄和恶毒的流言出现在国王死后人们获得言论特许权的时候；此刻，人们对于激怒权贵没有任何畏惧之心；此刻，人们把对皇室的指责和侮辱看成丰功伟绩。”尽管在这个宣言似的说明里，克拉兰敦充满自信；但是，世人绝对很难相信在四处流传的流言中，毫无真相可言。就像他所断言的那样，来自于人们的质询并不严密，权威的亲信们利用所有能用到的法律以外的影响，将这些质询否决。在布里斯托尔伯爵控告白金汉公爵的著名案件中，詹姆斯国王的中毒案是所控告的罪行之一；然而，在当时，包含证据总结的那几页历史记录被撕去了。

白金汉公爵的毒药据说购自一个叫作兰姆的医生。此人是个巫师兼江湖医生，以算命先生为掩护经营毒药业务。大众把对他的主顾的满腔愤怒统统转移到他的身上；当然，和毒药相比，这种愤怒是无害的。从此，他再也不能安然无恙地在伦敦街头出现。他的最终命运让人悲叹。一天，他走在齐普赛街头，他认为他的乔装足以掩人耳目，但是，他还是被几个闲逛的男孩子认了出来。他们用垃圾轰赶和袭击他，同时，大声叫喊：“投毒者！投毒者！打倒巫师！打倒他！”很快，民众群集而来，这位医生只好撒开了腿，拼命奔逃。在伍德街，人们追上并抓住了他。从那里，他被揪着头发，拖过泥坑，一路走到了圣·保罗十字路口；乱作一团的众人用石头和棍子不停地打他，并且大喊：“杀了巫师！杀了投毒者！”

查理一世一听到消息，就立即骑马从白厅出发到出事地去平息暴乱；但是，他到的太晚了，没有来得及挽救这位众怒的牺牲品。他身上的每一根骨头都已断裂，他已经彻底地死去了。查理十分生气。因为伦敦市政府不能把这场暴乱的头目绳之以法，国王只好罚了这个城市600英镑了事。

然而，投毒的盛行之地是在意大利。很久以前，投毒在那里被认为是除掉敌人的十分正当的方式。16、17世纪的意大利人用投毒的方式害死他们的对手，投毒心境之坦然犹如当今英国人以法律程序起诉对他们造成伤害的人一样。根据当代作家的作品中所写，在斯芭拉和托菲尼雅进行这个罪恶交易的时代，女士们就堂而皇之地将毒药瓶放在她们的梳妆台上，并且，可以毫无顾忌地把它们用到别人身上，简直就像现代女士在自己身上使用古龙香水和薰衣草香水一样轻松。这种时尚的影响是如此之大，以至于谋杀竟然可以被认为是可以原谅的小过失。1648年，最后一位吉斯公爵不知天高地厚地想要掌控那不勒斯政府。在他的回忆录中，我们了解到当时人们普遍对投毒的一些奇怪的感觉。一个名叫吉纳罗·安尼斯的人，在马萨尼埃洛做了一段时间的渔夫。时间虽短，却成就辉煌，这让他成为公众眼中的首领人物。吉斯公爵对他的这副模样十分地深恶痛绝，因此，前者的跟随者决定将后者谋杀。公爵本人以十分冷静的态度告诉我们，护卫队队长被安排来承担这项任务。有人给他提建议说匕首是最有效的工具，但是，这个人翻了翻眼睛，对这个提议表示出极其虔诚的畏惧。他准备毒死吉纳罗·安尼斯，只要一声令下，他绝对毫不犹豫；但是，他说用匕首刺死他实在和护卫队官员的身份不符！最后，人们达成一致意见：同意投毒。一个深受公爵信任的律师奥古斯提诺·莫拉把装有液体的瓶子带到了他的主人面前。下面是公爵自己的描述：

夜晚，奥古斯提诺来到我这里，告诉我：“我给你带来了一个东西，他将使你摆脱吉纳罗给你带来的烦恼和不快。他死有余辜，至于采取什么样的形式将他正法并不重要。看看这个盛满了清澈的、美丽的液体的小药瓶。4天后，它就会惩罚他所有的罪过。护卫队长负责把这个药瓶给他；因为药瓶液体没有味道，吉纳罗不会怀疑什么。”

后来，公爵告诉我们说调配药量十分合适。但是，吉纳罗的幸运之处在于他那天的晚餐只吃了卷心菜抹植物油，而这些正好可以作为解毒药。他吃下之后便开始剧烈呕吐，就这样，这些东西救了他的命。他重病5天，但是从来没有怀疑有人给他投毒这件事。

随着时间的推移，兜售毒药成了十分赚钱的生意。此后11年间，投毒行为在罗马十分猖狂，最后，一向懒怠的政府不得不出面干预。贝克曼在他的《发明史》，勒布瑞特在他的《国家教堂物质史杂志》中对此事都有详细的阐释：1659年，教皇亚历山大七世得知，到忏悔室中忏悔的很多年轻妇女都说她们用慢性毒药毒死了她们的丈夫。天主教神职人员普遍认为忏悔秘密神圣不可侵犯，但是，他们为这个罪行的盛行之极感到震惊和恐惧。虽然，他们不愿意透露忏悔者的姓名，但是，他们认为他们应该向教堂首领报告这些人所犯下的滔天大罪。在罗马，十分流行的一个聊天话题就是年轻的寡妇多得有点不正常。同时，人们的议论内容还包括如下内容：如果一对夫妇生活不幸福，那么，不久后，丈夫就会生病，然后死去。罗马教皇机关开始调查，迅即获悉有个年轻夫人协会，协会夜间在一个叫作希罗尼玛·斯芭拉的女人家里聚会，聚会目的十分神秘。这个老太婆是个著名的巫婆和占卜者，担任这群年轻悍妇的首领。后来证实，这群悍妇中有几个出身上层罗马家庭。

为了获取这个妇女秘密团体实际活动的直接证据，政府雇佣了一位女士以寻求和她们直接接触的机会。这位女士把自己打扮得华丽无比，而且，政府给予她极其丰富的钱财。当她说明自己的目的后，她发现成为斯芭拉的信徒并加入她的团体一点都不难。她装作因为丈夫的不忠和虐待而极其痛苦的模样，并恳求斯芭拉给她几滴受到全罗马女性追捧的、可以让她残酷的丈夫长眠的那种神药。斯芭拉中了圈套，她卖给了她几滴，其价钱和购买者的财富相匹配。

经过化验分析，这些液体就是人们所怀疑的慢性毒药——清澈、无味、透明，和吉斯公爵的描述别无二致。获得这个证据后，警察包围了巫婆的房子，斯芭拉和她的同伴们被拘留。根据人们的描述，斯芭拉是位身材矮小、面目丑陋的老女人。在经受严刑拷打之后，她仍旧顽固地拒绝认罪。另一个叫作格拉提奥萨的女人没有那么坚定的意志，坦白交代了这个罪恶的妇女团体的所有秘密。虽然，她的坦白是经严刑逼供获得的，但是，仍有足够的证据向后世证明她们的罪过。这些人被认定有罪，并且根据她们罪行的不同程度，被判处不同的惩罚。斯芭拉、格拉提奥萨和其他3个毒死她们丈夫的年轻女人在罗马被集体绞死。30多位妇女在众目睽睽中，被鞭笞着穿过所有街道；几个女人的高位让她们免于羞辱的惩罚，但是被驱逐出国，并被罚以重金；几个月之后，又有9位女人因投毒被绞死；而另一群年轻貌美的女孩，半裸着身子在罗马的街道上被鞭笞。

这种严厉的惩罚并没有制止投毒行为。迫不及待地要继承父亲、叔父，或者兄弟财产的妒妇贪夫选择了投毒。因为毒药无色无味，所以投毒时不容易引起怀疑。技艺高超的兜售者将毒药制成药效不同的等级，投毒者只需说明他们想让服毒者在多长时间内死去：一周、一月，或是半年；然后，他们就会得到相应的剂量。兜售者主要是女人，其中最著名的是叫作托菲尼雅的女巫，她以这种方式成为杀害600多人的帮凶。这个女人似乎从少女时代就开始经营毒药，她刚开始住在巴勒莫，后来搬到了那不勒斯。娱乐旅行家，勒巴老爹在他的《来自意大利的书信》中，对这个人做了很多奇怪的描写。1719年，当他在契维塔韦基亚的时候，那不勒斯的总督发现大量的毒药买卖在当地进行，毒药被冠以“水”或“小水”的称号。通过进一步的调查，他断定托菲尼雅把写有“巴里圣人尼古拉斯甘露”的小瓶大量地发往意大利各地。（当时，这位女人已经有70岁高龄，并且她是在处死斯芭拉之后，马上就开始这个罪恶交易的。）

巴里圣人尼古拉斯的墓闻名整个意大利。据说，从墓中，有一股神奇的油流出，只要服用者有足够的信念，这个油可以包治百病。托菲尼雅巧妙地利用这个名字命名她的毒药，目的是逃避海关官员的警觉，因为，他们和其他人一样，对巴里圣人尼古拉斯和他的神油虔诚而恭敬。

这个毒药和斯芭拉所制作的毒药十分类似。顺势疗法创始人哈奈曼医生，在写到这个物质的时候说，毒药的成分为含砷的中性盐，它让受害者失去食欲、身体衰弱、胃部疼痛、力气消失、肺部衰竭。神父加利亚尔迪说，投毒的做法通常是将它放入茶、巧克力或汤里，它起作用的过程十分缓慢，几乎不会被察觉。奥地利国王的医生加雷利在给霍夫曼的信中说，毒药就是用煎煮的形式融化到大量的水里的晶状砷，然后再加上芯巴草（原因不明）。那不勒斯人称它为托夫妮娜水，很快，这种毒药就以托夫妮娜水之名，在整个欧洲臭名远扬。

虽然，这个女人从事罪恶贸易的范围十分广泛，但是，却很难遇到她。她一直生活在惧怕被发现的担忧里。她不断地更换名字和居住地；有时候，她会假扮成极其虔诚的信徒，在修道院连续待上几个月。每当她担心被发现的时候，她就会到教会里去寻求庇护。她很快得到了那不勒斯总督搜捕她的消息，然后，根据她的经验，躲到了修道院里。或者是因为搜寻不够严密，或者是因为她的隐藏手段十分高超；总之，持续好几年，她都设法逃过了官方的警觉。更加离奇的是，通过解构她的生意内容，人们发现她的贸易范围和以前一样大。勒巴告诉我们说，她十分同情那些憎恨她们的丈夫、想把她们的丈夫除掉但又没钱买这个神“水”的女人们。对于这些人，她把这些毒水作为礼物送给了她们。

然而，上天是不会允许她一直玩下去的。最后，总督在一个女修道院里发现了她，并且切断了她的退路。总督几次三番抗议，要求修道院院长将其交出。但是，有主教教区大主教支持的修道院院长一再拒绝。因为他们之间的屡次交涉，这个罪犯似乎显得格外重要。公众好奇心大发，成千上万的人到这个修道院里去，只为能看上她一眼。

反反复复的推延终于耗尽了总督的耐心。总督是理智之人，而且并非狂热的天主教徒，所以，他坚决认为即便是教堂也不能庇护罪恶如此深重的罪犯。他选择了无视修道院的权威，派了一个部队，推倒墙壁，用武力将她带走。大主教、红衣主教皮尼亚泰利十分生气。他威胁说要把整个城市逐出教会，并且要封锁整个城市。受团队精神激发的所有下级神职人员都参与到这个争端中，并且对那些迷信而偏执的人施加影响。结果，这些人磨刀霍霍地要攻击总督官府，解救囚犯。

形势十分严峻，但是，总督并不是可以被吓倒的人。实际上，在事件的整个过程中，他都表现出了少有的机智、冷静和活力。为了避免逐出教会的威胁所带来的恶劣后果，他派兵包围了大主教的住所。他断定，主教绝对不会把整个城市逐出教会，饿死包括他自己在内的全市市民。这样的傻事，他是绝对不会做的。只要城市处于封锁之中，那些商人是绝对不敢为这个城市供应食品的。这个措施势必会给他以及他的神职兄弟们带来诸多不便。正如总督所料，这位心地善良的大主教平息了自己的雷霆之怒。

民众的情绪也尚待安抚。为了避免怒气冲天的骚乱和迫在眉睫的暴乱，政府的代表巧妙地混到民众中，并且到处散布消息说这个城市里所有的井水和泉水都被托菲尼雅施了毒。就此，大功告成。公众的愤怒情绪立即转向了她。那些前一秒还把她看成圣人的人，此刻已把她作为恶魔来诅咒，他们要马上惩罚她的急切心情丝毫不亚于当时希望她逃脱的愿望。随后，托菲尼雅被严刑拷问。她一一承认了她罄竹难书的罪行，并一一列出她的主顾名单。不久，她就被绞死。她的尸体被隔墙扔到她曾住过的修道院的花园里。这个行为似乎是为了安抚那些神职人员。毕竟，这是允许他们去埋葬曾在他们的地盘上避过难的人。

在她死后，投毒的狂热似乎降低了。但是，我们在下面要看一下这股狂热是如何在更早的时期控制法国人的。1670年到1680年间，投毒活动在法国风靡一时，以至于塞维涅夫人在她的一封信中说她十分害怕法国人和投毒者这两个表达方式会成为近义词。

正如在意大利，政府也是从一个牧师那里第一次获悉这个罪行之盛。社会地位从高到低的女性都曾在她们的忏悔中承认她们毒死了她们的丈夫。真相大白后，名为奥克西利和格拉泽的两个意大利人被捕，并被囚禁在巴士底狱，原因是，有人控告他们配制并兜售用于谋杀的毒药。格拉泽死于狱中，但是，奥克西利一连几个月待在狱中，并未受到审判。到监狱后不久，他就认识了一位名叫圣克鲁瓦的狱友。当时，这位圣克鲁瓦所创造的投毒模式仍旧在法国人中流传。

在所有从此人处学得投毒知识的人中，最声名狼藉的当属布兰维利耶夫人。这个人有着极其高贵的出身背景和婚姻背景。她在青年时期似乎就没心没肺、道德败坏。如果我们相信她自己的忏悔的话，那就是，在她还是个小姑娘的时候，她的心中就装满了邪恶。但是，她不但美丽，且外在修养十足；在世人的眼里，她温柔可爱，堪作典范。盖奥特·德·皮塔瓦尔在他的《著名的事业》中，以及赛维纳夫人在她的《书信》中，对她的描述都是举止文雅、得体。从对外貌的描述上，丝毫看不出其内在灵魂的邪恶。她于1651年嫁给了布兰维利耶侯爵，婚后几年的生活并不愉快。他放荡不羁，沉迷酒色。就是他本人将圣克鲁瓦介绍给了他的夫人。这个人给她的生活蒙上了毁灭的阴影，他拉着她一步步走向犯罪的深渊，直到她的罪过大到让她无法承受，一想起便让她浑身发抖的地步。对这个人，她心中充满激情，为了满足这罪恶的激情，她一头扎进了罪恶的深渊。她被拉到了罪孽的最深处，直到惩罚降临。

到那时为止，她始终以美好的形象示人；然而，她的丈夫却没有能力掩盖自己的恶行；所以，在寻求和她的丈夫合法分居的过程中，她几乎没有遇到阻力。这件事大大地冒犯了她的家人。自此之后，她完全扔掉了她的面具，开始和她的情人圣克鲁瓦堂而皇之地进行她的阴谋。她的父亲为她的行为感到可耻，他获得了逮捕密令，将圣克鲁瓦在巴士底狱囚禁了12个月。

圣克鲁瓦曾生活在意大利，在毒药方面，仅仅是业余水平。他知道罪大恶极的斯芭拉的一些秘密配方。入狱后，他迅速地和奥克西利建立起所谓的友谊，后来，在奥克西利的指导下，迅速提升了他对这些秘方的运用能力。奥克西利不仅向他展示了如何准备液体毒药的技巧，并且教他学会了如何使用其粉末状替代品。后来，这个粉末状的替代品在法国广为人知。像他的情妇一样，他外表谦和、诙谐、智慧；在他的身上，人们绝对看不到他的内心有两种罪恶的激情在熊熊燃烧：复仇和贪婪；这两个激情在折磨着他的心。他的这两个激情要在不幸的德奥布雷家族身上得到满足：满足复仇，是因为他们囚禁了他；满足贪婪，是因为他们很富有。由于他的粗心大意和挥金如土，他总是处于缺钱状态，只有布兰维利耶夫人供给他的开销，但是她所拥有的财产远远不能满足他的需求。一想到他和那些财富之间的障碍，他就十分沮丧；为此，他萌生了可怕的罪恶念头：毒死她的父亲德奥布雷先生和她的两个哥哥，让她继承财产。谋杀3个人对于这样的一个恶棍来说不足挂齿。他把他的计划告诉了布兰维利耶夫人，后者毫不犹豫地同意和他协作：他负责配制，她负责投放。她着手工作的激情和欣然令人难以置信。圣克鲁瓦发现她很擅长学习。很快，她配制毒药的技巧和他一样具有了专业水准。为了试验第一批剂量的强度，她把这些毒药用在狗、兔子和鸽子身上。随后，为了进一步确认这些毒药的功效，她在各个医院假装慈善，把毒药放到她送给那些穷病人的汤里。所有这些毒药的剂量都不会一次致死，这就使得她在每个人身上尝试一次的方式不会引起谋杀的嫌疑。她还在鸽肉馅饼中投毒，在她父亲邀请的客人身上做这个罪恶的实验。为了进一步确认，她甚至接着给自己投毒！当用这种孤注一掷的方式确认了剂量的功效之后，她服下了从圣克鲁瓦那里得来的解药。所有的疑虑都被解除之后，她开始给她头发灰白的父亲投毒。她亲自将第一剂放到了她父亲的巧克力里，毒药作用发挥良好。这位老人病倒了，他那看起来焦急而体贴的女儿守护在他的床前。第二天，她给她父亲端来她声称很有营养的肉汤，汤内也已投毒。她就以这种方式耗尽了他的体质，不到10天，他就成了一具尸体。他的死看起来确实是疾病带来的后果，没有引起任何人的怀疑。

当俩兄弟悲哀地从外省赶来为他们的父亲办丧事的时候，他们发现他们的妹妹悲哀至极。最起码，从表面看来，最孝顺的感情也莫过于此了。但是，这两位年轻人的到来只不过是送死而已。他们站在了圣克鲁瓦和他已经到手一半的金子之间，他们必须命丧黄泉。一个叫肖斯的人被圣克鲁瓦雇来投放毒药，不到6周的时间，俩兄弟双双进了坟墓。

此时，人们开始怀疑；但是，所有的一切都做得天衣无缝，找不到任何和此事有牵连的人。这位女侯爵有个妹妹，由于亲人的亡故，她有权获得一半的财产。然而，只有全部的财产才能满足圣克鲁瓦的贪欲。所以，他决定：她必须死去，就像她的父兄一样。然而，她实在太多疑了。她最终离开了巴黎，也因此躲过了潜在的生命威胁。

女侯爵所进行的上述谋杀是为了取悦她的情人，现在，她急切地想再次犯罪，这次，是为她自己。她渴望嫁给圣克鲁瓦，但是，虽然她和丈夫分居，却并未离婚。她认为毒死他比向法院起诉离婚更加简单。因为，在法院，她极有可能被拒绝。但是，圣克鲁瓦不再爱他这个罪恶的工具。恶棍往往并不钟情同类。虽然圣克鲁瓦自己罪孽深重，却并没有再娶一个恶婆的愿望，所以，他一点也不急于让侯爵死去。然而，他看起来还是参与到了这个阴谋中，并为她提供了毒死她丈夫的毒药；但是，他很小心地一并提供了解药。布兰维利耶夫人第一天给她丈夫投毒，圣克鲁瓦第二天就给他解药。他就以这种方式被他们二人反反复复折磨了一段时间之后，最终幸免于难，但是，体质被损，伤心欲绝。

但是，报应之日已近在眼前。一个可怕的灾难让谋杀的真相大白于天下。圣克鲁瓦所配制的毒药毒性极大，所以，当他在实验室工作的时候，他必须带上面罩以防窒息而死。一天，面罩不幸滑落，这个卑鄙小人就这样玩火自焚。第二天，人们在他实验室所在的昏暗住处发现了他的尸体。因为他无亲无友，警察就接管了他的财产。在所有的东西中，他们发现了一个小盒子，盒子中附有下面这个奇怪的文件：

我恳求，无论此盒落入何人之手，请务必帮我把它转给布兰维利耶侯爵夫人，夫人住在纽芬兰·圣·保罗大街。盒中所有之物和她有关，仅属她所有，且仅能为她所用。如若她先我而逝，望将此盒连同内部所有一起焚毁，切勿打开或做任何更改。为避免有人以不知情为由将其打开，我以我所尊敬的上帝和所有圣人之名发誓，我要保证我如下所言事实的应验：如果我合理且正义的意图被违背，我将让他们的良心在今生来世里都不得安宁，并以此换取我内心之平静。这就是我的临终遗嘱。1672年5月25日于巴黎。

圣克鲁瓦

这份急切的恳求并没有带来主人所期望的尊重，反而激起了人们的好奇心。盒子被打开了，人们发现里面装有文件、几个小药瓶和一些粉末。小药瓶和粉末交给药剂师分析成分，那些文件被警察留下并打开查阅。在这些文件中，有一个布兰维利耶夫人付给圣克鲁瓦的、价值3万法郎的期票。其他的文件更加重要，因为它们暗示了她和她的仆人肖斯参与了最近的谋杀事件。她一得知克鲁瓦圣人的死讯，就企图马上得到他的文件和盒子；但是，她的要求被拒绝了。她感觉没有了犹豫的时间，立即逃跑。第二天清晨，警察奋力追踪，但是，她成功地逃到了英国。而肖斯却没有那么幸运。他对那个将他的罪行大白于天下的致命事件一无所知，他做梦都没想到他会有危险。法院逮捕并审讯了他：在严刑拷问下，他承认他曾给德奥布雷父子投毒，为此，他从圣克鲁瓦和布兰维利耶侯爵夫人那里得到100个金币，以及养老金的承诺。对他的最终判决是活活摔死在车轮上；在侯爵夫人缺席的情况下，对她的宣判是斩首。1673年，在巴黎的格雷夫的广场上，按照宣判，肖斯被处死。

布兰维利耶夫人大概在英国住了3年。1676年初，她觉得严格的追查应该已经结束，她应该可以冒险回到欧洲大陆，随后，她秘密到了列日。尽管她小心翼翼，她返回的消息还是迅速被报告给了法国政府，后者马上和那个城市的政府作出安排，以便法国的警察可以在他们法律允许的范围内将其逮捕。毛利肖斯的警官德格雷按照安排，离开巴黎去往目的地。他一到列日就发现她已经藏在了一个修道院内。在这里，法律是鞭长莫及；但是，德格雷绝非知难而退之人。他巧用智谋完成了法律无法完成的使命。他把自己装扮成教父，获得了进入修道院的许可，然后，寻机和布兰维利耶夫人见面。他说，作为路过列日的法国人，他一定要见一位女士，因为她的美貌和不幸尽人皆知。这些恭维之词满足了她的虚荣心。用稍显粗鲁却十分到位的表述来说，那就是，德格雷已经完全掌控了她，而她却对德格雷无从知晓。他继续巧妙地向她倾吐爱慕之词，直到这位已经被骗上当的侯爵夫人完全失去警觉。无需太多恳求，她就同意在修道院墙外和他幽会，因为，在那里，他们的私通比在里边要方便得多。按照她和她所谓的新情人的约定，她出现在了那里；结果发现等待她的不是勇士的拥抱，而是警察的拘捕。

对她的审判很快就开始进行。罪证充分！肖斯的临终遗言就足以证明她的罪行；除此之外，还有圣克鲁瓦盒子里那些神秘的文件；她逃离法国的行为；以及比其他任何证据都更有说服力，更能将她置于死地的证据：在圣克鲁瓦的财产中发现的由她亲自签署的文件，在这个文件里，她向他详述了她一生所犯下的罪行，而这些罪行就包括她对父兄的谋杀。所有这一切都确凿地证明了她的罪恶。在审判期间，整个巴黎都处于骚乱不安的状态，人们讨论的唯一话题就是布兰维利耶。她犯罪的所有细节都被公之于众，被公众如饥似渴地关注。对于成百上千的人来说，这是他们第一次接触秘密投毒的想法，而这些人在后来也犯下了同样的罪行。

1676年7月16日，巴黎最高刑事法庭对她谋杀父兄以及企图谋杀妹妹的犯罪事实进行宣判，判处死刑。死刑执行前，她被放在一个架子上，光着脚，脖子上套着绳子，手里拿着燃烧的火炬，被一路拉到巴黎圣母院的门口。在这里，她在众目睽睽之下当众谢罪；然后，从那里，她被带到格雷夫广场斩首。死后，她的尸体被烧掉，连灰烬都化为乌有。

在对她进行判决之后，她对自己的罪行供认不讳。看起来似乎对死亡无所畏惧，但，实际上，她的精神支柱是不顾后果的鲁莽而非勇气。塞维涅夫人说，她恳求忏悔牧师利用他对行刑者的影响，让他站在她身边，使他的身体挡住她的视线，以免她会看到“那个设圈套抓她的流氓德格雷”。她还问爬到窗口看游行队伍的女士们，她们在看什么，并且补充道：“你们所看到的景象确实十分美妙！”被放到绞刑台上的时候，她放声大笑；和活着的时候一样，临死，她仍旧不知悔改，没心没肺。第二天，人们成群结队地去搜集她的骨灰，并将它作为纪念物保存下来。人们把她看作是殉难的圣人，认为她的骨灰被神赋予了包治百病的力量。大众的愚蠢总是让他们莫名其妙地去神化某些人，而这些人的所谓神圣之名实在是有待考究；但是，在这件事情上，这些乌合之众的愚蠢实在是令人作呕、无与伦比。

在她死之前，控告身兼朗格多克省[20]财长及牧师总收款人佩诺捷先生的诉讼程序启动。控告者是一位叫作圣·劳伦的女士。她控告佩诺捷为了获得她丈夫，即前任牧师总收款人的职位，将他毒死。这个案件的详情从未外泄，有人不遗余力地阻止针对此案的审讯。据悉，被告和圣克鲁瓦及布兰维利耶夫人有着密切的联系，所以，人们认为他的毒药是从他们那里获得。但是，布兰维利耶拒绝提供任何有可能牵连到他的细节。佩诺捷在巴士底狱被囚禁几个月之后，审讯最后无果而终。

根据当时的流言所传，红衣主教邦齐被指为佩诺捷的帮凶。红衣主教的财产每年必须为几个人支付几笔数额不菲的年金；而到投毒盛行之时，所有领取年金的人一一死亡。后来提到这些领取年金者时，红衣主教说：“多亏了我的福星，我活得比他们都长！”一个头脑机智的人看到他和佩诺捷同乘一辆马车，他大声喊道：“那就是红衣主教邦齐和他的福星！”这声呼喊无疑和主教所言遥相呼应。

就在当时，投毒的狂热开始控制普通民众的头脑。自此直到1682年，法国的监狱里挤满了被控告犯有此罪的犯人；同时，让人不可思议的是，其他罪行成比例减少。我们已经看到了它在意大利的疯狂程度，如果这个程度尚未登峰造极，仍旧可以被超越的话，法国绝对远远超越了意大利。这些毫无气味的毒药给谋杀活动带来的轻松如魔鬼般引诱着那些心怀叵测之人。嫉妒、复仇、贪婪，甚至仅仅是小小的怨恨都可能让人选择投毒。有些人因害怕被发现而拒绝使用手枪、匕首，以及大剂量毒药等可以立刻致死的手段，这些人肆无忌惮地选择了慢性毒药。虽然，当时的政府腐败到可以对一个像佩诺捷一样富有而又有影响力的朝臣的暴行视而不见，然而，对这个罪行在民众中的盛行也感到震惊不已。在欧洲人的眼里，耻辱就是法国人的代名词。为了制止这个恶行，路易十四设立了火焰法庭，或者叫燃烧室，在这里，法官拥有审讯和惩罚罪犯的无上权力。

在当时，有两位女人尤其臭名昭著，她们是杀害成千上万个人的帮凶。这两个人名叫拉瓦辛和拉韦高胡，都住在巴黎。她们模仿斯芭拉和托菲尼雅，像她们俩人一样，她们也是主要把毒药卖给那些想除掉丈夫的女人；偶尔，也会卖给想除掉妻子的丈夫。她们假扮的职业是助产士，同时，她们还假装成算命者，顾客来自社会各个阶层。穷人和富人蜂拥到她们的住处，去寻求未来的秘密。她们的预言主要和死亡有关。她们给女人们预告向她们的丈夫走来的死亡；她们给心情急迫的继承人计算他们富有的亲人的死期，因为正如拜伦所述，这些亲人让他们等得太久了。她们总是小心翼翼地去促成她们所预言之事的应验，做法通常是告诉那些倍受困扰的主人说，预示死亡的迹象将会在屋子里发生，比如摔碎一个瓷器或玻璃器皿；然后，她们就会重金贿赂仆人们，让他们在约定的时间，貌似偶然地摔碎一样东西。助产士的身份让她们了解到许多家庭的秘密，她们随后就把这些秘密变成了可怕的故事。

在被发现之前，她们从事这个罪恶的交易已有多久，人们不得而知。她们最终在1679年底被察觉。经过审判并证实罪行后，两人的手被炽热的烙铁烫穿，用刀砍下。1680年2月22日，两人被活活烧死在格雷夫广场。她们在巴黎和外省的无数同谋也被发现，并经受了审判。一些作者记录为30人，另一些记录为50人，在主要城市被绞死。这些人中大部分为女人。

拉瓦辛留有一份所有到她住处买毒药的顾客的名单。在她被捕后，警察获得了这份名单，并带到法院进行审查。名单包括卢森堡的元帅、苏瓦松伯爵夫人和布永公爵夫人。元帅的罪行似乎只是在于他拜访了这样一位女人，充其量也只能算是个不体面的蠢事；但是，当时民众的呼声给他的定性绝非愚蠢那么简单。《乌得勒支和平后的欧洲事务回忆录》的作者说：“那个经营毒药和预言未来的犯罪团伙声称他已经投奔了魔鬼。一个叫作杜邦的女孩曾经被他毒死。在其他故事中，她们说，为了让他的儿子和鲁瓦侯爵的女儿成婚，他和魔鬼签订了合同。面对这个恶毒而荒谬的控告，元帅高傲而无辜地说：‘当我的祖先马提厄·德·蒙特默伦西和路易斯·勒·格罗斯的寡妻结婚的时候，他求助的是议会而不是魔鬼，其目的是获得蒙特默伦西家族对未成年国王的支持。’这个时候，这位元帅已经因为第一次的控告而被囚于巴士底狱了。这位勇士被囚禁在长仅6.5英尺的牢房里。他的审讯停滞了几周后，又继续进行了14个月。最终，没有对他进行任何判决。”

苏瓦松伯爵夫人没有冒被审判的危险，直接逃到了布鲁塞尔。她因为企图用粉末状毒药分步毒死西班牙女王的罪行，而将自己永远地钉在了耻辱柱上。布永公爵夫人被捕后被火焰法庭审判。但是，她似乎和慢性投毒没有任何关系，而只是想探究她们可以预知未来的秘密，看一眼魔鬼以满足她的好奇心。火焰法庭的庭长之一雷尼是个面貌丑陋、身材矮小的小男人。他问她是否真的见到了魔鬼。面对这个问题，这位女士眼睁睁地看着他的脸答道：“噢，是的！我现在看到他了。他是一位身材矮小、面貌丑陋的老男人，脾气坏极了，而且还穿着国家级法律顾问的长袍。”面对这样一位头脑机敏、言语犀利的女士，雷尼小心翼翼地停止了对她的审问。公爵夫人在巴士底狱被囚禁了几个月，没有发现任何可以证明她有罪的证据。最后，在她有权势的朋友的干涉下，她被释放了。对于这些有名望的罪犯的惩罚本应降低平民效仿的热度；相反，一些名人免受惩罚的现实对事态的发展起了反作用。佩诺捷和他的雇主红衣主教邦齐的逃跑对社会造成了极其恶劣的影响。在后来长达两年的时间里，这个罪行继续肆虐，直到火刑的火柱熊熊燃烧，绞刑的绳索高高悬挂，100多个人被处死后，罪行才最后被完全镇压。[21]

[1]贝朗热（Pierre-Jean de Béranger），法国抒情诗人。原文：La faridondaine-la faridondon, Vive la faridondaine！法国民谣中的句子，没有实际含义，仅为凑足韵律。——译者注

[2]南华克区（Southwark）位于英国伦敦中心地带，人口密度比较高，被称作伦敦的城中城。——编者注

[3]伊索寓言中的故事：大山有临盆的征兆，结果最后只跑出一只老鼠来。形容期望很高，而结果却十分令人失望。——译者注

[4]密西西比泡沫事件是指法国在1719至1720年的密西西比公司股市泡沫破裂的金融事件。其始作俑者约翰·劳主张通过增加货币供给，可以在不提高物价水平的前提下，增加就业机会并增加国民产出。在约翰·劳的影响下，法国政府为了缓解财政亏空，大量发行纸币，制造虚假经济繁荣，最终引发了剧烈通货膨胀，法国金融体系因此崩溃。——编者注

[5]位于巴黎，密西西比泡沫破灭前，该地进行了大量印度股票交易。——编者注

[6]卡珊德拉（Cassandra）是希腊神话中特洛伊（Troy）的公主，别名为亚历珊德拉（Alexandra）。神话中突出的形象是一名遭诅咒的女先知，预言能力百发百中，然而无人听信。——译者注

[7]英国旧时金币，约合63英镑。——译者注

[8]雅法（Joppa）：以色列中西部的古城。——译者注

[9]卡斯提尔（Castile）：古代西班牙北部一王国。——译者注

[10]在那个灾难之年，诗人盖伊（约翰·盖伊，1685—1732，英国诗人及剧作家。——译者注）从年轻的克莱格斯那里收到一些南海公司的股票作为礼物。他立刻想象自己可以拥有2万英镑。他的朋友们劝他卖掉自己的股份，但是他梦想着荣华富贵，无法忍受自己的财路就此阻断。后来，人们又强烈建议他卖掉一部分，至少可以保证他在有生之年，每年可以有100英镑用来支配。芬顿给他的分析说：“最起码，（接上页）这可以保证你每天有洁净的衬衣穿，有一个羊肩可以享用。”这个建议被拒绝了，结果血本无归。在这场灾难中，盖伊一蹶不振，甚至到了生命垂危的地步。——约翰逊的《诗人的生活》。

[11]指近代英国杰出的历史学家爱德华·吉本（Edward Gibbon，1737—1794），著有影响深远的史学名著《罗马帝国衰之史》，18世纪欧洲启蒙时代史学的卓越代表。——译者注

[12]原文为Foyeuse，为误写。——译者注

[13]伊卡洛斯（Icarus）是希腊神话中代达罗斯的儿子，与代达罗斯使用蜡和羽毛造的翼逃离克里特岛时，他因飞得太高，双翼上的蜡遭太阳融化跌落水中丧生，被埋葬在一个海岛上。——译者注

[14]直到1845年，南海公司计划一直是英国历史上全民迷恋商业赌博的最典型事例。本系列书籍第一版在铁路大狂热发生之前及之后一年出版。

[15]卢坎：罗马诗人（公元39年11月3日——公元65年4月30日）。他最著名的著作是史诗《法沙利亚》，描述凯撒与庞培之间的内战。这部史诗虽是未完成作品，却被誉为是维吉尔《埃涅阿斯》之外最伟大的拉丁文史诗。引文即出自这部作品。——译者注

[16]货币单位：1弗罗林（florin）=2先令（shilling）——译者注

[17]1派瑞特（perit）=1/4608000盎司（ounce）——译者注

[18]公元1世纪末2世纪初的罗马诗人，以擅长写讽刺诗著称，著有《讽刺诗集》（Satires）——译者注

[19]对于违抗法庭命令的罪犯的惩罚可以用3个短语来表示：压死、冻死和饿死。压死指的是，罪犯应该趴在地上；然后，在他的身上压重物，重量慢慢增加，直到他咽气为止。有时候，惩罚并不会达到这个程度，而是允许罪犯恢复，但是要经历第二个部分，即冻死。在第二部分，罪犯要赤身裸体地在众目睽睽之下，站在户外的某个地方。第三种方式，饿死，更加可怕。法令规定：“在行刑之前，让罪犯以最粗糙的面包和遇到的下一个阴沟或泥坑里的水为食；一天中，饮水和吃面包他只能选择其中之一。”在这种折磨中，只要罪犯的身体还能撑得住，就只能苟延残喘，死期由天意决定。

[20]古时法国南部一省份。——译者注

[21]不幸的是，慢性投毒这个罪行最近几年在英国死灰复燃，犯罪范围之广足以让整个民族蒙羞。投毒者主要是社会地位较低的女人，而她们的牺牲品是她们的丈夫和孩子。绝大部分的犯罪目的之卑劣让人难以想象：仅为获得他们所属的埋葬社团支付的保险金或埋葬费。人们寄希望于新颁布的限制砒霜及毒药的法令，即使不能彻底消灭这种令人发指的罪行，至少可以减少悲剧的发生。（1851）

2
The South-Sea Bubble

At length corruption, like a general flood,

Did deluge all, and avarice creeping on,

Spread, like a low-born mist, and hid the sun.

Statesmen and patriots plied alike the stocks,

Peeress and butler shared alike the box;

And judges jobbed, and bishops bit the town,

And mighty dukes packed cards for half a crown:

Britain was sunk in lucre's sordid charms.

Pope

The South-Sea Company was originated by the celebrated Harley, Earl of Oxford, in the year 1711, with the view of restoring public credit, which had suffered by the dismissal of the Whig ministry, and of providing for the discharge of the army and navy debentures, and other parts of the floating debt, amounting to nearly ten millions sterling. A company of merchants, at that time without a name, took this debt upon themselves, and the government agreed to secure them, for a certain period, the interest of six per cent. To provide for this interest, amounting to £600,000 per annum, the duties upon wines, vinegar, India goods, wrought silks, tobacco, whale-fins, and some other articles, were rendered permanent. The monopoly of the trade to the South Seas was granted, and the company, being incorporated by Act of Parliament, assumed the title by which it has ever since been known. The minister took great credit to himself for his share in this transaction, and the scheme was always called by his flatterers 'the Earl of Oxford's masterpiece'.

Even at this early period of its history, the most visionary ideas were formed by the company and the public of the immense riches of the western coast of South America. Everybody had heard of the gold and silver mines of Peru and Mexico; everyone believed them to be inexhaustible, and that it was only necessary to send the manufactures of England to the coast, to be repaid a hundredfold in gold and silver ingots by the natives. A report, industriously spread, that Spain was willing to concede four ports, on the coasts of Chile and Peru for the purposes of traffic, increased the general confidence, and for many years the South-Sea Company's stock was in high favour.

Philip V of Spain, however, never had any intention of admitting the English to a free trade in the ports of Spanish America. Negotiations were set on foot, but their only result was the assiento contract, or the privilege of supplying the colonies with Negroes for thirty years, and of sending once a year a vessel, limited both as to tonnage and value of cargo, to trade with Mexico, Peru, or Chile. The latter permission was only granted upon the hard condition, that the King of Spain should enjoy one-fourth of the profits, and a tax of five per cent on the remainder. This was a great disappointment to the Earl of Oxford and his party, who were reminded much oftener than they found agreeable of the 'Parturiunt montes, nascitur ridiculus mus'. But the public confidence in the South-Sea Company was not shaken. The Earl of Oxford declared that Spain would permit two ships, in addition to the annual ship, to carry out merchandise during the first year; and a list was published, in which all the ports and harbours of these coasts were pompously set forth as open to the trade of Great Britain. The first voyage of the annual ship was not made till the year 1717, and in the following year the trade was suppressed by the rupture with Spain.

The king's speech, at the opening of the session of 1717, made pointed allusion to the state of public credit, and recommended that proper measures should be taken to reduce the national debt. The two great monetary corporations, the South-Sea Company and the Bank of England, made proposals to parliament on the 20th of May ensuing. The South-Sea Company prayed that their capital stock of ten millions might be increased to twelve, by subscription or otherwise, and offered to accept five per cent instead of six upon the whole amount. The bank made proposals equally advantageous. The house debated for some time, and finally three acts were passed, called the South-Sea Act, the Bank Act, and the General Fund Act. By the first, the proposals of the South-Sea Company were accepted, and that body held itself ready to advance the sum of two millions towards discharging the principal and interest of the debt due by the state for the four lottery funds of the ninth and tenth years of Queen Anne. By the second act, the bank received a lower rate of interest for the sum of £1,775,027 15s. due to it by the state, and agreed to deliver up to be cancelled as many exchequer bills as amounted to two millions sterling, and to accept of an annuity of one hundred thousand pounds, being after the rate of five per cent, the whole redeemable at one year's notice. They were further required to be ready to advance, in case of need, a sum not exceeding £2,500,000 upon the same terms of five per cent interest, redeemable by parliament. The General Fund Act recited the various deficiencies, which were to be made good by the aids derived from the foregoing sources.

The name of the South-Sea Company was thus continually before the public. Though their trade with the South American States produced little or no augmentation of their revenues, they continued to flourish as a monetary corporation. Their stock was in high request, and the directors, buoyed up with success, began to think of new means for extending their influence. The Mississippi scheme of John Law, which so dazzled and captivated the French people, inspired them with an idea that they could carry on the same game in England. The anticipated failure of his plans did not divert them from their intention. Wise in their own conceit, they imagined they could avoid his faults, carry on their schemes for ever, and stretch the cord of credit to its extremest tension, without causing it to snap asunder.

It was while Law's plan was at its greatest height of popularity, while people were crowding in thousands to the Rue Quincampoix, and ruining themselves with frantic eagerness, that the South-Sea directors laid before parliament their famous plan for paying off the national debt. Visions of boundless wealth floated before the fascinated eyes of the people in the two most celebrated countries of Europe. The English commenced their career of extravagance somewhat later than the French; but as soon as the delirium seized them, they were determined not to be outdone. Upon the 22nd of January, 1720, the House of Commons resolved itself into a committee of the whole house, to take into consideration that part of the king's speech at the opening of the session which related to the public debts, and the proposal of the SouthSea Company towards the redemption and sinking of the same. The proposal set forth at great length, and under several heads, the debts of the state, amounting to £30,981,712 which the company were anxious to take upon themselves, upon consideration of five per cent per annum, secured to them until Midsummer 1727; after which time, the whole was to become redeemable at the pleasure of the legislature, and the interest to be reduced to four per cent. The proposal was received with great favour; but the Bank of England had many friends in the House of Commons, who were desirous that that body should share in the advantages that were likely to accrue. On behalf of this corporation it was represented, that they had performed great and eminent services to the state in the most difficult times, and deserved, at least, that if any advantage was to be made by public bargains of this nature, they should be preferred before a company that had never done anything for the nation. The further consideration of the matter was accordingly postponed for five days. In the mean time, a plan was drawn up by the governors of the bank. The South-Sea Company, afraid that the bank might offer still more advantageous terms to the government than themselves, reconsidered their former proposal, and made some alterations in it, which they hoped would render it more acceptable. The principal change was a stipulation that the government might redeem these debts at the expiration of four years, instead of seven, as at first suggested. The bank resolved not to be outbidden in this singular auction, and the governors also reconsidered their first proposal, and sent in a new one.

Thus, each corporation having made two proposals, the house began to deliberate. Mr Robert Walpole was the chief speaker in favour of the bank, and Mr Aislabie, the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the principal advocate on behalf of the South-Sea Company. It was resolved, on the 2nd of February, that the proposals of the latter were most advantageous to the country. They were accordingly received, and leave was given to bring in a bill to that effect.

Exchange Alley was in a fever of excitement. The company's stock, which had been at a hundred and thirty the previous day, gradually rose to three hundred, and continued to rise with the most astonishing rapidity during the whole time that the bill in its several stages was under discussion. Mr Walpole was almost the only statesman in the house who spoke out boldly against it. He warned them, in eloquent and solemn language, of the evils that would ensue. It countenanced, he said, 'the dangerous practice of stock-jobbing, and would divert the genius of the nation from trade and industry. It would hold out a dangerous lure to decoy the unwary to their ruin, by making them part with the earnings of their labour for a prospect of imaginary wealth. The great principle of the project was an evil of first-rate magnitude; it was to raise artificially the value of the stock, by exciting and keeping up a general infatuation, and by promising dividends out of funds which could never be adequate to the purpose.' In a prophetic spirit he added, that if the plan succeeded, the directors would become masters of the government, form a new and absolute aristocracy in the kingdom, and control the resolutions of the legislature. If it failed, which he was convinced it would, the result would bring general discontent and ruin upon the country. Such would be the delusion, that when the evil day came, as come it would, the people would start up, as from a dream, and ask themselves if these things could have been true. All his eloquence was in vain. He was looked upon as a false prophet, or compared to the hoarse raven, croaking omens of evil. His friends, however, compared him to Cassandra, predicting evils which would only be believed when they came home to men's hearths, and stared them in the face at their own boards. Although, in former times, the house had listened with the utmost attention to every word that fell from his lips, the benches became deserted when it was known that he would speak on the South-Sea question.

The bill was two months in its progress through the House of Commons. During this time every exertion was made by the directors and their friends, and more especially by the chairman, the noted Sir John Blunt, to raise the price of the stock. The most extravagant rumours were in circulation. Treaties between England and Spain were spoken of, whereby the latter was to grant a free trade to all her colonies; and the rich produce of the mines of Potosi-la-Paz was to be brought to England until silver should become almost as plentiful as iron. For cotton and woollen goods, with which we could supply them in abundance, the dwellers in Mexico were to empty their golden mines. The company of merchants trading to the South Seas would be the richest the world ever saw, and every hundred pounds invested in it would produce hundreds per annum to the stockholder. At last the stock was raised by these means to near four hundred; but, after fluctuating a good deal, settled at three hundred and thirty, at which price it remained when the bill passed the Commons by a majority of 172 against 55.

In the House of Lords the bill was hurried through all its stages with unexampled rapidity. On the 4th of April it was read a first time; on the 5th, it was read a second time; on the 6th, it was committed; and on the 7th, was read a third time and passed.

Several peers spoke warmly against the scheme; but their warnings fell upon dull, cold ears. A speculating frenzy had seized them as well as the plebeians. Lord North and Grey said the bill was unjust in its nature, and might prove fatal in its consequences, being calculated to enrich the few and impoverish the many. The Duke of Wharton followed; but, as he only retailed at second-hand the arguments so eloquently stated by Walpole in the Lower House, he was not listened to with even the same attention that had been bestowed upon Lord North and Grey. Earl Cowper followed on the same side, and compared the bill to the famous horse of the siege of Troy. Like that, it was ushered in and received with great pomp and acclamations of joy, but bore within it treachery and destruction. The Earl of Sunderland endeavoured to answer all objections; and on the question being put, there appeared only seventeen peers against, and eighty-three in favour of the project. The very same day on which it passed the Lords, it received the Royal assent, and became the law of the land.

It seemed at that time as if the whole nation had turned stock-jobbers. Exchange Alley was every day blocked up by crowds, and Cornhill was impassable for the number of carriages. Everybody came to purchase stock. 'Every fool aspired to be a knave.' In the words of a ballad, published at the time, and sung about the streets,

Then stars and garters did appear

Among the meaner rabble;

To buy and sell, to see and hear

The Jews and Gentiles squabble.

The greatest ladies thither came,

And plied in chariots daily,

Or pawned their jewels for a sum

The inordinate thirst of gain that had afflicted all ranks of society was not to be slaked even in the South Sea. Other schemes, of the most extravagant kind, were started. The share-lists were speedily filled up, and an enormous traffic carried on in shares, while, of course, every means were resorted to to raise them to an artificial value in the market.

Contrary to all expectation, South-Sea stock fell when the bill received the royal assent. On the 7th of April the shares were quoted at three hundred and ten, and on the following day at two hundred and ninety. Already the directors had tasted the profits of their scheme, and it was not likely that they should quietly allow the stock to find its natural level, without an effort to raise it. Immediately their busy emissaries were set to work. Every person interested in the success of the project endeavoured to draw a knot of listeners around him, to whom he expatiated on the treasures of the South American seas. Exchange Alley was crowded with attentive groups. One rumour alone, asserted with the utmost confidence, had an immediate effect upon the stock. It was said that Earl Stanhope had received overtures in France from the Spanish Government to exchange Gibraltar and Port Mahon for some places on the coast of Peru, for the security and enlargement of the trade in the South Seas. Instead of one annual ship trading to those ports, and allowing the king of Spain twenty-five per cent out of the profits, the company might build and charter as many ships as they pleased, and pay no percentage whatever to any foreign potentate. 'Visions of ingots danced before their eyes', and stock rose rapidly. On the 12th of April, five days after the bill had become law, the directors opened their books for a subscription of a million, at the rate of £300 for every £100 capital. Such was the concourse of persons of all ranks, that this first subscription was found to amount to above two millions of original stock. It was to be paid at five payments, of £60 each for every £100. In a few days the stock advanced to three hundred and forty, and the subscriptions were sold for double the price of the first payment. To raise the stock still higher, it was declared, in a general court of directors, on the 21st of April, that the midsummer dividend should be ten per cent, and that all subscriptions should be entitled to the same. These resolutions answering the end designed, the directors, to improve the infatuation of the monied men, opened their books for a second subscription of a million, at four hundred per cent. Such was the frantic eagerness of people of every class to speculate in these funds, that in the course of a few hours no less than a million and a half was subscribed at that rate.

In the mean time, innumerable joint-stock companies started up everywhere. They soon received the name of Bubbles, the most appropriate that imagination could devise. The populace are often most happy in the nicknames they employ. None could be more apt than that of Bubbles. Some of them lasted for a week, or a fortnight, and were no more heard of, while others could not even live out that short span of existence. Every evening produced new schemes, and every morning new projects. The highest of the aristocracy were as eager in this hot pursuit of gain as the most plodding jobber in Cornhill. The Prince of Wales became governor of one company, and is said to have cleared £40,000 by his speculations. The Duke of Bridgewater started a scheme for the improvement of London and Westminster, and the Duke of Chandos another. There were nearly a hundred different projects, each more extravagant and deceptive than the other. To use the words of the Political State, they were 'set on foot and promoted by crafty knaves, then pursued by multitudes of covetous fools, and at last appeared to be, in effect, what their vulgar appellation denoted them to be — bubbles and mere cheats'. It was computed that near one million and a half sterling was won and lost by these unwarrantable practices, to the impoverishment of many a fool, and the enriching of many a rogue.

Some of these schemes were plausible enough, and, had they been undertaken at a time when the public mind was unexcited, might have been pursued with advantage to all concerned. But they were established merely with the view of raising the shares in the market. The projectors took the first opportunity of a rise to sell out, and next morning the scheme was at an end. Maitland, in his History of London, gravely informs us, that one of the projects which received great encouragement, was for the establishment of a company 'to make deal boards out of sawdust'. This is no doubt intended as a joke; but there is abundance of evidence to show that dozens of schemes, hardly a whit more reasonable, lived their little day, ruining hundreds ere they fell. One of them was for a wheel for perpetual motion — capital, one million; another was 'for encouraging the breed of horses in England, and improving of glebe and church lands, and repairing and rebuilding parsonage and vicarage houses'. Why the clergy, who were so mainly interested in the latter clause, should have taken so much interest in the first, is only to be explained on the supposition that the scheme was projected by a knot of the foxhunting parsons, once so common in England. The shares of this company were rapidly subscribed for. But the most absurd and preposterous of all, and which showed, more completely than any other, the utter madness of the people, was one started by an unknown adventurer, entitled 'A company for carrying on an undertaking of great advantage, but nobody to know what it is'. Were not the fact stated by scores of credible witnesses, it would be impossible to believe that any person could have been duped by such a project. The man of genius who essayed this bold and successful inroad upon public credulity, merely stated in his prospectus that the required capital was half a million, in five thousand shares of £100 each, deposit £2 per share. Each subscriber, paying his deposit, would be entitled to £100 per annum per share. How this immense profit was to be obtained, he did not condescend to inform them at that time, but promised that in a month full particulars should be duly announced, and a call made for the remaining £98 of the subscription. Next morning, at nine o'clock, this great man opened an office in Cornhill. Crowds of people beset his door, and when he shut up at three o'clock, he found that no less than one thousand shares had been subscribed for, and the deposits paid. He was thus, in five hours, the winner of £2,000. He was philosopher enough to be contented with his venture, and set off the same evening for the Continent. He was never heard of again.

Well might Swift exclaim, comparing Change Alley to a gulf in the South Sea:

Subscribers here by thousands float,

　And jostle one another down,

Each paddling in his leaky boat,

　And here they fish for gold, and drown.

Now buried in the depths below,

　Now mounted up to heaven again,

They reel and stagger to and fro,

　At their wit's end, like drunken men.

Meantime, secure on Garraway cliffs,

　A savage race, by shipwrecks fed,

Lie waiting for the foundered skiffs,

　And strip the bodies of the dead.

Another fraud that was very successful was that of the 'Globe Permits', as they were called. They were nothing more than square pieces of playing-cards, on which was the impression of a seal, in wax, bearing the sign of the Globe Tavern, in the neighbourhood of Exchange Alley, with the inscription of 'Sail-Cloth Permits'. The possessors enjoyed no other advantage from them than permission to subscribe at some future time to a new sail-cloth manufactory, projected by one who was then known to be a man of fortune, but who was afterwards involved in the peculation and punishment of the South-Sea directors. These permits sold for as much as sixty guineas in the Alley.

Persons of distinction, of both sexes, were deeply engaged in all these bubbles; those of the male sex going to taverns and coffee-houses to meet their brokers, and the ladies resorting for the same purpose to the shops of milliners and haberdashers. But it did not follow that all these people believed in the feasibility of the schemes to which they subscribed; it was enough for their purpose that their shares would, by stock-jobbing arts, be soon raised to a premium, when they got rid of them with all expedition to the really credulous. So great was the confusion of the crowd in the alley, that shares in the same bubble were known to have been sold at the same instant ten per cent higher at one end of the alley than at the other. Sensible men beheld the extraordinary infatuation of the people with sorrow and alarm. There were some both in and out of parliament who foresaw clearly the ruin that was impending. Mr Walpole did not cease his gloomy forebodings. His fears were shared by all the thinking few, and impressed most forcibly upon the government. On the 11th of June, the day the parliament rose, the king published a proclamation, declaring that all these unlawful projects should be deemed public nuisances, and prosecuted accordingly, and forbidding any broker, under a penalty of five hundred pounds, from buying or selling any shares in them. Notwithstanding this proclamation, roguish speculators still carried them on, and the deluded people still encouraged them. On the 12th of July, an order of the Lords Justices assembled in privy council was published, dismissing all the petitions that had been presented for patents and charters, and dissolving all the bubble companies. The following copy of their lordships' order, containing a list of all these nefarious projects, will not be deemed uninteresting at the present day, when there is but too much tendency in the public mind to indulge in similar practices:

At the Council Chamber, Whitehall, the 12th day of July, 1720.

Present, their Excellencies the Lords Justices in Council.

Their Excellencies, the Lords Justices, in council, taking into consideration the many inconveniences arising to the public from several projects set on foot for raising of joint-stock for various purposes, and that a great many of his Majesty's subjects have been drawn in to part with their money on pretence of assurances that their petitions for patents and charters, to enable them to carry on the same, would be granted: to prevent such impositions, their excellencies this day ordered the said several petitions, together with such reports from the Board of Trade, and from his majesty's attorney and solicitorgeneral, as had been obtained thereon, to be laid before them; and after mature consideration thereof, were pleased, by advice of his majesty's privy council, to order that the said petitions be dismissed, which are as follow:

1. Petition of several persons, praying letters patent for carrying on a fishing trade, by the name of the Grand Fishery of Great Britain.

2. Petition of the Company of the Royal Fishery of England, praying letters patent for such further powers as will effectually contribute to carry on the said fishery.

3. Petition of George James, on behalf of himself and divers persons of distinction concerned in a national fishery, praying letters patent of incorporation to enable them to carry on the same.

4. Petition of several merchants, traders, and others, whose names are thereunto subscribed, praying to be incorporated for reviving and carrying on a whale fishery to Greenland and elsewhere.

5. Petition of Sir John Lambert, and others thereto subscribing, on behalf of themselves and a great number of merchants, praying to be incorporated for carrying on a Greenland trade, and particularly a whale fishery in Davis's Straits.

6. Another petition for a Greenland trade.

7. Petition of several merchants, gentlemen, and citizens, praying to be incorporated for buying and building of ships to let or freight.

8. Petition of Samuel Antrim and others, praying for letters patent for sowing hemp and flax.

9. Petition of several merchants, masters of ships, sail-makers, and manufacturers of sail-cloth, praying a charter of incorporation, to enable them to carry on and promote the said manufactory by a joint-stock.

10. Petition of Thomas Boyd, and several hundred merchants, owners and masters of ships, sail-makers, weavers, and other traders, praying a charter of incorporation, empowering them to borrow money for purchasing lands, in order to the manufacturing sail-cloth and fine Holland.

11. Petition on behalf of several persons interested in a patent granted by the late King William and Queen Mary, for the making of linen and sail-cloth, praying that no charter may be granted to any persons whatsoever for making sail-cloth, but that the privilege now enjoyed by them may be confirmed, and likewise an additional power to carry on the cotton and cotton-silk manufactures.

12. Petition of several citizens, merchants, and traders in London, and others, subscribers to a British stock for a general insurance from fire in any part of England, praying to be incorporated for carrying on the said undertaking.

13. Petition of several of his majesty's loyal subjects of the city of London and other parts of Great Britain, praying to be incorporated for carrying on a general insurance from losses by fire within the kingdom of England.

14. Petition of Thomas Burges, and others his majesty's subjects thereto subscribing, in behalf of themselves and others, subscribers to a fund of £1,200,000 for carrying on a trade to his majesty's German dominions, praying to be incorporated, by the name of the Harburg Company.

15. Petition of Edward Jones, a dealer in timber, on behalf of himself and others, praying to be incorporated for the importation of timber from Germany.

16. Petition of several merchants of London, praying a charter of incorporation for carrying on a salt-work.

17. Petition of Captain Macphedris of London, merchant, on behalf of himself and several merchants, clothiers, hatters, dyers, and other traders, praying a charter of incorporation empowering them to raise a sufficient sum of money to purchase lands for planting and rearing a wood called madder, for the use of dyers.

18. Petition of Joseph Galendo of London, snuffmaker, praying a patent for his invention to prepare and cure Virginia tobacco for snuff in Virginia, and making it into the same in all his majesty's dominions.

LIST OF BUBBLES

The following Bubble Companies were by the same order declared to be illegal, and abolished accordingly:

1. For the importation of Swedish iron.

2. For supplying London with sea-coal. Capital, three millions.

3. For building and rebuilding houses throughout all England. Capital, three millions.

4. For making of muslin.

5. For carrying on and improving British alum-works.

6. For effectually settling the island of Blanco and Sal Targatus.

7. For supplying the town of Deal with fresh water.

8. For the importation of Flanders lace.

9. For improvement in lands of Great Britain. Capital, four millions.

10. For encouraging the breed of horses in England, and improving the glebe and church lands, and for repairing and rebuilding parsonage and vicarage houses.

11. For making of iron and steel in Great Britain.

12. For improving the land in the county of Flint. Capital, one million.

13. For purchasing lands to build on. Capital, two millions.

14. For trading in hair.

15. For erecting salt-works in holy Island. Capital, two millions.

16. For buying and selling estates, and lending money on mortgage.

17. For carrying on an undertaking of great advantage, but nobody to know what it is.

18. For paving the streets of London. Capital, two millions.

19. For furnishing funerals to any part of Great Britain.

20. For buying and selling lands and lending money at interest. Capital, five millions.

21. For carrying on the Royal Fishery of Great Britain. Capital, ten millions.

22. For assuring of seamen's wages.

23. For erecting loan-offices for the assistance and encouragement of the industrious. Capital, two millions.

24. For purchasing and improving leasable lands. Capital, four millions.

25. For importing pitch and tar, and other naval stores, from North Britain and America.

26. For the clothing, felt, and pantile trade.

27. For purchasing and improving a manor and royalty in Essex.

28. For insuring of horses. Capital, two millions.

29. For exporting the woollen manufacture, and importing copper, brass, and iron. Capital, four millions.

30. For a grand dispensary. Capital, three millions.

31. For erecting mills and purchasing lead mines. Capital, two millions.

32. For improving the art of making soap.

33. For a settlement on the island of Santa Cruz.

34. For sinking pits and smelting lead ore in Derbyshire.

35. For making glass bottles and other glass.

36. For a wheel for perpetual motion. Capital, one million.

37. For improving of gardens.

38. For insuring and increasing children's fortunes.

39. For entering and loading goods at the Customhouse, and for negotiating business for merchants.

40. For carrying on a woollen manufacture in the north of England.

41. For importing walnut trees from Virginia. Capital, two millions.

42. For making Manchester stuffs of thread and cotton.

43. For making Joppa and Castile soap.

44. For improving the wrought-iron and steel manufactures of this kingdom. Capital, four millions.

45. For dealing in lace, hollands, cambrics, lawns, &amp;c. Capital, two millions.

46. For trading in and improving certain commodities of the produce of this kingdom, &c. Capital, three millions.

47. For supplying the London markets with cattle.

48. For making looking-glasses, coach glasses, &c. Capital, two millions.

49. For working the tin and lead mines in Cornwall and Derbyshire.

50. For making rape-oil.

51. For importing beaver fur. Capital, two millions.

52. For making pasteboard and packing-paper.

53. For importing of oils and other materials used in the woollen manufacture.

54. For improving and increasing the silk manufactures.

55. For lending money on stock, annuities, tallies, &c.

56. For paying pensions to widows and others, at a small discount. Capital, two millions.

57. For improving malt liquors. Capital, four millions.

58. For a grand American fishery.

59. For purchasing and improving the fenny lands in Lincolnshire. Capital, two millions.

60. For improving the paper manufacture of Great Britain.

61. The Bottomry Company.

62. For drying malt by hot air.

63. For carrying on a trade in the river Oronooko.

64. For the more effectual making of baize, in Colchester and other parts of Great Britain.

65. For buying of naval stores, supplying the victualling, and paying the wages of the workmen.

66. For employing poor artificers, and furnishing merchants and others with watches.

67. For improvement of tillage and the breed of cattle.

68. Another for the improvement of our breed of horses.

69. Another for a horse-insurance.

70. For carrying on the corn trade of Great Britain.

71. For insuring to all masters and mistresses the losses they may sustain by servants. Capital, three millions.

72. For erecting houses or hospitals, for taking in and maintaining illegitimate children. Capital, two millions.

73. For bleaching coarse sugars, without the use of fire or loss of substance.

74. For building turnpikes and wharfs in Great Britain.

75. For insuring from thefts and robberies.

76. For extracting silver from lead.

77. For making china and delft ware. Capital, one million.

78. For importing tobacco, and exporting it again to Sweden and the north of Europe. Capital, four millions.

79. For making iron with pit coal.

80. For furnishing the cities of London and Westminster with hay and straw. Capital, three millions.

81. For a sail and packing-cloth manufactory in Ireland.

82. For taking up ballast.

83. For buying and fitting out ships to suppress pirates.

84. For the importation of timber from Wales. Capital, two millions.

85. For rock-salt.

86. For the transmutation of quicksilver into a malleable fine metal.

Besides these bubbles, many others sprang up daily, in spite of the condemnation of the government and the ridicule of the still sane portion of the public. The printshops teemed with caricatures, and the newspapers with epigrams and satires, upon the prevalent folly. An ingenious card-maker published a pack of South-Sea playingcards, which are now extremely rare, each card containing, besides the usual figures, of a very small size, in one corner, a caricature of a bubble company, with appropriate verses underneath. One of the most famous bubbles was 'Puckle's Machine Company', for discharging round and square cannon-balls and bullets, and making a total revolution in the art of war. Its pretensions to public favour were thus summed up, on the eight of spades:

A rare invention to destroy the crowd

Of fools at home, instead of fools abroad.

Fear not, my friends, this terrible machine,

They're only wounded who have shares therein.

The nine of hearts was a caricature of the English Copper and Brass Company, with the following epigram:

The headlong fool that wants to be a swopper

Of gold and silver coin for English copper,

May, in Change Alley, prove himself an ass,

And give rich metal for adulterate brass.

The eight of diamonds celebrated the company for the colonisation of Acadia, with this doggerel:

He that is rich and wants to fool away

A good round sum in North America,

Let him subscribe himself a headlong sharer,

And asses' ears shall honour him or bearer.

And in a similar style every card of the pack exposed some knavish scheme, and ridiculed the persons who were its dupes. It was computed that the total amount of the sums proposed for carrying on these projects was upwards of three hundred millions sterling.

It is time, however, to return to the great South-Sea gulf, that swallowed the fortunes of so many thousands of the avaricious and the credulous. On the 29th of May, the stock had risen as high as five hundred, and about two-thirds of the government annuitants had exchanged the securities of the state for those of the South-Sea Company. During the whole of the month of May the stock continued to rise, and on the 28th it was quoted at five hundred and fifty. In four days after this it took a prodigious leap, rising suddenly from five hundred and fifty to eight hundred and ninety. It was now the general opinion that the stock could rise no higher, and many persons took that opportunity of selling out, with a view of realising their profits. Many noblemen and persons in the train of the king, and about to accompany him to Hanover, were also anxious to sell out. So many sellers, and so few buyers, appeared in the Alley on the 3rd of June, that the stock fell at once from eight hundred and ninety to six hundred and forty. The directors were alarmed, and gave their agents orders to buy. Their efforts succeeded. Towards evening confidence was restored, and the stock advanced to seven hundred and fifty. It continued at this price, with some slight fluctuation, until the company closed their books on the 22nd of June.

It would be needless and uninteresting to detail the various arts employed by the directors to keep up the price of stock. It will be sufficient to state that it finally rose to one thousand per cent. It was quoted at this price in the commencement of August. The bubble was then full-blown, and began to quiver and shake, preparatory to its bursting.

Many of the government annuitants expressed dissatisfaction against the directors. They accused them of partiality in making out the lists for shares in each subscription. Further uneasiness was occasioned by its being generally known that Sir John Blunt, the chairman, and some others, had sold out. During the whole of the month of August the stock fell, and on the 2nd of September it was quoted at seven hundred only.

The state of things now became alarming. To prevent, if possible, the utter extinction of public confidence in their proceedings, the directors summoned a general court of the whole corporation, to meet in Merchant Tailors' Hall on the 8th of September. By nine o'clock in the morning, the room was filled to suffocation; Cheapside was blocked up by a crowd unable to gain admittance, and the greatest excitement prevailed. The directors and their friends mustered in great numbers. Sir John Fellowes, the sub-governor, was called to the chair. He acquainted the assembly with the cause of their meeting; read to them the several resolutions of the court of directors, and gave them an account of their proceedings; of the taking in the redeemable and unredeemable funds, and of the subscriptions in money. Mr Secretary Craggs then made a short speech, wherein he commended the conduct of the directors, and urged that nothing could more effectually contribute to the bringing this scheme to perfection than union among themselves. He concluded with a motion for thanking the court of directors for their prudent and skilful management, and for desiring them to proceed in such manner as they should think most proper for the interest and advantage of the corporation. Mr Hungerford, who had rendered himself very conspicuous in the House of Commons for his zeal in behalf of the South-Sea Company, and who was shrewdly suspected to have been a considerable gainer by knowing the right time to sell out, was very magniloquent on this occasion. He said that he had seen the rise and fall, the decay and resurrection of many communities of this nature, but that, in his opinion, none had ever performed such wonderful things in so short a time as the South-Sea Company. They had done more than the crown, the pulpit, or the bench could do. They had reconciled all parties in one common interest; they had laid asleep, if not wholly extinguished, all the domestic jars and animosities of the nation. By the rise of their stock, monied men had vastly increased their fortunes; >country gentlemen had seen the value of their lands doubled and trebled in their hands. They had at the same time done good to the Church, not a few of the reverend clergy having got great sums by the project. In short, they had enriched the whole nation, and he hoped they had not forgotten themselves. There was some hissing at the latter part of this speech, which for the extravagance of its eulogy was not far removed from satire; but the directors and their friends, and all the winners in the room, applauded vehemently. The Duke of Portland spoke in a similar strain, and expressed his great wonder why anybody should be dissatisfied: of course, he was a winner by his speculations, and in a condition similar to that of the fat alderman in Joe Miller's Jests, who, whenever he had eaten a good dinner, folded his hands upon his paunch, and expressed his doubts whether there could be a hungry man in the world.

Several resolutions were passed at this meeting, but they had no effect upon the public. Upon the very same evening the stock fell to six hundred and forty, and on the morrow to five hundred and forty. Day after day it continued to fall, until it was as low as four hundred. In a letter, dated September 13th, from Mr Broderick MP to Lord Chancellor Middleton, and published in Coxe's Walpole, the former says: 'Various are the conjectures why the South-Sea directors have suffered the cloud to break so early. I made no doubt but they would do so when they found it to their advantage. They have stretched credit so far beyond what it would bear, that specie proves insufficient to support it. Their most considerable men have drawn out, securing themselves by the losses of the deluded, thoughtless numbers, whose understandings have been overruled by avarice and the hope of making mountains out of molehills. Thousands of families will be reduced to beggary. The consternation is inexpressible — the rage beyond description, and the case altogether so desperate that I do not see any plan or scheme so much as thought of for averting the blow, so that I cannot pretend to guess what is next to be done.' Ten days afterwards, the stock still falling, he writes: 'The company have yet come to no determination, for they are in such a wood that they know not which way to turn. By several gentlemen lately come to town, I perceive the very name of a South-Sea-man grows abominable in every country. A great many goldsmiths are already run off, and more will daily. I question whether one-third, nay, one-fourth, of them can stand it. From the very beginning, I founded my judgement of the whole affair upon the unquestionable maxim, that ten millions (which is more than our running cash) could not circulate two hundred millions, beyond which our paper credit extended. That, therefore, whenever that should become doubtful, be the cause what it would, our noble state machine must inevitably fall to the ground.'

On the 12th of September, at the earnest solicitation of Mr Secretary Craggs, several conferences were held between the directors of the South Sea and the directors of the Bank. A report which was circulated, that the latter had agreed to circulate six millions of the South-Sea Company's bonds, caused the stock to rise to six hundred and seventy; but in the afternoon, as soon as the report was known to be groundless, the stock fell again to five hundred and eighty; the next day to five hundred and seventy, and so gradually to four hundred.[〔1〕]

The ministry were seriously alarmed at the aspect of affairs. The directors could not appear in the streets without being insulted; dangerous riots were every moment apprehended. Despatches were sent off to the king at Hanover, praying his immediate return. Mr Walpole, who was staying at his country seat, was sent for, that he might employ his known influence with the directors of the Bank of England to induce them to accept the proposal made by the South-Sea Company for circulating a number of their bonds.

The Bank was very unwilling to mix itself up with the affairs of the company; it dreaded being involved in calamities which it could not relieve, and received all overtures with visible reluctance. But the universal voice of the nation called upon it to come to the rescue. Every person of note in commercial politics was called in to advise in the emergency. A rough draft of a contract drawn up by Mr Walpole was ultimately adopted as the basis of further negotiations, and the public alarm abated a little.

On the following day, the 20th of September, a general court of the South-Sea Company was held at Merchant Tailors' Hall, in which resolutions were carried, empowering the directors to agree with the Bank of England, or any other persons, to circulate the company's bonds, or make any other agreement with the bank which they should think proper. One of the speakers, a Mr Pulteney, said it was most surprising to see the extraordinary panic which had seized upon the people. Men were running to and fro in alarm and terror, their imaginations filled with some great calamity, the form and dimensions of which nobody knew:

Black it stood as night —

Fierce as ten furies — terrible as hell.

At a general court of the Bank of England held two days afterwards, the governor informed them of the several meetings that had been held on the affairs of the South-Sea Company, adding that the directors had not yet thought fit to come to any decision upon the matter. A resolution was then proposed, and carried without a dissentient voice, empowering the directors to agree with those of the South Sea to circulate their bonds, to what sum, and upon what terms, and for what time, they might think proper.

Thus both parties were at liberty to act as they might judge best for the public interest. Books were opened at the Bank for a subscription of three millions for the support of public credit, on the usual terms of £15 per cent deposit, £3 per cent premium, and £5 per cent interest. So great was the concourse of people in the early part of the morning, all eagerly bringing their money, that it was thought the subscription would be filled that day; but before noon, the tide turned. In spite of all that could be done to prevent it, the South-Sea Company's stock fell rapidly. Their bonds were in such discredit, that a run commenced upon the most eminent goldsmiths and bankers, some of whom having lent out great sums upon South-Sea stock were obliged to shut up their shops and abscond. The Sword-blade Company, who had hitherto been the chief cashiers of the South-Sea Company, stopped payment. This being looked upon as but the beginning of evil, occasioned a great run upon the Bank, who were now obliged to pay out money much faster than they had received it upon the subscription in the morning. The day succeeding was a holiday (the 29th of September), and the Bank had a little breathing time. They bore up against the storm; but their former rivals, the South-Sea Company, were wrecked upon it. Their stock fell to one hundred and fifty, and gradually, after various fluctuations, to one hundred and thirty-five.

The Bank, finding they were not able to restore public confidence, and stem the tide of ruin, without running the risk of being swept away with those they intended to save, declined to carry out the agreement into which they had partially entered. They were under no obligation whatever to continue; for the so-called Bank contract was nothing more than the rough draught of an agreement, in which blanks had been left for several important particulars, and which contained no penalty for their secession. 'And thus,' to use the words of the Parliamentary History, 'were seen, in the space of eight months, the rise, progress, and fall of that mighty fabric, which, being wound up by mysterious springs to a wonderful height, had fixed the eyes and expectations of all Europe, but whose foundation, being fraud, illusion, credulity, and infatuation, fell to the ground as soon as the artful management of its directors was discovered.'

In the heyday of its blood, during the progress of this dangerous delusion, the manners of the nation became sensibly corrupted. The parliamentary inquiry, set on foot to discover the delinquents, disclosed scenes of infamy, disgraceful alike to the morals of the offenders and the intellects of the people among whom they had arisen. It is a deeply interesting study to investigate all the evils that were the result. Nations, like individuals, cannot become desperate gamblers with impunity. Punishment is sure to overtake them sooner or later. A celebrated writer[〔2〕] is quite wrong, when he says, 'that such an era as this is the most unfavourable for a historian; that no reader of sentiment and imagination can be entertained or interested by a detail of transactions such as these, which admit of no warmth, no colouring, no embellishment; a detail of which only serves to exhibit an inanimate picture of tasteless vice and mean degeneracy.' On the contrary — and Smollett might have discovered it, if he had been in the humour — the subject is capable of inspiring as much interest as even a novelist can desire. Is there no warmth in the despair of a plundered people? — no life and animation in the picture which might be drawn of the woes of hundreds of impoverished and ruined families? of the wealthy of yesterday become the beggars of today? of the powerful and influential changed into exiles and outcasts, and the voice of self-reproach and imprecation resounding from every corner of the land? Is it a dull or uninstructive picture to see a whole people shaking suddenly off the trammels of reason, and running wild after a golden vision, refusing obstinately to believe that it is not real, till, like a deluded hind running after an ignis fatuus, they are plunged into a quagmire? But in this false spirit has history too often been written. The intrigues of unworthy courtiers to gain the favour of still more unworthy kings; or the records of murderous battles and sieges have been dilated on, and told over and over again, with all the eloquence of style and all the charms of fancy; while the circumstances which have most deeply affected the morals and welfare of the people have been passed over with but slight notice as dry and dull, and capable of neither warmth nor colouring.

During the progress of this famous bubble, England presented a singular spectacle. The public mind was in a state of unwholesome fermentation. Men were no longer satisfied with the slow but sure profits of cautious industry. The hope of boundless wealth for the morrow made them heedless and extravagant for today. A luxury, till then unheard-of, was introduced, bringing in its train a corresponding laxity of morals. The overbearing insolence of ignorant men, who had arisen to sudden wealth by successful gambling, made men of true gentility of mind and manners blush that gold should have power to raise the unworthy in the scale of society. The haughtiness of some of these 'cyphering cits', as they were termed by Sir Richard Steele, was remembered against them in the day of their adversity. In the parliamentary inquiry, many of the directors suffered more for their insolence than for their peculation. One of them, who, in the full-blown pride of an ignorant rich man, had said that he would feed his horse upon gold, was reduced almost to bread and water for himself; every haughty look, every overbearing speech, was set down, and repaid them a hundredfold in poverty and humiliation.

The state of matters all over the country was so alarming, that George I shortened his intended stay in Hanover, and returned in all haste to England. He arrived on the 11th of November, and parliament was summoned to meet on the 8th of December. In the mean time, public meetings were held in every considerable town of the empire, at which petitions were adopted, praying the vengeance of the Legislature upon the South-Sea directors, who, by their fraudulent practices, had brought the nation to the brink of ruin. Nobody seemed to imagine that the nation itself was as culpable as the South-Sea Company. Nobody blamed the credulity and avarice of the people — the degrading lust of gain, which had swallowed up every nobler quality in the national character, or the infatuation which had made the multitude run their heads with such frantic eagerness into the net held out for them by scheming projectors. These things were never mentioned. The people were a simple, honest, hardworking people, ruined by a gang of robbers, who were to be hanged, drawn, and quartered without mercy.

This was the almost unanimous feeling of the country. The two Houses of Parliament were not more reasonable. Before the guilt of the South-Sea directors was known, punishment was the only cry. The king, in his speech from the throne, expressed his hope that they would remember that all their prudence, temper, and resolution were necessary to find out and apply the proper remedy for their misfortunes. In the debate on the answer to the address, several speakers indulged in the most violent invectives against the directors of the South-Sea project. The Lord Molesworth was particularly vehement. 'It had been said by some, that there was no law to punish the directors of the South-Sea Company, who were justly looked upon as the authors of the present misfortunes of the state. In his opinion they ought upon this occasion to follow the example of the ancient Romans, who, having no law against parricide, because their legislators supposed no son could be so unnaturally wicked as to embrue his hands in his father's blood, made a law to punish this heinous crime as soon as it was committed. They adjudged the guilty wretch to be sown in a sack, and thrown alive into the Tiber. He looked upon the contrivers and executors of the villainous South-Sea scheme as the parricides of their country, and should be satisfied to see them tied in like manner in sacks, and thrown into the Thames.' Other members spoke with as much want of temper and discretion. Mr Walpole was more moderate. He recommended that their first care should be to restore public credit. 'If the city of London were on fire, all wise men would aid in extinguishing the flames, and preventing the spread of the conflagration before they enquired after the incendiaries. Public credit had received a dangerous wound, and lay bleeding, and they ought to apply a speedy remedy to it. It was time enough to punish the assassin afterwards.' On the 9th of December an address, in answer to his majesty's speech, was agreed upon, after an amendment, which was carried without a division, that words should be added expressive of the determination of the house not only to seek a remedy for the national distresses, but to punish the authors of them.

The inquiry proceeded rapidly. The directors were ordered to lay before the house a full account of all their proceedings. Resolutions were passed to the effect that the calamity was mainly owing to the vile arts of stockjobbers, and that nothing could tend more to the reestablishment of public credit than a law to prevent this infamous practice. Mr Walpole then rose, and said, that 'as he had previously hinted, he had spent some time upon a scheme for restoring public credit, but that the execution of it depending upon a position which had been laid down as fundamental, he thought it proper, before he opened out his scheme, to be informed whether he might rely upon that foundation. It was, whether the subscription of public debts and encumbrances, money subscriptions, and other contracts, made with the SouthSea Company should remain in the present state?' This question occasioned an animated debate. It was finally agreed, by a majority of 259 against 117, that all these contracts should remain in their present state, unless altered for the relief of the proprietors by a general court of the South-Sea Company, or set aside by due course of law. On the following day Mr Walpole laid before a committee of the whole house his scheme for the restoration of public credit, which was, in substance, to engraft nine millions of South-Sea stock into the Bank of England, and the same sum into the East India Company, upon certain conditions. The plan was favourably received by the house. After some few objections, it was ordered that proposals should be received from the two great corporations. They were both unwilling to lend their aid, and the plan met with a warm but fruitless opposition at the general courts summoned for the purpose of deliberating upon it. They, however, ultimately agreed upon the terms on which they would consent to circulate the South-Sea bonds, and their report, being presented to the committee, a bill was brought in, under the superintendence of Mr Walpole, and safely carried through both Houses of Parliament.

A bill was at the same time brought in, for restraining the South-Sea directors, governor, sub-governor, treasurer, cashier, and clerks from leaving the kingdom for a twelvemonth, and for discovering their estates and effects, and preventing them from transporting or alienating the same. All the most influential members of the house supported the bill. Mr Shippen, seeing Mr Secretary Craggs in his place, and believing the injurious rumours that were afloat of that minister's conduct in the SouthSea business, determined to touch him to the quick. He said, he was glad to see a British House of Commons resuming its pristine vigour and spirit, and acting with so much unanimity for the public good. It was necessary to secure the persons and estates of the South-Sea directors and their officers; 'but,' he added, looking fixedly at Mr Craggs as he spoke, 'there were other men in high station, whom, in time, he would not be afraid to name, who were no less guilty than the directors.' Mr Craggs arose in great wrath, and said, that if the innuendo were directed against him, he was ready to give satisfaction to any man who questioned him, either in the House or out of it. Loud cries of order immediately arose on every side. In the midst of the uproar Lord Molesworth got up, and expressed his wonder at the boldness of Mr Craggs in challenging the whole House of Commons. He, Lord Molesworth, though somewhat old, past sixty, would answer Mr Craggs whatever he had to say in the House, and he trusted there were plenty of young men beside him, who would not be afraid to look Mr Craggs in the face, out of the House. The cries of order again resounded from every side; the members arose simultaneously; everybody seemed to be vociferating at once. The speaker in vain called order. The confusion lasted several minutes, during which Lord Molesworth and Mr Craggs were almost the only members who kept their seats. At last, the call for Mr Craggs became so violent that he thought proper to submit to the universal feeling of the House, and explain his unparliamentary expression. He said, that by giving satisfaction to the impugners of his conduct in that House, he did not mean that he would fight, but that he would explain his conduct. Here the matter ended, and the House proceeded to debate in what manner they should conduct their inquiry into the affairs of the SouthSea Company, whether in a grand or a select committee. Ultimately, a secret committee of thirteen was appointed, with power to send for persons, papers, and records.

The Lords were as zealous and as hasty as the Commons. The Bishop of Rochester said the scheme had been like a pestilence. The Duke of Wharton said the House ought to show no respect of persons; that, for his part, he would give up the dearest friend he had, if he had been engaged in the project. The nation had been plundered in a most shameful and flagrant manner, and he would go as far as anybody in the punishment of the offenders. Lord Stanhope said, that every farthing possessed by the criminals, whether directors or not directors, ought to be confiscated, to make good the public losses.

During all this time the public excitement was extreme. We learn, from Coxe's Walpole, that the very name of a South-Sea director was thought to be synonymous with every species of fraud and villainy. Petitions from counties, cities, and boroughs, in all parts of the kingdom, were presented, crying for the justice due to an injured nation and the punishment of the villainous peculators. Those moderate men, who would not go to extreme lengths, even in the punishment of the guilty, were accused of being accomplices, were exposed to repeated insults and virulent invectives, and devoted, both in anonymous letters and public writings, to the speedy vengeance of an injured people. The accusations against Mr Aislabie, Chancellor of the Exchequer, and Mr Craggs, another member of the ministry, were so loud, that the House of Lords resolved to proceed at once into the investigation concerning them. It was ordered, on the 21st of January, that all brokers concerned in the South-Sea scheme should lay before the house an account of the stock or subscriptions bought or sold by them for any of the officers of the Treasury or Exchequer, or in trust for any of them, since Michaelmas 1719. When this account was delivered, it appeared that large quantities of stock had been transferred to the use of Mr Aislabie. Five of the South-Sea directors, including Mr Edward Gibbon, the grandfather of the celebrated historian, were ordered into the custody of the black rod. Upon a motion made by Earl Stanhope, it was unanimously resolved, that the taking in or giving credit for stock without a valuable consideration actually paid or sufficiently secured; or the purchasing stock by any director or agent of the South-Sea Company, for the use or benefit of any member of the administration, or any member of either House of Parliament, during such time as the South-Sea bill was yet pending in parliament, was a notorious and dangerous corruption. Another resolution was passed a few days afterwards, to the effect that several of the directors and officers of the company having, in a clandestine manner, sold their own stock to the company, had been guilty of a notorious fraud and breach of trust, and had thereby mainly caused the unhappy turn of affairs that had so much affected public credit. Mr Aislabie resigned his office as Chancellor of the Exchequer, and absented himself from parliament until the formal inquiry into his individual guilt was brought under the consideration of the legislature.

In the mean time, Knight, the treasurer of the company, and who was entrusted with all the dangerous secrets of the dishonest directors, packed up his books and documents, and made his escape from the country. He embarked in disguise, in a small boat on the river, and proceeding to a vessel hired for the purpose, was safely conveyed to Calais. The Committee of Secrecy informed the House of the circumstance, when it was resolved unanimously that two addresses should be presented to the king; the first praying that he would issue a proclamation offering a reward for the apprehension of Knight; and the second, that he would give immediate orders to stop the ports, and to take effectual care of the coasts, to prevent the said Knight, or any other officers of the South-Sea Company, from escaping out of the kingdom. The ink was hardly dry upon these addresses before they were carried to the king by Mr Methuen, deputed by the House for that purpose. The same evening a royal proclamation was issued, offering a reward of two thousand pounds for the apprehension of Knight. The Commons ordered the doors of the House to be locked, and the keys to be placed upon the table. General Ross, one of the members of the Committee of Secrecy, acquainted them that they had already discovered a train of the deepest villainy and fraud that hell had ever contrived to ruin a nation, which in due time they would lay before the House. In the mean time, in order to a further discovery, the Committee thought it highly necessary to secure the persons of some of the directors and principal South-Sea officers, and to seize their papers. A motion to this effect having been made, was carried unanimously. Sir Robert Chaplin, Sir Theodore Janssen, Mr Sawbridge, and Mr F. Eyles, members of the House, and directors of the South-Sea Company, were summoned to appear in their places, and answer for their corrupt practices. Sir Theodore Janssen and Mr Sawbridge answered to their names, and endeavoured to exculpate themselves. The House heard them patiently, and then ordered them to withdraw. A motion was then made, and carried nemine contradicente, that they had been guilty of a notorious breach of trust — had occasioned much loss to great numbers of his majesty's subjects, and had highly prejudiced the public credit. It was then ordered that, for their offence, they should be expelled the House, and taken into the custody of the sergeant-at-arms. Sir Robert Chaplin and Mr Eyles, attending in their places four days afterwards, were also expelled the House. It was resolved at the same time to address the king to give directions to his ministers at foreign courts to make application for Knight, that he might be delivered up to the English authorities, in case he took refuge in any of their dominions. The king at once agreed, and messengers were despatched to all parts of the Continent the same night.

Among the directors taken into custody, was Sir John Blunt, the man whom popular opinion has generally accused of having been the original author and father of the scheme. This man, we are informed by Pope, in his epistle to Allen, Lord Bathurst, was a dissenter, of a most religious deportment, and professed to be a great believer. He constantly declaimed against the luxury and corruption of the age, the partiality of parliaments, and the misery of party spirit. He was particularly eloquent against avarice in great and noble persons. He was originally a scrivener, and afterwards became, not only a director, but the most active manager of the South-Sea Company. Whether it was during his career in this capacity that he first began to declaim against the avarice of the great, we are not informed. He certainly must have seen enough of it to justify his severest anathema; but if the preacher had himself been free from the vice he condemned, his declamations would have had a better effect. He was brought up in custody to the bar of the House of Lords, and underwent a long examination. He refused to answer several important questions. He said he had been examined already by a committee of the House of Commons, and as he did not remember his answers, and might contradict himself, he refused to answer before another tribunal. This declaration, in itself an indirect proof of guilt, occasioned some commotion in the House. He was again asked peremptorily whether he had ever sold any portion of the stock to any member of the administration, or any member of either House of Parliament, to facilitate the passing of the bill. He again declined to answer. He was anxious, he said, to treat the House with all possible respect, but he thought it hard to be compelled to accuse himself. After several ineffectual attempts to refresh his memory, he was directed to withdraw. A violent discussion ensued between the friends and opponents of the ministry. It was asserted that the administration were no strangers to the convenient taciturnity of Sir John Blunt. The Duke of Wharton made a reflection upon the Earl Stanhope, which the latter warmly resented. He spoke under great excitement, and with such vehemence as to cause a sudden determination of blood to the head. He felt himself so ill that he was obliged to leave the House and retire to his chamber. He was cupped immediately, and also let blood on the following morning, but with slight relief. The fatal result was not anticipated. Towards evening he became drowsy, and turning himself on his face, expired. The sudden death of this statesman caused great grief to the nation. George I was exceedingly affected, and shut himself up for some hours in his closet, inconsolable for his loss.

Knight, the treasurer of the company, was apprehended at Tirlemont, near Liège, by one of the secretaries of Mr Leathes, the British resident at Brussels, and lodged in the citadel of Antwerp. Repeated applications were made to the court of Austria to deliver him up, but in vain. Knight threw himself upon the protection of the states of Brabant, and demanded to be tried in that country. It was a privilege granted to the states of Brabant by one of the articles of the Foyeuse Entrée, that every criminal apprehended in that country should be tried in that country. The states insisted on their privilege, and refused to deliver Knight to the British authorities. The latter did not cease their solicitations; but in the mean time, Knight escaped from the citadel.

On the 16th of February the Committee of Secrecy made their first report to the House. They stated that their inquiry had been attended with numerous difficulties and embarrassments; everyone they had examined had endeavoured, as far as in him lay, to defeat the ends of justice. In some of the books produced before them, false and fictitious entries had been made; in others, there were entries of money, with blanks for the name of the stockholders. There were frequent erasures and alterations, and in some of the books leaves were torn out. They also found that some books of great importance had been destroyed altogether, and that some had been taken away or secreted. At the very entrance into their inquiry, they had observed that the matters referred to them were of great variety and extent. Many persons had been entrusted with various parts in the execution of the law, and under colour thereof had acted in an unwarrantable manner, in disposing of the properties of many thousands of persons, amounting to many millions of money. They discovered that, before the SouthSea Act was passed, there was an entry in the company's books of the sum of £1,259,325, upon account of stock stated to have been sold to the amount of £574,500. This stock was all fictitious, and had been disposed of with a view to promote the passing of the bill. It was noted as sold at various days, and at various prices, from 150 to 325 per cent. Being surprised to see so large an account disposed of, at a time when the company were not empowered to increase their capital, the Committee determined to investigate most carefully the whole transaction. The governor, sub-governor, and several directors were brought before them, and examined rigidly. They found that, at the time these entries were made, the company was not in possession of such a quantity of stock, having in their own right only a small quantity, not exceeding thirty thousand pounds at the utmost. Pursuing the inquiry, they found that this amount of stock was to be esteemed as taken in or holden by the company for the benefit of the pretended purchasers, although no mutual agreement was made for its delivery or acceptance at any certain time. No money was paid down, nor any deposit or security whatever given to the company by the supposed purchasers; so that if the stock had fallen, as might have been expected, had the act not passed, they would have sustained no loss. If, on the contrary, the price of stock advanced (as it actually did by the success of the scheme), the difference by the advanced price was to be made good to them. Accordingly, after the passing of the act, the account of stock was made up and adjusted with Mr Knight, and the pretended purchasers were paid the difference out of the company's cash. This fictitious stock, which had been chiefly at the disposal of Sir John Blunt, Mr Gibbon, and Mr Knight, was distributed among several members of the government and their connections, by way of bribe, to facilitate the passing of the bill. To the Earl of Sunderland was assigned £50,000 of this stock; to the Duchess of Kendal £10,000; to the Countess of Platen £10,000; to her two nieces £10,000; to Mr Secretary Craggs £30,000; to Mr Charles Stanhope (one of the secretaries of the Treasury) £10,000; to the Swordblade company £50,000. It also appeared that Mr Stanhope had received the enormous sum of £250,000 as the difference in the price of some stock, through the hands of Turner, Caswall, and Co., but that his name had been partly erased from their books, and altered to Stangape. Aislabie, the Chancellor of the Exchequer, had made profits still more abominable. He had an account with the same firm, who were also South-Sea directors, to the amount of £794,451. He had, besides, advised the company to make their second subscription one million and a half, instead of a million, by their own authority, and without any warrant. The third subscription had been conducted in a manner as disgraceful. Mr Aislabie's name was down for £70,000; Mr Craggs, senior, for £659,000; the Earl of Sunderland's for £160,000; and Mr Stanhope for £47,000. This report was succeeded by six others, less important. At the end of the last, the committee declared that the absence of Knight, who had been principally entrusted, prevented them from carrying on their enquiries.

The first report was ordered to be printed, and taken into consideration on the next day but one succeeding. After a very angry and animated debate, a series of resolutions were agreed to, condemnatory of the conduct of the directors, of the members of the parliament and of the administration concerned with them; and declaring that they ought, each and all, to make satisfaction out of their own estates for the injury they had done the public. Their practices were declared to be corrupt, infamous, and dangerous; and a bill was ordered to be brought in for the relief of the unhappy sufferers.

Mr Charles Stanhope was the first person brought to account for his share in these transactions. He urged in his defence that, for some years past, he had lodged all the money he was possessed of in Mr Knight's hands, and whatever stock Mr Knight had taken in for him, he had paid a valuable consideration for it. As to the stock that had been bought for him by Turner, Caswall, and Co., he knew nothing about it. Whatever had been done in that matter was done without his authority, and he could not be responsible for it. Turner and Co. took the latter charge upon themselves; but it was notorious to every unbiassed and unprejudiced person that Mr Stanhope was a gainer of the £250,000 which lay in the hands of that firm to his credit. He was, however, acquitted by a majority of three only. The greatest exertions were made to screen him. Lord Stanhope, the son of the Earl of Chesterfield, went round to the wavering members, using all the eloquence he was possessed of to induce them either to vote for the acquittal or to absent themselves from the House. Many weak-headed country gentlemen were led astray by his persuasions, and the result was as already stated. The acquittal caused the greatest discontent throughout the country. Mobs of a menacing character assembled in different parts of London; fears of riots were generally entertained, especially as the examination of a still greater delinquent was expected by many to have a similar termination. Mr Aislabie, whose high office and deep responsibilities should have kept him honest, even had native principle been insufficient, was very justly regarded as perhaps the greatest criminal of all. His case was entered into on the day succeeding the acquittal of Mr Stanhope. Great excitement prevailed, and the lobbies and avenues of the House were beset by crowds, impatient to know the result. The debate lasted the whole day. Mr Aislabie found few friends: his guilt was so apparent and so heinous that nobody had courage to stand up in his favour. It was finally resolved, without a dissentient voice, that Mr Aislabie had encouraged and promoted the destructive execution of the South-Sea scheme with a view to his own exorbitant profit, and had combined with the directors in their pernicious practices, to the ruin of the public trade and credit of the kingdom: that he should for his offences be ignominiously expelled from the House of Commons, and committed a close prisoner to the Tower of London; that he should be restrained from going out of the kingdom for a whole year, or till the end of the next session of Parliament; and that he should make out a correct account of all his estate, in order that it might be applied to the relief of those who had suffered by his malpractices.

This verdict caused the greatest joy. Though it was delivered at half-past twelve at night, it soon spread over the city. Several persons illuminated their houses in token of their joy. On the following day, when Mr Aislabie was conveyed to the Tower, the mob assembled on Tower-hill with the intention of hooting and pelting him. Not succeeding in this, they kindled a large bonfire, and danced around it in the exuberance of their delight. Several bonfires were made in other places; London presented the appearance of a holiday, and people congratulated one another as if they had just escaped from some great calamity. The rage upon the acquittal of Mr Stanhope had grown to such a height that none could tell where it would have ended, had Mr Aislabie met with the like indulgence.

To increase the public satisfaction, Sir George Caswall, of the firm of Turner, Caswall, and Co., was expelled from the House on the following day, committed to the Tower, and ordered to refund the sum of £250,000.

That part of the report of the Committee of Secrecy which related to the Earl of Sunderland was next taken into consideration. Every effort was made to clear his lordship from the imputation. As the case against him rested chiefly on the evidence extorted from Sir John Blunt, great pains were taken to make it appear that Sir John's word was not to be believed, especially in a matter affecting the honour of a peer and privy councillor. All the friends of the ministry rallied around the earl, it being generally reported that a verdict of guilty against him would bring a Tory ministry into power. He was eventually acquitted by a majority of 233 against 172; but the country was convinced of his guilt. The greatest indignation was everywhere expressed, and menacing mobs again assembled in London. Happily no disturbances took place.

This was the day on which Mr Craggs the elder expired. The morrow had been appointed for the consideration of his case. It was very generally believed that he had poisoned himself. It appeared, however, that grief for the loss of his son, one of the secretaries of the Treasury, who had died five weeks previously of the smallpox, preyed much on his mind. For this son, dearly beloved, he had been amassing vast heaps of riches: he had been getting money, but not honestly; and he for whose sake he had bartered his honour and sullied his fame, was now no more. The dread of further exposure increased his trouble of mind, and ultimately brought on an apoplectic fit, in which he expired. He left a fortune of a million and a half, which was afterwards confiscated for the benefit of the sufferers by the unhappy delusion he had been so mainly instrumental in raising.

One by one the case of every director of the company was taken into consideration. A sum amounting to two millions and fourteen thousand pounds was confiscated from their estates towards repairing the mischief they had done, each man being allowed a certain residue, in proportion to his conduct and circumstances, with which he might begin the world anew. Sir John Blunt was only allowed £5,000 out of his fortune of upwards of £183,000; Sir John Fellows was allowed £10,000 out of £243,000; Sir Theodore Janssen, £50,000 out of £243,000; Mr Edward Gibbon, £10,000 out of £106,000; Sir John Lambert, £5,000 out of £72,000. Others, less deeply involved, were treated with greater liberality. Gibbon, the historian, whose grandfather was the Mr Edward Gibbon so severely mulcted, has given, in the Memoirs of his Life and Writings, an interesting account of the proceedings in parliament at this time. He owns that he is not an unprejudiced witness; but, as all the writers from which it is possible to extract any notice of the proceedings of these disastrous years were prejudiced on the other side, the statements of the great historian become of additional value. If only on the principle of audi alteram partem, his opinion is entitled to consideration. 'In the year 1716,' he says, 'my grandfather was elected one of the directors of the South-Sea company, and his books exhibited the proof that before his acceptance of that fatal office, he had acquired an independent fortune of £60,000. But his fortune was overwhelmed in the shipwreck of the year 1720, and the labours of thirty years were blasted in a single day. Of the use or abuse of the South-Sea scheme, of the guilt or innocence of my grandfather and his brother directors, I am neither a competent nor a disinterested judge. Yet the equity of modern times must condemn the violent and arbitrary proceedings, which would have disgraced the cause of justice, and rendered injustice still more odious. No sooner had the nation awakened from its golden dream, than a popular, and even a parliamentary clamour demanded its victims; but it was acknowledged on all sides, that the directors, however guilty, could not be touched by any known laws of the land. The intemperate notions of Lord Molesworth were not literally acted on; but a bill of pains and penalties was introduced — a retroactive statute, to punish the offences which did not exist at the time they were committed. The legislature restrained the persons of the directors, imposed an exorbitant security for their appearance, and marked their character with a previous note of ignominy. They were compelled to deliver, upon oath, the strict value of their estates, and were disabled from making any transfer or alienation of any part of their property. Against a bill of pains and penalties, it is the common right of every subject to be heard by his counsel at the bar. They prayed to be heard. Their prayer was refused, and their oppressors, who required no evidence, would listen to no defence. It had been at first proposed, that one-eighth of their respective estates should be allowed for the future support of the directors; but it was especially urged that, in the various shades of opulence and guilt, such a proportion would be too light for many, and for some might possibly be too heavy. The character and conduct of each man were separately weighed; but, instead of the calm solemnity of a judicial inquiry, the fortune and honour of thirty-three Englishmen were made the topics of hasty conversation, the sport of a law-less majority; and the basest member of the committee, by a malicious word, or a silent vote, might indulge his general spleen or personal animosity. Injury was aggravated by insult, and insult was embittered by pleasantry. Allowances of £20 or 1s. were facetiously moved. A vague report that a director had formerly been concerned in another project, by which some unknown persons had lost their money, was admitted as a proof of his actual guilt. One man was ruined because he had dropped a foolish speech, that his horses should feed upon gold; another, because he was grown so proud, that one day, at the Treasury, he had refused a civil answer to persons much above him. All were condemned, absent and unheard, in arbitrary fines and forfeitures, which swept away the greatest part of their substance. Such bold oppression can scarcely be shielded by the omnipotence of parliament. My grandfather could not expect to be treated with more lenity than his companions. His Tory principles and connections rendered him obnoxious to the ruling powers. His name was reported in a suspicious secret. His well-known abilities could not plead the excuse of ignorance or error. In the first proceedings against the South-Sea directors, Mr Gibbon was one of the first taken into custody, and in the final sentence the measure of his fine proclaimed him eminently guilty. The total estimate, which he delivered on oath to the House of Commons, amounted to £106,543 5s. 6d., exclusive of antecedent settlements. Two different allowances of £15,000 and of £10,000 were moved for Mr Gibbon; but, on the question being put, it was carried without a division for the smaller sum. On these ruins, with the skill and credit of which parliament had not been able to despoil him, my grandfather, at a mature age, erected the edifice of a new fortune. The labours of sixteen years were amply rewarded; and I have reason to believe that the second structure was not much inferior to the first.'

The next consideration of the legislature, after the punishment of the directors, was to restore public credit. The scheme of Walpole had been found insufficient, and had fallen into disrepute. A computation was made of the whole capital stock of the South-Sea Company at the end of the year 1720. It was found to amount to thirty-seven millions eight hundred thousand pounds, of which the stock allotted to all the proprietors only amounted to twenty-four millions five hundred thousand pounds. The remainder of thirteen millions three hundred thousand pounds belonged to the company in their corporate capacity, and was the profit they had made by the national delusion. Upwards of eight millions of this were taken from the company, and divided among the proprietors and subscribers generally, making a dividend of about £33 6s. 8d. per cent. This was a great relief. It was further ordered, that such persons as had borrowed money from the South-Sea Company upon stock actually transferred and pledged at the time of borrowing to or for the use of the company, should be free from all demands, upon payment of ten per cent of the sums so borrowed. They had lent about eleven millions in this manner, at a time when prices were unnaturally raised; and they now received back one million one hundred thousand, when prices had sunk to their ordinary level.

But it was a long time before public credit was thoroughly restored. Enterprise, like Icarus, had soared too high, and melted the wax of her wings; like Icarus, she had fallen into a sea, and learned, while floundering in its waves, that her proper element was the solid ground. She has never since attempted so high a flight.

In times of great commercial prosperity there has been a tendency to over-speculation on several occasions since then. The success of one project generally produces others of a similar kind. Popular imitativeness will always, in a trading nation, seize hold of such successes, and drag a community too anxious for profits into an abyss from which extrication is difficult. Bubble companies, of a kind similar to those engendered by the South-Sea project, lived their little day in the famous year of the panic, 1825. On that occasion, as in 1720, knavery gathered a rich harvest from cupidity, but both suffered when the day of reckoning came. The schemes of the year 1836 threatened, at one time, results as disastrous; but they were happily averted before it was too late.[〔3〕]

注　释

〔1〕 Gay (the poet), in that disastrous year, had a present from young Craggs of some South-Sea stock, and once supposed himself to be master of twenty thousand pounds. His friends persuaded him to sell his share, but he dreamed of dignity and splendour, and could not bear to obstruct his own fortune. He was then importuned to sell as much as would purchase a hundred a year for life, 'which,' says Fenton, 'will make you sure of a clean shirt and a shoulder of mutton every day.' This counsel was rejected; the profit and principal were lost, and Gay sunk under the calamity so low that his life became in danger. — Johnson's Lives of the Poets.

〔2〕 Smollett.

〔3〕 The South-Sea project remained until 1845 the greatest example in British history of the infatuation of the people for commercial gambling. The first edition of these volumes was published some time before the outbreak of the Great Railway Mania of that and the following year.

导读

约翰·罗斯金（John Ruskin，1819—1900），生于英国伦敦，是英国著名的艺术评论家，也是维多利亚时代艺术美学的重要代表及实用艺术最积极的推动者。1843年，罗斯金凭借《现代画家》一书崭露头角，书中他高度赞扬了威廉·特纳的画作，主张艺术应当传达对自然的理解和欣赏。他的艺术评论代表了维多利亚时代艺术的欣赏趣味，并因此被誉为“美的使者”。同时，罗斯金还是一位文学家、思想家，其作品题材广泛而不拘泥于文体风格，语言优美凝练，内容深刻，对甘地、托尔斯泰和普鲁斯特都有较大影响。此外，作为工业设计思想的奠基者，罗斯金关注工业化生产成果的艺术质量，倡导通过工艺设计来找回人类被机械化生产和劳动分工所剥夺的创造性。这一主张唤醒了人们对工业革命之后艺术现状的反思，对“工艺美术”运动起到了巨大的推动作用。

罗斯金一生都在为“美”战斗，他坚决维护个人的艺术自由，反感维多利亚时代批量生产的艺术，其洞见深刻改变了社会对创意设计的理解，对当今的审美观仍有着极大的价值。本书选取的罗斯金的两篇文章“哥特式的性质”和“铁在自然、艺术和政治中的功用”，正是其艺术美学理念和人道主义思想的集中体现。

“哥特式的性质”选自罗斯金的《威尼斯的石头》一书，并且被他本人看作是“最重要的部分”。在这一章节中，罗斯金从外部和内部两方面论述了哥特式建筑的本质。首先，哥特式建筑普遍拥有尖拱和穹隆屋顶等的外在形式，而它的内在要素则是建造者精神趋向的表现，具有原始、多变、自然主义、怪诞、刚劲和冗余等六大特征。哥特式一词最初是用于表达对北方建筑原始野蛮的风格的贬抑，但罗斯金却在这种粗陋的建筑中找到了艺术最好的表现形式。哥特式建筑忠于自然主义，但那并不是对自然的机械模仿，而是对自然的“阐述”和“解释”。不同于希腊建筑的精益求精，哥特式建筑是允许“不完美”的，它坦率地承认自己的粗陋，诚实地展现了建造者自由思考创造的成果。与此同时，哥特式学派还热衷于变化，他们不盲从现有的原则，而是孜孜不倦地追求创新，这份奇异的不安分给哥特式精神带来了无限的生机与活力。另外，在罗斯金看来，北方民族的韧性在哥特式作品中也是有迹可循的。他们对于坚强意志、独立个性及既定目标的坚定追求，对权威和命运的反抗铸就了哥特式精神，而正是这种精神，这种粗糙刚劲与质朴自然的特性，赋予了哥特式建筑生命的张力和永恒的魅力，也成就了它的伟大。

“铁在自然、艺术和政治中的功用”则是罗斯金的一篇演讲稿。在这部分内容中，作者用生动优美的语言讲述了铁在自然、艺术和政治中的用途。在罗斯金眼中，生锈的铁是因“呼吸”而鲜活的铁；铁氧化物是大自然的染料，让世界变得温暖鲜活，更具生机，这是铁在自然中所能呈现的最好的形态。另一方面，铁坚固而又易延展，这一特性使得铁在雕塑等类型的艺术创作中极富表现力和庄严性。最后，在讲到铁的政治用途时，罗斯金充满激情地批判了不劳而获、压迫民众的统治者。他通过犁、脚镣和刀剑三个与铁相关的意象来阐释国家的三个护身符，即劳动、法律和勇气。罗斯金认为，一个国家只有做到劳动合理分配、律法完善、注重军队建设和士气的培养，才能够维持和平，长久地生存下去。

哥特式的性质

1.读者如果回想一下第一卷第一章[1]关于主题的划分，就会发现，我们即将展开对威尼斯建筑学派的研究。这一学派不仅是拜占庭风格与哥特式风格的过渡，而且，我发现，要找出该学派与哥特式风格之间的联系并不困难。为了弄清楚这一变化过程中每一步的趋势，最好从一开始就试着形成关于最终结果的基本概念。我们已经洞悉拜占庭建筑的由来及其演变，我们还应当大致了解由它过渡到哥特式建筑的情况。因此，我力图在本章向读者提供一个宽泛而明确的概念，即关于真正意义上的哥特式建筑真实本质的概念。此概念所涉及的不仅仅是威尼斯的哥特式建筑，而且是全世界的哥特式建筑：这将会是我们随后的论述中最有趣的部分，即发现威尼斯建筑达到了何等普遍或完美的哥特式形态，以及它在何种程度上有所欠缺，或者采用外来的、独立的形式。

2.这样做的难度主要源于以下事实：在某个重要方面，哥特时期的每一座建筑都各不相同；而且，很多建筑拥有的特征，如果出现在其他建筑物上，根本不会被视为哥特式风格。因此，我们只能判断——请允许我这样表达——我们所观察的每一座建筑或多或少都是“哥特式”的。我想要界定的正是这种哥特式的性质，即，根据在一座建筑物上能够发现这种特性的多寡，使其或多或少表现“哥特式”风格的特性。就像是如果有人试图解释“红色”的本质，却找不到任何一样纯粹是红色的事物；即使能找到橙色或紫色的事物来指称，这毕竟还是不准确的。假设他有一朵石楠花和一片枯萎的橡树叶子，他可以说，将这片橡树叶子的黄色和这朵石楠花的蓝色混合在一起的颜色就是红色；但是，要将这一抽象概念说得明白易懂却十分困难；而要将哥特式特征这一抽象概念说得明白易懂却难上加难，因为这一特征本身是由很多混合的概念组成的，只能以合成的方式存在。也就是说，尖拱并不构成哥特式风格，穹隆屋顶也不是，拱扶垛或怪异雕塑也不是，但是以上所有或部分事物，以及其他很多与之相关的表象组合在一起时就有了生命。

3.同时，在建议的定义中，我应该只努力分析我认为已经在读者脑海中存在的概念。关于哥特式这个术语的含义，我们都有一些自己的理解，大部分人的理解是确定无疑的，但我知道，很多人并不能为之下一个具体的定义。也就是说，他们只是泛泛地知道威斯敏斯特教堂是哥特式的，而圣保罗大教堂不是；斯特拉斯堡大教堂是哥特式的，而圣彼得大教堂不是；但对于它们彼此之间具象的差异，他们并不能说清楚。这种差异的陈述可以让我们知道威斯敏斯特教堂或斯特拉斯堡大教堂的工艺有多纯粹，或者一些缺乏特征的建筑，如圣詹姆斯宫或者温莎城堡，他们的哥特式元素有多么欠缺。我相信这种质询是愉快而有益的，而且追踪这幅灰暗的、朦胧的、峰峦迭起的哥特式精神的图像，并辨别出它与我们北方人的心灵之间存在怎样的亲近关系，会让我们感觉趣味无穷。另外，如果在进行质询的任何时候，我干扰到读者之前形成的概念，或者在某些他可能不认同的意义上使用哥特式这个术语，我并不要求他接受；我只是想研究和阐述我的观点，这对于理解接下的工作是必不可少的。

4.我们已经对哥特式特征进行了分析，就好像将粗糙的矿石交给化学家进行分析一样。在融合了很多其他种类的物质后，它自身也许就不再纯粹，或者仅能在瞬间显现出纯粹的形式，但是，无论表面上是如何错综复杂或杂乱无章，它依然有一个确定而独立的本质。现在我们看到，化学家将他的矿石分为两种不同的特征：它的晶体状态、硬度、光泽等是它的外部形态，它的原子组成的比例和本质是其内部元素。以同样的方式区分，我们发现哥特式建筑也有外部形态和内部元素。就内部元素而言，建造者的一些精神趋向被清晰地表现出来，如他们对新奇性、多样性、多元化的热爱等。它的外部形态是尖拱、穹隆屋顶等。除非内部元素和外部形态都存在，否则我们无法称之为哥特式风格。如果它没有力量和生命，仅有形式是不够的，而如果没有形式，仅有力量也是不够的。因此，我们必须相继探究这两个特征，并确定两个恰当的称谓：什么是哥特式建筑的“精神表达”；什么是哥特式建筑的“物质形态”。

5.第一，精神力量的表达。我们要发现什么特征是“哥特式建造者”所热爱的，或者哪些特征自然而然地表现在他们的作品中，使其与其他建造者截然不同？

6.我们再回到化学领域。在用化学成分来定义一种矿物质的时候就会发现，这种矿物质并不是某种单一的元素构成的，而是所有元素的集合。比如，粉笔并不是由碳或者氧或者钙组成的，而是这三种化学元素以特定比例组合而成的。这三种元素都在与粉笔完全不同的物体里存在着，而且碳和氧本身与粉笔毫无相似之处，但是它们对于粉笔的存在仍然是至关重要的。

7.因此组成哥特式精神的各种心理特征，并不是某种单一的存在，而是以特定比例组合在一起的整体。每种特征都存在于哥特式建筑以外的许多建筑中。如果没有它们，或者没有以某种方式提供给它们位置的话，哥特式风格就无法存在。矿物的组成和建筑风格的形成有着极大的不同，如果我们从矿物中抽离其中一个元素，它的形态就会完全改变，而它作为这样一种矿物的存在也会被摧毁，但如果我们从哥特式风格中抽离其中一个精神元素，它只是比之前减弱了一点哥特式风格。两三个元素的组合足以彰显某种特定的哥特式特征。也就是说，如果我们增加元素，哥特式特征就会加强；如果我们减少元素，哥特式特征就会减弱。

8.我认为，按照重要性的顺序排列，哥特式特征或精神元素有以下几项：

（1）原始性

（2）多边性

（3）自然性

（4）怪异性

（5）严格性

（6）冗余性

9.以上特征用于建筑风格的表达，而对于建造者来说，以下描述更确切一些：（1）原始或粗野；（2）热爱变化；（3）热爱自然；（4）想象力混乱；（5）顽固；（6）慷慨。我再重复一遍，抽离一两个特征并不会立刻破坏一座建筑的哥特式特征，但是将大部分特征都抽离的话就会令其丧失哥特式风格。接下来我要一一阐释上述特征。

10.原始性。我不能肯定“哥特式”一词何时首次普遍应用于北方的建筑，但是我推测，不管何时首次运用，它都有指责的意味，同时表明这些建筑兴起的国度具有野蛮的特性。它从不意味着在字面上与哥特式是一脉相承的，也不意味着这类建筑是由哥特人自己最初建造的，但它确实表明哥特人及其建筑共同展现了一定程度的苛刻和粗野品性。与南方以及东方国家的特性相对比，它似乎是哥特人与罗马人初次遭遇时所形成反差的永久体现。在所谓的黑暗时代即将结束之时，衰落的罗马帝国穷奢极欲，傲慢无礼，成为开化的欧洲模仿的对象。自此，哥特式一词便成了十足的轻蔑称呼，而且混杂着人们的嫌恶。通过二十世纪古董商和建筑师的努力，哥特式建筑已沉冤昭雪；当我们欣赏其构造的壮丽科学及其所表达的神圣感时，或许我们有些人会渴望这种古老的轻蔑称呼被取消，而改用其他具有褒奖的词来取代它。事实上，没有可能也没有必要进行这种取代，只要这个词用于表达轻蔑的含义，它就属于错误使用，但只要正确地理解，这个词并不带有耻辱的意味；相反，它包含深厚的真理，而人类仅凭本能就可不知不觉地辨认出来。的确，北方的建筑是粗陋而原始的，但因为这个原因我们就要责备它或轻视它，那就不对了。恰恰相反，我认为，正是这种特性才值得我们最深厚的敬意。

11.现代科学所绘制的世界航海图将大量知识投入狭窄的意义空间，但我还从来没有看到哪一幅图能够令观察者想象出北方和南方国度之间存在的实质性差异。我们知道细节上的差异，但我们没有充分感受到在视野和理解上的广泛差异。我们知道龙胆生于阿尔卑斯山脉，橄榄长在亚平宁山脉，但是，这不足以让我们设想出如同飞鸟在迁徙中所看到的世界表面的、斑驳的马赛克图景，或者像鹳鸟和燕子乘着热风远远看到龙胆和橄榄所生长地域的不同。我们暂且把自己提升到比鸟儿飞得更高的高度，想象地中海在我们下面宛如一片不规则的湖泊，所有古老的海角在阳光下沉睡。雷声四处响起，暴雨的灰色污点洒落在灼热的土地上。白色的火山烟雾如同固定的花环，被一圏灰烬所包围。在大部分宁静的光亮中，叙利亚和希腊，意大利和西班牙，好像一条条金色的大道探入蔚蓝的大海。当我们俯身靠近时，它们追逐着山脉历经风吹雨打的凸起部分，梯形花园发出柔和的光。花儿带着浓浓的乳香，混合着大量的月桂、柑橘和羽毛般棕榈叶的芬芳。它们灰绿色的阴影减弱了大理石的炽热，斑岩的突起部分斜斜地伸入明亮的沙滩。我们继续向北方进发，直到我们看到东方的色彩逐渐变为一片巨大的雨林，瑞士的牧场、法国的白杨木山谷、多瑙河与喀尔巴阡山脉的黑森林，从卢瓦尔河口延伸至伏尔加河口。透过雨云灰色漩涡的裂缝和小溪薄薄的雾纱，低低地向牧场土地延伸。继续往北可看到大地隆起，形成大片深灰色的岩石和荒野，边缘是一片广阔的深紫色荒原，那片田野和林地分裂为北方海域中不规则的、骇人的岛屿，经暴雨捶打，冰流冷冻，猛烈潮汐冲击，直到最后一片森林的根须在深山峡谷中枯萎，凌厉的北风将山峰啃得寸草不生。最后，钢铁般坚固的冰墙在极地曙光中用它苍白的牙齿死死地撕咬着我们。沉思默想中，我们已穿越广袤大地上成片的鸢尾花地块。我们可以再靠近一点，观察动物带的平行变化。大量动作敏捷、色彩艳丽的生物在空中和海上匆匆掠过，或踩踏着南方地区的沙地，其中包括斑马、豹和蛇，以及紫色和猩红色的鸟儿。我们对比一下色彩的雅致和艳丽、行动的敏捷与北方部落被霜冻束缚的力量、邋里邋遢的遮蔽物和暗淡无光的华服吧；对比阿拉伯马与设德兰小种马，虎豹与狼熊，羚羊与麋鹿，天堂鸟与鱼鹰，然后发自内心的信服统领地球及其所载万物的伟大法则。对于人类在生养他的土地上的生存法则，我们不要责备而是颂扬。我们满怀敬意地看着他把闪闪发亮的宝石一字排开，用布艺装点碧玉的柱子，使它们不断反射出阳光，同时腾空而起，直达云霄。我们以同样的敬意站在他身边，看着他以粗暴的力量和仓促的举止，猛力击打岩石，释放出粗野的勃勃生气，这种生气他原本已在荒野苔藓中消耗殆尽。他在昏暗的空中筑起一道铁质拱壁和凹凸不平的墙，他的作品充满着与北方海域同样狂野、任性的想象力。这些外形笨拙、肢体僵硬、充满狼性的生物，像击打他们的狂风一样猛烈，像遮蔽他们的云团一样多变。

12.我再重复一下，这里没有贬抑和责备，而只有尊崇和颂扬。要是不能辨别北方现有建筑的本质特征，或者不承认这其实是一种可取的特征，那么我们就很可悲地错了，因为它可能是粗野的想法和粗糙的工艺，是大教堂和阿尔卑斯山之间高山仰止的体现，是由于触摸的手指被刺骨寒风冻僵、双眼被荒野的薄雾所模糊或为冰雹所蒙蔽而只能更积极地推进的强大力量的光华，是既没有从土地上获得丰硕果实也没有享受过慵懒和煦阳光的人的强烈精神的表达，他们只能劈山取食、伐木取火，即便是为了取乐，他们挥舞斧头、犁田耕地而锻炼出来的手臂和心灵，可见其生活艰难。

13.如果仅仅作为其源自北方国家的一种表述，哥特式建筑的原始性也许在某些方面可以被认为是一种高贵的特征，但当它被看作宗教信念而不是气候标志时，它甚至拥有更高贵的特性。

14.本作品第一卷第二十一章第十三和第十四段讲到了建筑装饰体系。确切地来说，此装饰体系可以被分为三类：（1）盲从装饰。卑微工匠的执行或权力完全服从于高层的意志。（2）合成装饰。工匠在一定程度上是独立执行，有自己的意志，但只能承认地位低下并服从于更高的权力。（3）创新装饰。绝不承认执行力低下。在这里我必须对上述分类的性质再多作一些解释。

15.盲从装饰的主要代表是希腊人、尼尼微人[2]和埃及人，但他们的盲从又各不相同。希腊的工匠领袖在知识和权力上都远比尼尼微人和埃及人先进。希腊人及其雇主都不能忍受在任何事情上的不完美表现。所以希腊人指定下属去作的装饰都只是由单纯的几何图形组成，如球形、山脉及完美对称的叶子，这些都通过线条和规则得以完全精确地执行，并且在完成后就和他自己的人物雕像一样完美。与之相反，尼尼微人和埃及人对任何精确的形式都没有那么多认知，他们满足于由低等工匠来完成自己的人物雕像，但将执行的方法降低到所有工匠都能达到的程度，然后加以非常严格的训练，使得工匠绝无达不到指定标准的可能。希腊人不会给次等工匠无法完美执行的任务，尼尼微人只给工匠不能完美执行的任务，但为他的不完美设定一个法定标准。在这两个体系中，工匠都是“奴隶”。

16.在中世纪，尤其在基督教的装饰体系中，这种奴性被彻底扫荡。基督教认识到，无论事物大小，每个灵魂都有其个人价值。它不仅意识到了这种价值，而且还承认它的不完美，承认无价值的尊严。这种对于丧失权力和堕落本性的承认，希腊人或尼尼微人感觉非常痛苦并且尽可能拒绝。基督教徒每时每刻都在无畏地思考，并最终倾向于上帝的更大荣耀。因此，被基督教召唤的每一个神灵都这样劝告：尽可能去做吧，同时要坦率地承认你做不了的事情。既不要因为害怕失败而减少你的努力，也不要因为出于羞愧而不敢忏悔。也许这就是哥特派建筑最令人钦佩之处，他们接受地位低下者的劳动成果，在充满缺陷的碎片里，在每一次触碰中超越不完美，以宽容的心怀建立一个庄严而又无可指责的整体。

17.现代英国与希腊在思想上有很多共同之处，它们都强烈地渴望与本性的契合达到极致或完美。概括来说，这是一种高贵的特性。当它使我们忘记了本性自身的尊严，并且偏爱低级本性的完美胜过高级本性的不完美时，它就变得卑劣了。没有考虑到，如果按照这种规则来判断，所有野蛮的动物都比人类更好，因为它们在功能和种类上更完美，但动物总还是比人类要低等，同样，种类上更完美的人类作品，实际上比那些种类上有更多缺点和短处的作品要低等，因为，本质越美好，通过它的清澈就会显示越多瑕疵。“缺憾美”是这个世界的法则，最好的东西都几乎不是以最好的形态出现。野草生长茂盛，年复一年，而小麦由于本质更高贵而更容易得枯萎病。因此，即使我们在看到或做过的所有事情上都渴望完美，并且为之努力，我们仍然不能置成就微弱的低等事物于进步显著的高贵事物之上；不能尊崇稳定的细微进步而轻视遭到破坏的威严；不能偏爱平庸的成功而无视体面的失败；不能降低我们的目标，从而使我们可能更有把握享受成功的满足感。不过当我们面对其他人的灵魂时，我们要注意如何以严格的要求或慎重，来检查也许会导向一个非凡成果的努力。况且，我们还应注意如何保留对杰作的敬重，即使它们混入了粗糙的缺陷。目前，不管人们的手艺或本性有多么粗陋或简单，我们雇佣的人都有令其完善的力量。即使在最坏的情况下，他们也有一些迟缓的想象力、迟钝的情感和步履蹒跚的思想。在很多情况下，他们的迟缓或迟钝都是我们造成的，但他们不会变强，除非我们满足于他们软弱的状态，除非我们奖赏和尊崇他们的不完备，而不去重视最好的、最完美的手工技艺。这就是我们不得不对待所有劳动者的方式，在他们身上寻找思考的部分，并且发掘出来——不管我们会为此失去什么，不管我们会为此犯下什么过错。因为他们身上最好的部分不会自己显现，所以只能伴随着错误一起出现。要明确地理解这一点：你能够教会一个人画一条直线并切割它，描绘一条曲线并雕刻它；于是，他就会用令人赞赏的速度和完美的精确度复制和雕刻出无数特定的线条或形状。你发现他的工作非常完美，但如果你叫他思考那些形式，思考他是否能用自己的头脑发现更好的方面，他就顿住了，他的行动变得犹豫不决。他思考的时候，十有八九是想错了；另外十有八九他作为思想者第一次接触他的作品时就犯了错，但你因而使他成为了人；他以前只是一个机器，一个会动的工具。

18.请注意，在这件事上你遇到了一个两难的选择。你要么把人变成工具，要么把他塑造成人，只能二选一。一方面，不能用工具的精确性去衡量人，不能要求他们所有的动作都精确而完美。如果你想要他们精确，让他们的手指像嵌齿轮那样测量角度，他们的手臂像圆规那样画曲线，那他们就不是人了。他们的全部精神力量应该用来制作他们自己的齿轮和圆规；他们所有的注意力和精力都应该用来完成有意义的活动。灵魂之眼必须专注于指尖，灵魂之力必须充满指导它的所有无形的神经。每天有十个小时，凭借严格的精确性，可能不会出错，但灵魂和眼界会变得很疲倦，整个人最终迷失，就像是一堆散乱的碎屑一样。就世界上的脑力工作而言，只要被心灵所拯救，就不能进入齿轮和圆规的形态，但十个小时之后才可以膨胀为火边的人。另一方面，如果你在工作中塑造了人，就不能把他当作工具。当他开始想象、思考，试着做任何值得做的事时，由动力转变而来的精确性就会立刻丧失。他所有的粗糙、迟钝和无能都会涌现出来，羞愧连着羞愧、失败连着失败、停顿连着停顿。同时，他的全部威严也相继出现。只有当我们看到云朵在他的头上停留时才知道它的高度。不管云朵是明亮还是灰暗，转变是不可避免的。

19.现在，请读者环顾你自己的英式房间，这是你经常为之自豪的地方，因为它的工艺是如此美妙和坚固，装饰如此精巧。再仔细观察所有精细的铸件，完美的磨光，风干的木头和回火的钢材，没有因任何偏差而进行调整。很多次你为之欢呼雀跃，并且想着英国是多么伟大，因为最细微的工艺也制作得如此彻底。天啊！如果确切地加以解读，这些完美恰恰是我们英国的奴隶制存在的迹象，甚至要比受难的非洲人或受奴役的希腊人痛苦和可耻一千倍。人类可以被殴打、被禁锢、被拷问，像畜生一样被套上枷锁，像夏天的苍蝇一样被拍死，但在某种意义上依然是并且确确实实是自由的。这些使得他们的灵魂窒息，使得他们吸取人类智慧养分的根须枯萎和腐烂，使得经过蛆虫的作用之后呈现在上帝面前的血肉和肌肤，变成扼住机器的皮带，这实际上就是奴隶与主人的关系。英国可能有更多的自由——尽管封建主子轻轻的一句话都能要人的命，尽管哀伤百姓的鲜血滴落在田野的沟壑上，但是大批民众像燃料一样被送去燃烧工厂的烟囱，他们的精力每天都浪费在织物的纯度上，或者被线条的精确所折磨。

20.继续注视古老的大教堂正面吧，你曾经常常对着古老雕刻家的荒诞无知微笑。再看看那些丑陋的小精灵，形体不明的怪物，不苟言笑的雕像，无法剖析、一成不变。不要嘲笑它们，因为它们是雕刻石头的每一个工匠的生命和自由的象征。一种思想的自由，在存在的维度上名列前茅，没有法律、宪章或慈善机构为其提供保障，但必定是今天整个欧洲为子孙后代努力的首要目标。

21.我不想被看作是信口胡说、夸夸其谈，正是这种机械化操作的退化，比这个时代的其他所有罪恶更甚，引导世界各地的民众为了他们无法说明其性质的自由进行徒然的、不相干的毁灭性斗争。他们对财富、贵族的普遍抗议既不是来自饥荒的压力，也不是来自受辱的尊严。这种情形已经在历史上存在很久了，但是社会的基础还从未像今天这样被撼动。并不是人们吃不饱，而是他们赖以谋生的工作毫无乐趣，于是将财富视为快乐的唯一来源；并不是人们因为上层社会的轻蔑而痛苦，而是他们无法忍受自己的阶层，他们感觉不得不从事的劳动确实有失体面，使得他们人不像人。上层社会从未像今天这样同情下层、宽厚仁慈，而他们也从未被如此憎恨过，因为在以前，贵族和穷人的隔离只是一堵法律的墙，但现在是名副其实的立场之分，在人性领域存在高等和低等的绝壁，底部弥漫着氤氲之气。我不知道理解合理自由本质的那一天是否会到来。届时，人们会明白，服从一个人，为他工作，向他或他的地位表示敬畏，这并不是奴役，而往往是最好的自由，由关怀而来的自由。一个人对另一个人说，走吧，于是他就走了，再对另一个人说，来吧，然后他就来了，在大多数情况下发令者比服从者要有更多的克制和困难。一个人的行动被肩上的重担所阻碍，另一个则被嘴上的笼头所限制。他们的重担没有办法减轻，但如果我们不咬住缰绳，就可以不必受制于人。向他人表示敬畏，让我们自己以及我们的同类任其处置，这并不是奴役，而其实是一个人在这个世上存在的最高贵的形态。确实有一种敬畏是低劣的，是不合理的或自私的，但也有高贵的敬畏，也就是合理的、关爱的敬畏。一个人表达这种敬畏的时候，是无比高贵的，即使感觉越过纯粹理性的界限，一个人也会因关爱而升华。事实上，大多数人的身上是有奴性的。比如，过去的爱尔兰农民躺在地上等待主人，他那火枪的枪口插入参差不齐的树篱；年老的山仆，两百年前在印威基辛为首领牺牲了他自己和七个儿子的生命。一个人倒下时会呼唤他的兄弟前仆后继，“为了赫克托再来一个！”在历代各国，人们彼此表达敬畏，作出牺牲，不仅毫无怨言而且满心欣喜，饥荒、险境、刀剑和所有罪恶、所有耻辱，都已经心甘情愿地奉献给主人和国王的事业。心灵的天赋使得给予者变得高贵，也使得接受者高贵起来。这些都是本性使然，而上帝给予了他们奖赏，但是，如果感觉到自己的灵魂逐渐泯灭，不知感恩，结果发现其整个存在坠入不可名状的深渊，被归为一堆以轮子来计数、以锤程来计重的机械，这样一来，本性不会激起——上帝也不会祝福——因此，人性无法持久。

22.关于分工的伟大文明创新，我们已经作了很多研究和完善，只不过我们给了它一个错误的名字。说实话，并不是工作被分割了，而是人被分割为个体生命的碎片和碎屑。于是留存在人身上的智慧小碎片不足以生产出一根针或一枚钉子，而只能将精力耗尽在生产针尖钉上。的确，一天能生产出很多针既是好事也合乎理想；但是，如果我们只看到针头是用什么样的水晶砂来打磨——人类灵魂之砂，要放大很多倍才能辨别清楚，那么，我们应该想到其中也会有所损失。而我们所有制造业城市产生的巨大喧嚣，比炉子爆炸还要响，实际上都是为了这一点——我们制造出了人类以外的所有物品。我们漂白棉花、锤炼钢材、精选砂糖、塑造陶器，但是漂白、锤炼、精选或塑造一个活生生的灵魂，从来不是我们优先考虑的事项。而喧嚣迫使众生趋向所有罪恶的方式只有一种：不是通过教授或传道，因为教授是向他们彰显他们的苦难，而向他们传道则是一种嘲弄，如果我们只是在传道的话。这只能以一种所有阶层都正确理解的方式来达成，我们必须明白什么样的劳动对人有益，怎样才能提升他们，使他们快乐；我们坚决放弃那些以工人的退化为代价而达成的便利、美感或廉价；同样坚决对健康和有尊严的劳动产品表示需求。

23.现在问题来了，这些产品是被认可的吗？这种需求是有管制的吗？很简单，遵守以下三个广泛而又简单的规则就可以了。

24.一、决不鼓励生产任何不是绝对必需的物品，或进行任何没有创新的生产。

25.二、决不为了完成而完成，而只为特定的、实际的或高尚的目的而完成。

26.三、决不鼓励任何形式的模仿或抄袭，除非是为了保存伟大作品的记录。

27.第二条原则是唯一直接出于对当前主题的考虑，但我先来简要地解释一下第一条原则的意义和范围，第三条则在以后涉及。

28.一、决不鼓励生产任何不是绝对必需的物品，或进行任何没有创新的生产。

29.比如，玻璃珠是完全不需要的，在制造中也没有运用到设计或理念。首先将玻璃拉成棒，再手工切成珠子大小的断片，然后将断片放在炉子里打造成圆形。切玻璃棒的工人整天坐着干活，他们的手随着持续不断、精确定时的痉挛颤动着，玻璃珠在他们的颤动下像冰雹一样坠落。他们以及那些拉出玻璃棒、熔化断片的人都几乎没有机会运用人类的才能，因此每一位购买玻璃珠的年轻女士就都被牵涉到奴隶交易中去，并且这是一种比我们长久努力去推翻的还要更残酷的交易。

30.玻璃杯和玻璃管是精致发明的主体，如果我们购买这些东西我们就报偿了发明，也就是说，报偿了美丽的外形、颜色或雕刻，这不仅仅是为了完工，我们是在为人性作贡献。

31.因此，在通常情况下，雕刻宝石几乎不需要运用智力，除了为了避免瑕疵的机智和判断等以外，没有什么涉及到全部心智。每个人只为了其价值而佩戴珠宝的人都是把人当奴隶驱使的人。

32.不过，金匠的工作以及各种分解整合珠宝和珐琅的设计工作可以成为最高贵的人类智慧的主体。因此，把钱花在购买精心设计的碟子，用心雕刻的花瓶、宝石或珐琅上，都对人性有贡献。在这种工艺下，珠宝可以用来提升光彩，而切割也是为了达到高贵目的而付出的代价，这是完全被容许的。

33.我会在别处更深入地推进这一法则，但我们目前主要关注第二条原则，即决不为了完成而完成，而只为高尚的目的而完成。请注意，我阐述哥特式的粗陋或任何其他种类的不完美，认为这是可取的，只是因为没有这些就不可能得到设计或想法。如果你想要得到一个粗鲁的、没有教养的人的想法，你必须以粗鲁和没有教养的方式得到。一个受过教育的人，一个可以用有教养的方式毫不费力地表达自己的人，就会优雅地表达并且充满感激。要得到想法，而不要因为农民不能说很好的语法就不准他说话，或者直到你把语法教给他之后才让他说话。语法和精致是好的，两者都是，只是要保证优先考虑更好的事情。在艺术领域中，大师们的精细完工是可取的，也往往是由他们所赋予的。在某些地方，米开朗基罗、莱昂纳多·达芬奇、菲迪亚斯、佩鲁吉诺和特纳，他们都以最精细的关注完成作品，而他们的完工往往使得他们的高贵目标更好地实现，但略逊于他们的人则无法如此完工，因为作品的完美需要完善的知识，所以我们必须接受不是所有人都能拿出完美作品的事实。规则很简单，始终优先考虑创新，然后寻找有助于创新的执行方案，以及不费力就能完成的发明者，仅此而已。更重要的是，在没有思想的时候就不要求精细地执行，因为那是奴隶的工作，是没有被认可的。这时候，比起平滑的工艺，我们宁可选择粗糙的工艺，以此来满足实际的用途，我们也没有理由为任何用耐心和砂纸就能完成的事情而骄傲。

34.我只给出一个例子来向读者表明我的意图，也就是已经提及过的玻璃的制造。现代玻璃在质地上是相当清晰的，形状上很准确，切割也很精确。我们引以为豪。事实上，我们应该为此而感到惭愧。古代威尼斯的玻璃总的来说是模糊的，形状不准确，切割也很笨拙，但古代威尼斯人仍然为之而骄傲，因为在英国和威尼斯工匠之间存在着区别，前者只看重图案的精确匹配，曲线的极度准确，边缘的极度锋利，从而仅成为一台磨圆曲线和磨砺边缘的机器，而古代威尼斯人一点儿也不在乎边缘是否锋利，而是为制作的每一个玻璃制品发明新的设计，每铸造一个把手或边缘都有新的想象力。因此，尽管某些由笨拙和不善创造的工匠所制作的威尼斯玻璃非常丑陋和笨拙，而另一些威尼斯玻璃的形状却非常可爱，价格再高也值。而且，我们从未看到过两块一模一样的玻璃。完美的工艺和变化的形状，只能二选一。如果工匠在考虑线条，他就无法考虑设计，如果考虑了设计就无法考虑线条。你是选择可爱的外形或完美的工艺时，你也在选择是想要工匠成为人还是磨刀石。

35.不，读者打断我说：“如果工匠能作出完美的设计，我不会把他关在锅炉房里。我会让他离开那儿并成为绅士，拥有工作室，在那儿设计他的玻璃，我也会请普通工匠来为他吹塑和切割玻璃，这样我就既拥有设计又有好的工艺了。”

36.所有此类想法都基于两个错误的推测：第一，一个人的想法可以或应该可以经由另一个人之手而实现；第二，被智力所支配的手工劳动是一种退化。

37.从广义上来说，在由线条和规则所决定的工艺里，一个人的想法应该由其他人的劳动来实现，这确实是可能和必须的。从这个意义上来说，我觉得最好的建筑出自儿童之手。从狭义上来讲，在设计不能被精确地定义的情况下，一个人的想法永远无法被另一个人所表达，而设计者与服从指令的人之间的思想差别，往往就是伟大作品和平庸作品之间的差别。原版作品和二手作品之间的距离有多大，这点我将在以后阐释。在这里，我们的目的不是去标记轻视智力所支配的手工是多么致命的过失，因为轻视智力支配下的手工与因其本身的缘故而重视它都属于致命的过失。我们一直在努力区分这两者，我们想要一个人总在思考，而另一个人总在操作，我们把一个称为绅士，另一个称为工人。实际上，在最好的层面上，工人应该也要思考，思考者也应该要工作，最好是两者都是绅士。既然如此，我们使得两者都不高贵，一个变得嫉妒，另一个总爱轻视。社会上的大多数人由病态的思想者和苦难的工人组成。现在思想只能因劳动而变得健康，而劳动也只能通过思考而变得快乐，两者不能被截然分开。要是我们所有人都是某些领域的优秀手工艺人，而手工劳动的不体面也一扫而光，这样即使贵族和普通人之间仍然存在着严格的种族区分，在后者中间也不会有严格的职业区分，诸如闲散的和工作的人，有文化的和没文化的职业。所有的职业都应该是有文化的，这样人们就不会为特定的职业而只为成就的卓越而骄傲。在每种职业里，能工巧匠不会骄傲得不肯去做最艰苦的工作。画家应该自己研磨颜料，建筑师在泥瓦匠的庭院里和工人一起工作，制造业主比他厂里的所有工人都更懂生产技术，一个人和另一个人的差别只在于技术与经验，以及自然和公平地得到的权威和财富。

38.要是我继续追溯这个有趣的主题，我将会离题太远。我相信我已经说得够多了，已经向读者显示了哥特式这个术语在最开始被赋予的粗陋和不完美的含义，如果正确地加以理解，其实是基督教建筑里最高贵的特征之一，而且不仅仅是高贵，更是本质的特征。这似乎是奇异的矛盾，不过却是最重要的事实，即任何并非不完备的建筑都不会是真正高贵的建筑。这一点很容易被论证，因为我们假定建筑师能够将所有工艺都做到完美，但他不能凡事亲力亲为，他必须要么以古代希腊或现代英国的方式来使得他的工人成为奴隶，从而把他的工艺降低到奴隶的能力水平，也就是降格；要么他必须接受工人本来的样子，让他们显示自己的长处和短处，这样就会带来哥特式的不完美，但给整件作品保存了这个时代的智力所能达到的高贵特征。

39.不过这个原理还能更广泛地加以陈述。我已经将例证限制在建筑上，但我不能就这样算了，否则就会显得好像只对建筑有效。到目前为止，我使用不完美和完美这两个词，只是为了区别非常拙劣的工艺和平常精细的工艺。我已经说明，任何程度的拙劣都应被接受，这样工人的思想才会有机会表达。准确地说，并非所有好的工艺都是完美的，而对完美的奢求常常象征着对艺术目的的误解。

40.这是出于两个基于永恒法则的理由。第一，所有伟人都不会停止工作，直到他完全失败，也就是说，他的想法总是超前于他的执行能力，而后者会不时地让出道路来努力跟随前者。另外，他总是对次要的工作投注更少的注意力，由于他的伟大，他习惯于对所能达到的极致依然感到不满意，在对自己生气和厌倦疲乏的时刻他不会在意，但旁观者也不满意。我认为只有一个人不会承认这种必要性，并且总是努力达到完美——莱奥纳多，他徒然努力的结果总是使他在一幅画上花费十年时间却依然未完成。因此，如果我们要让伟人工作，或让普通人做到最好，无论作品有多漂亮，它都是不完美的。对于人类工艺来说，只有坏的才可能是完美的，以它特有的坏的方式表现完美。[3]

41.第二，不完美在某些程度上对所有生命来说都是必不可少的。在凡人的身上这是一种生命的象征，也就是说，处于一个持续进步和变革的状态。没有任何活着的事物是，或可能是非常完美的。总有一部分在衰退；一部分在萌芽。比如毛地黄，三分之一是花蕾，三分之一已开败，还有三分之一完全盛开，这就是这个世界上的一种生命形态。所有生物都有特定的不规则和缺陷，这不仅是生命的迹象，同时也是美的来源。人类脸部的两侧线条也不是完全一致的，树叶的裂片并不完美，树枝也不对称。这些都意味着变化，因而必须承认这种不规则。摒弃不完美也就是毁灭表达，阻止发挥、麻痹活力。上帝创造的所有事物都因其不完美而变得更好、更可爱、更宜人。人类生命的法则可能是努力，而人类判断的法则却是仁慈。

42.请接受这样的普遍法则，即建筑以及人类的任何其他高贵工艺都不可能是好的，除非它是不完美的。我们准备好接受这个似乎有点奇怪的事实，我们进入文艺复兴时期后，将会清晰地看到，欧洲艺术衰落的首因是对完美的不懈追求，同样也是不能做到因对伟大的敬畏而沉默，因对单纯的谅解而变得温和。

43.这就是关于哥特式建筑的第一个精神元素“粗陋”，即“原始”。它也是很多其他合宜建筑中的元素，如拜占庭和罗马建筑，但没有了它，真正的哥特式建筑就不会存在。

44.前面提到的第二个精神元素是“多变性”，即“多样性”。

45.我已经强调了允许低等工匠独立操作，仅仅作为对他的一种职责，并且通过赋予其更多基督教的色彩而使得建筑更显高贵。我们现在要考虑，履行了这一职责以后可以得到什么报偿，也就是建筑特征的永恒多样性。

46.只要是工匠被完全奴役的地方，建筑的各个部分必然是完全相似的，通过训练他只做一件事而不做其他事来实现完美的执行。因此，工匠被降格的程度可见一斑，只需观察建筑的各个部分是否相似，如果像希腊建筑那样，所有的柱头都相同，所有的模制都没有变化，那么降格是非常彻底的。如果像埃及和尼尼微的建筑，尽管实现特定形状的方式总是一样的，设计的顺序却一直在变化，那么降格就没有那么彻底。如果像哥特式建筑，在设计和执行上都有不断的变化，工匠就一定是自由的。

47.旁观者能从劳动者的自由上获得多少好处，这个问题可能是在英国提出的。在这里，几乎每一个人的头脑中最强大的本能之一就是对秩序的热爱。它使得我们渴望我们房子的窗户应该像四轮马车的马一样成双成对，并且使得我们毫不犹豫地屈从于我们的信念，即为任何事物设定形式并禁止变动的建筑理论。我不会非难这种对秩序的热爱，这是英国思想中最有用的元素之一，在商业以及所有纯粹实用的事物上，它会给我们帮助；并且在很多情况下，它还是道德的基石之一，只是我们不要以为，对秩序的热爱就是对艺术的热爱。秩序在最高层面上确实是艺术的必然性之一，就好像时间是音乐的必然性一样。对秩序的热爱和我们对建筑或绘画的欣赏，并没有什么关系，就好像对准时的热爱和欣赏歌剧并没有关系一样。经验告诉我们，那些很快领悟或拥有丰富的艺术创造力的人，在日常生活中几乎没有一丝不苟和有条不紊的习惯，然而，这两个天性之间没有什么不一致的地方，也没有什么阻碍我们在保留商业习惯的同时，充分容许和欣赏创新的高贵成果。在除了建筑以外的艺术领域及所有其他分支，我们已经这样做了。我们不这样做，只是因为我们被教导说这是错误的。我们的建筑严肃地告诉我们，正如算术有四大法则一样，建筑也有五大秩序。我们单纯地认为这是合理的，并且对之深信不疑。这五大秩序也告诉我们，科林斯式柱、多利安式柱、爱奥尼亚式柱都有适当的形状。我们考虑到字母A、B和C也都有适当的形状，于是认为这也是合理的，然后接受了这个命题。我们要知道，所说的立柱只有一个形状是适当的，其他的都不是，因而，认真勤勉者害怕所有不适当性。我们允许建筑师向我们提供所说的立柱，以及适当的形状，适当的数量，并且保证合法的形状在所有其他的点也都被遵循。这些都做完了以后，我们不得不相信，我们的住房设计非常完美。

48.我们更高的本能却不会被蒙骗。我们在提供给我们的建筑里，无法得到像我们在新书或图画里得到的乐趣。我们可能会为它的规模而自豪，满足于它的正确性，并为其便利而高兴。在一间秩序井然的房间或一件技艺精巧的作品上，我们也可以从对称和工艺中得到乐趣。我们认为这些就是建筑所能给予的全部乐趣。我们从来没有想过可以像阅读弥尔顿和但丁那样阅读建筑，并且从石头上得到像诗节那样的快乐。这是因为，诗歌里确实有韵律，严格得就好像建筑的对称和节奏，但韵律之外的东西使它美丽一千倍。诗歌被创造出来，不是像柱头那样为了秩序或者为了相配，我们在它们那里可以得到适当感之外的乐趣。如果要撼动常识、放弃我们在过去两个世纪中被教导的所有东西，需要很大的努力，来使我们的感觉苏醒，这个事实很简单很确定也很新颖：伟大的艺术不管是以文字、颜色还是石头来表达，都不会一遍又一遍地重复表达同样的东西。建筑的价值，如同所有其他艺术形式一样，体现为它表达了崭新的、不同的东西。重复自己不是绘画杰作的特征，同样也不是大理石杰作的特征。我们可以在不违反任何好品味的法则的情况下，像要求一位小说家那样要求一位建筑师。建筑，不应该只是正确的，应该也是有趣的。

49.这些都是事实，不证自明，只是如同很多其他不证自明的事物一样，由于错误的教导而被遮蔽了。任何一件在生产中遵循规则或模型的作品，都不是伟大的艺术作品。正如遵循已知的规则，基于给定模型的建筑都不是艺术品，而只是加工品。比起从提香的画里抄袭头和手然后自称画家的人，去菲迪亚斯的建筑中抄袭柱头和模制然后自称为建筑师的人，是更不合理的——因为这更容易。

50.我们要明白，变化或者说多样性，对于人类的心灵和头脑来说是一种必需品，在书本中和在建筑中是一样的。即使可以有一些偶然的应用，但总体来说，单调是没有价值的。我们不期望从一个装饰单一、柱式均等的建筑中得到乐趣或者益处，正如我们不期望从一个云朵形状单一、树木大小均等的宇宙得到乐趣一样。

51.这一点即使不用言语表达，我们实际上已经相信了。十九世纪的人从艺术中得到的所有愉悦，都是来自图画、雕塑、小件艺术品或者中世纪建筑，我们因其奇特有趣而欣赏不已。在现代建筑中我们得不到任何愉悦，我们发现所有拥有真实感觉的人都乐于从现代都市逃向自然风光：因此正如我将阐释的一样，对于风景的独特热爱是这个时代的特征。要是在所有其他事物中，我们都能够为了顺从既定法则而容忍我们不喜欢的东西，就像我们能够容忍建筑那样就好了。

52.如此贬抑的法则怎么会被建立起来，关于这点我们将会在描述文艺复兴学派的时候看到。在这里，我们只需注意作为哥特式精神的第二个最基本的元素，它打破了现有法则。它不仅敢于而且乐于违反每一条盲从原则，并且发明了一系列的形式，它们的价值不仅在于创新，而且在于有能力永久保持新颖。尖拱并不仅仅是圆拱的大胆变异，它本身还能产生成千上万的变化，因为尖拱的比例可以不断地变动，而圆拱总是一样的；成组的柱身并不仅仅是单个柱身的大胆变异，而是在组合的方式上有成千上万的变化。石制花饰的引入并不仅仅导致窗户光线令人吃惊的改变，而且在花饰条本身的组合上有着无穷的变化。因此，在所有现存的基督教建筑里都有着对多样性的热爱，而哥特式学派则以绝顶的能量展示了这种热爱。它们的影响无论延伸到哪里，都会被追踪到这个特征上去。采纳哥特式形态的趋势总是首先显示为外在的不规则性和更丰富的变化，这远在尖拱或任何其他哥特式建筑的可辨别的外部特征出现之前就存在了。

53.如此，我们必须仔细地关注对于变化的健康和病态热爱之间的区别。哥特式建筑引发的对于变化的健康热爱，部分是对于变化的病态热爱的结果。为了更好地理解这一点，有必要考虑变化和单调在自然中的体现。两者都是有用的，就像黑暗和光明，如果缺少一个，另一个也无法被欣赏。漫长的单调之后的变化是多么可喜，正如眼睛闭上一段时间后再看到的光线是多么灿烂。

54.我相信单调和变化的真实关联可以简单地通过对音乐的观察来理解。我们首先要注意到，单调有一种快速或经常变动所没有的崇高和威严。自然界一向如此，大海的崇高大部分来自于它的单调，荒野和山色同样如此。尤其是动态的崇高，如一束光线安静不变地升起和落下。同样，在黑暗中也有在光明中所没有的崇高。

55.经过一段时间之后，或者超过一定程度，单调就会变得无趣或者无法忍受，音乐家不得不以一两种方式打破它，要么在曲调和段落被不断重复时，音节的加强与调和有所变化；或者在一定数量的重复段落后，接入一个崭新的段落，根据之前单调的长度，这样或多或少地增加了愉悦感。自然界不断地运用以上两种变化。大部分的海浪彼此相似，但是在微小的部分和曲线上则互不相同，这是第一种单调。广阔的平原被突兀的岩石或树丛所切断，这是第二种单调。

56.此外，为了在每种情形下都享受变化，需要听众或观众具有一定的耐心。在第一种情形下，他必须耐心忍受声音或形式的大量重复，然后在微小的细节里仔细地观察寻找乐趣。在第二种情形下，他必须耐心忍受某些时刻的单调痛苦，以便感受到变化所带来的全新体验。即使在最短的音乐章节里，只要运用了单调的元素，情形莫不如此。在更威严的单调情形中，需要更多的耐心，有时候变成了一种痛苦，而这就是为了即将到来的愉悦所付出的代价。

57.重申一下，作曲家的才华不在于单调而在于变化，在某些地方或某种程度上，他可以借助单调来表达情感和品味，也就是说，借助各种各样的运用来实现不同的表达，但他的才华总是在新的安排和发明上体现出来，而不是通过一成不变的方式来体现。

58.最后，如果变化的愉悦重复的太多，它就不再是愉悦的了，因为这样一来，变化本身也就成为单调了。我们被迫在极端和奇异的层面上寻找乐趣，这就是之前提到的对于变化的病态热爱。

59.从以上事实我们可以大致地了解到，正如黑暗一样，单调就其本身来说是且应当是令我们痛苦的。一幢整体看来单调的建筑，是一幢黑暗或死寂的建筑，而那些热爱它的人们，实际上可能会这样说，“他们热爱黑暗而不是光明”。特定量的单调，会给变化带来价值，尤其是那种透明的单调。正如伟大画家画的影子，通过它看到并感受各种模糊的形状，可以在建筑中发挥其作用。对于健康的心灵而言，对单调的忍耐和对黑暗的忍耐一样。也就是说，一个强大的智者会对暴风雨和曙光的肃穆，以及闪烁其间的断裂而神秘的光心生愉悦，而不仅仅对光辉和闪耀心生愉悦，而一个轻佻的人会害怕阴影和风暴。一个伟人准备好忍受命运的黑暗，以便到达力量或幸福的更高处，而一个低等的人就不会付出这种代价。正像一个伟大的心灵会接受甚至享受单调，而对一个低等心智的人来说，单调是令人厌烦的，这是因为他没有准备好为了更大的愉悦而付出代价。在所有情形下，高贵的本性并不是热爱单调，正如它也不热爱黑暗或痛苦一样，但是它可以忍受，并在忍受和耐心中得到更高的愉悦，这是一种对世界的安宁来说必不可少的愉悦。那些不能接受暂时的雷同，迅速地从一个变化跳到另一个变化的人，最终也厌倦了变化本身，并为整个世界带来无所遁逃的阴影和倦怠。

60.在世界经济中普遍运用各种变化的过程中，我们可以同时理解它在建筑中的运用和滥用。哥特式学派的变化是更健康、更美丽的，因为在很多情况下，它是完全自然而不造作的，其成果不是单纯地来源于对变化的热爱，而是来源于实际的需要。从这一点来说，哥特式不仅是最好的，而且也是唯一理性的建筑，因为它可以最方便地应用于各种服务，雅俗共赏。不确定的屋顶倾斜度、柱身高度、拱门宽度或平面图的安排，都使得它既可以收缩为角楼，也可以扩展为大厅；既可以卷曲成楼梯也可以弹升为尖塔，而其魅力不减，能量不耗。无论它在形式和功能上有什么变化，它总能在不损失一点儿完整性和威严性的情况下达成。它像暴烈的蛇一样敏锐和灵活，但总是听从于耍蛇人的声音。这是哥特式建造者最主要的品质之一，他们从不用外部的对称和一致去妨碍他们作品的真实用途和价值。如果他们想要一扇窗户，他们就开一扇；想要一间房间，就加一间；想要一面扶墙，就建一面。完全不管一切既定的关于外观的陈规陋习，因为他们知道（正如实际总是发生的那样）那些对于形式的大胆突破会带给对称性额外的益处而不是破坏，所以在哥特式风格的鼎盛时代，人们宁可为了制造惊奇而在一个意外的地方开一扇无用的窗户，也不要为了符合对称而开一扇有用的窗户。每一个被雇佣来实施伟大工程的继任建筑师，都以他自己的方式来设计，完全不管前任所采用的风格。如果两座塔楼在大教堂的正面矗立，名义上它们相符，但其中一座肯定与另一座不一样的，而且每一座从顶部到底部的风格也是不一的。

61.这些显著的变化只是一个永恒变化的伟大系统的一部分。经历了每一种哥特式设计，为旁观者查询建造者的想象力提供了无尽的空间。在最佳学派里，变化是微妙和精巧的，并且通过混合高贵的单调而变得更加愉悦；在更原始的学派里，变化则颇为怪诞和多余，但总体而言，变化是学派的生命力所必备的恒定条件。有时候变化是这种特征，有时是另一种特征。变化可能体现在柱头、卷叶饰、壁龛或石制花饰上，或者全部都有所体现。总之，这样或那样的特征总会被找到。如果模制是固定的，那么表面雕塑就会有变化；如果柱头的设计是固定的，那么石制花饰就会有变化；如果石制花饰是单调的，那么柱头就会有变化。如果像在早期英国的一些建筑学派那样，模制、柱头和花饰的形态都几乎不变，那么变化就体现在摆放位置的不同，以及雕塑形象的差异。

62.在放弃这方面的考虑之前，我必须要参考《建筑学七灯》第三章的开头来谈谈哥特式建筑的第二个精神元素。此书对于集合者和管理者之间作了区分，同时也对从自然中接受乐趣和在其安排中行使权威或想象的权力之间作了区分。对于这两种精神元素来说，我们刚才分析的哥特式建筑和所有优秀建筑均属于此类。它们之所以值得赞美，主要是因为人类的作品以及人类一般力量的表达，胜过艺术的其他任何主题。一幅画或一首诗常常只不过是出于人类自己赞赏某事物的微弱表达，但是建筑更接近于他自己的创造，由他的需要而产生，并且表达了他的本性。同样，在整个种族的作品中，如果说图画或雕塑只是个体的创作，大多数情况下这一个体要比他的同类更有天赋。因此，我们期望优秀建筑的头两个元素应该表达一些属于整个种族的伟大真理，而且在他们在世界各地完成的所有作品中，都应该被理解或感受到。观察一下就会发现，它们是对于不完美的告白，是对于渴望变化的告白。小鸟和蜜蜂的建筑不需要表达这样的东西，它是完美的、不变的。正因为我们是比小鸟和蜜蜂更优等的生物，我们的建筑必须要承认我们还没有达到所能想象的完美程度，而且不能停留在我们已经达到的状态。如果我们假装已经达到了完美或者满足，我们就降低了我们自己和我们的作品。“上帝之工”，也许可以这样表达，但我们从未达到“一切所造的都甚好”的境界。再来观察一下，对于高贵来说多样性是必要的。这并不仅仅是给建筑提供了包含各种知识的书籍，或者宝贵思想的矿藏。至关重要的原则不是对于知识的热爱，而是对于变化的热爱。哥特式精神奇异的不安分正是它的伟大之处。梦幻般思想的躁动，在壁龛四处游荡，在尖塔周围兴奋地闪烁，在墙壁和屋顶的复杂结构和阴影里忽隐忽现，却还不满足，也不会满足。希腊人可以待在他的竖条纹饰里，内心平静，但是富有哥特式心灵的作品是回纹细工，无法安于劳动或从劳动中得到安宁，必须不眠不休地继续下去，直到它对变化的热爱在变化中得到慰藉，就像如果他们沉睡了，就必须被唤醒一样。

63.哥特式精神的第三个组成元素被称为自然性。也就是说，热爱自然事物本身的样子，并且坦率地呈现，不受艺术法规的制约。

64.这个风格特征部分地遵循了之前阐述的两个特征。只要工匠可以自由地呈现他选择的物品，他一定会面向他周围的自然来寻找素材，并且努力呈现出他看到的样子，精确度视其掌握的技巧而定。这个过程带着很多玩笑的情绪，也很少有对法则的尊重，然而即使两者的工匠都是自由的，西方人和东方人的想象力还是有明显的不同。西方人或说哥特人乐于对事实的表现，而东方人（阿拉伯人、波斯人和中国人）则强调颜色和形式的和谐。每种处理方式都有其特定的错误和滥用形式。〔……〕

65.由此而产生的各种形式的伤害在这里就不谈了，读者可能已经有些厌烦这个引得我们偏离主题的陈述了，但我既然将“自然性”列为哥特式建筑的第三个最基本的特征，为了可以清晰地定义我使用这个词的含义，是需要离题的。我的意思是，哥特式建造者在我们刚刚作出的艺术家的分类里是居于中心或最伟大的级别。考虑到艺术家有的关注设计，有的关注事实，也有的两者都关注，哥特式建造者是属于两者都关注的范畴；考虑到艺术家有的是纯化论者，有的是自然主义者，也有的是感官主义者，哥特式建造者都是自然主义者。

66.我首先要说，哥特式建造者是将事实与设计融合的中心阶层，但他们自己尤其看重的是真实性。他们的艺术创造或者设置的力量并不比罗马和拜占庭工匠更强大，他们由这些工匠传授设计原理，并从中取得模型，但在拜占庭对于装饰的感觉和丰富的热爱之上。哥特式建造者增添了一份对真实的热爱，而这种热爱在南方从不存在。希腊人和罗马人都在装饰上运用因袭的叶子，将一种并不是叶子的东西传承下去，结成奇怪的杯状的花蕾或花丛，长出无生命的杆而不是茎。哥特式雕刻家们一开始理所当然地接受了这些样式，但他们无法安心于此。他们认为它们没有真实性、没有知识、没有生命力。当他们可以为所欲为时，他们就忍不住更喜欢真实的叶子，他们每次一点点慎重地将自然加入到他的作品中，直到它最终完全变成真实的样子，却仍然保留原始的完美设计和有节制的规划中的珍贵特征。

67.哥特式工匠并不仅在外部和可见的主题上寻找真实，他们对于表现想象力的真实也一样坚定。也就是说，当一个想法被罗马人或拜占庭人以象征的手法来表现时，哥特人则将其最大可能地真实化。比如，炼狱之火在托切罗岛（罗马）的马赛克上被表现为红色的水流，像一条缎带一样纵向垂下，从基督的宝座上降下来，逐渐延伸以遮盖邪恶。只要我们被告知这样代表着什么，它也就达到目的了，但是哥特派发明者使得这个象征不需要解释，他尽可能把火做得逼真，在鲁昂的圣马克卢教堂的门廊上雕刻的火焰从地狱之门喷发而出，翻腾的石制舌头闪耀着穿过了壁龛的空隙，就好像整个教堂都着火了。这是一个极端的例子，但这既是两派艺术的性情和想法整体差别的精彩表现，也是对影响哥特式设计的真实性的强烈热爱。

68.我并不是说这种对真实性的热爱在应用上总是健康的。之前我已经注意到由于轻视设计而犯的错，在刚刚举的例子中还有一个显而易见的错误，即对真实的热爱太过轻率，以致只抓住了表面的而不是内在的真实。在表现地狱之火时，最需要表现的并不仅仅是火焰的形状，而是它的永不止歇，它的神圣命令和限制，以及它内在的凶猛，不是形体和物质上的凶猛，而是对上帝的愤怒的激烈表达，但这些事物是不能经由模仿火焰从手杖中闪现来表达的。如果我们考虑一下他的象征，我们也许会发现，罗马建造者用血红色的水流在特定的岸间流动，流出上帝的宝座并仿佛有永恒的水流延伸到罪恶被抛弃的湖里，这比哥特式建造者用壁龛里闪烁的火炬表现得更为真实。这不是我们的直接目标，我此刻不是要强调在哥特时代的后期因对真实的热爱而导致的错误，而是在感觉本身，在于作为北方建造者的光荣而独有的特征。注意观察，即使在以上的例子中，导致错误的也不是对真实的热爱而是对思想的需求。对真实的热爱是好的，但当它被轻率所误导，或被虚荣心过分激励，就会抓住几乎没有价值的事实，或者把它们集中起来，只是为了可以夸耀其掌控力和理解力，这样它的工作就会变得乏味或者令人不快，然而我们不应指责对于真实的内在热爱，而应针对选择的不谨慎，以及陈述的不恰当。

69.其次，我认为，在参考所有艺术安排时，如纯粹主义、自然主义或感官主义的艺术，哥特式作品属于自然主义艺术。这个特征必然符合它对真实的极端热爱，并胜过了美的感觉，使其乐于创作每一种肖像画，表达人类面部表情和形态的各种特征，正如它表现树叶的多样性和树枝的参差不齐一样。这个趋势因与我们提到的哥特式作品的第一个特征所表达的同样的基督谦卑而得到加强，并变得高贵起来。由于谦卑因承认工匠的不完美而产生，这个自然主义肖像画因为这种谦卑而变得更加可信，因为它承认了这个主题的不完美。希腊雕刻家既不能忍受承认自己的低能，也不会坦白他所描绘的形状的错误，但是基督教工匠相信最终一切都会协同向善，因而能够坦承这两个方面，并且既不掩饰其作品的粗糙，也不掩饰其工艺主题的粗糙。这种坦率大部分是和在其他方向的深厚的宗教体验联合起来的，特别是和仁慈联系起来的。在最好的哥特式雕塑中有一种纯粹主义的倾向，所以它经常达到形式上的尊严和表达上的柔和，但在任何肖像画中决不会丧失肖像画的真实性：既不歌颂国王为半神，也不描绘圣人为天使长，而是充分表现出他们身上的王性和圣洁，混杂着他们应有的错误记录。这在很大程度上舍弃了像圣经历史那样的强烈漠视，圣经历史以坚定的、不容置疑的果断，设定了提到的所有人的美德和错误，使得读者形成他自己的评价，而不管历史学家的评判。这种真实性由哥特式雕塑家在微观和宏观上体现出来，正如公正性由轮廓体现出来一样。因为他们的艺术不模仿圣人和国王的肖像，而是加入了最熟悉的场景以及最简单的主题，在圣经历史的背景上填充日常生活中最常见的事件，加以生动和奇特的表现，并且利用每一个场合，要么作为一种象征，要么作为一个场景或时间的解释，而工匠的眼睛所熟悉的事物可以被引进和加以叙述，所以哥特式雕塑和绘画不仅充满了伟人的珍贵肖像画，还有它繁荣时代的所有家庭风俗和低等艺术的丰富记录。[4]

70.然而哥特式工匠的自然主义倾向有一个方向是特别明显的，这个方向作为哥特派的特征甚至超过自然主义本身。我是指他们特别热衷于草木图案。在提供日常生活的各种情境时，埃及和尼尼微的雕塑与哥特式的一样直率和散漫。从国家的盛世到战争的胜利，一直到最琐碎的家庭艺术和娱乐，都对拥挤的戏剧性产生了恒久的兴趣。早期伦巴第和罗马雕塑对于熟悉的战争和狩猎场景的描绘同样很丰富，但在由这些国家的工匠所描绘的所有场景里，草木只是作为辅助说明而存在，加入芦苇是为了标记河流的路线，树木是为了标记野兽的隐蔽处或者敌人的埋伏点，而对草木图案的特殊兴趣从来没有强大到把它们作为单独的主题和精确的研究对象。再者，在那些仅仅延续设计艺术的国家，草木图案是贫乏和普通的，它们真正复杂的生命既没有被欣赏也没有被表达，但是对于哥特式工匠来说，草木是他们深爱的主题，他们努力以精确性及适应于设计的法则和材料的质地，来呈现它所有的特征，却不会为自己的热情所驱使，违背一方面或隐藏另一方面。

71.这里有一点特别重要，它象征比之前建筑所显示的文明更高，气质更温和。粗陋以及对于变化的热爱，这两个我们强调为哥特式的首要元素，也是所有建筑流派共有的元素。只是对于哥特式风格自身而言，这里有一个更柔和的元素与之相混合。在处理人类形式时呈现出的粗陋或无知，还没有强大到阻止对路边植物的成功表现。而对于变化的热爱，在追随猎人的迅捷和角斗者的愤怒时，会变得病态和狂热，在它看到藤蔓的漫游、花朵的盛开时，立刻变得平静和满足。这并不是全部，精神兴趣的新方向标志了生活的习惯和手段上的无穷变化。一个主要的支持在于狩猎、主要的兴趣在于战争、主要的乐趣在于宴会的国家，不会关注树叶和花朵的形状，也不会注意庇护他们的森林树木的形状——表明可以用作最锋利的枪矛、最密闭的屋顶、最炽热的火焰的木头的特征除外。对于草木的魅力和外部特征的充满感情的观察，当然象征着一个更宁静、更温和的存在，由那片土地的馈赠所维系，因其光辉而愉悦。物种的仔细区分以及未受干扰的细致组织的丰富性，作为哥特式设计的特征，都有一个乡野和周到生活的历程，受惯常的亲切感的影响，致力于巧妙的询问。凿子每一次有差别的、细致的触碰，当它搓圆花瓣或者指引树枝时，这就成为自然科学主体发展的预言，以医学、文学的发现，以及家庭智慧和国家和平的最必要原则的确立为出发点。

72.我之前已经提及的奇怪和徒然的推想，即哥特式建筑的原始概念起源于植物，即起源于林荫道的对称和树枝的交错。这是一个在任何知晓早期哥特式风格的人的头脑里都不会产生的推想，但无论是多么无用的理论，它用来证明完美风格的特征还是有价值的，因为这个理论的反面是事实。因为哥特式建筑并不是从此而来的，而是发展自植物的相似性，所以这个相似性表明了建造者的性情。几乎没有可能去提议拱门的形状根据树枝的弯曲度而设计，但是对于自然美的逐步、持续的发现可以被越来越完美地转移到石头上，并且立即影响到人们的心灵和建筑形式。哥特式建筑以厚实的如大山般的力量出现，以斧头砍成，铁块绑成，石块堆着石块，以一种修士的热情和战士的力量震撼着人们。箍住和撑起如此可怕墙壁的重量仿佛可以将隐士埋葬于黑暗中，可以击退战争中最猛烈的进攻，在同样穿过阳光或者弓箭的狭窄通道里遭受折磨。渐渐地，当修士的热情变得更为深沉，战争的声响在修道院或城堡主楼的门上变得越来越虚弱，石柱变得修长，穹隆屋顶变得光亮，直到他们自己被夏天的树木和死去的野花所遮盖，走过长长的血路，甜美的纪念碑塑像永远鲜活地立于庙宇的门廊下，或坟墓的檐蓬下。

73.它也不仅是一个更温和、更精致的思想符号，而且是这种趋向精致的最大可能的证据。哥特式风格表现出来的植物生命的倾向是值得赞赏的。《创世纪》里有句话，“我将青草赐给它们作为食物”，和书中其余的内容一样，这句话既有字面上的含义也有深刻的象征。它不仅是身体的营养，还是灵魂的食物。在大自然中，绿色植物对于人类健康的精神生活是最为关键的。我们大部分人不需要美好的风景，绝壁和山峰并不打算被所有人看到——也许他们的力量对那些尚未习惯他们的人来说是最强大的，但是树木、田野和花朵是为所有人准备的，对所有人而言也是必需的。上帝将攸关生计的工作和有益人心的欢乐联系起来，他把土地造得坚固，也把植物造得芬芳，花朵造得美丽。人类能够建造的最自豪的建筑与田野荒草的形象和记忆相比并不更加荣耀，因为这不过是他存在的形态和证明。当漂亮的建筑被雕刻成天堂之叶的样子时最为辉煌，而伟大的哥特式精神，当我们展示它不安中的高贵时，它在对本性的执着上是尊贵的。它确实如诺亚的鸽子，没有在水面上停歇，也像“鸽子嘴里叼着一片新拧下来的橄榄叶子”。

74.前面提到的哥特式精神的第四个要素是“怪异性”。要等到我们有机会研究文艺复兴学派的一个部分时，我才会对这个最古怪、最微妙的特征进行定义，因为这种怪异性病态地影响了这些学派。强调这一点也许不是很有必要，因为每个熟悉哥特式建筑的读者都一定会明白我的意思。我相信，他们也会毫不犹豫地承认，对于奇异和可笑的喜好，正如对于庄严的图像的喜好一样，这种倾向是哥特式想象力的一个普遍天性。

75.前面提到的第五个要素是“严格性”。这个特征我必须努力仔细地加以定义，因为无论是我使用的这个词，还是我能想到的任何词，都无法精准地表达它的含义。我的意思不仅是稳定而且是积极的严格，这种给行动以张力、给反抗以限制的奇特能量，使得最猛烈的闪电变成叉状而不是变得曲线，使得最粗壮的橡树枝长出尖角而不是变得弯曲，在枪矛的震颤和冰柱的闪烁中同样可以见到。

76.我之前有机会注意到这种能量或曰稳固的显现，但在这里它必须经过更仔细地考虑，因为它在哥特式工艺的整个结构和装饰上都有表现。埃及和希腊建筑大部分依靠自己的重量和质量而挺立，一块石头顺从地依靠着另一块，但是在哥特式建筑的圆拱和石制花饰里有一种形同腿骨或树的纤维般的僵硬特征，这是从一个部分到另一个部分有弹性的张力和力量的传播，也是建筑的每条可见线条上的细致表现。同样，希腊和埃及装饰或者仅仅是表面雕刻，就好像墙面被印上了封条，或者它的线条是流动的、柔和的、丰富的，在每种情况下，装饰本身的框架里都没有能量的表达，但是哥特式装饰以敏感的独立性和冷淡的坚毅性凸显出来，伸入卷叶浮雕，固定为尖塔，在这里制作一个怪物，在那里萌发一朵花。很快，它又将编结为一条树枝，不停地变换着多刺、凸起和多毛的形态，或者扭曲为任何各种纠结的形式。即使在最优雅的状态下，从没有一个时刻是无精打采的，始终是树篱的形状，即便有错误，也只是出现在唐突无礼的情况下。

77.在作品中体现这一特征的工匠的感觉或习惯，要比迄今提过的任何雕塑表现更复杂和多样化。他有刻苦和快速工作的习惯，北方部落的勤勉因气候的寒冷不断加强，赋予其所有作品以犀利的表达。与南方部落的倦怠不同，不管在那个倦怠的心灵有多大的激情，即便是火山熔岩也是缓慢流动的。还有在寒冷的迹象里寻找乐趣的习惯，我相信，阿尔卑斯山脉以南国家的居民从来没有这种习惯。对他们来说，寒冷是一种不可饶恕的罪恶，是需要尽快经历并遗忘的。而北方的漫长冬季迫使想要快乐生活的哥特人（我是指英国人、法国人、丹麦人或德国人）在坏天气里找到快乐的来源，在光秃的森林里像在成荫的森林里一样快乐。这些我们都全心全意地去做，在圣诞节的火炉旁得到像夏日阳光下那样的满足，在冬天的冰野上得到健康和力量——就像在春天的草地上一般。因此，对于我们的感觉来说，被寒冷抑制的窄小、僵硬的植物结构既没什么不好，也并不痛苦。南方雕塑家只寻求表现被柔和所滋养的柔软枝叶，贪图暖风和热光的富饶，而我们在植物的暴躁、乖张、怪僻的生机上得到愉悦，它们从天上和地上都没有得到过多少善意，但是，它们一季又一季地尽自己最大的努力生长着，即便它们被霜冻麻痹，最灿烂的花蕾埋藏在雪中，漂亮的树枝被暴雨砍去。

78.很多微妙的同情和感情被加入进来，从而加强哥特式精神对于主题的独特选择。当我们加入这些影响时，随之而来的必然是更粗糙原料的使用，迫使工匠寻求显著的效果，而不是改进质地或确定形状。对于北方和南方在概念上的很多不同之处，我们有直接和明显的原因，但是我们没有直接的原因来把握一个在哥特式心灵上更为重要的位置，尽管它们对设计的影响没有那么直接。意志的力量、个性的独立、目标的坚决、对于过分控制的不耐烦，以及树立个体理性对抗权威、个人行为对抗命运的普遍倾向，这使得北方部落在各个时期都在抗争无力的服从，而在南方出于对传统的考虑以及天命的目的，或多或少可在北方哥特式装饰的僵硬线条、强烈多样的色块以及大胆的设计和独立结构上找到它们的踪迹。相反的感觉同样清晰地在优雅、柔和的海浪和环绕的花纹中显现，这是南方装饰经常涉及的内容。在它丧失独立、融入投射其上的大块表面的倾向里，在处理这些大块的时候，经常表现为不可避免的需要或无精打采的静止而放弃他们的力量。

79.对于这些哥特式精神特征及其创造的风格来说，适量即美德，过量即有错。最好的建筑以及最好的调剂是将他们两者联合起来，因此哥特式心灵的第五个冲动是最需要慎于耽溺。它比其他几个都具有更明确的哥特式特征，但是最好的哥特式建筑，并不是最具哥特式特性的建筑：它可以坦率地承认自己的粗陋，它变化丰富，忠实于自然主义。它可能太坚硬了，就像伟大的清教徒精神在极端的情形下因为各种轻浮或乖僻的目的而失去了自我。在后期也确实是如此，但是它有幸记得在它最高贵的时候，那些曾被认为最有害的趋向，那些依靠自己和不断追寻的新教精神在每一根线条里得以表达。从第一世纪到第十五世纪，每一座基督教的教会建筑都蕴含信念和渴望，但是在当今，英格兰所拥有的那种伟大归功于道德习惯——哲学研究的习惯，精确思考、家庭隔离和独立的习惯，严格自律和对于宗教真理的真诚探究的习惯。这些只可在哥特学派富有特色的建筑特征中找到踪迹，在有脉纹的叶子上，在多刺的回纹细工上，在朦胧的壁龛里，在拱壁的扶壁上，在精妙的尖塔和拥有顶饰的、极高的高楼上，如同一个“送向苍穹的困惑的疑问”。

80.由于是这个高贵学派的组合元素中最微不足道的一个元素是冗余，这是慷慨馈赠的劳动财富。确实有很多哥特式建筑，而且是在最佳时期的建筑里都鲜有这个元素的踪迹，它的影响几乎专门依靠简单设计的可爱和无关部分的魅力，然而在最有特色的建筑上，它们的特定影响依靠装饰的累积，并且很多对于人类心灵的最大影响是以这个单独的特征来实现的，尽管通过对这个学派的仔细研究有可能达到一个品位的高度。比起整个由回纹细工覆盖的正面，我们更满足于一些完美的线条，但是满足于这种品味的建筑并不是最好的建筑，因为正如我们在前面所看到的，哥特式建筑首先应该包容从最粗陋到最优雅的心灵的欣赏诉求。尽管这听起来有些矛盾，但哥特式作品的丰富性的确是它谦卑的一个部分。从来没有如此简单却又如此傲慢的建筑，只以一些清晰和强烈的线条来吸引眼球，只提供少得可怜的值得关注的事物，这也意味着，凡是提供的都是完美的。因其特征的复杂性或吸引力而不屑于阻碍我们的调查，或者使我们无意中流露出欢愉。那种谦卑，正是哥特学派的生命所在，并不仅仅在其不完美中显现，也在装饰的累积上表现出来。工匠的较次等级同样显示在他作品的丰富性和粗糙中。若想每双手都能够合作，每颗心都能被接受，我们就必须容许这种冗余——当它假装脆弱者的失败时，却赢得疏忽者的关注。在哥特式的心灵里更为高贵的兴趣混合着对于装饰累积的原始之爱，这是一种巨大的热情，感觉好像它做什么都不足以实现其理想。这是一种无私的牺牲，仿佛宁可在祭坛前抛下无结果的劳动也不要在市场上虚度。一种对于物质世界的充足和财富的深厚同情从自然主义中产生，我们已经努力解释了它的运作过程。在森林的叶子上寻找模型的雕刻家很快深刻地意识到，复杂性不一定导致优雅的丧失，丰富性也不一定导致宁静的丧失。他花在研究大自然的微小和多样工艺上的时间，使得他更强烈地感受到人类缺乏最好的工艺。这也无须惊奇，当看到大自然大量涌现完美和精致的创造，且观念无法把握，数量无法统计时，他会认为吝啬自己粗陋的手艺是多么病态。在整个宇宙中，他看到一种无瑕的美丽在花团锦簇的田野和山间无边的空间蔓延，他怨恨自己将一块石头堆在另一块上的不完美的劳动，这些只是为了居住或者纪念。在他的任务完成之前，他已经丧失了大好年华，但是一代又一代人以不倦的热情前赴后继，大教堂的正面终于被花纹的装饰所覆盖，就像岩石掩映在春天繁茂的草木间一。

81.现在，我相信，关于构成哥特式建筑的内在精神的各种道德或想象元素，我们已经有了一个接近圆满的看法……

铁在自然、艺术和政治中的功用

1858年2月16日在塔布里奇威尔斯所作的演讲

1.当我刚刚得知你们想要我今晚作这个演讲的时候，我有一点疑惑，因为我不知道自己是否能找到一个可以引起你们足够兴趣的主题，值得你们在这样的一个冬夜从温暖的家中赶来听我演讲。当我冒险去讲述我自己对于艺术的特别感觉时，大部分时候都是面对艺术系的学生；在他们面前我可以允许自己乏味一点，只要我感觉自己还有点用，但是一次纯粹的关于艺术的演讲，特别是没有例子可以援引的时候（我也没有办法为这次演讲准备什么有用的插图），对于一般听众来说都是鲜有兴趣的。当我在考虑你们最可能容忍我谈论什么话题的时候，我很自然地想到了一个与你们所居住的这个城镇的起源和当前的繁荣相关联的主题，对我来说，在艺术的诸多分支中，唯有它可以引发普遍的兴趣。很久以前（我很怕去想有多久），塔布里奇威尔斯，就是瑞士。有一年夏天我被带到这儿，那时我还是一个非常活泼的孩子，因为可以攀爬砂岩——高得惊人的峭壁而高兴。我推想，与威尔斯的所有孩子的童年相比，那是我生命中的黑暗岁月。在波形瓦和镶边建筑风格充斥各处的不幸中，我唯一的慰藉是散步时在每一个转角观看泉水从大理石水池的橙色边缘喷涌而出。记忆中清澈的泉水，闪耀过橘黄色的污点，变成与这个地方相关的最强烈的景象。我想，今晚你们应该不会不愿意来稍微思考一下那个橘黄色污点的意义，以及其他的方式和功能，以及使这里许多人恢复生机和力量的铁的意义。它一直是那么重要，而且作为地球的珍贵馈赠会日复一日地越来越引人注目。

2.当然这个主题太广泛，只能点到为止，尽管我的提议不多，而且主要是以我自己工作的领域为出发点，然而我认为我应该有时间来指明一些思考的过程。如你们感兴趣的话，这些想法可能以后自己也可以一探究竟。因此，我不会缩小我已向你们宣布的这个主题的范围，即“铁在自然、艺术和政治上的功用”。

3.开场白到此为止，下面我开始论述第一方面。

4.一、自然中的铁。你们想必都知道，往往被认为毁坏了泉水池的红褐色污点是铁生锈的状态。当你在其他地方看到生锈的铁时你通常会想，它不仅破坏了它沾染的地方，而且也毁坏了自己，生锈的铁是腐坏的铁。

5.对于铁的大多数的功用来说确实如此，因为一把生锈的厨刀或剃刀不如磨光的好使，我们就认定铁会生锈是它的一大缺陷。事实并非如此，相反，铁最完美和最有用的形态就是红褐色的污点，它被赋予了一个天生的性情来使得自己进入这种形态。铁容易生锈不是铁的过错，而是它的优点，因为在那种情形下它满足了它在宇宙中最重要的功能以及对人类最善意的职责。不，在某种意义上，而且几乎是在字面意义上，我们可以说生锈的铁是鲜活的，而它被磨光或者提炼后，则是死的。你们可能都知道，在我们呼吸的空气里最关键的成分被称为氧气，这个物质对所有动物来说都是至关重要的。以这个词语最精确的含义来说，是“生命的气息”。生命的力量是另一回事，但是如果没有呼吸的辅助元素，血液和生命都得不到滋养，这种辅助元素就是氧气。铁就是被氧化然后生锈的，它像我们一样贪婪地从空气中吸取氧气，尽管它的目的与我们不同。铁将吸收的养分都保存了起来，我们和其他的动物则只保存了部分，而铁完全保存了它从空气的馈赠中吸收到的养分。我们如此蔑视的红褐色的尘埃事实上比纯铁要高贵得多，因为它是铁和空气的结合。它不仅更高贵也更有用，因为正如我要向你们展示的一样，这个金属以及所有其他金属的主要功用，不是在制造厨刀和剪刀、拨火棒和平底锅，而是在制造我们赖以生存的土地，以及几乎所有对我们的生存所必需的物质。这一切都只需金属和氧气——会呼吸的金属。沙子、石灰、粘土和土地的其他部分，钾碱和苏打，以及其他碱类，都是金属经过了氧化这一重大变化过程才形成的，并且已经通过与其本身呼吸的纯粹空气永久结合变得适合服务于人类。只有一种金属不会轻易生锈，从它迄今对人类的影响来看，已经导致了死亡而不是生命，除非它被用于铺设人行道，被踏在脚底下，否则它就不能算是被正确使用。[5]

6.在这个无生命的创造物所提供的类型或教训里难道没有引人注目的部分？你拥有坚硬、光亮、冰冷、无生命的金属，它们质地精良足以制作剑和剪刀，但不能用来制成食品。你认为，也许铁以一种纯粹的形式存在十分有用，但是你怎么可能会喜欢这个世界——如果你所有的草地长出了铁丝而不是青草，如果所有的耕地不是由沙和粘土组成而是忽然变成了平坦的钢面，如果整个地球不是绿色的灼热球体，长满了森林和花朵，而是变成可怕机车上的巨大熔炉的景象，一个黑暗的、无生命的、被撕去表皮的地球？它将会变成这个样子，也许它曾经就是这个样子。要不是它所构成的物质吮吸和呼吸了空气的精华，它确实会变成这个样子。当它呼吸的时候，它无情的坚硬被软化，变成了富有成效的有益的尘埃，再次聚集起来成为我们赖以生存的土地，以及我们用来建造的石头，并成为形成山脉的岩石和约束海洋的沙滩。

7.当你拿起脚边最不起眼的鹅卵石，你不可能看不出里面蕴含的教义。一开始你看着它，仿佛它只是土地，不，它回答：“我不是土地，我是土地与空气的混合体，是你所热爱和渴望的蓝天的一部分，这是我全部的生命，没有它我就什么都不是了，也什么都不能了。要不是因为我在创造中的需要和地位，在我身上有一种灵魂，我将不能帮助你，也不能滋养你，我将会变成残忍和无用，但如今我在生命的循环中既有益又有用。”

8.同样的情况也适用于所有的土地，以及构成土地的所有金属，但是那个染污了你泉边的大理石的红褐色的铁与之有着更深的关系并得到了更大的益处。它染污了大理石以外的很多东西，它染污了你在这片土地上看到的所有东西。它是被指定用来给地球染色的染色剂，也是用来服务于人类的。你看到山脉上覆盖着积雪，也许一开始你会欣赏它美丽的白色与松树林的黑色相对比，但是你有没有考虑过，你怎么会喜欢它们永远是白色的——不是纯白色，而是肮脏的白色——融雪的白色，有着雪的寒意，却没有它的光亮？那就是地球没有铁的时候会变成的颜色。那就是不仅这里或那里，而是所有地方所有时候都会变成的颜色。顺着这个思路，你在细节上会有所认知。首先，想象你在自家花园里漂亮的碎石路上散步，像黄色的花床之间的阳光一样美好；然后想象一下它们忽然全都变成灰烬的颜色，这就是如果没有红褐色铁的话它们会变成的样子。再想象你在公园里蜿蜒漫步，眼底温暖、足底干燥，然后想象一下它们全都忽然化为灰色的煤渣会是什么景象？然后穿过公园进入乡村，在你所看到的阳光下第一块遍布山间的耕地前停留，它深褐色的犁沟和赤热的山脊在耕地边上凸起，就好像手织天鹅绒斗篷的深深折痕一般。想象这些全都忽然变成在一片污泥地里的可怕的犁沟——这就是没有铁的话会变成的样子。继续在想象中前行，越过山丘和山谷，直到你到达弯曲的海岸线，走到吹着微风的海滩，观看白色的泡沫在琥珀色的海滩上飞溅，整片蓝色的大海在金色的沙滩里栖息，然后想象那些席卷海岸的小圏忽然变成了悲痛的堤坝，所有金色的沙子变成了灰色的烂泥，仙女们再也无法互相呼唤，“来这片黄色的沙滩吧”，而是说，“来这片褐色的沙滩吧”——这就是如果没有铁的话它们会变成的样子。

9.因此，在某些方面，铁是山水的阳光和光线——只要光线依赖着土地。它也是另一种阳光的来源，对我们如今生存的方式来说同样重要，它不是景观的阳光而是住所的。

10.在这个急速流动的时代，我可以断定，大部分听众都去过英格兰以外的地方，如去过苏格兰、法国或瑞士。不管他们对这些国家有什么样的印象，在他们回到祖国的时候，面对她在其他方面的优势或劣势，他们只能感受到一件事情——她的城镇和乡村舒适的样子。外国的城镇往往是风景如画，非常美丽，但是他们从来没有那种温暖的自足和整体的宁静，就像我们的村庄被绿色的田野环抱的样子。如果你不辞辛劳地去研究这种印象的来源，你会发现，这种温暖和舒适外表很大部分来自砖瓦的深红色。它不属于整洁的建筑——每座整洁的建筑都有一个不舒适的样子——但是它属于暖色调的建筑。我们的村庄装扮着红色的瓦，就像我们的老妇人戴着红色的斗篷。不管斗篷有多温暖或者屋顶有多倾斜，只要它们上面没有洞，只要这个沉静的不会消减的颜色还在头巾的阴影里闪耀，还在山墙的绿色苔藓中燃烧。你觉得是什么染成了你们村舍屋瓦的颜色？不是油漆，是自然为你把可爱的朱红色放进粘土，而可爱的朱红色是铁的氧化物。然后想一想城镇的街道，其中一些已经很丑，但看上去依然很舒适，如果这些房子失去那个温暖的砖红色而变成了胡椒和盐的颜色，想象那时会变成什么样子。想想你们村庄的那个家常的深红色，那个象征了艰苦得来的和平颜色，就好像经历过艰苦战役后战士的红衣一样可爱。而如果所有的村舍屋顶全都变成未经烘烤的粘土的颜色，或者雨季里街道排水沟的颜色——这就是没有铁的话它们会变成的样子。

11.在我们英国的村镇里，颜色还有另外一个作用，也许你自己没有注意到，但是你一定大概听到过。它们不常是温暖的深红色，更多是温暖的紫色，一个更美丽的颜色。它们将这颜色归功于混合了我们威尔士屋顶上板岩的深灰色调或紫色调的朱红色，由空气的干扰而使得颜色变得更蓝。如果你检查一片刚切开的威尔士板岩，你会发现它的紫色是清晰和鲜艳的。尽管在长期暴露以后就不会如此鲜明了，但它总是保留了足够的色彩来提供丰富的搭配，将遥远的紫色与树林和田野的绿色作映照。不管色彩有什么光亮或力量，它总是完全归因于铁的氧化物。没有它，板岩会要么变成苍白石头的颜色，要么是冰冷的灰色或黑色。

12.以上我们只是考虑了铁在普通泥土里的作用和魅力。有三种泥土以混合的质量和普遍的数量，组成了这个世界，以日常语言来说，它们是粘土、石灰土和燧石土。很多其他元素以一定的比例与它们混合，但是地球的大框架和基本内容是由这三种泥土组成的，所以无论你站在坚实大地上的任何地方，在地球上的任何国度，在你脚下的主要物质要么是粘土，要么是石灰土，或者是燧石土与其他两种混合的。

13.这些是我们经常要面对的，自然看上去已经下定决心来尽可能使得这三种物质对我们来说既有趣又美丽。粘土作为一种柔软可变的物质，自然没有花费大力气就能把它烤干了——正如我们看到的一样。只有在获得一个永久的形状时它才会有颜色。自然以自己的方式来给自然状态下的石灰石和燧石上色，她给它们上色的目的就和给花朵上色一样，使得我们粗心和懒惰的人类观察自然，然后看到她在做些什么，她在为我们——她的孩子做好事。自然总是对石灰石和燧石做一些奇怪的事情，在海底安置它们的温床，从海里建造出岛屿，用神奇的珠宝来填充山的裂缝和脉络，硬化苔藓、树木还有贝壳。事实上，大自然做着地下和海底的所有这些事情，对我们来说，看着这一切进行是非常惬意的，我们从中得益并赖此为生。为了引导我们这样做，大自然为我们制作了石灰石和燧石的图画书，就像我们是幼稚的孩子那样诱惑我们，因为它们美丽的颜色而去看她的书。石灰石书的美丽颜色形成了斑驳的大理石，从史前开始，所有的人类都很乐于磨光并且用它来建造房屋。燧石书的美丽颜色形成了玛瑙、碧玉、红玉髓、血石、缟玛瑙、黑水晶、绿玉髓，从史前开始所有的人类都很乐于切割、磨光它们，然后将它们制成饰物。他们多像孩子一样，多喜欢看着图片而不是阅读文字，我怀疑在经过了六千年的切割和磨光后，在一百个人里是否有超过两三个人知道或者想知道，一粒玛瑙或一颗大理石是怎么做出来，又如何被上色的。

14.怎么做出来的？这不是很容易说明白，但是它是如何被上色的就没有什么疑问了。所有西西里和西班牙的美丽大理石的紫色脉纹和斑驳，锡耶纳的大理石闪耀的橘色和琥珀色，紫罗红的深红褐色，所有丰富了意大利庙宇的珍贵碧玉的血红色，最后，所有苏格兰和莱茵河的鹅卵石色彩的可爱转变，形成了——尽管不是最宝贵的，但——迄今为止是我们现代珠宝匠的工作里最有趣的部分。所有这些都是自然只以一种物质的不同比例和应用来上色的，也就是染污了你们塔布里奇的泉水的铁氧化物。

15.这不是全部，也不是铁最好的功用。大自然出产那些美丽的石头是只供给负担得起采石和磨光的富人的。而大自然上色是为了全世界，无论是穷人还是富人，大自然装饰山脉最深处的岩石，诱惑你们去调查，或者纵情于奢侈。她更仔细地为山脉的外部上色，这是为了愉悦牧羊人和庄稼汉的眼睛。我刚才说到了我们村庄屋顶的紫色石板瓦的作用，但是如果石板哪怕在屋顶上排成扁平正规的一排也是美丽的，那么它们在本地山脉崎岖的山巅和侧面就会更好看了。你有没有想过，当我们讲到遥远的蓝色山丘时，是什么使得它们变成蓝色的？在一定程度上是距离，但是仅有距离是无法造成的，很多山丘不管离得多远，看上去都是白色的。我们威尔士和高地山脉可爱的深紫色并不仅仅是出于距离，而是因为它们的岩石。一些岩石的颜色确实太深了，黑色或者灰色，很不好看，这是由于不完美的多孔结构造成的。当你看到这种深色掺入了红褐色和蓝色，在绿色的蕨类植物里大量出现，呈现那样的紫色时，一开始你很难说清楚这是岩石还是石楠，这时你一定要感谢你的塔布里奇的老朋友，铁氧化物。

16.但这还不是全部。为了山丘的美丽景色，大自然应该不止为她柔软的岩石上色，也要为坚硬的岩石上色。她用同样的物质给它们上色，而且更漂亮。也许你会质疑为何我将紫色这个词如此频繁地运用于岩石上。在对紫色都有着极大尊重的希腊和罗马，很久以前就将紫色用在岩石上了。最宝贵的硬性大石头里，你们都听过斑岩。给予它那个高贵名字的颜色，就像给予所有埃及蔷薇色的花岗岩以流溢的红色，是的，就像给予阿尔卑斯山脉最富蔷薇色的山巅，也还是要归功于同样的物质——你们认为卑下的铁氧化物。

17.最后，一个比所有这些都要更高贵的颜色，在这个地球上所见的最高贵的颜色，属于一种比埃及花岗岩更大的强度，比落日或玫瑰更美的颜色，依然与这个深色的铁的存在有着神秘的联系。我相信，虽然我们还没有探知血液的深红色到底依赖于什么，但是这个颜色一定与它的生命力有关联，而那个生命力则和铁作为其中一个组成元素的存在有关联。

18.这个严酷、坚固的金属竟然如此微妙地混合在我们人类的生命里，要是没有它我们甚至不能脸红，这个发现难道不神奇吗？想一想，我亲爱的文雅的听众，这个取舍有多可怕：有时你实际上没有选择，要么厚脸皮，要么铁面皮！

19.在这个对铁的一些功用的简短回顾里，你注意到我严格限制在它作为染色元素的活动上。要是我努力描绘它作为实质元素的作用，无论是分解岩石，还是加强岩石硬度、影响植物，我只会混淆你们对于事实的看法，因此我甚至没有提到铁在自然经济中更为重要的作用。但是我希望你们仔细听取的是，回想如果没有空气的话所有这些金属就都一无是处了。纯金属没有力量，而且在自然中也从来不会存在——除了在陨石中，它的坠落是无法预测的，而在坠落之后也就没有用处了。在这个世界上必需的物质里，铁总是和氧气结合在一起，而且一旦没有它的话，铁就失去作用也不再好看了。

20.二、艺术中的铁。现在，从铁在自然中的活动转到它在人类手中的作用。你一定记得在开始时，由无生命的金属展现给你的金属类型，是人类身体和灵魂一起行动的结果，在所有人类能量的活动中都有高贵的原型。所有配得上这个名字的艺术都是能量，既不是只有身体，也不是只有精神，而是两者的结合，一个指导着另一个。好的手艺和手指的工作与好的情感和心灵的工作相互结合。

21.如果两者没有结合的话，就不可能产生好的艺术，也不可能进行艺术评判，然而我们总是试图将两者分离。业余艺术家不能被说服，他们认为：一方面，没有经过必要辛劳的苦工，仅凭幻想和敏感就能制造出美好的艺术。那是完全没有希望实现的。没有一定数量的劳动，事实上如果没有相当大数量的手工操作——正如学习其他手工技艺一样需要仔细和经常的练习——是不可能画画的。另一方面，工匠及其雇用者仍然试图以手工技巧或习惯来生产艺术品，而不用想象力或敏感来制造艺术。那也是没有希望实现的。心灵的情感如果没有混合着手的力量，艺术是不可能产生的。最高水平的艺术总是以最强烈的程度将两者结合起来：最灵巧的手工和最丰富的心灵。

22.因此，只有通过手的最微妙的触觉以及接收和保持这种触碰的材料，才能产生艺术的最大力量。这只手是宇宙中现有物质力量最完美的中介，它完全的精妙只在它施予的物质完全屈从时才会显现。一个完美的乐器和音会接收它，但是不完美的乐器不会。鹅毛笔柔软弯曲的笔尖以及缓缓融化的颜色可以接收它，但粉笔或钢笔就不会，钢头、凿子或大理石更不会。雕刻家的手的确会像画家的手一样灵巧，但是它的灵巧不是随处适用或表现的，提香、柯勒乔或特纳的风格，是紧张劳作之下的杰作，而非仅通过颜色来表达，或者像音乐中凭借对主旋律的表现来表达。用以加工的物质越不精妙，所需的执行力就越低，艺术性也就越低，这是所有工艺中的一个主要原则。另一个原则是，无论你选择什么物质来加工，如果你没有将这种物质的独特品质表现出来，那么你的艺术性就是低下的。

23.第二条原则的理由是，如果你不需要你所采用的物质的特质，你就应该去采用别的物质。你利用一种陌生的物质，可能只是因为做作以及想要展现你的技艺的欲望，那么你的艺术就会变得低下。比如玻璃在本质上显然是透明的，如果你不想要这种透明，你就不要用玻璃。不要试图让一扇窗户看上去像一幅不透明的画，如果想要这种效果，你应该在一个不透明的基础物上做画。另外，大理石明显是结实、巨大的物质，除非你想要巨大和结实的特质，不然就不要用大理石。如果你想要轻巧，用木头；想要自由，用灰泥；想要延展，用玻璃。不要试图用大理石来雕刻羽毛、树木、网或者泡沫，请只用它来雕刻洁白的四肢和宽广的胸膛。

24.因此，我再次申明，铁明显是易延展的坚固的物质，比所有物质都坚固，比大部分物质都易于延展。如果你想要坚固以及复杂的形式，就用铁。很明显它是为此而存在的。它是作为大理石的同伴提供给雕刻家的，伴随着一个好像从地球母亲的嘴里随意说出来的讯息：“这是给你们雕刻用的，那是给你们敲打用的。塑造这个，扭曲那个。雕刻结实和简单的，敲打细薄和复杂的。我给你们所有的形式去产生愉悦，摆动的树叶和美好的身体，扭曲的四肢和舒展的额头。你可以通过敲打和扭曲来表现树叶和树枝，身体和额头则需要你细心的点缀，从而形成你所需要的样子。如果你选对了也做对了，你做的一切就应当是安全的。细长的树叶不会折断坚固的铁，尽管它们在铁的衰退期会有一点生锈。宽广的表面不会在纯洁的水晶般的大理石上磨损，它们不会腐朽。如果你用会在碰触中破裂的大理石雕刻，或者用会在锈或铜的污点中腐坏的金属铸造，这就是你的错而不是我的错。”

25.这些就是这一事项上的主要原则，就像在艺术中所有其他正确的原则一样，我们现代人总是乐于尽可能直接和专门地予以反驳。在展览会上我们不断地寻找并赞美以易碎的石头雕刻出来的面纱、蕾丝、细叶和所有尽可能地逼向不可能的事物，只是为了展现雕刻家的灵巧。[6]另一方面，我们将铁制成铁条，尽管有一寸厚但依然易碎，磨利它们的顶端，然后认为围墙和所有由此制成的东西都是可用作装饰的！我相信单要计算我们英格兰的品位因为这种铁围墙而造成的伤害并非易事。如果有人要求我们用一个特征把乡村的住处分为两个大的分区，将一个分区的人们设定为简单、快乐、善良和诚实的；而另一分区的人们则是世故的、无情的、不自在的和无原则的。我认为有一个特征可以作为明确的评判标准：不自在和无原则的那部分人住在铁栏杆里，而自在和有原则的那部分人则没有铁栏杆的限制。你会说这是泛泛的概括，也许是有一点太宽泛了，但是只要我们足够严肃，就会发现它比你想象的还要正确。想一想其他种类的围墙或栏杆，你会发现它们总有一些优点，但是铁栏杆没有任何优点。首先，石头的城堡城墙，在围墙的范畴里似乎显得有点太宏伟了。其次，花园或公园的砖墙，从外面看上去确实总是一副不友善的样子，但其实它很谦逊。通常它并不意味着建造者想要把你关闭在花园景色之外，而只是想阻止你看到他本人，这是一个坦率的声明，他需要一定时间的独处，所以他需要留给自己一定的空间，当他卷起袖子在那儿锄地，或者和他放学的孩子玩跳蛙游戏，或者和他的妻子聊起旧日时光，在晚霞中漫步时，他不想被盯着看。另外，砖墙也有很好的实用性，为你遮蔽东风，催熟你的桃子和油桃，在秋天里像明媚的堤岸一样发光。再者，砖墙要是建造得宜的话，可以保持相当长的时间，当它变旧了，它庄重的紫红色布满绿色的青苔，就会非常好看。

26.紧靠着高贵的墙壁和围栏的是密密麻麻的木栅栏。它更令人反感，因为它通常意味着比人们想要的还要更大范围的围栏。不过对于舒适的公园和维护得很好的野外小道，牧鹿人和其他此类的贵族式田园生活来说，这依然是有意义的。在一个国家，这里或那里有它们恰当的位置，可以不带任何疑惑地通行。

27.紧接着木栅栏的是矮石堤、山墙，一瞥即可见原始的山野或者土壤下的石床。山篱对于所有的结合都感到愉悦，但更喜欢组成它的松散石头的各种陡峭形状。紧靠着矮石墙的是低地篱，在大片整齐的绿色线上，显示着伊丽莎白时代的老房子的舒适，有便于老年人腿脚的平稳小路和适于年轻人的离奇迷宫。美丽的野蔷薇和未经使用的凉亭交错，沿着乡村的路边投掷其芳香。在美丽的山间，秋天给孩子可尽情采摘的大丛树莓，冬天给小鸟可供觅食的深红色山楂。最后，在围墙里最难分级的是扶手，它表达了很多的东西。它带着一个会意的邪恶表情，这时它是赛马场上的栏杆；有时是无辜的温和表情，这时它是乡村长满水芹的小溪上的小桥栏杆；有时是谨慎的防卫表情，这时它是阿尔卑斯山脉边线上的栏杆，那里它有花岗岩的标杆和松树的栅栏，护卫着悬崖的顶端和山洪的堤岸。所有这些围栏都有一些好的、愉悦的或者高贵的意义，但是铁栏杆有什么意义？要么你和很坏的人住在一起，你必须要用栏杆的力量把他们隔绝开来，要么你自己就是需要以同样的方式关在里面的人。铁栏杆总是意味着外面有小偷或者里面是疯人院。它只能是这个意思。如果外面的人是好的，只要一点围墙的暗示就足够了，但是因为他们是暴力的并且对你有敌意，你不得不在顶端安上密集的铁棒和长钉。去年夏天我暂居于乡下的一处村舍，在我低矮的窗户前面有雏菊的花床，还有一排鹅莓和醋栗的灌木，然后是一面大约三英尺高的矮墙，覆盖着岩芥菜。外面有一片麦田，绿色的麦穗在阳光下闪耀，有一条小径经过花园大门，穿过田野。我可以从窗户看到乡间的每一个农民经过，他们手上挎着篮子去赶集，或者肩上扛着铲子去种地。当我想要社交的时候我就靠在墙上，然后可以跟任何人说话；当我想要作科学研究的时候，可以沿着墙头作植物研究，光墙头上就长了四种岩芥菜；当我想要锻炼的时候，可以在墙上来来回回地跳。这就是基督教国家应该有的围墙，而不是那种你在里面走却好像是被囚禁的野兽，或者在早晨从窗口往外看却没想到晚上有人被钉在上面的围墙上。

28.此外，请注意铁栏杆是无用的围墙，它不能遮蔽什么，也不能援助什么，你不能把桃子钉在上面，也不能用它来保护花朵，或者从它代价高昂的暴政里生产出什么东西来。它不只是无用，还是粗野的，它公然地对每个经过的人说：“也许你是一个诚实的人，但你也有可能是一个小偷，不管你是不是诚实，你都不能到这儿来，因为我是一个远比你高尚的人，你只能看看我用了多大的一块地方来隔离你，看看这儿，然后谦卑地离去吧。”

29.这是当前文明通常的表述方式，而且在很多地区，铁栏杆很不幸是不可避免的，但是你是否有必要把它弄得那么丑呢，并且带着罪恶的意味呢？在伦敦你必须要在广场周围以及地区的边界上安上栏杆，但你需要安上这么丑的栏杆，以至于它们不变的景观足以中和这片国土上所有艺术院校的积极影响么？不需要这样！不仅远不需要，你甚至可以将所有铁栅栏的警力扭转为绘画大师的杰作及自然历史学家的记录。当然这样做会有一些困难，并且要付出一些代价，但你在这个世界上做任何值得做的事情都会遇到困难，而你想得到任何值得拥有的东西也都需要付出代价。主要的问题只在于什么是值得做的和值得拥有的，想一想，这件事是否值得。你的铁栏杆像一头无知的怪物，一个阴郁的管家，除了永恒的“禁止入内！”“走远些！”不会说其他的。难道不值得花一些力气和费用来把这个不雅的、残忍的门卫变成一个有教养的仆人？当他严厉禁止有恶意的人入内的同时，也学会对善良的人们表示善意。万一过路的向他提问，他会以和善的表情提供他掌握的一些有用的信息。

30.今晚我们没有时间来看铁很多制品的例子，而我碰巧有的例子也不一定是最好的，因为铁制品并不是我研究的专题，所以我只有一些备忘录，有些例子是在我准备其他内容的时候不经意收集的。另外，外用的铁制品要比其他种类的古代艺术还要难找到好作品，因为当它变得生锈和断裂，人们就断定它不再有用，然后把它送到旧铁铺里去，再拿回一个好的新铁器。因为这个原因，在意大利的伟大城市，旧铁几乎全部不在了，在露天里最好的遗存我记得是在布雷西亚，月桂般的叶子的铁制品喷出的神奇水柱从花园大门上升起，在维也纳有一些精妙的断片，围绕着斯卡拉坟墓有一些好的格子棚架，但是总体上，它们的风格并不纯粹。最有意思的作品可以在外省的城镇里找到，在那里人们不关心铁制品或者无法作适当的改建。比如，在阿尔卑斯山以南、锡安以北的贝林佐纳小镇，在他们的阳台和葡萄园大门上呈现着铁制品的两个完整的学派。贝林佐纳是最好的，尽管不是很旧，我推想大部分是十七世纪的，它依然非常古雅和美丽。比如这里是两栋不同房子的两个阳台，一个是鲜红色的，檐帽是阳台的主要装饰，它的流苏是用愉悦的精细和自由锻造成的，即使在大片茂盛的花叶间也能很清晰地看到。这些流苏和串饰正是适合铁制品表现的主题，高贵的铁制品，在之前提到的地方，它们用大理石来表现的话可能就一点也不高贵了。夹竹桃在窗户前很愉快地丰富了整个建筑物的线条。

31.在同一条街上，一个看上去非常普通的房子的阳台，在细节上要更加有趣。去年夏天在横木上是并置的旋花植物，箭形的真叶混合了铁的叶子……它的中心是一朵大郁金香，然后是两朵头巾百合，然后是两朵抽象化的石竹花，然后是两朵水仙，然后是两朵难以名状的或至少是我不知道的花，然后是两个暗色的花蕾，以及一些叶子。我说暗色的花蕾是因为所有这些花朵都是以它们原初的状态来上色的。这个组合的规划相当简单，全部围绕着一个尖拱，大片的郁金香形成了顶点，每边都有一颗六层的星，然后是不对称的星，然后是五层的星，再然后是对称的星或玫瑰，最后是一个小花蕾，以便在整个组合里建立关联和节奏。整个轮廓非常自由和美好，阳台的上部围栏在效果上相当漂亮，一点儿也没有因为运用的方法极端简单而受到影响。一根细条的铁弯向方形的杆，在这个细条的边缘切了一系列的三角形的口，顶上最宽，放置突出的铁齿。每一个突出的小片均被榔头用力敲打过，向内打碎它的边缘，同时把它撕开一点，然后就完成了。

32.瑞士铁制品的普通形态要比意大利阳台的少一点自然，更多地依靠各种曲线的美丽组合，然而，在弗里堡有一个丰富的自然主义派别，在那儿还保存有铃型把手，由分成月桂和其他树叶的铁棒组成。在日内瓦，现代化改良已经没有留下什么了，但是在安锡还有一些好的作品。特别是老市政厅的阳台，湖里的鳟鱼——大概是城镇的手臂——形成了它的中心装饰。

33.只要你能坐在这儿听，我可以整晚地细说关于必要主题的处理方法，或者有关老工匠的愉悦的奇思妙想的介绍。但是我们没有多少剩余时间了，我必须停止这个部分的主题，正如如果不进入曲线设计的全套理论，就不能向你们解释铁制品的内在价值一样。希望我留给你们这个清晰的论断，很多自然物品的离奇的美丽和特性，就像错综的树枝、草木、叶子（特别是多刺的树枝和叶子），也像很多动物，羽毛的、尖刺的、刚毛的，只能用铁来实现雕塑的表达，用铁就会达到最大程度的庄严和表现力。你使用的每一件金属品，如果正确加以对待的话，可能不只是极好的装饰，而且也是自然形式的极有价值的概括，它们和植物的画作的关系恰如人的画作和雕像的关系。对于从周围丰富的、扰乱了我们微弱注意力的环境抽象出来的形状极简单的事物，你很难得到一个优雅的、有意思的印象。每一丛植物都会提供五十个这样的组合，每一个组合都能轻易融入铁，（当然是与其作用相匹配的）并带来无限的庄严。

34.三、政治中的铁。我们已经掌握了一些铁在艺术中运用的概念，即依靠它的延展性，我当然不需要再阐述它在制造业和商业上的用处了。关于这些，我们都知道得足够多了，也许有点太多了。因此在最后我要来思考它在政治中的运用，这主要依靠它的坚韧性，也就是说，它能够承受拉扯、迎接刀锋的力量。这些力量使得它可以刺穿、约束和重击，使得它适合做成三种伟大的工具，它的政治行为可被简单地典型化，即犁、脚镣和剑。

35.我们对这三个工具的正确用途的理解，需要依靠我们作为国家的权力和作为个体的幸福感。

36.犁。首先，根据我们对于犁的正确运用的理解，为对我们的劳动者公平起见，我们必须联系到女性的犁——针。对于一个国家幸福的首要要求是，了解这个世界上两个伟大工具的功能：一个幸福的国家可以被定义为丈夫的手扶着犁，妻子的手拿着针，这样到时候农民就能穿着漂亮的衣服来收获金色的果实；而一个不幸福的国家就是不承认犁或针的作用，最后一定会发现它的仓库空虚、面临饥荒，它的子民赤裸着胸膛受冻。

37.也许你认为这只不过是不言而喻的道理，我在这里重复只是浪费你们的时间。但愿如此。

38.在当下文明的欧洲，很大部分的苦难和罪恶是从不明白这个不言而喻的道理的人们那里产生的。他们不明白，农产品或财富是和天地法则永久地联系起来的，是由不懈的劳动而来的。他们希望以某些方式欺骗或废除这个生命的永恒法则，想在没有耕地的地方得到食物，想在没有编织的地方得到温暖。

39.我重复一下，几乎所有的苦难和罪恶都是从这种误解而来的。自然法则是，必须进行一定量的劳动才能产生一定量的物品，不管其种类如何。如果想要知识，就必须辛苦工作；如果想要食物，必须辛苦工作；想要欢乐，也必须辛苦工作。但是人们不承认这条法则，或者努力逃避它，希望不劳动就能获得知识、食物和欢乐。这样的话，他们要么什么也得不到，并且依然无知和痛苦，要么通过让他人为了自己的利益劳动，以期获得这些东西。这样，他们就成了暴君和强盗。是的，甚至比强盗更糟糕。我绝不是怀疑或争论本世纪在很多对人类有益的事情上的进步，但在我看来，存在着一个黑暗的迹象，即我们以如此的漠然来看待追求财富中的欺诈和残酷。在尼布甲尼撒的梦里，只有脚是半铁半土的，但是现在我们很多人变得如此贪婪和残酷，看上去我们的心好像也是半铁半土的。

40.从我对这个镇上的居民所了解到的情况来看，我不怀疑我可以在这里被允许做一些在其他地方通常被认为很不恰当和荒唐的事，也就是，援引《圣经》中的一些语句来达到实际的效果。

41.你一定注意到了当人们在日常生活中寻求指导、安慰或帮助的时候，那些最可能被打开的篇章，也就是《诗篇》和《箴言》，这两部分提到了“欺压”穷人的罪行。注意，不是“忽视”他们，而是“压迫”他们：这个词很常见，也很奇怪。你打开这些篇章的任何部分，在某些页上会发现关于坏人企图压迫穷人的描述，比如：“他拉网，就把困苦人掳去。”（《诗篇》10：9）

“他在村庄埋伏等候，他的眼睛窥探无倚无靠的人。”（《诗篇》10：8）

“恶人在骄横中，把困苦人追得火急，他祝福贪财的，却轻慢耶和华。”（《诗篇》10：2）

“他满口是咒骂、诡诈、欺压，他在隐密处杀害无辜的人。作孽的没有知识吗？他们吞吃我的百姓如同吃饭一样？恶人已经弓上弦、刀出鞘，要打倒困苦穷乏的人。”（《诗篇》10：7）

“他们讥笑人，凭恶意说欺压人的话。”（《诗篇》73：8）

“所以骄傲如链子戴在他们的项上。强暴像衣裳遮住他们的身体。”（《诗篇》73：6）

“他们的毒气好像蛇的毒气。你们在地上秤出你们手所行的强暴。”（《诗篇》58）

42.是的，“你们在地上秤出你们手所行的强暴。”也请掂量这些话吧。我们通常最不会想到去掂量的就是圣经里的话。我们喜欢梦想和争论它们，却从来没有想过掂量它们，看看它们真实的内涵是什么。请掂量一下，因为我已经故意拿来所有这些诗文，也许连起来读，要比分散在诗篇里更惊人，因为对于所有属于这个国家的教会的人们来说，这些诗篇是指定的功课，由他们的牧师分配给他们，每个月都要读一遍。大概无论我们会错过或遗忘圣经的什么部分，在所有情况下，这些诗篇都不断让我们奉行，并作为日常生活的实用性指导。现在，我们还要问自己这些段落的真实含义是什么，这些邪恶的人是谁，谁在“谋杀无辜的人”？你知道这是相当非凡的语言！第一次听到这样的语言，我们也许可以称它有力量。谋杀！谋杀无辜的人！不，甚至是一种同类相食。吃人，是的，而且是上帝的子民，吃我的人民好像他们是面包！弓已上弦，刀已出鞘，蛇毒已调好！手的暴力被掂量、衡量和贩卖，用如此多的货币！这些都发生在哪里？你以为这些都只发生在大卫的时代，除了犹太人没有别人谋杀穷人？如果是这样，不要咕哝着埋怨，与我们无关的日常教训一定是更明智的。如果它可能会有一丝与我们有关，而且如果《诗篇》里关于人类罪行的描述，正如关于人类悲伤的描述是普遍适用的，知道在我们周围犯下，或我们自己会犯下这个罪行，这难道不是明智的么？当我们以公理会的方式念着《圣经》里的话，确定我们只是想吟唱一首动人的关于别人的诗歌——我们不知道到底是给谁的——或者声明我们对负荷着我们自己和我们日常事务的真相的信念。如果你打定主意不再这样做了，并努力调查这件事情，你会发现这些奇怪的语句，并不只是发生在一些地方，而是几乎在《诗篇》《箴言》或《预言》交替的每一章，惊人地反复出现。这不是为一个国家或一个时代所写的，而是为了所有国家和语言，为了所有地方和所有时代。而且对于现在的坏人是如此，就像对于拿八或戴夫斯一样，“他的眼睛窥探无依无靠的人”。

43.请注意，是窥探无依无靠的人。不是将目光从穷人身上移开，也不是忽视或不看他们，而是窥探，也就是折磨和毁灭他们。这就是我想要让你们注意的要点。你经常会听到关于忽视或不关心穷人的布道，但是忽视和不关心完全不是要点。《圣经》几乎从不谈论对于穷人的忽视，它总是在说对穷人的压迫。这是两件非常不同的事情。它并不仅仅在说从另一边经过，不缝合伤口，而是在说抽出剑然后把人击倒。在传染病隔离医院里，无所事事不开药不会被指控，但是在传染病隔离医院里忙忙碌碌开出很多毒药就会被指控。

44.就在今晚，经过考虑后我们再关注这件事，然后首先要问，这些穷人是谁？

45.没有他们的话，国家就不会存在也将不存在。也就是通常来说，这是一个其劳动只能提供生存、没有任何可观度量的财产积累的阶层。这个阶层有一定数量的人，我们不能很剧烈地去压迫，一个能干、聪明、稳重、诚实、勤劳的工人，总是会为他的工作要求一个合理的价格，积累了几年以后就有足够的财产使得他在劳动市场里好好地把握自己，但不是所有人都是能干的，或者聪明的、或者勤劳的，你不能指望他们都是。对我来说，没有比今天的人们谈论工人的道德方式更可笑和可悲的了。你对一个工人生活的希冀几乎一无所知，却一开始就擅自假定，以一小笔道德资产起始，他将拥有苏格拉底的美德、柏拉图的哲学，及伊巴密浓达的英雄行径。“请保证，我的好人”，你对他说，“如果你终生每天稳定地工作十个小时，如果你除了水别的什么都不喝，或者只喝最淡的啤酒，只吃最简单的食物，从不发脾气，每周日上教堂，始终满足于天命安排给你的位置，从不埋怨，或者咒骂，总是保持你的衣服整洁，起得很早，利用每个机会来改善自己，你会活得很好，永不去教区请求救济。”

46.所有这些都是完全正确的，但是在如此自信地给出建议之前，我们应该自己实际去试一下，花上一年的时间去从事艰难的体力劳动，而不以娱乐的姿态去感受。比如去犁地或耕地，只有相当少的啤酒，主餐只有面包和奶酪，早晨没有报纸也没有松饼，晚上没有沙发也没有杂志，一个小房间用作客厅和厨房，一大帮孩子总是在地板的中央玩耍。如果我们觉得自己可以在这样的情况下扮演苏格拉底或伊巴密浓达，觉得我们完全满足了，那么我们才有理由要求我们的贫穷邻居有同样的表现。如果不能的话，我们的确应该考虑一下，在对于穷人的各种形式的压迫中，我们是否不应该以高人一等的姿态，来对他们期望太多。

47.但是先把这些放下，承认我们对于压迫稳重、勤劳、聪明、模范的工人从不感到内疚。世界上总有些既不聪明也不模范的人，我相信我们最后应该会发现大部分人都是不怎么聪明的。有些人喜欢闲散，偶尔在星期六的晚上喝醉。我们也必须准备好听到堕落的人在星期天早上喜欢九柱游戏胜过祷告，还有不近人情的父母把孩子送出去乞讨而不让他们去上学。

48.这些就是你可能去压迫的人们，你也确实压迫着他们，而且是故意的。你以更多的残忍和更大的伤害去压迫他们，而他们将自己置于你的权力之下，是他们本身的过错。你知道关于恶人的语句；“他拉网，就把困苦人掳去。”这样被掳去只不过是受难者的过错或愚蠢，是他们自己不注意或者懈怠了，但是他一旦在网里了，对于他的压迫，以及使得他百般苦恼的人，是我们。我们用来反对穷人的网，正是那些世俗的困窘，他们的无知或缺乏远见一定会在某些时候使得他们被俘获。然后就在我们应该赶快帮助他们、解救他们、教他们如何在未来更好地面对的时候，我们却忙着去掠夺他们，尽可能地在他们的逆境中压迫他们。我来举一个例子，请记住，不夸张地来说，这就是我们所做的。每当我们购买或者试图购买便宜的商品，那些价格无法偿付所付出的劳力的商品，每当我们购买这种商品时，请记住我们是在偷窃别人的劳动。我们不要矫揉造作，我以简单的英语来说，“偷窃”就是拿走一个人劳动所应得的报酬，然后放入我们自己的口袋。你很清楚地知道，这件商品不可能以那个价格卖给你，除非生产者迫于贫困而不得不出卖它。你利用了这种贫困，你尽可能地压迫他。中世纪的男爵通常用“拇指夹”来强取财产，我们现代人则更喜欢用饥饿或者家庭苦难，但是强取的实质是一样的。无论我们是打他的肚子来抢夺财产还是夹他的手指，在解剖学上会有一些不同，但在道德上没有一点不同。我们使用拷问迫使他放弃财产，我们事实上利用了人们自身的焦虑而不是折磨、他挨饿的危险而不是指着头部的手枪。除此之外，我们与恶棍弗兰特·德·贝夫或者路匪迪克·特平的不同仅仅在于我们没有那么灵巧，同时我们更懦弱、更残忍。我说更残忍，因为残暴的男爵和可怕的强盗只是抢夺，至少更喜欢抢夺富人。我们购买自己的制服，给我们的祈祷书镀金，从孩子和病人的薪水里克扣金钱，这就在一定程度上证明了你也是窃贼，但你会通过精心分配来最大可能地消弭因盗窃而来的罪恶感。

49.这只是常见的压迫穷人的一种形式，只是把我们的手从犁头拿开，然后绑上别人的手而已。这样做的第一种方式是经济的方法，一种被谨慎和善良的人们所偏好的方法。大胆的方法是贪得的方法、投机的方法。我们正在思考一个国家自我毁灭的不同模式，其中就有不承认犁头和愉悦的永恒联系，试图不劳而获、免费得到愉悦。我说过最优先和最普通的方法是试着取走别人劳动的果实，然后自己享受，在他们贫困的时候贬低他们的劳动。然而第二种方法是观察市场的机会，投机的方法。当然也有一些投机是公正和诚实的，比如用我们自己的钱进行投机，我们的获利不涉及别人的成败。但是通常来说，现代投机涉及很多别人的风险，而获利的机会只留给我们自己，甚至在最好的情形下它也只是一种赌博或敛财。要么离开平稳的犁和平稳的生命朝圣之旅，寻找路旁的银矿，要么停留在名利场的骰子桌边，在牌落下的时候投注灵魂所有的思想和感情，宁愿等待运气的偶尔光顾，而不是辛苦劳作的平稳和累积的回报——这是非常具有破坏性的，至少对我们的和平与美德来说是如此。这破坏的通常还不只是我们的和平或美德。你有没有设想过估量大交易所的商人或大银行的失败必然导致的苦难、罪恶和死亡？作为最小可能的推测，以最少的量来计算，多少家庭的谋生被牵涉进这场灾难中来？然后，在破产的消息传出的早晨，让我们带着最诚挚的想法走进他们中间，让我们使用那个经常浪费在假想的不幸上的想象，去衡量大面积贫困的可怕事实。敲开他们的房门，然后安静地融入家庭的悲惨中。看看老人，在生命的晚景，为了他们衰退的精力，保留剩余的休息，无助地退回到烦恼和拥挤中。看看中年人，他们活跃的精力忽然变得虚弱，希望被粉碎，好不容易挣来的报酬也在同一个瞬间被抢走。心立刻枯萎了，右臂突然断掉了。看看可怜的孩子，被精心养育的孩子，柔和的眼睛里充满了对父母的悲痛的好奇，很快也一定会被置于饥饿的阴影中。除此以外，尽管生活艰难困苦，还是渴望能活得超越不幸的长度，现在要么是在不可预期和缺乏经验的激烈尝试中进行，要么更痛苦地从头开始，然后再经历第二次苦难——承认珍贵希望的毁灭和逝去岁月的脆弱。因它所带来的内在情感的不断讽刺和嘲弄而受苦，不是因为特定情形的公平进程，而是悲惨的意外和荒唐的背叛而受苦。最后，透过这一层看看那些在尝试中迟疑的人的混乱命运，他们从新生沦落为绝望。然后想一想，是否将毒药倒入生命的泉水中的手比把毒药倒进杯子或者把匕首插入心脏的手沾染鲜血的罪恶要少一点？我们带着恐惧阅读博尔吉亚或者托法那的罪恶，但博尔吉亚从来没有像现在这样活在我们中间。残忍的女士菲拉拉只在情感的力量中减速，她只因为那些阻碍其目的或惹恼其灵魂的人而略微减速。当她严厉而突然减速时，就会使得她的受害者的命运受苦，没有毁灭的预兆，没有痛苦的延长，最后，她不是不带着悔恨或同情减速。但是我们没有感情的风暴，没有盲目的愤怒，我们以平静的、清晰的、不动心的自私，倾倒我们的毒药，不是只为了一些人，而是为了很多人；不是为了那些错怪或抵抗我们的人，而是为了那些信任和帮助我们的人。我们没有仁慈和无意识地死亡的天赋，而只有饥饿的、缓慢的消耗和失望与绝望的无聊折磨！最终我们实施谋杀，不是以同情的中止或者良心的焦虑，而是带着轻巧的、健忘的、心灵的平静。因此我们一天天自得地读着那些描述恶人的话，仿佛他们只是意味着除我们以外的人：“他们嘴里有虺蛇的毒气，他们飞跑去杀人。”

50.也许你会想在这件事情上找很多借口，是因为这个罪孽是相当无意识的，所以当这个罪孽没有被领会的时候就不是那么大。这样就使无心的杀害比自觉的杀害更可原谅。我认为这种感觉是完全错误的。事实上，在天堂的景观里，这种以生命的代价来追求自己利益的麻木和漠不关心，尽管没有明确地出于罪恶的目的，也是一种比不受约束的情感中最野蛮的越轨要更可憎、更绝望的精神状态。在最后的情况下，个性里可能会混合着一些好的和想要弥补的元素，但是在其他情况下，这种元素还很少甚至没有。在愤怒中杀了仇敌的人也许有希望，甚至在恐惧中背叛了朋友的人也有希望，但是以被疏忽的血来交易，将财富建立在毫无悔悟的背叛上的人就完全没有希望。

51.尽管可能是这样的，尽管你以公正约束自己以归罪于更大的罪孽，要确定问题只是责任之一，而不是事实。我们现代人匆忙致富的必然结果一定是而且经常是：每年由我们亲手谋杀一定数量的人。我没有时间细说，总体来说，我们造成穷人毁灭的最广泛、最可怕的方式，即奢侈和浪费的方式，不知节制地破坏了原本可以供养几千人的东西。如果你自己在家遵循节约，或者以后你决定这样做，今晚我努力在你面前呈现的才是对你有用的。你会发现，无论何时何地人们尽力匆忙地挣钱，而且尽力避开天命指定的体面收益的唯一来源——劳动，而且无论何时何地他们允许自己奢侈地花费，没有考虑到他们如何误导了别人的劳动，在这两种情况下，实际上他们都确实因为自己的利益或愉悦而导致了一定数目的年度死亡人数。因此，这世上每一个人所面临的选择，简单来说就是他会变成一个劳动者还是一名刺客，也就是他会把手放在犁的扶手上，就是把手放在匕首的柄上。

52.对我来说，今晚试图循着思路讲述铁在脚镣和剑上的伟大政治作用也是徒然的，我只在这两方面略述几句。

53.脚镣。正如犁是辛勤劳动的典型工具一样，脚镣对于一个国家来说是必需的束缚和征服的典型工具。要么从字面上理解是限制为恶者；要么在既定的法律里、从比喻意义上理解，是限制为善者。你必须从比喻和字面的意义上进行选择，据此，你遵循的法律越多，你要经受的处罚就越少。对于一个高尚的国家来说，明智的法律和公正的约束不是锁链而是锁子甲，是力量和防御，尽管同时也是一种职责。请记住，对于人的体面来说，我们需要这种约束，就像需要劳动一样。你每天听到很多愚蠢的人谈论自由，好像它是一件异常体面的事情。事实远非如此，总体上而且在最广泛的意义上，它是一件不体面的事情，而且是低等生物的特性。不管多么伟大或强势的人，都不可能像鱼儿那么自由。总有一些是他必须去做或者决不能做的，而鱼可以做任何想做的事。地球上所有的王国拼起来都没有海洋的一半大，所有已有或将有的铁路和轮子，都没有鱼鳍那样安逸轻便。只要好好地想一想，你会发现人类的可敬之处是束缚而不是自由。而且，即使对于低等动物而言，束缚也是可敬的。蝴蝶要比蜜蜂自由得多，但是你更尊敬蜜蜂，就因为它服从一些适合蜜蜂社会的有序运作法则。在整个世界上，自由和束缚两个抽象的事物之中，束缚总是更可敬的。确实，在这些和所有其他的事情上，你从来无法从抽象中得出判断，因为当高尚地作出选择的时候，自由和束缚就都是好的，而当卑鄙地作出选择时就都是坏的。我重复一下，在这两者中，束缚才是高等生物的特征，而且也能使得低等生物变得更好。从天使长的照拂到昆虫的劳作，从行星的平衡到尘埃的引力，所有生物、所有物质的力量和光荣都存在于他们的服从里，而不是在他们的自由中。太阳没有自由，一片枯叶有很多自由。形成你的尘埃没有自由，但它的自由会到来——连同它的腐朽一起。

54.因此，尽管在英格兰这样说有点奇怪，我还是要公然宣称，一个国家的首要权力在于知道如何引导犁，第二项权力在于知道如何使用脚镣。

55.剑。这是它的第三个权力，知道如何挥舞宝剑而使国家变得完美。这样国家的三个护身符就可以用三个简短的词来表达：劳动、法律和勇气。

56.我们至少拥有最后一个美德，所有不利于我们的宣称是说我们不够尊敬它。不是指尊敬它在服务上的意义，尽管有时候我们甚至连这个也怠慢了，但是我们像对战士的生活和精神始终如一的关注那样去尊敬它。你在最近的病亡报告里已经看到，我们是如何放纵地浪费了他们的生命，而其实只需很少的医护和科学知识就足以防止其发生，但是我们甚至更少关注他们的精神世界，把他们保持在无知和闲散的状态里，只把他们看作是战争的工具。关于维护一支正常军队的争论，经常只谈及在意外战争情况下的权宜之计，而维护一支军队的主要原因之一则是军事系统作为一种教育方式是有优势的。在下等和上等阶层里，最暴躁、最任性的同时也往往是最有天分、最慷慨的年轻人，总是有种将自己看作是士兵的倾向。其他公民能力虚弱、不堪服役的人，在偶然的机会下被诱惑或骗入军队。面对这种暴躁和粗鲁的材质，只有战士的纪律才能带来完整的价值和力量。即使现在，仅仅依靠命令和权威的力量，军队仍是拯救无数人的地方，在其他情况下会变得倦怠和散逸的人们，会因为一种能立刻振奋和引导其精力的服务而恢复高贵的生命。除此以外军事教育还能做什么，这点只有在你把它真正变成教育体制的时候才会发现。我们没有借口听任我们的士兵停留在如今无知而缺乏修养的水平上，因为我们常常发现，官员和士兵里最文雅和见多识广的，恰恰也是最英勇的。在今天的政治局势下，或者我相信在任何与之关联的、在这个世界上很多年后会变成可能的情形下，我们都没有借口缩减我们的军队。

57.我这样说你可能会感到吃惊，也许惊讶于我暗示战争本身可能是正确的，或者是必需的，甚至是高贵的。我不是说所有的战争都是必需的，或者所有的战争都是高贵的。和平与战争都是根据它们的种类和场合来区分高贵和无知的。没有人比我对不名誉战争的恐怖和罪恶有更深刻的感觉了。我亲眼看到它对国家的影响，对于精神和肉体的十足罪恶，我与那些你在和平时期不断听到的高谈阔论的人一样抱有相同的同情和愤慨，但是和平可以通过两种方法找到，一个是犹太勇士基甸的方法，他在俄弗拉建立他的圣坛，命名为“上帝送来和平”，然后寻找他所热爱的和平。因为他是受命去寻找和平，然后和平就以上帝的方式送来了，“在基甸的时代这个国家和平了四十年。”另一个寻找和平的方法是米拿现的方法，他给亚述国王一千个银币，使得“他的手可以和他在一起”，也就是你要么可以赢得和平，要么买得和平。赢得，是凭借对罪恶的抵抗；买得，是对罪恶的妥协。你可以用沉默的良心来买到和平，可以用打破的誓约来买，用谎言来买，用卑下的纵容来买，用残杀的鲜血来买，用俘虏的哭喊来买，用迷失灵魂的沉默来买。越过地球的半球，当你笑着坐在宁静的火炉边，清晨黄昏默念着舒适的祷告，数着你漂亮的新教珠子（是扁平的、金子的，而不是像僧侣的那种圆的、乌木的），不断地喃喃自语，“和平，和平”，但其实并没有和平，对你和所有你不去拯救的人来说，只有囚禁和死亡，而你的世界要比他们的更黑暗。

在这件事情上我不会向你们发表看法，我们都看得太模糊了，然而我们伟大世界的职责是什么？没有人清楚，因此难以对其扩大的阴影进行概括，但是再考虑一下我说过的话，今晚你回到你安静的家时，反思一下，和平不是由你亲手赢得的，而是由很久以前为了你和他们的后代而牺牲了自己生命的人换来的。请记住，这个继承来的和平或其他形式的和平只有通过相同的危险才能得以维护。和平不可能通过借口或协议从命运中赢得；和平不是为了我们任何人而准备的，我们应该通过战胜耻辱或罪恶来赢得，通过战胜压迫的罪恶来赢得，通过战胜腐败来赢得。在未来的很多年里，每个正义国家都必须将剑锋磨利以实现拯救或征服。和平不是通过其他人对苦难的忍耐而赢得，而是通过你自己的奉献而赢得，因而你会接近地球上的铁经历重大变革的时代——人类将他们的剑锤炼成犁，将他们的矛锤炼成修枝刀的时代。此后他们也就不再需要了解战争了。

[1]原注：即《威尼斯之石》。

[2]译者注：尼尼微，西亚古城。意为“上帝面前最伟大的城市”，其址位于伊拉克的北部，底格里斯河的东岸，隔河与今天的摩苏尔城相望。圣经中曾提到尼尼微城名：“耶和华必伸手攻击北方，毁灭亚述，使尼尼微荒芜，干旱如旷野。”

[3]原注：很多人都认为英国不列颠博物馆所藏古希腊大理石雕刻是“完美”的。在最重要的部分它们确实接近完美，但也不过如此。帷幔没有完工，动物的毛发没有完工，整个檐壁的浮雕是粗制滥造的。

[4]原注：最好的艺术或者表现所处时代的事实，或者，如果是表现过去的事实，就以作品所产生的时代的附属品来表达。因而所有表现过去事件的好的艺术，都充满了最明显的时代错误，而且总是应该如此。画家没有必要成为文物研究者。我们不想要他的印象或想象去尊重过去的事物，我们要他清晰的断言来尊重现代的事物。

[5]原注：金

[6]原注：我并不是想要责备那些为了特定表现目的而以大理石来表现树叶的努力。蒙罗先生的晚期作品中某些最微妙的思想就依赖于对这种配件的精致和灵巧的运用。通常情况下，树叶雕刻是好的、令人赞赏的，如果它像在哥特作品里那样通过光与影的安排来呈现叶子的优雅和轻盈——通过底下石头的力量很好地支撑了主体。但是所有以细致为目的的雕刻，试图模仿稀薄和纤弱事物的纯粹细薄，就像很多现代的木雕作品那样，都是劣等的。一两年前，我在意大利看到过一个以鸟巢为主题的大理石雕塑。

The Nature of Gothic

1. IF the reader will look back to the division of our subject which was made in the first chapter of the first volume,[【1】] he will find that we are now about to enter upon the examination of that school of Venetian architecture which forms an intermediate step between the Byzantine and Gothic forms; but which I find may be conveniently considered in its connexion with the latter style. In order that we may discern the tendency of each step of this change, it will be wise in the outset to endeavour to form some general idea of its final result. We know already what the Byzantine architecture is from which the transition was made, but we ought to know something of the Gothic architecture into which it led. I shall endeavour therefore to give the reader in this chapter an idea, at once broad and definite, of the true nature of Gothic architecture, properly so called; not of that of Venice only, but of universal Gothic: for it will be one of the most interesting parts of our subsequent inquiry to find out how far Venetian architecture reached the universal or perfect type of Gothic, and how far it either fell short of it, or assumed foreign and independent forms.

2. The principal difficulty in doing this arises from the fact that every building of the Gothic period differs in some important respect from every other; and many include features which, if they occurred in other buildings, would not be considered Gothic at all; so that all we have to reason upon is merely, if I may be allowed so to express it, a greater or less degree of Gothicness in each building we examine. And it is this Gothicness, — the character which, according as it is found more or less in a building, makes it more or less Gothic, — of which I want to define the nature; and I feel the same kind of difficulty in doing so which would be encountered by any one who undertook to explain, for instance, the nature of Redness, without any actually red thing to point to, but only orange and purple things. Suppose he had only a piece of heather and a dead oak-leaf to do it with. He might say, the colour which is mixed with the yellow in this oak-leaf, and with the blue in this heather, would be red, if you had it separate; but it would be difficult, nevertheless, to make the abstraction perfectly intelligible; and it is so in a far greater degree to make the abstraction of the Gothic character intelligible, because that character itself is made up of many mingled ideas, and can consist only in their union. That is to say, pointed arches do not constitute Gothic, nor vaulted roofs, nor flying buttresses, nor grotesque sculptures; but all or some of these things, and many other things with them, when they come together so as to have life.

3. Observe also, that, in the definition proposed, I shall only endeavour to analyze the idea which I suppose already to exist in the reader's mind. We all have some notion, most of us a very determined one, of the meaning of the term Gothic, but I know that many persons have this idea in their minds without being able to define it: that is to say, understanding generally that Westminster Abbey is Gothic, and St Paul's is not, that Strasburg Cathedral is Gothic, and St Peter's is not, they have, nevertheless, no clear notion of what it is that they recognize in the one or miss in the other, such as would enable them to say how far the work at Westminster or Strasburg is good and pure of its kind; still less to say of any nondescript building, like St James's Palace or Windsor Castle, how much right Gothic element there is in it, and how much wanting. And I believe this inquiry to be a pleasant and profitable one; and that there will be found something more than usually interesting in tracing out this grey, shadowy, many-pinnacled image of the Gothic spirit within us; and discerning what fellowship there is between it and our Northern hearts. And if, at any point of the inquiry, I should interfere with any of the reader's previously formed conceptions, and use the term Gothic in any sense which he would not willingly attach to it, I do not ask him to accept, but only to examine and understand, my interpretation, as necessary to the intelligibility of what follows in the rest of the work.

4. We have, then, the Gothic character submitted to our analysis, just as the rough mineral is submitted to that of the chemist, entangled with many other foreign substances, itself perhaps in no place pure, or ever to be obtained or seen in purity for more than an instant; but nevertheless a thing of definite and separate nature, however inextricable or confused in appearance. Now observe: the chemist defines his mineral by two separate kinds of character; one external, its crystalline form, hardness, lustre, etc.; the other internal, the proportions and nature of its constituent atoms. Exactly in the same manner, we shall find that Gothic architecture has external forms and internal elements. Its elements are certain mental tendencies of the builders, legibly expressed in it; as fancifulness, love of variety, love of richness, and such others. Its external forms are pointed arches, vaulted roofs, etc. And unless both the elements and the forms are there, we have no right to call the style Gothic. It is not enough that it has the Form, if it have not also the power and life. It is not enough that it has the Power, if it have not the form. We must therefore inquire into each of these characters successively; and determine first, what is the Mental Expression, and secondly, what the Material Form of Gothic architecture, properly so called.

5. 1st Mental Power of Expression. What characters, we have to discover, did the Gothic builders love, or instinctively express in their work, as distinguished from all other builders?

6. Let us go back for a moment to our chemistry, and note that, in defining a mineral by its constituent parts, it is not one nor another of them, that can make up the mineral, but the union of all: for instance, it is neither in charcoal, nor in oxygen, nor in lime, that there is the making of chalk, but in the combination of all three in certain measures; they are all found in very different things from chalk, and there is nothing like chalk either in charcoal or in oxygen, but they are nevertheless necessary to its existence.

7. So in the various mental characters which make up the soul of Gothic. It is not one nor another that produces it; but their union in certain measures. Each one of them is found in many other architectures beside Gothic; but Gothic cannot exist where they are not found, or, at least, where their place is not in some way supplied. Only there is this great difference between the composition of the mineral and of the architectural style, that if we withdraw one of its elements from the stone, its form is utterly changed, and its existence as such and such a mineral is destroyed; but if we withdraw one of its mental elements from the Gothic style, it is only a little less Gothic than it was before, and the union of two or three of its elements is enough already to bestow a certain Gothicness of character, which gains in intensity as we add the others, and loses as we again withdraw them.

8. I believe, then, that the characteristic or moral elements of Gothic are the following, placed in the order of their importance:

　　　　　1. Savageness.

　　　　　2. Changefulness.

　　　　　3. Naturalism.

　　　　　4. Grotesqueness.

　　　　　5. Rigidity.

　　　　　6. Redundance.

9. These characters are here expressed as belonging to the building; as belonging to the builder, they would be expressed thus: — 1. Savageness or Rudeness. 2. Love of Change. 3. Love of Nature. 4. Disturbed Imagination. 5. Obstinacy. 6. Generosity. And I repeat, that the withdrawal of any one, or any two, will not at once destroy the Gothic character of a building, but the removal of a majority of them will. I shall proceed to examine them in their order.

10. SAVAGENESS. I am not sure when the word 'Gothic' was first generically applied to the architecture of the North; but I presume that, whatever the date of its original usage, it was intended to imply reproach, and express the barbaric character of the nations among whom that architecture arose. It never implied that they were literally of Gothic lineage, far less that their architecture had been originally invented by the Goths themselves; but it did imply that they and their buildings together exhibited a degree of sternness and rudeness, which, in contradistinction to the character of Southern and Eastern nations, appeared like a perpetual reflection of the contrast between the Goth and the Roman in their first encounter. And when that fallen Roman, in the utmost impotence of his luxury, and insolence of his guilt, became the model for the imitation of civilized Europe, at the close of the so-called Dark ages, the word Gothic became a term of unmitigated contempt, not unmixed with aversion. From that contempt, by the exertion of the antiquaries and architects of this century, Gothic architecture has been sufficiently vindicated; and perhaps some among us, in our admiration of the magnificent science of its structure, and sacredness of its expression, might desire that the term of ancient reproach should be withdrawn, and some other, of more apparent honourableness, adopted in its place. There is no chance, as there is no need, of such a substitution. As far as the epithet was used scornfully, it was used falsely; but there is no reproach in the word, rightly understood; on the contrary, there is a profound truth, which the instinct of mankind almost unconsciously recognizes. It is true, greatly and deeply true, that the architecture of the North is rude and wild; but it is not true, that, for this reason, we are to condemn it, or despise. Far otherwise: I believe it is in this very character that it deserves our profoundest reverence.

11. The charts of the world which have been drawn up by modern science have thrown into a narrow space the expression of a vast amount of knowledge, but I have never yet seen any one pictorial enough to enable the spectator to imagine the kind of contrast in physical character which exists between Northern and Southern countries. We know the differences in detail, but we have not that broad glance and grasp which would enable us to feel them in their fulness. We know that gentians grow on the Alps, and olives on the Apennines; but we do not enough conceive for ourselves that variegated mosaic of the world's surface which a bird sees in its migration, that difference between the district of the gentian and of the olive which the stork and the swallow see far off, as they lean upon the sirocco wind. Let us, for a moment, try to raise ourselves even above the level of their flight, and imagine the Mediterranean lying beneath us like an irregular lake, and all its ancient promontories sleeping in the sun: here and there an angry spot of thunder, a grey stain of storm, moving upon the burning field; and here and there a fixed wreath of white volcano smoke, surrounded by its circle of ashes; but for the most part a great peacefulness of light, Syria and Greece, Italy and Spain, laid like pieces of a golden pavement into the sea-blue, chased, as we stoop nearer to them, with bossy beaten work of mountain chains, and glowing softly with terraced gardens, and flowers heavy with frankincense, mixed among masses of laurel, and orange, and plumy palm, that abate with their grey-green shadows the burning of the marble rocks, and of the ledges of porphyry sloping under lucent sand. Then let us pass farther towards the north, until we see the orient colours change gradually into a vast belt of rainy green, where the pastures of Switzerland, and poplar valleys of France, and dark forests of the Danube and Carpathians stretch from the mouths of the Loire to those of the Volga, seen through clefts in grey swirls of rain-cloud and flaky veils of the mist of the brooks, spreading low along the pasture lands: and then, farther north still, to see the earth heave into mighty masses of leaden rock and heathy moor, bordering with a broad waste of gloomy purple that belt of field and wood, and splintering into irregular and grisly islands amidst the northern seas, beaten by storm, and chilled by ice-drift, and tormented by furious pulses of contending tide, until the roots of the last forests fail from among the hill ravines, and the hunger of the north wind bites their peaks into barrenness; and, at last, the wall of ice, durable like iron, sets, deathlike, its white teeth against us out of the polar twilight. And, having once traversed in thought this gradation of the zoned iris of the earth in all its material vastness, let us go down nearer to it, and watch the parallel change in the belt of animal life; the multitudes of swift and brilliant creatures that glance in the air and sea, or tread the sands of the southern zone; striped zebras and spotted leopards, glistening serpents, and birds arrayed in purple and scarlet. Let us contrast their delicacy and brilliancy of colour, and swiftness of motion, with the frost-cramped strength, and shaggy covering, and dusky plumage of the northern tribes; contrast the Arabian horse with the Shetland, the tiger and leopard with the wolf and bear, the antelope with the elk, the bird of paradise with the osprey; and then, submissively acknowledging the great laws by which the earth and all that it bears are ruled throughout their being, let us not condemn, but rejoice in the expression by man of his own rest in the statutes of the lands that gave him birth. Let us watch him with reverence as he sets side by side the burning gems, and smooths with soft sculpture the jasper pillars, that are to reflect a ceaseless sunshine, and rise into a cloudless sky: but not with less reverence let us stand by him, when, with rough strength and hurried stroke, he smites an uncouth animation out of the rocks which he has torn from among the moss of the moorland, and heaves into the darkened air the pile of iron buttress and rugged wall, instinct with work of an imagination as wild and wayward as the northern sea; creatures of ungainly shape and rigid limb, but full of wolfish life; fierce as the winds that beat, and changeful as the clouds that shade them.

12. There is, I repeat, no degradation, no reproach in this, but all dignity and honourableness: and we should err grievously in refusing either to recognize as an essential character of the existing architecture of the North, or to admit as a desirable character in that which it yet may be, this wildness of thought, and roughness of work; this look of mountain brotherhood between the cathedral and the Alp; this magnificence of sturdy power, put forth only the more energetically because the fine finger-touch was chilled away by the frosty wind, and the eye dimmed by the moor-mist, or blinded by the hail; this outspeaking of the strong spirit of men who may not gather redundant fruitage from the earth, nor bask in dreamy benignity of sunshine, but must break the rock for bread, and cleave the forest for fire, and show, even in what they did for their delight, some of the hard habits of the arm and heart that grew on them as they swung the axe or pressed the plough.

13. If, however, the savageness of Gothic architecture, merely as an expression of its origin among Northern nations, may be considered, in some sort, a noble character, it possesses a higher nobility still, when considered as an index, not of climate, but of religious principle.

14. In the 13th and 14th paragraphs of Chapter XXI of the first volume of this work, it was noticed that the systems of architectural ornament, properly so called, might be divided into three: — 1. Servile ornament, in which the execution or power of the inferior workman is entirely subjected to the intellect of the higher; — 2. Constitutional ornament, in which the executive inferior power is, to a certain point, emancipated and independent, having a will of its own, yet confessing its inferiority and rendering obedience to higher powers; — and 3. Revolutionary ornament, in which no executive inferiority is admitted at all. I must here explain the nature of these divisions at somewhat greater length.

15. Of Servile ornament, the principal schools are the Greek, Ninevite, and Egyptian; but their servility is of different kinds. The Greek master workman was far advanced in knowledge and power above the Assyrian or Egyptian. Neither he nor those for whom he worked could endure the appearance of imperfection in anything; and, therefore, what ornament he appointed to be done by those beneath him was composed of mere geometrical forms, — balls, ridges, and perfectly symmetrical foliage, — which could be executed with absolute precision by line and rule, and were as perfect in their way, when completed, as his own figure sculpture. The Assyrian and Egyptian, on the contrary, less cognisant of accurate form in anything, were content to allow their figure sculpture to be executed by inferior workmen, but lowered the method of its treatment to a standard which every workman could reach, and then trained him by discipline so rigid, that there was no chance of his falling beneath the standard appointed. The Greek gave to the lower workman no subject which he could not perfectly execute. The Assyrian gave him subjects which he could only execute imperfectly, but fixed a legal standard for his imperfection. The workman was, in both systems, a slave.

16. But in the mediæval, or especially Christian, system of ornament, this slavery is done away with altogether; Christianity having recognized, in small things as well as great, the individual value of every soul. But it not only recognizes its value; it confesses its imperfection, in only bestowing dignity upon the acknowledgment of unworthiness. That admission of lost power and fallen nature, which the Greek or Ninevite felt to be intensely painful, and, as far as might be, altogether refused, the Christian makes daily and hourly, contemplating the fact of it without fear, as tending, in the end, to God's greater glory. Therefore, to every spirit which Christianity summons to her service, her exhortation is: Do what you can, and confess frankly what you are unable to do; neither let your effort be shortened for fear of failure, nor your confession silenced for fear of shame. And it is, perhaps, the principal admirableness of the Gothic schools of architecture, that they thus receive the results of the labour of inferior minds; and out of fragments full of imperfection, and betraying that imperfection in every touch, indulgently raise up a stately and unaccusable whole.

17. But the modern English mind has this much in common with that of the Greek, that it intensely desires, in all things, the utmost completion or perfection compatible with their nature. This is a noble character in the abstract, but becomes ignoble when it causes us to forget the relative dignities of that nature itself, and to prefer the perfectness of the lower nature to the imperfection of the higher; not considering that as, judged by such a rule, all the brute animals would be preferable to man, because more perfect in their functions and kind, and yet are always held inferior to him, so also in the works of man, those which are more perfect in their kind are always inferior to those which are, in their nature, liable to more faults and shortcomings. For the finer the nature, the more flaws it will show through the clearness of it; and it is a law of this universe, that the best things shall be seldomest seen in their best form. The wild grass grows well and strongly, one year with another; but the wheat is, according to the greater nobleness of its nature, liable to the bitterer blight. And therefore, while in all things that we see or do, we are to desire perfection, and strive for it, we are nevertheless not to set the meaner thing, in its narrow accomplishment, above the nobler thing, in its mighty progress; not to esteem smooth minuteness above shattered majesty; not to prefer mean victory to honourable defeat; not to lower the level of our aim, that we may the more surely enjoy the complacency of success. But, above all, in our dealings with the souls of other men, we are to take care how we check, by severe requirement or narrow caution, efforts which might otherwise lead to a noble issue; and, still more, how we withhold our admiration from great excellencies, because they are mingled with rough faults. Now, in the make and nature of every man, however rude or simple, whom we employ in manual labour, there are some powers for better things; some tardy imagination, torpid capacity of emotion, tottering steps of thought, there are, even at the worst; and in most cases it is all our own fault that they are tardy or torpid. But they cannot be strengthened, unless we are content to take them in their feebleness, and unless we prize and honour them in their imperfection above the best and most perfect manual skill. And this is what we have to do with all our labourers; to look for the thoughtful part of them, and get that out of them, whatever we lose for it, whatever faults and errors we are obliged to take with it. For the best that is in them cannot manifest itself, but in company with much error. Understand this clearly: You can teach a man to draw a straight line, and to cut one; to strike a curved line, and to carve it; and to copy and carve any number of given lines or forms, with admirable speed and perfect precision; and you find his work perfect of its kind: but if you ask him to think about any of those forms, to consider if he cannot find any better in his own head, he stops; his execution becomes hesitating; he thinks, and ten to one he thinks wrong; ten to one he makes a mistake in the first touch he gives to his work as a thinking being. But you have made a man of him for all that. He was only a machine before, an animated tool.

18. And observe, you are put to stern choice in this matter. You must either make a tool of the creature, or a man of him. You cannot make both. Men were not intended to work with the accuracy of tools, to be precise and perfect in all their actions. If you will have that precision out of them, and make their fingers measure degrees like cog-wheels, and their arms strike curves like compasses, you must unhumanize them. All the energy of their spirits must be given to make cogs and compasses of themselves. All their attention and strength must go to the accomplishment of the mean act. The eye of the soul must be bent upon the finger-point, and the soul's force must fill all the invisible nerves that guide it, ten hours a day, that it may not err from its steely precision, and so soul and sight be worn away, and the whole human being be lost at last — a heap of sawdust, so far as its intellectual work in this world is concerned: saved only by its Heart, which cannot go into the form of cogs and compasses, but expands, after the ten hours are over, into fireside humanity. On the other hand, if you will make a man of the working creature, you cannot make a tool. Let him but begin to imagine, to think, to try to do anything worth doing; and the engine-turned precision is lost at once. Out come all his roughness, all his dulness, all his incapability; shame upon shame, failure upon failure, pause after pause: but out comes the whole majesty of him also; and we know the height of it only when we see the clouds settling upon him. And, whether the clouds be bright or dark, there will be transfiguration behind and within them.

19. And now, reader, look round this English room of yours, about which you have been proud so often, because the work of it was so good and strong, and the ornaments of it so finished. Examine again all those accurate mouldings, and perfect polishings, and unerring adjustments of the seasoned wood and tempered steel. Many a time you have exulted over them, and thought how great England was, because her slightest work was done so thoroughly. Alas! if read rightly, these perfectnesses are signs of a slavery in our England a thousand times more bitter and more degrading than that of the scourged African, or helot Greek. Men may be beaten, chained, tormented, yoked like cattle, slaughtered like summer flies, and yet remain in one sense, and the best sense, free. But to smother their souls with them, to blight and hew into rotting pollards the suckling branches of their human intelligence, to make the flesh and skin which, after the worm's work on it, is to see God, into leathern thongs to yoke machinery with, — this is to be slave-masters indeed; and there might be more freedom in England, though her feudal lords' lightest words were worth men's lives, and though the blood of the vexed husbandman dropped in the furrows of her fields, than there is while the animation of her multitudes is sent like fuel to feed the factory smoke, and the strength of them is given daily to be wasted into the fineness of a web, or racked into the exactness of a line.

20. And, on the other hand, go forth again to gaze upon the old cathedral front, where you have smiled so often at the fantastic ignorance of the old sculptors: examine once more those ugly goblins, and formless monsters, and stern statues, anatomiless and rigid; but do not mock at them, for they are signs of the life and liberty of every workman who struck the stone; a freedom of thought, and rank in scale of being, such as no laws, no charters, no charities can secure; but which it must be the first aim of all Europe at this day to regain for her children.

21. Let me not be thought to speak wildly or extravagantly. It is verily this degradation of the operative into a machine, which, more than any other evil of the times, is leading the mass of the nations everywhere into vain, incoherent, destructive struggling for a freedom of which they cannot explain the nature to themselves. Their universal outcry against wealth, and against nobility, is not forced from them either by the pressure of famine, or the sting of mortified pride. These do much, and have done much in all ages; but the foundations of society were never yet shaken as they are at this day. It is not that men are ill fed, but that they have no pleasure in the work by which they make their bread, and therefore look to wealth as the only means of pleasure. It is not that men are pained by the scorn of the upper classes, but they cannot endure their own; for they feel that the kind of labour to which they are condemned is verily a degrading one, and makes them less than men. Never had the upper classes so much sympathy with the lower, or charity for them, as they have at this day, and yet never were they so much hated by them: for, of old, the separation between the noble and the poor was merely a wall built by law; now it is a veritable difference in level of standing, a precipice between upper and lower grounds in the field of humanity, and there is pestilential air at the bottom of it. I know not if a day is ever to come when the nature of right freedom will be understood, and when men will see that to obey another man, to labour for him, yield reverence to him or to his place, is not slavery. It is often the best kind of liberty, — liberty from care. The man who says to one, Go, and he goeth, and to another, Come, and he cometh, has, in most cases, more sense of restraint and difficulty than the man who obeys him. The movements of the one are hindered by the burden on his shoulder; of the other by the bridle on his lips: there is no way by which the burden may be lightened; but we need not suffer from the bridle if we do not champ at it. To yield reverence to another, to hold ourselves and our likes at his disposal, is not slavery; often it is the noblest state in which a man can live in this world. There is, indeed, a reverence which is servile, that is to say, irrational or selfish: but there is also noble reverence, that is to say, reasonable and loving; and a man is never so noble as when he is reverent in this kind; nay, even if the feeling pass the bounds of mere reason, so that it be loving, a man is raised by it. Which had, in reality, most of the serf nature in him, — the Irish peasant who was lying in wait yesterday for his landlord, with his musket muzzle thrust through the ragged hedge; or that old mountain servant, who 200 years ago, at Inverkeithing, gave up his own life and the lives of his seven sons for his chief? — as each fell, calling forth his brother to the death, 'Another for Hector!' And therefore, in all ages and all countries, reverence has been paid and sacrifice made by men to each other, not only without complaint, but rejoicingly; and famine, and peril, and sword, and all evil, and all shame, have been borne willingly in the causes of masters and kings; for all these gifts of the heart ennobled the men who gave, not less than the men who received them, and nature prompted, and God rewarded the sacrifice. But to feel their souls withering within them, unthanked, to find their whole being sunk into an unrecognized abyss, to be counted off into a heap of mechanism numbered with its wheels, and weighed with its hammer strokes — this, nature bade not, — this, God blesses not, — this, humanity for no long time is able to endure.

22. We have much studied and much perfected, of late, the great civilized invention of the division of labour; only we give it a false name. It is not, truly speaking, the labour that is divided; but the men: — Divided into mere segments of men — broken into small fragments and crumbs of life; so that all the little piece of intelligence that is left in a man is not enough to make a pin, or a nail, but exhausts itself in making the point of a pin or the head of a nail. Now it is a good and desirable thing, truly, to make many pins in a day; but if we could only see with what crystal sand their points were polished, — sand of human soul, much to be magnified before it can be discerned for what it is — we should think there might be some loss in it also. And the great cry that rises from all our manufacturing cities, louder than their furnace blast, is all in very deed for this, — that we manufacture everything there except men; we blanch cotton, and strengthen steel, and refine sugar, and shape pottery; but to brighten, to strengthen, to refine, or to form a single living spirit, never enters into our estimate of advantages. And all the evil to which that cry is urging our myriads can be met only in one way: not by teaching nor preaching, for to teach them is but to show them their misery, and to preach to them, if we do nothing more than preach, is to mock at it. It can be met only by a right understanding, on the part of all classes, of what kinds of labour are good for men, raising them, and making them happy; by a determined sacrifice of such convenience, or beauty, or cheapness as is to be got only by the degradation of the workman; and by equally determined demand for the products and results of healthy and ennobling labour.

23. And how, it will be asked, are these products to be recognized, and this demand to be regulated? Easily: by the observance of three broad and simple rules:

24.1. Never encourage the manufacture of any article not absolutely necessary, in the production of which Invention has no share.

25.2. Never demand an exact finish for its own sake, but only for some practical or noble end.

26.3. Never encourage imitation or copying of any kind, except for the sake of preserving records of great works.

27. The second of these principles is the only one which directly rises out of the consideration of our immediate subject; but I shall briefly explain the meaning and extent of the first also, reserving the enforcement of the third for another place.

28.1. Never encourage the manufacture of anything not necessary, in the production of which invention has no share.

29. For instance. Glass beads are utterly unnecessary, and there is no design or thought employed in their manufacture. They are formed by first drawing out the glass into rods; these rods are chopped up into fragments of the size of beads by the human hand, and the fragments are then rounded in the furnace. The men who chop up the rods sit at their work all day, their hands vibrating with a perpetual and exquisitely timed palsy, and the beads dropping beneath their vibration like hail. Neither they, nor the men who draw out the rods or fuse the fragments, have the smallest occasion for the use of any single human faculty; and every young lady, therefore, who buys glass beads is engaged in the slave-trade, and in a much more cruel one than that which we have so long been endeavouring to put down.

30. But glass cups and vessels may become the subjects of exquisite invention; and if in buying these we pay for the invention, that is to say, for the beautiful form, or colour, or engraving, and not for mere finish of execution, we are doing good to humanity.

31. So, again, the cutting of precious stones, in all ordinary cases, requires little exertion of any mental faculty; some tact and judgment in avoiding flaws, and so on, but nothing to bring out the whole mind. Every person who wears cut jewels merely for the sake of their value is, therefore, a slave-driver.

32. But the working of the goldsmith, and the various designing of grouped jewellery and enamel-work, may become the subject of the most noble human intelligence. Therefore, money spent in the purchase of well-designed plate, of precious engraved vases, cameos, or enamels, does good to humanity; and, in work of this kind, jewels may be employed to heighten its splendour; and their cutting is then a price paid for the attainment of a noble end, and thus perfectly allowable.

33. I shall perhaps press this law farther elsewhere, but our immediate concern is chiefly with the second, namely, never to demand an exact finish, when it does not lead to a noble end. For observe, I have only dwelt upon the rudeness of Gothic, or any other kind of imperfectness, as admirable, where it was impossible to get design or thought without it. If you are to have the thought of a rough and untaught man, you must have it in a rough and untaught way; but from an educated man, who can without effort express his thoughts in an educated way, take the graceful expression, and be thankful. Only get the thought, and do not silence the peasant because he cannot speak good grammar, or until you have taught him his grammar. Grammar and refinement are good things, both, only be sure of the better thing first. And thus in art, delicate finish is desirable from the greatest masters, and is always given by them. In some places Michael Angelo, Leonardo, Phidias, Perugino, Turner, all finished with the most exquisite care; and the finish they give always leads to the fuller accomplishment of their noble purposes. But lower men than these cannot finish, for it requires consummate knowledge to finish consummately, and then we must take their thoughts as they are able to give them. So the rule is simple: Always look for invention first, and after that, for such execution as will help the invention, and as the inventor is capable of without painful effort, and no more. Above all, demand no refinement of execution where there is no thought, for that is slaves' work, unredeemed. Rather choose rough work than smooth work, so only that the practical purpose be answered, and never imagine there is reason to be proud of anything that may be accomplished by patience and sand-paper.

34. I shall only give one example, which however will show the reader what I mean, from the manufacture already alluded to, that of glass. Our modern glass is exquisitely clear in its substance, true in its form, accurate in its cutting. We are proud of this. We ought to be ashamed of it. The old Venice glass was muddy, inaccurate in all its forms, and clumsily cut, if at all. And the old Venetian was justly proud of it. For there is this difference between the English and Venetian workman, that the former thinks only of accurately matching his patterns, and getting his curves perfectly true and his edges perfectly sharp, and becomes a mere machine for rounding curves and sharpening edges; while the old Venetian cared not a whit whether his edges were sharp or not, but he invented a new design for every glass that he made, and never moulded a handle or a lip without a new fancy in it. And therefore, though some Venetian glass is ugly and clumsy enough when made by clumsy and uninventive workmen, other Venetian glass is so lovely in its forms that no price is too great for it; and we never see the same form in it twice. Now you cannot have the finish and the varied form too. If the workman is thinking about his edges, he cannot be thinking of his design; if of his design, he cannot think of his edges. Choose whether you will pay for the lovely form or the perfect finish, and choose at the same moment whether you will make the worker a man or a grindstone.

35. Nay, but the reader interrupts me, — 'If the workman can design beautifully, I would not have him kept at the furnace. Let him be taken away and made a gentleman, and have a studio, and design his glass there, and I will have it blown and cut for him by common workmen, and so I will have my design and my finish too.'

36. All ideas of this kind are founded upon two mistaken suppositions: the first, that one man's thoughts can be, or ought to be, executed by another man's hands; the second, that manual labour is a degradation, when it is governed by intellect.

37. On a large scale, and in work determinable by line and rule, it is indeed both possible and necessary that the thoughts of one man should be carried out by the labour of others; in this sense I have already defined the best architecture to be the expression of the mind of manhood by the hands of childhood. But on a smaller scale, and in a design which cannot be mathematically defined, one man's thoughts can never be expressed by another: and the difference between the spirit of touch of the man who is inventing, and of the man who is obeying directions, is often all the difference between a great and a common work of art. How wide the separation is between original and second-hand execution, I shall endeavour to show elsewhere; it is not so much to our purpose here as to mark the other and more fatal error of despising manual labour when governed by intellect; for it is no less fatal an error to despise it when thus regulated by intellect, than to value it for its own sake. We are always in these days endeavouring to separate the two; we want one man to be always thinking, and another to be always working, and we call one a gentleman, and the other an operative; whereas the workman ought often to be thinking, and the thinker often to be working, and both should be gentlemen, in the best sense. As it is, we make both ungentle, the one envying, the other despising, his brother; and the mass of society is made up of morbid thinkers, and miserable workers. Now it is only by labour that thought can be made healthy, and only by thought that labour can be made happy, and the two cannot be separated with impunity. It would be well if all of us were good handicraftsmen in some kind, and the dishonour of manual labour done away with altogether; so that though there should still be a trenchant distinction of race between nobles and commoners, there should not, among the latter, be a trenchant distinction of employment, as between idle and working men, or between men of liberal and illiberal professions. All professions should be liberal, and there should be less pride felt in peculiarity of employment, and more in excellence of achievement. And yet more, in each several profession, no master should be too proud to do its hardest work. The painter should grind his own colours; the architect work in the mason's yard with his men; the master-manufacturer be himself a more skilful operative than any man in his mills; and the distinction between one man and another be only in experience and skill, and the authority and wealth which these must naturally and justly obtain.

38. I should be led far from the matter in hand, if I were to pursue this interesting subject. Enough, I trust, has been said to show the reader that the rudeness or imperfection which at first rendered the term 'Gothic' one of reproach is indeed, when rightly understood, one of the most noble characters of Christian architecture, and not only a noble but an essential one. It seems a fantastic paradox, but it is nevertheless a most important truth, that no architecture can be truly noble which is not imperfect. And this is easily demonstrable. For since the architect, whom we will suppose capable of doing all in perfection, cannot execute the whole with his own hands, he must either make slaves of his workmen in the old Greek, and present English fashion, and level his work to a slave's capacities, which is to degrade it; or else he must take his workmen as he finds them, and let them show their weaknesses together with their strength, which will involve the Gothic imperfection, but render the whole work as noble as the intellect of the age can make it.

39. But the principle may be stated more broadly still. I have confined the illustration of it to architecture, but I must not leave it as if true of architecture only. Hitherto I have used the words imperfect and perfect merely to distinguish between work grossly unskilful, and work executed with average precision and science; and I have been pleading that any degree of unskilfulness should be admitted, so only that the labourer's mind had room for expression. But, accurately speaking, no good work whatever can be perfect, and the demand for perfection is always a sign of a misunderstanding of the ends of art.

40. This is for two reasons, both based on everlasting laws. The first, that no great man ever stops working till he has reached his point of failure: that is to say, his mind is always far in advance of his powers of execution, and the latter will now and then give way in trying to follow it; besides that he will always give to the inferior portions of his work only such inferior attention as they require; and according to his greatness he becomes so accustomed to the feeling of dissatisfaction with the best he can do, that in moments of lassitude or anger with himself he will not care though the beholder be dissatisfied also. I believe there has only been one man who would not acknowledge this necessity, and strove always to reach perfection, Leonardo; the end of his vain effort being merely that he would take ten years to a picture and leave it unfinished. And therefore, if we are to have great men working at all, or less men doing their best, the work will be imperfect, however beautiful. Of human work none but what is bad can be perfect, in its own bad way.[【2】]

41. The second reason is, that imperfection is in some sort essential to all that we know of life. It is the sign of life in a mortal body, that is to say, of a state of progress and change. Nothing that lives is, or can be, rigidly perfect; part of it is decaying, part nascent. The foxglove blossom, — a third part bud, a third part past, a third part in full bloom, — is a type of the life of this world. And in all things that live there are certain irregularities and deficiencies which are not only signs of life, but sources of beauty. No human face is exactly the same in its lines on each side, no leaf perfect in its lobes, no branch in its symmetry. All admit irregularity as they imply change; and to banish imperfection is to destroy expression, to check exertion, to paralyze vitality. All things are literally better, lovelier, and more beloved for the imperfections which have been divinely appointed, that the law of human life may be Effort, and the law of human judgment, Mercy.

42. Accept this then for a universal law, that neither architecture nor any other noble work of man can be good unless it be imperfect; and let us be prepared for the otherwise strange fact, which we shall discern clearly as we approach the period of the Renaissance, that the first cause of the fall of the arts of Europe was a relentless requirement of perfection, incapable alike either of being silenced by veneration for greatness, or softened into forgiveness of simplicity.

43. Thus far then of the Rudeness or Savageness, which is the first mental element of Gothic architecture. It is an element in many other healthy architectures also, as the Byzantine and Romanesque; but true Gothic cannot exist without it.

44. The second mental element above named was CHANGEFULNESS, or Variety.

45. I have already enforced the allowing independent operation to the inferior workman, simply as a duty to him, and as ennobling the architecture by rendering it more Christian. We have now to consider what reward we obtain for the performance of this duty, namely, the perpetual variety of every feature of the building.

46. Wherever the workman is utterly enslaved, the parts of the building must of course be absolutely like each other; for the perfection of his execution can only be reached by exercising him in doing one thing, and giving him nothing else to do. The degree in which the workman is degraded may be thus known at a glance, by observing whether the several parts of the building are similar or not; and if, as in Greek work, all the capitals are alike, and all the mouldings unvaried, then the degradation is complete; if, as in Egyptian or Ninevite work, though the manner of executing certain figures is always the same, the order of design is perpetually varied, the degradation is less total; if, as in Gothic work, there is perpetual change both in design and execution, the workman must have been altogether set free.

47. How much the beholder gains from the liberty of the labourer may perhaps be questioned in England, where one of the strongest instincts in nearly every mind is that Love of Order which makes us desire that our house windows should pair like our carriage horses, and allows us to yield our faith unhesitatingly to architectural theories which fix a form for everything, and forbid variation from it. I would not impeach love of order: it is one of the most useful elements of the English mind; it helps us in our commerce and in all purely practical matters; and it is in many cases one of the foundation stones of morality. Only do not let us suppose that love of order is love of art. It is true that order, in its highest sense, is one of the necessities of art, just as time is a necessity of music; but love of order has no more to do with our right enjoyment of architecture or painting, than love of punctuality with the appreciation of an opera. Experience, I fear, teaches us that accurate and methodical habits in daily life are seldom characteristic of those who either quickly perceive, or richly possess, the creative powers of art; there is, however, nothing inconsistent between the two instincts, and nothing to hinder us from retaining our business habits, and yet fully allowing and enjoying the noblest gifts of Invention. We already do so, in every other branch of art except architecture, and we only do not so there because we have been taught that it would be wrong. Our architects gravely inform us that, as there are four rules of arithmetic, there are five orders of architecture; we, in our simplicity, think that this sounds consistent, and believe them. They inform us also that there is one proper form for Corinthian capitals, another for Doric, and another for Ionic. We, considering that there is also a proper form for the letters A, B, and C, think that this also sounds consistent, and accept the proposition. Understanding, therefore, that one form of the said capitals is proper, and no other, and having a conscientious horror of all impropriety, we allow the architect to provide us with the said capitals, of the proper form, in such and such a quantity, and in all other points to take care that the legal forms are observed; which having done, we rest in forced confidence that we are well housed.

48. But our higher instincts are not deceived. We take no pleasure in the building provided for us, resembling that which we take in a new book or a new picture. We may be proud of its size, complacent in its correctness, and happy in its convenience. We may take the same pleasure in its symmetry and workmanship as in a well-ordered room, or a skilful piece of manufacture. And this we suppose to be all the pleasure that architecture was ever intended to give us. The idea of reading a building as we would read Milton or Dante, and getting the same kind of delight out of the stones as out of the stanzas, never enters our mind for a moment. And for good reason; — There is indeed rhythm in the verses, quite as strict as the symmetries or rhythm of the architecture, and a thousand times more beautiful, but there is something else than rhythm. The verses were neither made to order, nor to match, as the capitals were; and we have therefore a kind of pleasure in them other than a sense of propriety. But it requires a strong effort of common sense to shake ourselves quit of all that we have been taught for the last two centuries, and wake to the perception of a truth just as simple and certain as it is new: that great art, whether expressing itself in words, colours, or stones, does not say the same thing over and over again; that the merit of architectural, as of every other art, consists in its saying new and different things; that to repeat itself is no more a characteristic of genius in marble than it is of genius in print; and that we may, without offending any laws of good taste, require of an architect, as we do of a novelist, that he should be not only correct, but entertaining.

49. Yet all this is true, and self-evident; only hidden from us, as many other self-evident things are, by false teaching. Nothing is a great work of art, for the production of which either rules or models can be given. Exactly so far as architecture works on known rules, and from given models, it is not an art, but a manufacture; and it is, of the two procedures, rather less rational (because more easy) to copy capitals or mouldings from Phidias, and call ourselves architects, than to copy heads and hands from Titian, and call ourselves painters.

50. Let us then understand at once that change or variety is as much a necessity to the human heart and brain in buildings as in books; that there is no merit, though there is some occasional use, in monotony; and that we must no more expect to derive either pleasure or profit from an architecture whose ornaments are of one pattern, and whose pillars are of one proportion, than we should out of a universe in which the clouds were all of one shape, and the trees all of one size.

51. And this we confess in deeds, though not in words. All the pleasure which the people of the nineteenth century take in art, is in pictures, sculpture, minor objects of virtù, or mediæval architecture, which we enjoy under the term picturesque: no pleasure is taken anywhere in modern buildings, and we find all men of true feeling delighting to escape out of modern cities into natural scenery: hence, as I shall hereafter show, that peculiar love of landscape, which is characteristic of the age. It would be well, if in all other matters, we were as ready to put up with what we dislike, for the sake of compliance with established law, as we are in architecture.

52. How so debased a law ever came to be established, we shall see when we come to describe the Renaissance schools; here we have only to note, as a second most essential element of the Gothic spirit, that it broke through that law wherever it found it in existence; it not only dared, but delighted in, the infringement of every servile principle; and invented a series of forms of which the merit was, not merely that they were new, but that they were capable of perpetual novelty. The pointed arch was not merely a bold variation from the round, but it admitted of millions of variations in itself; for the proportions of a pointed arch are changeable to infinity, while a circular arch is always the same. The grouped shaft was not merely a bold variation from the single one, but it admitted of millions of variations in its grouping, and in the proportions resultant from its grouping. The introduction of tracery was not only a startling change in the treatment of window lights, but admitted endless changes in the interlacement of the tracery bars themselves. So that, while in all living Christian architecture the love of variety exists, the Gothic schools exhibited that love in culminating energy; and their influence, wherever it extended itself, may be sooner and farther traced by this character than by any other; the tendency to the adoption of Gothic types being always first shown by greater irregularity, and richer variation in the forms of architecture it is about to supersede, long before the appearance of the pointed arch or of any other recognizable outward sign of the Gothic mind.

53. We must, however, herein note carefully what distinction there is between a healthy and a diseased love of change; for as it was in healthy love of change that the Gothic architecture rose, it was partly in consequence of diseased love of change that it was destroyed. In order to understand this clearly, it will be necessary to consider the different ways in which change and monotony are presented to us in nature; both having their use, like darkness and light, and the one incapable of being enjoyed without the other: change being most delightful after some prolongation of monotony, as light appears most brilliant after the eyes have been for some time closed.

54. I believe that the true relations of monotony and change may be most simply understood by observing them in music. We may therein notice first, that there is a sublimity and majesty in monotony, which there is not in rapid or frequent variation. This is true throughout all nature. The greater part of the sublimity of the sea depends on its monotony; so also that of desolate moor and mountain scenery; and especially the sublimity of motion, as in the quiet, unchanged fall and rise of an engine beam. So also there is sublimity in darkness which there is not in light.

55. Again, monotony after a certain time, or beyond a certain degree, becomes either uninteresting or intolerable, and the musician is obliged to break it in one of two ways: either while the air or passage is perpetually repeated, its notes are variously enriched and harmonized; or else, after a certain number of repeated passages, an entirely new passage is introduced, which is more or less delightful according to the length of the previous monotony. Nature, of course, uses both these kinds of variation perpetually. The sea-waves, resembling each other in general mass, but none like its brother in minor divisions and curves, are a monotony of the first kind; the great plain, broken by an emergent rock or clump of trees, is a monotony of the second.

56. Farther: in order to the enjoyment of the change in either case, a certain degree of patience is required from the hearer or observer. In the first case, he must be satisfied to endure with patience the recurrence of the great masses of sound or form, and to seek for entertainment in a careful watchfulness of the minor details. In the second case, he must bear patiently the infliction of the monotony for some moments, in order to feel the full refreshment of the change. This is true even of the shortest musical passage in which the element of monotony is employed. In cases of more majestic monotony, the patience required is so considerable that it becomes a kind of pain, — a price paid for the future pleasure.

57. Again: the talent of the composer is not in the monotony, but in the changes: he may show feeling and taste by his use of monotony in certain places or degrees; that is to say, by his various employment of it; but it is always in the new arrangement or invention that his intellect is shown, and not in the monotony which relieves it.

58. Lastly: if the pleasure of change be too often repeated, it ceases to be delightful, for then change itself becomes monotonous, and we are driven to seek delight in extreme and fantastic degrees of it. This is the diseased love of change of which we have above spoken.

59. From these facts we may gather generally that monotony is, and ought to be, in itself painful to us, just as darkness is; that an architecture which is altogether monotonous is a dark or dead architecture; and of those who love it, it may be truly said, 'they love darkness rather than light.' But monotony in certain measure, used in order to give value to change, and above all, that transparent monotony, which, like the shadows of a great painter, suffers all manner of dimly suggested form to be seen through the body of it, is an essential in architectural as in all other composition; and the endurance of monotony has about the same place in a healthy mind that the endurance of darkness has: that is to say, as a strong intellect will have pleasure in the solemnities of storm and twilight, and in the broken and mysterious lights that gleam among them, rather than in mere brilliancy and glare, while a frivolous mind will dread the shadow and the storm; and as a great man will be ready to endure much darkness of fortune in order to reach greater eminence of power or felicity, while an inferior man will not pay the price; exactly in like manner a great mind will accept, or even delight in, monotony which would be wearisome to an inferior intellect, because it has more patience and power of expectation, and is ready to pay the full price for the great future pleasure of change. But in all cases it is not that the noble nature loves monotony, any more than it loves darkness or pain. But it can bear with it, and receive a high pleasure in the endurance or patience, a pleasure necessary to the well-being of this world; while those who will not submit to the temporary sameness, but rush from one change to another, gradually dull the edge of change itself, and bring a shadow and weariness over the whole world from which there is no more escape.

60. From these general uses of variety in the economy of the world, we may at once understand its use and abuse in architecture. The variety of the Gothic schools is the more healthy and beautiful, because in many cases it is entirely unstudied, and results, not from mere love of change, but from practical necessities. For in one point of view Gothic is not only the best, but the only rational architecture, as being that which can fit itself most easily to all services, vulgar or noble. Undefined in its slope of roof, height of shaft, breadth of arch, or disposition of ground plan, it can shrink into a turret, expand into a hall, coil into a staircase, or spring into a spire, with undegraded grace and unexhausted energy; and whenever it finds occasion for change in its form or purpose, it submits to it without the slightest sense of loss either to its unity or majesty, — subtle and flexible like a fiery serpent, but ever attentive to the voice of the charmer. And it is one of the chief virtues of the Gothic builders, that they never suffered ideas of outside symmetries and consistencies to interfere with the real use and value of what they did. If they wanted a window, they opened one; a room, they added one; a buttress, they built one; utterly regardless of any established conventionalities of external appearance, knowing (as indeed it always happened) that such daring interruptions of the formal plan would rather give additional interest to its symmetry than injure it. So that, in the best times of Gothic, a useless window would rather have been opened in an unexpected place for the sake of the surprise, than a useful one forbidden for the sake of symmetry. Every successive architect, employed upon a great work, built the pieces he added in his own way, utterly regardless of the style adopted by his predecessors; and if two towers were raised in nominal correspondence at the sides of a cathedral front, one was nearly sure to be different from the other, and in each the style at the top to be different from the style at the bottom.

61. These marked variations were, however, only permitted as part of the great system of perpetual change which ran through every member of Gothic design, and rendered it as endless a field for the beholder's inquiry as for the builder's imagination: change, which in the best schools is subtle and delicate, and rendered more delightful by intermingling of a noble monotony; in the more barbaric schools is somewhat fantastic and redundant; but, in all, a necessary and constant condition of the life of the school. Sometimes the variety is in one feature, sometimes in another; it may be in the capitals or crockets, in the niches or the traceries, or in all together, but in some one or other of the features it will be found always. If the mouldings are constant, the surface sculpture will change; if the capitals are of a fixed design, the traceries will change; if the traceries are monotonous, the capitals will change; and if even, as in some fine schools, the early English for example, there is the slightest approximation to an unvarying type of mouldings, capitals, and floral decoration, the variety is found in the disposition of the masses, and in the figure sculpture.

62. I must now refer for a moment, before we quit the consideration of this, the second mental element of Gothic, to the opening of the third chapter of the Seven Lamps of Architecture, in which the distinction was drawn between man gathering and man governing; between his acceptance of the sources of delight from nature, and his development of authoritative or imaginative power in their arrangement: for the two mental elements, not only of Gothic, but of all good architecture, which we have just been examining, belong to it, and are admirable in it, chiefly as it is, more than any other subject of art, the work of man, and the expression of the average power of man. A picture or poem is often little more than a feeble utterance of man's admiration of something out of himself; but architecture approaches more to a creation of his own, born of his necessities, and expressive of his nature. It is also, in some sort, the work of the whole race, while the picture or statue is the work of one only, in most cases more highly gifted than his fellows. And therefore we may expect that the first two elements of good architecture should be expressive of some great truths commonly belonging to the whole race, and necessary to be understood or felt by them in all their work that they do under the sun. And observe what they are: the confession of Imperfection, and the confession of Desire of Change. The building of the bird and the bee needs not express anything like this. It is perfect and unchanging. But just because we are something better than birds or bees, our building must confess that we have not reached the perfection we can imagine, and cannot rest in the condition we have attained. If we pretend to have reached either perfection or satisfaction, we have degraded ourselves and our work. God's work only may express that; but ours may never have that sentence written upon it, — 'And behold, it was very good.' And, observe again, it is not merely as it renders the edifice a book of various knowledge, or a mine of precious thought, that variety is essential to its nobleness. The vital principle is not the love of Knowledge, but the love of Change. It is that strange disquietude of the Gothic spirit that is its greatness; that restlessness of the dreaming mind, that wanders hither and thither among the niches, and flickers feverishly around the pinnacles, and frets and fades in labyrinthine knots and shadows along wall and roof, and yet is not satisfied, nor shall be satisfied. The Greek could stay in his triglyph furrow, and be at peace; but the work of the Gothic heart is fretwork still, and it can neither rest in, nor from, its labour, but must pass on, sleeplessly, until its love of change shall be pacified for ever in the change that must come alike on them that wake and them that sleep.

63. The third constituent element of the Gothic mind was stated to be NATURALISM; that is to say, the love of natural objects for their own sake, and the effort to represent them frankly, unconstrained by artistical laws.

64. This characteristic of the style partly follows in necessary connection with those named above. For, so soon as the workman is left free to represent what subjects he chooses, he must look to the nature that is round him for material, and will endeavour to represent it as he sees it, with more or less accuracy according to the skill he possesses, and with much play of fancy, but with small respect for law. There is, however, a marked distinction between the imaginations of the Western and Eastern races, even when both are left free; the Western, or Gothic, delighting most in the representation of facts, and the Eastern (Arabian, Persian, and Chinese) in the harmony of colours and forms. Each of these intellectual dispositions has its particular forms of error and abuse [...]

65. Of the various forms of resultant mischief it is not here the place to speak; the reader may already be somewhat wearied with a statement which has led us apparently so far from our immediate subject. But the digression was necessary, in order that I might clearly define the sense in which I use the word Naturalism when I state it to be the third most essential characteristic of Gothic architecture. I mean that the Gothic builders belong to the central or greatest rank in both the classifications of artists which we have just made; that considering all artists as either men of design, men of facts, or men of both, the Gothic builders were men of both; and that again, considering all artists as either Purists, Naturalists, or Sensualists, the Gothic builders were Naturalists.

66. I say first, that the Gothic builders were of that central class which unites fact with design; but that the part of the work which was more especially their own was the truthfulness. Their power of artistical invention or arrangement was not greater than that of Romanesque and Byzantine workmen: by those workmen they were taught the principles, and from them received their models, of design; but to the ornamental feeling and rich fancy of the Byzantine the Gothic builder added a love of fact which is never found in the South. Both Greek and Roman used conventional foliage in their ornament, passing into something that was not foliage at all, knotting itself into strange cup-like buds or clusters, and growing out of lifeless rods instead of stems; the Gothic sculptor received these types, at first, as things that ought to be, just as we have a second time received them; but he could not rest in them. He saw there was no veracity in them, no knowledge, no vitality. Do what he would, he could not help liking the true leaves better; and cautiously, a little at a time, he put more of nature into his work, until at last it was all true, retaining, nevertheless, every valuable character of the original well-disciplined and designed arrangement.

67. Nor is it only in external and visible subject that the Gothic workman wrought for truth: he is as firm in his rendering of imaginative as of actual truth; that is to say, when an idea would have been by a Roman, or Byzantine, symbolically represented, the Gothic mind realizes it to the utmost. For instance, the purgatorial fire is represented in the mosaic of Torcello (Romanesque) as a red stream, longitudinally striped like a riband, descending out of the throne of Christ, and gradually extending itself to envelop the wicked. When we are once informed what this means, it is enough for its purpose; but the Gothic inventor does not leave the sign in need of interpretation. He makes the fire as like real fire as he can; and in the porch of St Maclou at Rouen the sculptured flames burst out of the Hades gate, and flicker up, in writhing tongues of stone, through the interstices of the niches, as if the church itself were on fire. This is an extreme instance, but it is all the more illustrative of the entire difference in temper and thought between the two schools of art, and of the intense love of veracity which influenced the Gothic design.

68. I do not say that this love of veracity is always healthy in its operation. I have above noticed the errors into which it falls from despising design; and there is another kind of error noticeable in the instance just given, in which the love of truth is too hasty, and seizes on a surface truth instead of an inner one. For in representing the Hades fire, it is not the mere form of the flame which needs most to be told, but its unquenchableness, its Divine ordainment and limitation, and its inner fierceness, not physical and material, but in being the expression of the wrath of God. And these things are not to be told by imitating the fire that flashes out of a bundle of sticks. If we think over his symbol a little, we shall perhaps find that the Romanesque builder told more truth in that likeness of a blood-red stream, flowing between definite shores, and out of God's throne, and expanding, as if fed by a perpetual current, into the lake wherein the wicked are cast, than the Gothic builder in those torch-flickerings about his niches. But this is not to our immediate purpose; I am not at present to insist upon the faults into which the love of truth was led in the later Gothic times, but on the feeling itself, as a glorious and peculiar characteristic of the Northern builders. For, observe, it is not, even in the above instance, love of truth, but want of thought, which causes the fault. The love of truth, as such, is good, but when it is misdirected by thoughtlessness or over-excited by vanity, and either seizes on facts of small value, or gathers them chiefly that it may boast of its grasp and apprehension, its work may well become dull or offensive. Yet let us not, therefore, blame the inherent love of facts, but the incautiousness of their selection, and impertinence of their statement.

69. I said, in the second place, that Gothic work, when referred to the arrangement of all art, as purist, naturalist, or sensualist, was naturalist. This character follows necessarily on its extreme love of truth, prevailing over the sense of beauty, and causing it to take delight in portraiture of every kind, and to express the various characters of the human countenance and form, as it did the varieties of leaves and the ruggedness of branches. And this tendency is both increased and ennobled by the same Christian humility which we saw expressed in the first character of Gothic work, its rudeness. For as that resulted from a humility which confessed the imperfection of the workman, so this naturalist portraiture is rendered more faithful by the humility which confesses the imperfection of the subject. The Greek sculptor could neither bear to confess his own feebleness, nor to tell the faults of the forms that he portrayed. But the Christian workman, believing that all is finally to work together for good, freely confesses both, and neither seeks to disguise his own roughness of work, nor his subject's roughness of make. Yet this frankness being joined, for the most part, with depth of religious feeling in other directions, and especially with charity, there is sometimes a tendency to Purism in the best Gothic sculpture; so that it frequently reaches great dignity of form and tenderness of expression, yet never so as to lose the veracity of portraiture wherever portraiture is possible: not exalting its kings into demi-gods, nor its saints into archangels, but giving what kingliness and sanctity was in them, to the full, mixed with due record of their faults; and this in the most part with a great indifference like that of Scripture history, which sets down, with unmoved and unexcusing resoluteness, the virtues and errors of all men of whom it speaks, often leaving the reader to form his own estimate of them, without an indication of the judgment of the historian. And this veracity is carried out by the Gothic sculptors in the minuteness and generality, as well as the equity, of their delineation: for they do not limit their art to the portraiture of saints and kings, but introduce the most familiar scenes and most simple subjects: filling up the backgrounds of Scripture histories with vivid and curious representations of the commonest incidents of daily life, and availing themselves of every occasion in which, either as a symbol, or an explanation of a scene or time, the things familiar to the eye of the workman could be introduced and made of account. Hence Gothic sculpture and painting are not only full of valuable portraiture of the greatest men, but copious records of all the domestic customs and inferior arts of the ages in which it flourished.[【3】]

70. There is, however, one direction in which the Naturalism of the Gothic workmen is peculiarly manifested; and this direction is even more characteristic of the school than the Naturalism itself; I mean their peculiar fondness for the forms of Vegetation. In rendering the various circumstances of daily life, Egyptian and Ninevite sculpture is as frank and as diffuse as the Gothic. From the highest pomps of state or triumphs of battle, to the most trivial domestic arts and amusements, all is taken advantage of to fill the field of granite with the perpetual interest of a crowded drama; and the early Lombardic and Romanesque sculpture is equally copious in its description of the familiar circumstances of war and the chase. But in all the scenes portrayed by the workmen of these nations, vegetation occurs only as an explanatory accessary; the reed is introduced to mark the course of the river, or the tree to mark the covert of the wild beast, or the ambush of the enemy, but there is no especial interest in the forms of the vegetation strong enough to induce them to make it a subject of separate and accurate study. Again, among the nations who followed the arts of design exclusively, the forms of foliage introduced were meagre and general, and their real intricacy and life were neither admired nor expressed. But to the Gothic workman the living foliage became a subject of intense affection, and he struggled to render all its characters with as much accuracy as was compatible with the laws of his design and the nature of his material, not unfrequently tempted in his enthusiasm to transgress the one and disguise the other.

71. There is a peculiar significance in this, indicative both of higher civilization and gentler temperament, than had before been manifested in architecture. Rudeness, and the love of change, which we have insisted upon as the first elements of Gothic, are also elements common to all healthy schools. But here is a softer element mingled with them, peculiar to the Gothic itself. The rudeness or ignorance which would have been painfully exposed in the treatment of the human form, are still not so great as to prevent the successful rendering of the wayside herbage; and the love of change, which becomes morbid and feverish in following the haste of the hunter and the rage of the combatant, is at once soothed and satisfied as it watches the wandering of the tendril, and the budding of the flower. Nor is this all: the new direction of mental interest marks an infinite change in the means and the habits of life. The nations whose chief support was in the chase, whose chief interest was in the battle, whose chief pleasure was in the banquet, would take small care respecting the shapes of leaves and flowers; and notice little in the forms of the forest trees which sheltered them, except the signs indicative of the wood which would make the toughest lance, the closest roof, or the clearest fire. The affectionate observation of the grace and outward character of vegetation is the sure sign of a more tranquil and gentle existence, sustained by the gifts, and gladdened by the splendour, of the earth. In that careful distinction of species, and richness of delicate and undisturbed organization, which characterize the Gothic design, there is the history of rural and thoughtful life, influenced by habitual tenderness, and devoted to subtle inquiry; and every discriminating and delicate touch of the chisel, as it rounds the petal or guides the branch, is a prophecy of the development of the entire body of the natural sciences, beginning with that of medicine, of the recovery of literature, and the establishment of the most necessary principles of domestic wisdom and national peace.

72. I have before alluded to the strange and vain supposition, that the original conception of Gothic architecture had been derived from vegetation, — from the symmetry of avenues, and the interlacing of branches. It is a supposition which never could have existed for a moment in the mind of any person acquainted with early Gothic; but, however idle as a theory, it is most valuable as a testimony to the character of the perfected style. It is precisely because the reverse of this theory is the fact, because the Gothic did not arise out of, but developed itself into a resemblance to vegetation, that this resemblance is so instructive as an indication of the temper of the builders. It was no chance suggestion of the form of an arch from the bending of a bough, but a gradual and continual discovery of a beauty in natural forms which could be more and more perfectly transferred into those of stone, that influenced at once the heart of the people, and the form of the edifice. The Gothic architecture arose in massy and mountainous strength, axe-hewn, and iron-bound, block heaved upon block by the monk's enthusiasm and the soldier's force; and cramped and stanchioned into such weight of grisly wall, as might bury the anchoret in darkness, and beat back the utmost storm of battle, suffering but by the same narrow crosslet the passing of the sunbeam, or of the arrow. Gradually, as that monkish enthusiasm became more thoughtful, and as the sound of war became more and more intermittent beyond the gates of the convent or the keep, the stony pillar grew slender and the vaulted roof grew light, till they had wreathed themselves into the semblance of the summer woods at their fairest, and of the dead field-flowers, long trodden down in blood, sweet monumental statues were set to bloom for ever, beneath the porch of the temple, or the canopy of the tomb.

73. Nor is it only as a sign of greater gentleness or refinement of mind, but as a proof of the best possible direction of this refinement, that the tendency of the Gothic to the expression of vegetative life is to be admired. That sentence of Genesis, 'I have given thee every green herb for meat,' like all the rest of the book, has a profound symbolical as well as a literal meaning. It is not merely the nourishment of the body, but the food of the soul, that is intended. The green herb is, of all nature, that which is most essential to the healthy spiritual life of man. Most of us do not need fine scenery; the precipice and the mountain peak are not intended to be seen by all men, — perhaps their power is greatest over those who are unaccustomed to them. But trees and fields and flowers were made for all, and are necessary for all. God has connected the labour which is essential to the bodily sustenance with the pleasures which are healthiest for the heart; and while He made the ground stubborn, He made its herbage fragrant, and its blossoms fair. The proudest architecture that man can build has no higher honour than to bear the image and recall the memory of that grass of the field which is, at once, the type and the support of his existence; the goodly building is then most glorious when it is sculptured into the likeness of the leaves of Paradise; and the great Gothic spirit, as we showed it to be noble in its disquietude, is also noble in its hold of nature; it is, indeed, like the dove of Noah, in that she found no rest upon the face of the waters, — but like her in this also, 'Lo, IN HER MOUTH WAS AN OLIVE BRANCH, PLUCKED OFF.'

74. The fourth essential element of the Gothic mind was above stated to be the sense of the GROTESQUE; but I shall defer the endeavour to define this most curious and subtle character until we have occasion to examine one of the divisions of the Renaissance schools, which was morbidly influenced by it. It is the less necessary to insist upon it here, because every reader familiar with Gothic architecture must understand what I mean, and will, I believe, have no hesitation in admitting, that the tendency to delight in fantastic and ludicrous, as well as in sublime, images, is a universal instinct of the Gothic imagination.

75. The fifth element above named was RIGIDITY; and this character I must endeavour carefully to define, for neither the word I have used, nor any other that I can think of, will express it accurately. For I mean, not merely stable, but active rigidity; the peculiar energy which gives tension to movement, and stiffness to resistance, which makes the fiercest lightning forked rather than curved, and the stoutest oak-branch angular rather than bending, and is as much seen in the quivering of the lance as in the glittering of the icicle.

76. I have before had occasion to note some manifestations of this energy or fixedness; but it must be still more attentively considered here, as it shows itself throughout the whole structure and decoration of Gothic work. Egyptian and Greek buildings stand, for the most part, by their own weight and mass, one stone passively incumbent on another; but in the Gothic vaults and traceries there is a stiffness analogous to that of the bones of a limb, or fibres of a tree; an elastic tension and communication of force from part to part, and also a studious expression of this throughout every visible line of the building. And, in like manner, the Greek and Egyptian ornament is either mere surface engraving, as if the face of the wall had been stamped with a seal, or its lines are flowing, lithe, and luxuriant; in either case, there is no expression of energy in the framework of the ornament itself. But the Gothic ornament stands out in prickly independence, and frosty fortitude, jutting into crockets, and freezing into pinnacles; here starting up into a monster, there germinating into a blossom, anon knitting itself into a branch, alternately thorny, bossy, and bristly, or writhed into every form of nervous entanglement; but, even when most graceful, never for an instant languid, always quickset: erring, if at all, ever on the side of brusquerie.

77. The feelings or habits in the workman which give rise to this character in the work, are more complicated and various than those indicated by any other sculptural expression hitherto named. There is, first, the habit of hard and rapid working; the industry of the tribes of the North, quickened by the coldness of the climate, and giving an expression of sharp energy to all they do, as opposed to the languor of the Southern tribes, however much of fire there may be in the heart of that languor, for lava itself may flow languidly. There is also the habit of finding enjoyment in the signs of cold, which is never found, I believe, in the inhabitants of countries south of the Alps. Cold is to them an unredeemed evil, to be suffered and forgotten as soon as may be; but the long winter of the North forces the Goth (I mean the Englishman, Frenchman, Dane, or German), if he would lead a happy life at all, to find resources of happiness in foul weather as well as fair, and to rejoice in the leafless as well as in the shady forest. And this we do with all our hearts; finding perhaps nearly as much contentment by the Christmas fire as in the summer sunshine, and gaining health and strength on the ice-fields of winter, as well as among the meadows of spring. So that there is nothing adverse or painful to our feelings in the cramped and stiffened structure of vegetation checked by cold; and instead of seeking, like the Southern sculpture, to express only the softness of leafage nourished in all tenderness, and tempted into all luxuriance by warm winds and glowing rays, we find pleasure in dwelling upon the crabbed, perverse, and morose animation of plants that have known little kindness from earth or heaven, but, season after season, have had their best efforts palsied by frost, their brightest buds buried under snow, and their goodliest limbs lopped by tempest.

78. There are many subtle sympathies and affections which join to confirm the Gothic mind in this peculiar choice of subject; and when we add to the influence of these, the necessities consequent upon the employment of a rougher material, compelling the workman to seek for vigour of effect, rather than refinement of texture or accuracy of form, we have direct and manifest causes for much of the difference between the Northern and Southern cast of conception: but there are indirect causes holding a far more important place in the Gothic heart, though less immediate in their influence on design. Strength of will, independence of character, resoluteness of purpose, impatience of undue control, and that general tendency to set the individual reason against authority, and the individual deed against destiny, which, in the Northern tribes, has opposed itself throughout all ages, to the languid submission, in the Southern, of thought to tradition, and purpose to fatality, are all more or less traceable in the rigid lines, vigorous and various masses, and daringly projecting and independent structure of the Northern Gothic ornament: while the opposite feelings are in like manner legible in the graceful and softly guided waves and wreathed bands, in which Southern decoration is constantly disposed; in its tendency to lose its independence, and fuse itself into the surface of the masses upon which it is traced; and in the expression seen so often, in the arrangement of those masses themselves, of an abandonment of their strength to an inevitable necessity, or a listless repose.

79. There is virtue in the measure, and error in the excess, of both these characters of mind, and in both of the styles which they have created; the best architecture, and the best temper, are those which unite them both; and this fifth impulse of the Gothic heart is therefore that which needs most caution in its indulgence. It is more definitely Gothic than any other, but the best Gothic building is not that which is most Gothic: it can hardly be too frank in its confession of rudeness, hardly too rich in its changefulness, hardly too faithful in its naturalism; but it may go too far in its rigidity, and, like the great Puritan spirit in its extreme, lose itself either in frivolity of division, or perversity of purpose. It actually did so in its later times; but it is gladdening to remember that in its utmost nobleness, the very temper which has been thought most adverse to it, the Protestant spirit of self-dependence and inquiry, was expressed in its every line. Faith and aspiration there were, in every Christian ecclesiastical building, from the first century to the fifteenth; but the moral habits to which England in this age owes the kind of greatness that she has, — the habits of philosophical investigation, of accurate thought, of domestic seclusion and independence, of stern self-reliance and sincere upright searching into religious truth, — were only traceable in the features which were the distinctive creation of the Gothic schools, in the veined foliage, and thorny fretwork, and shadowy niche, and buttressed pier, and fearless height of subtle pinnacle and crested tower, sent like an 'unperplexed question up to Heaven.'

80. Last, because the least essential, of the constituent elements of this noble school, was placed that of REDUNDANCE, — the uncalculating bestowal of the wealth of its labour. There is, indeed, much Gothic, and that of the best period, in which this element is hardly traceable, and which depends for its effect almost exclusively on loveliness of simple design and grace of uninvolved proportion; still, in the most characteristic buildings, a certain portion of their effect depends upon accumulation of ornament; and many of those which have most influence on the minds of men, have attained it by means of this attribute alone. And although, by careful study of the school, it is possible to arrive at a condition of taste which shall be better contented by a few perfect lines than by a whole facade covered with fretwork, the building which only satisfies such a taste is not to be considered the best. For the very first requirement of Gothic architecture being, as we saw above, that it shall both admit the aid, and appeal to the admiration, of the rudest as well as the most refined minds, the richness of the work is, paradoxical as the statement may appear, a part of its humility. No architecture is so haughty as that which is simple; which refuses to address the eye, except in a few clear and forceful lines; which implies, in offering so little to our regards, that all it has offered is perfect; and disdains, either by the complexity or the attractiveness of its features, to embarrass our investigation, or betray us into delight. That humility, which is the very life of the Gothic school, is shown not only in the imperfection, but in the accumulation, of ornament. The inferior rank of the workman is often shown as much in the richness, as the roughness, of his work; and if the co-operation of every hand, and the sympathy of every heart, are to be received, we must be content to allow the redundance which disguises the failure of the feeble, and wins the regard of the inattentive. There are, however, far nobler interests mingling, in the Gothic heart, with the rude love of decorative accumulation: a magnificent enthusiasm, which feels as if it never could do enough to reach the fulness of its ideal; an unselfishness of sacrifice, which would rather cast fruitless labour before the altar than stand idle in the market; and, finally, a profound sympathy with the fulness and wealth of the material universe, rising out of that Naturalism whose operation we have already endeavoured to define. The sculptor who sought for his models among the forest leaves, could not but quickly and deeply feel that complexity need not involve the loss of grace, nor richness that of repose; and every hour which he spent in the study of the minute and various work of Nature, made him feel more forcibly the barrenness of what was best in that of man: nor is it to be wondered at, that, seeing her perfect and exquisite creations poured forth in a profusion which conception could not grasp nor calculation sum, he should think that it ill became him to be niggardly of his own rude craftsmanship; and where he saw throughout the universe a faultless beauty lavished on measureless spaces of broidered field and blooming mountain, to grudge his poor and imperfect labour to the few stones that he had raised one upon another, for habitation or memorial. The years of his life passed away before his task was accomplished; but generation succeeded generation with unwearied enthusiasm, and the cathedral front was at last lost in the tapestry of its traceries, like a rock among the thickets and herbage of spring.

81. We have now, I believe, obtained a view approaching to completeness of the various moral or imaginative elements which composed the inner spirit of Gothic architecture [...]

注释

【1】　i.e., of The Stones of Venice.

【2】　The Elgin marbles are supposed by many persons to be 'perfect'. In the most important portions they indeed approach perfection, but only there. The draperies are unfinished, the hair and wool of the animals are unfinished, and the entire bas-reliefs of the frieze are roughly cut.

【3】　The best art either represents the facts of its own day, or, if facts of the past, expresses them with accessaries of the time in which the work was done. All good art, representing past events, is therefore full of the most frank anachronism, and always ought to be. No painter has any business to be an antiquarian. We do not want his impressions or suppositions respecting things that are past. We want his clear assertions respecting things present.

The Work of Iron, in Nature, Art, and Policy

A Lecture delivered at Tunbridge Wells,
February 16th, 1858

1. WHEN first I heard that you wished me to address you this evening, it was a matter of some doubt with me whether I could find any subject that would possess any sufficient interest for you to justify my bringing you out of your comfortable houses on a winter's night. When I venture to speak about my own special business of art, it is almost always before students of art, among whom I may sometimes permit myself to be dull, if I can feel that I am useful: but a mere talk about art, especially without examples to refer to (and I have been unable to prepare any careful illustrations for this lecture), is seldom of much interest to a general audience. As I was considering what you might best bear with me in speaking about, there came naturally into my mind a subject connected with the origin and present prosperity of the town you live in; and, it seemed to me, in the outbranchings of it, capable of a very general interest. When, long ago (I am afraid to think how long), Tunbridge Wells was my Switzerland, and I used to be brought down here in the summer, a sufficiently active child, rejoicing in the hope of clambering sandstone cliffs of stupendous height above the common, there used sometimes, as, I suppose, there are in the lives of all children at the Wells, to be dark days in my life — days of condemnation to the pantiles and band — under which calamities my only consolation used to be in watching, at every turn in my walk, the welling forth of the spring over the orange rim of its marble basin. The memory of the clear water, sparkling over its saffron stain, came back to me as the strongest image connected with the place; and it struck me that you might not be unwilling, to-night, to think a little over the full significance of that saffron stain, and of the power, in other ways and other functions, of the steely element to which so many here owe returning strength and life; — chief as it has been always, and is yet more and more markedly so day by day, among the precious gifts of the earth.

2. The subject is, of course, too wide to be more than suggestively treated; and even my suggestions must be few, and drawn chiefly from my own fields of work; nevertheless, I think I shall have time to indicate some courses of thought which you may afterwards follow out for yourselves if they interest you; and so I will not shrink from the full scope of the subject which I have announced to you — the functions of Iron, in Nature, Art, and Policy.

3. Without more preface, I will take up the first head.

4.Ⅰ. IRON IN NATURE. — You all probably know that the ochreous stain, which, perhaps, is often thought to spoil the basin of your spring, is iron in a state of rust: and when you see rusty iron in other places you generally think, not only that it spoils the places it stains, but that it is spoiled itself — that rusty iron is spoiled iron.

5. For most of our uses it generally is so; and because we cannot use a rusty knife or razor so well as a polished one, we suppose it to be a great defect in iron that it is subject to rust. But not at all. On the contrary, the most perfect and useful state of it is that ochreous stain; and therefore it is endowed with so ready a disposition to get itself into that state. It is not a fault in the iron, but a virtue, to be so fond of getting rusted, for in that condition it fulfils its most important functions in the universe, and most kindly duties to mankind. Nay, in a certain sense, and almost a literal one, we may say that iron rusted is Living; but when pure or polished, Dead. You all probably know that in the mixed air we breathe, the part of it essentially needful to us is called oxygen; and that this substance is to all animals, in the most accurate sense of the word, 'breath of life'. The nervous power of life is a different thing; but the supporting element of the breath, without which the blood, and therefore the life, cannot be nourished, is this oxygen. Now it is this very same air which the iron breathes when it gets rusty. It takes the oxygen from the atmosphere as eagerly as we do, though it uses it differently. The iron keeps all that it gets; we, and other animals, part with it again; but the metal absolutely keeps what it has once received of this aërial gift; and the ochreous dust which we so much despise is, in fact, just so much nobler than pure iron, in so far as it is iron and the air. Nobler, and more useful — for, indeed, as I shall be able to show you presently — the main service of this metal, and of all other metals, to us, is not in making knives, and scissors, and pokers, and pans, but in making the ground we feed from, and nearly all the substances first needful to our existence. For these are all nothing but metals and oxygen — metals with breath put into them. Sand, lime, clay, and the rest of the earths — potash and soda, and the rest of the alkalies — are all of them metals which have undergone this, so to speak, vital change, and have been rendered fit for the service of man by permanent unity with the purest air which he himself breathes. There is only one metal which does not rust readily; and that in its influence on Man hitherto, has caused Death rather than Life; it will not be put to its right use till it is made a pavement of, and so trodden under foot.[【1】]

6. Is there not something striking in this fact, considered largely as one of the types, or lessons, furnished by the inanimate creation? Here you have your hard, bright, cold, lifeless metal — good enough for swords and scissors — but not for food. You think, perhaps, that your iron is wonderfully useful in a pure form, but how would you like the world, if all your meadows, instead of grass, grew nothing but iron wire — if all your arable ground, instead of being made of sand and clay, were suddenly turned into flat surfaces of steel — if the whole earth, instead of its green and glowing sphere, rich with forest and flower, showed nothing but the image of the vast furnace of a ghastly engine — a globe of black, lifeless, excoriated metal? It would be that, — probably it was once that; but assuredly it would be, were it not that all the substance of which it is made sucks and breathes the brilliancy of the atmosphere; and, as it breathes, softening from its merciless hardness, it falls into fruitful and beneficent dust; gathering itself again into the earths from which we feed, and the stones with which we build; — into the rocks that frame the mountains, and the sands that bind the sea.

7. Hence, it is impossible for you to take up the most insignificant pebble at your feet, without being able to read, if you like, this curious lesson in it. You look upon it at first as if it were earth only. Nay, it answers, 'I am not earth — I am earth and air in one; part of that blue heaven which you love, and long for, is already in me; it is all my life — without it I should be nothing, and able for nothing; I could not minister to you, nor nourish you — I should be a cruel and helpless thing; but, because there is, according to my need and place in creation, a kind of soul in me, I have become capable of good, and helpful in the circles of vitality.'

8. Thus far the same interest attaches to all the earths, and all the metals of which they are made; but a deeper interest and larger beneficence belong to that ochreous earth of iron which stains the marble of your springs. It stains much besides that marble. It stains the great earth wheresoever you can see it, far and wide — it is the colouring substance appointed to colour the globe for the sight, as well as subdue it to the service of man. You have just seen your hills covered with snow, and, perhaps, have enjoyed, at first, the contrast of their fair white with the dark blocks of pine woods; but have you ever considered how you would like them always white — not pure white, but dirty white — the white of thaw, with all the chill of snow in it, but none of its brightness? That is what the colour of the earth would be without its iron; that would be its colour, not here or there only, but in all places, and at all times. Follow out that idea till you get it in some detail. Think first of your pretty gravel walks in your gardens, and fine, like plots of sunshine between the yellow flower-beds; fancy them all suddenly turned to the colour of ashes. That is what they would be without iron ochre. Think of your winding walks over the common, as warm to the eye as they are dry to the foot, and imagine them all laid down suddenly with gray cinders. Then pass beyond the common into the country, and pause at the first ploughed field that you see sweeping up the hill sides in the sun, with its deep brown furrows, and wealth of ridges all a-glow, heaved aside by the ploughshare, like deep folds of a mantle of russet velvet — fancy it all changed suddenly into grisly furrows in a field of mud. That is what it would be without iron. Pass on, in fancy, over hill and dale, till you reach the bending line of the sea shore; go down upon its breezy beach — watch the white foam flashing among the amber of it, and all the blue sea embayed in belts of gold: then fancy those circlets of far sweeping shore suddenly put into mounds of mourning — all those golden sands turned into gray slime; the fairies no more able to call to each other, 'Come unto these yellow sands'; but, 'Come unto these drab sands.' That is what they would be, without iron.

9. Iron is in some sort, therefore, the sunshine and light of landscape, so far as that light depends on the ground; but it is a source of another kind of sunshine, quite as important to us in the way we live at present — sunshine, not of landscape, but of dwelling-place.

10. In these days of swift locomotion I may doubtless assume that most of my audience have been somewhere out of England — have been in Scotland, or France, or Switzerland. Whatever may have been their impression, on returning to their own country, of its superiority or inferiority in other respects, they cannot but have felt one thing about it — the comfortable look of its towns and villages. Foreign towns are often very picturesque, very beautiful, but they never have quite that look of warm self-sufficiency and wholesome quiet with which our villages nestle themselves down among the green fields. If you will take the trouble to examine into the sources of this impression, you will find that by far the greater part of that warm and satisfactory appearance depends upon the rich scarlet colour of the bricks and tiles. It does not belong to the neat building — every neat building has an uncomfortable rather than a comfortable look — but it depends on the warm building; our villages are dressed in red tiles as our old women are in red cloaks; and it does not matter how warm the cloaks, or how bent and bowed the roof may be, so long as there are no holes in either one or the other, and the sobered but unextinguishable colour still glows in the shadow of the hood, and burns among the green mosses of the gable. And what do you suppose dyes your tiles of cottage roof? You don't paint them. It is Nature who puts all that lovely vermilion into the clay for you; and all that lovely vermilion is this oxide of iron. Think, therefore, what your streets of towns would become — ugly enough, indeed, already, some of them, but still comfortable-looking — if instead of that warm brick red, the houses became all pepper-and-salt colour. Fancy your country villages changing from that homely scarlet of theirs which, in its sweet suggestion of laborious peace, is as honourable as the soldier's scarlet of laborious battle — suppose all those cottage roofs, I say, turned at once into the colour of unbaked clay, the colour of street gutters in rainy weather. That's what they would be without iron.

11. There is, however, yet another effect of colour in our English country towns, which, perhaps, you may not all yourselves have noticed, but for which you must take the word of a sketcher. They are not so often merely warm scarlet as they are warm purple; — a more beautiful colour still: and they owe this colour to a mingling with the vermilion of the deep grayish or purple hue of our fine Welsh slates on the more respectable roofs, made more blue still by the colour of intervening atmosphere. If you examine one of these Welsh slates freshly broken, you will find its purple colour clear and vivid; and although never strikingly so after it has been long exposed to weather, it always retains enough of the tint to give rich harmonies of distant purple in opposition to the green of our woods and fields. Whatever brightness or power there is in the hue is entirely owing to the oxide of iron. Without it the slates would either be pale stone colour, or cold gray, or black.

12. Thus far we have only been considering the use and pleasantness of iron in the common earth of clay. But there are three kinds of earth which, in mixed mass and prevalent quantity, form the world. Those are, in common language, the earths of clay, of lime, and of flint. Many other elements are mingled with these in sparing quantities; but the great frame and substance of the earth is made of these three, so that wherever you stand on solid ground, in any country of the globe, the thing that is mainly under your feet will be either clay, limestone, or some condition of the earth of flint, mingled with both.

13. These being what we have usually to deal with, Nature seems to have set herself to make these three substances as interesting to us, and as beautiful for us, as she can. The clay, being a soft and changeable substance, she doesn't take much pains about, as we have seen, till it is baked; she brings the colour into it only when it receives a permanent form. But the limestone and flint she paints, in her own way, in their native state: and her object in painting them seems to be much the same as in her painting of flowers; to draw us, careless and idle human creatures, to watch her a little, and see what she is about — that being on the whole good for us, — her children. For Nature is always carrying on very strange work with this limestone and flint of hers: laying down beds of them at the bottom of the sea; building islands out of the sea; filling chinks and veins in mountains with curious treasures; petrifying mosses, and trees, and shells; in fact, carrying on all sorts of business, subterranean or submarine, which it would be highly desirable for us, who profit and live by it, to notice as it goes on. And apparently to lead us to do this, she makes picture-books for us of limestone and flint; and tempts us, like foolish children as we are, to read her books by the pretty colours in them. The pretty colours in her limestone-books form those variegated marbles which all mankind have taken delight to polish and build with from the beginning of time; and the pretty colours in her flint-books form those agates, jaspers, cornelians, bloodstones, onyxes, cairngorms, chrysoprases, which men have in like manner taken delight to cut, and polish, and make ornaments of, from the beginning of time; and yet so much of babies are they, and so fond of looking at the pictures instead of reading the book, that I question whether, after six thousand years of cutting and polishing, there are above two or three people out of any given hundred who know, or care to know, how a bit of agate or a bit of marble was made, or painted.

14. How it was made, may not be always very easy to say; but with what it was painted there is no manner of question. All those beautiful violet veinings and variegations of the marbles of Sicily and Spain, the glowing orange and amber colours of those of Siena, the deep russet of the Rosso antico, and the blood-colour of all the precious jaspers that enrich the temples of Italy; and, finally, all the lovely transitions of tint in the pebbles of Scotland and the Rhine, which form, though not the most precious, by far the most interesting portion of our modern jewellers' work; — all these are painted by Nature with this one material only, variously proportioned and applied — the oxide of iron that stains your Tunbridge springs.

15. But this is not all, nor the best part of the work of iron. Its service in producing these beautiful stones is only rendered to rich people, who can afford to quarry and polish them. But Nature paints for all the world, poor and rich together; and while, therefore, she thus adorns the innermost rocks of her hills, to tempt your investigation, or indulge your luxury, — she paints, far more carefully, the outsides of the hills, which are for the eyes of the shepherd and the ploughman. I spoke just now of the effect in the roofs of our villages of their purple slates; but if the slates are beautiful even in their flat and formal rows on house-roofs, much more are they beautiful on the rugged crests and flanks of their native mountains. Have you ever considered, in speaking as we do so often of distant blue hills, what it is that makes them blue? To a certain extent it is distance; but distance alone will not do it. Many hills look white, however distant. That lovely dark purple colour of our Welsh and Highland hills is owing, not to their distance merely, but to their rocks. Some of their rocks are, indeed, too dark to be beautiful, being black or ashy gray; owing to imperfect and porous structure. But when you see this dark colour dashed with russet and blue, and coming out in masses among the green ferns, so purple that you can hardly tell at first whether it is rock or heather, then you must thank your old Tunbridge friend, the oxide of iron.

16. But this is not all. It is necessary for the beauty of hill scenery that Nature should colour not only her soft rocks, but her hard ones; and she colours them with the same thing, only more beautifully. Perhaps you have wondered at my use of the word 'purple', so often of stones; but the Greeks, and still more the Romans, who had profound respect for purple, used it of stone long ago. You have all heard of 'porphyry' as among the most precious of the harder massive stones. The colour which gave it that noble name, as well as that which gives the flush to all the rosy granite of Egypt — yes, and to the rosiest summits of the Alps themselves — is still owing to the same substance — your humble oxide of iron.

17. And last of all: A nobler colour than all these — the noblest colour ever seen on this earth — one which belongs to a strength greater than that of the Egyptian granite, and to a beauty greater than that of the sunset or the rose — is still mysteriously connected with the presence of this dark iron. I believe it is not ascertained on what the crimson of blood actually depends; but the colour is connected, of course, with its vitality, and that vitality with the existence of iron as one of its substantial elements.

18. Is it not strange to find this stern and strong metal mingled so delicately in our human life that we cannot even blush without its help? Think of it, my fair and gentle hearers; how terrible the alternative — sometimes you have actually no choice but to be brazen-faced, or iron-faced!

19. In this slight review of some of the functions of the metal, you observe that I confine myself strictly to its operations as a colouring element. I should only confuse your conception of the facts if I endeavoured to describe its uses as a substantial element, either in strengthening rocks or influencing vegetation by the decomposition of rocks. I have not, therefore, even glanced at any of the more serious uses of the metal in the economy of nature. But what I wish you to carry clearly away with you is the remembrance that in all these uses the metal would be nothing without the air. The pure metal has no power, and never occurs in nature at all, except in meteoric stones, whose fall no one can account for, and which are useless after they have fallen: in the necessary work of the world, the iron is invariably joined with the oxygen, and would be capable of no service or beauty whatever without it.

20. Ⅱ. IRON IN ART. — Passing, then, from the offices of the metal in the operations of nature to its uses in the hands of man, you must remember, in the outset, that the type which has been thus given you, by the lifeless metal, of the action of body and soul together, has noble antitype in the operation of all human power. All art worthy the name is the energy — neither of the human body alone, nor of the human soul alone, but of both united, one guiding the other: good craftsmanship and work of the fingers joined with good emotion and work of the heart.

21. There is no good art, nor possible judgment of art, when these two are not united; yet we are constantly trying to separate them. Our amateurs cannot be persuaded but that they may produce some kind of art by their fancy or sensibility, without going through the necessary manual toil. That is entirely hopeless. Without a certain number, and that a very great number, of steady acts of hand — a practice as careful and constant as would be necessary to learn any other manual business — no drawing is possible. On the other side, the workman, and those who employ him, are continually trying to produce art by trick or habit of fingers, without using their fancy or sensibility. That also is hopeless. Without mingling of heart-passion with hand-power, no art is possible. The highest art unites both in their intensest degrees: the action of the hand at its finest, with that of the heart at its fullest.

22. Hence it follows that the utmost power of art can only be given in a material capable of receiving and retaining the influence of the subtlest touch of the human hand. That hand is the most perfect agent of material power existing in the universe; and its full subtlety can only be shown when the material it works on, or with, is entirely yielding. The chords of a perfect instrument will receive it, but not of an imperfect one; the softly-bending point of the hair pencil, and soft melting of colour, will receive it, but not even the chalk or pen point, still less the steel point, chisel, or marble. The hand of a sculptor may, indeed, be as subtle as that of a painter, but all its subtlety is not bestowable nor expressible: the touch of Titian, Correggio, or Turner is a far more marvellous piece of nervous action than can be shown in anything but colour, or in the very highest conditions of executive expression in music. In proportion as the material worked upon is less delicate, the execution necessarily becomes lower, and the art with it. This is one main principle of all work. Another is, that whatever the material you choose to work with, your art is base if it does not bring out the distinctive qualities of that material.

23. The reason of this second law is, that if you don't want the qualities of the substance you use, you ought to use some other substance: it can be only affectation, and desire to display your skill, that lead you to employ a refractory substance, and therefore your art will all be base. Glass, for instance, is eminently, in its nature, transparent. If you don't want transparency, let the glass alone. Do not try to make a window look like an opaque picture, but take an opaque ground to begin with. Again, marble is eminently a solid and massive substance. Unless you want mass and solidity, don't work in marble. If you wish for lightness, take wood; if for freedom, take stucco; if for ductility, take glass. Don't try to carve feathers, or trees, or nets, or foam, out of marble. Carve white limbs and broad breasts only out of that.

24. So again, iron is eminently a ductile and tenacious substance — tenacious above all things, ductile more than most. When you want tenacity, therefore, and involved form, take iron. It is eminently made for that. It is the material given to the sculptor as the companion of marble, with a message, as plain as it can well be spoken, from the lips of the earth-mother, 'Here's for you to cut, and here's for you to hammer. Shape this, and twist that. What is solid and simple, carve out; what is thin and entangled, beat out. I give you all kinds of forms to be delighted in; fluttering leaves as well as fair bodies; twisted branches as well as open brows. The leaf and the branch you may beat and drag into their imagery: the body and brow you shall reverently touch into their imagery. And if you choose rightly and work rightly, what you do shall be safe afterwards. Your slender leaves shall not break off in my tenacious iron, though they may be rusted a little with an iron autumn. Your broad surfaces shall not be unsmoothed in my pure crystalline marble — no decay shall touch them. But if you carve in the marble what will break with a touch, or mould in the metal what a stain of rust or verdigris will spoil, it is your fault — not mine.'

25. These are the main principles in this matter; which, like nearly all other right principles in art, we moderns delight in contradicting as directly and specially as may be. We continually look for, and praise, in our exhibitions, the sculpture of veils, and lace, and thin leaves, and all kinds of impossible things pushed as far as possible in the fragile stone, for the sake of showing the sculptor's dexterity.[【2】] On the other hand, we cast our iron into bars — brittle, though an inch thick — sharpen them at the ends, and consider fences, and other work, made of such materials, decorative! I do not believe it would be easy to calculate the amount of mischief done to our taste in England by that fence ironwork of ours alone. If it were asked of us, by a single characteristic, to distinguish the dwellings of a country into two broad sections; and to set, on one side, the places where people were, for the most part, simple, happy, benevolent, and honest; and, on the other side, the places where at least a great number of the people were sophisticated, unkind, uncomfortable, and unprincipled, there is, I think, one feature that you could fix upon as a positive test: the uncomfortable and unprincipled parts of a country would be the parts where people lived among iron railings, and the comfortable and principled parts where they had none. A broad generalization, you will say! Perhaps a little too broad; yet, in all sobriety, it will come truer than you think. Consider every other kind of fence or defence, and you will find some virtue in it; but in the iron railing, none. There is, first, your castle rampart of stone — somewhat too grand to be considered here among our types of fencing; next, your garden or park wall of brick, which has indeed often an unkind look on the outside, but there is more modesty in it than unkindness. It generally means, not that the builder of it wants to shut you out from the view of his garden, but from the view of himself: it is a frank statement that as he needs a certain portion of time to himself, so he needs a certain portion of ground to himself, and must not be stared at when he digs there in his shirt-sleeves, or plays at leapfrogs with his boys from school, or talks over old times with his wife, walking up and down in the evening sunshine. Besides, the brick wall has good practical service in it, and shelters you from the east wind, and ripens your peaches and nectarines, and glows in autumn like a sunny bank. And, moreover, your brick wall, if you build it properly, so that it shall stand long enough, is a beautiful thing when it is old, and has assumed its grave purple red, touched with mossy green.

26. Next to your lordly wall, in dignity of enclosure, comes your close-set wooden paling, which is more objectionable, because it commonly means enclosure on a larger scale than people want. Still it is significative of pleasant parks, and well-kept field walks, and herds of deer, and other such aristocratic pastoralisms, which have here and there their proper place in a country, and may be passed without any discredit.

27. Next to your paling comes your low stone dyke, your mountain fence, indicative at a glance either of wild hill country, or of beds of stone beneath the soil; the hedge of the mountains — delightful in all its associations, and yet more in the varied and craggy forms of the loose stones it is built of: and next to the low stone wall, your lowland hedge, either in trim line of massive green, suggestive of the pleasances of old Elizabethan houses, and smooth alleys for aged feet, and quaint labyrinths for young ones, or else in fair entanglement of eglantine and virgin's bower, tossing its scented luxuriance along our country waysides: — how many such you have here among your pretty hills, fruitful with black clusters of the bramble for boys in autumn, and crimson hawthorn-berries for birds in winter. And then last, and most difficult to class among fences, comes your hand-rail, expressive of all sorts of things; sometimes having a knowing and vicious look, which it learns at race-courses; sometimes an innocent and tender look, which it learns at rustic bridges over cressy brooks; and sometimes a prudent and protective look, which it learns on passes of the Alps, where it has posts of granite and bars of pine, and guards the brows of cliffs and the banks of torrents. So that in all these kinds of defence there is some good, pleasant, or noble meaning. But what meaning has the iron railing? Either, observe, that you are living in the midst of such bad characters that you must keep them out by main force of bar, or that you are yourself of a character requiring to be kept inside in the same manner. Your iron railing always means thieves outside, or Bedlam inside; — it can mean nothing else than that. If the people outside were good for anything, a hint in the way of fence would be enough for them; but because they are violent and at enmity with you, you are forced to put the close bars and the spikes at the top. Last summer I was lodging for a little while in a cottage in the country, and in front of my low window there were, first, some beds of daisies, then a row of gooseberry and currant bushes, and then a low wall about three feet above the ground, covered with stone-cress; outside, a cornfield, with its green ears glistening in the sun, and a field path through it, just past the garden gate. From my window I could see every peasant of the village who passed that way, with basket on arm for market, or spade on shoulder for field. When I was inclined for society, I could lean over my wall, and talk to anybody; when I was inclined for science, I could botanize all along the top of my wall — there were four species of stone-cress alone growing on it; and when I was inclined for exercise, I could jump over my wall, backwards and forwards. That's the sort of fence to have in a Christian country; not a thing which you can't walk inside of without making yourself look like a wild beast, nor look at out of your window in the morning without expecting to see somebody impaled upon it in the night.

28. And yet farther, observe that the iron railing is a useless fence — it can shelter nothing, and support nothing; you can't nail your peaches to it, nor protect your flowers with it, nor make anything whatever out of its costly tyranny; and besides being useless, it is an insolent fence; — it says plainly to everybody who passes — 'You may be an honest person, — but, also, you may be a thief: honest or not, you shall not get in here, for I am a respectable person and much above you; you shall only see what a grand place I have got to keep you out of — look here, and depart in humiliation.'

29. This, however, being in the present state of civilization a frequent manner of discourse, and there being unfortunately many districts where the iron railing is unavoidable, it yet remains a question whether you need absolutely make it ugly, no less than significative of evil. You must have railings round your squares in London, and at the sides of your areas; but need you therefore have railings so ugly that the constant sight of them is enough to neutralise the effect of all the schools of art in the kingdom? You need not. Far from such necessity, it is even in your power to turn all your police force of iron bars actually into drawing masters, and natural historians. Not, of course, without some trouble and some expense; you can do nothing much worth doing, in this world, without trouble, you can get nothing much worth having, without expense. The main question is only — what is worth doing and having: — Consider, therefore, if this is not. Here is your iron railing, as yet, an uneducated monster; a sombre seneschal, incapable of any words, except his perpetual 'Keep out!' and 'Away with you!' Would it not be worth some trouble and cost to turn this ungainly ruffian porter into a well-educated servant; who, while he was severe as ever in forbidding entrance to evilly disposed people, should yet have a kind word for well-disposed people, and a pleasant look, and a little useful information at his command, in case he should be asked a question by the passers-by?

30. We have not time to-night to look at many examples of ironwork; and those I happen to have by me are not the best; ironwork is not one of my special subjects of study; so that I only have memoranda of bits that happened to come into picturesque subjects which I was drawing for other reasons. Besides, external ironwork is more difficult to find good than any other sort of ancient art; for when it gets rusty and broken, people are sure, if they can afford it, to send it to the old iron shop, and get a fine new grating instead; and in the great cities of Italy the old iron is thus nearly all gone: the best bits I remember in the open air were at Brescia; — fantastic sprays of laurel-like foliage rising over the garden gates; and there are a few fine fragments at Verona, and some good trellis-work enclosing the Scala tombs; but on the whole, the most interesting pieces, though by no means the purest in style, are to be found in out-of-the-way provincial towns, where people do not care, or are unable, to make polite alterations. The little town of Bellinzona, for instance, on the south of the Alps, and that of Sion on the north, have both of them complete schools of ironwork in their balconies and vineyard gates. That of Bellinzona is the best, though not very old — I suppose most of it of the seventeenth century; still it is very quaint and beautiful. Here, for example, are two balconies, from two different houses: one has been a cardinal's, and the hat is the principal ornament of the balcony, its tassels being wrought with delightful delicacy and freedom; and catching the eye clearly even among the mass of rich wreathed leaves. These tassels and strings are precisely the kind of subject fit for ironwork — noble in ironwork, they would have been entirely ignoble in marble, on the grounds above stated. The real plant of oleander standing in the window enriches the whole group of lines very happily.

31. The other balcony, from a very ordinary-looking house in the same street, is much more interesting in its details. It appeared last summer with convolvulus twined about the bars, the arrow-shaped living leaves mingled among the leaves of iron [...] It is composed of a large tulip in the centre; then two turkscap lilies; then two pinks, a little conventionalized; then two narcissi; then two nondescripts, or, at least, flowers I do not know; and then two dark buds, and a few leaves; I say dark buds, for all these flowers have been coloured in their original state. The plan of the group is exceedingly simple: it is all enclosed in a pointed arch, the large mass of the tulip forming the apex; a six-foiled star on each side; then a jagged star; then a five-foiled star; then an unjagged star or rose; finally a small bud, so as to establish relation and cadence through the whole group. The profile is very free and fine, and the upper bar of the balcony exceedingly beautiful in effect; — none the less so on account of the marvellously simple means employed. A thin strip of iron is bent over a square rod; out of the edge of this strip are cut a series of triangular openings — widest at top, leaving projecting teeth of iron; then each of these projecting pieces gets a little sharp tap with the hammer in front, which breaks its edge inwards, tearing it a little open at the same time, and the thing is done.

32. The common forms of Swiss ironwork are less naturalistic than these Italian balconies, depending more on beautiful arrangements of various curve; nevertheless there has been a rich naturalist school at Fribourg, where a few bell-handles are still left, consisting of rods branched into laurel and other leafage. At Geneva, modern improvements have left nothing; but at Annecy a little good work remains; the balcony of its old hôtel de ville especially, with a trout of the lake — presumably the town arms — forming its central ornament.

33. I might expatiate all night — if you would sit and hear me — on the treatment of such required subject, or introduction of pleasant caprice by the old workmen; but we have no more time to spare, and I must quit this part of our subject — the rather as I could not explain to you the intrinsic merit of such ironwork without going fully into the theory of curvilinear design; only let me leave with you this one distinct assertion — that the quaint beauty and character of many natural objects, such as intricate branches, grass, foliage (especially thorny branches and prickly foliage), as well as that of many animals, plumed, spined, or bristled, is sculpturally expressible in iron only, and in iron would be majestic and impressive in the highest degree; and that every piece of metal work you use might be, rightly treated, not only a superb decoration, but a most valuable abstract of portions of natural forms, holding in dignity precisely the same relation to the painted representation of plants that a statue does to the painted form of man. It is difficult to give you an idea of the grace and interest which the simplest objects possess when their forms are thus abstracted from among the surrounding of rich circumstance which in nature disturbs the feebleness of our attention. Every cluster of herbage would furnish fifty such groups, and every such group would work into iron (fitting it, of course, rightly to its service) with perfect ease, and endless grandeur of result.

34.Ⅲ. IRON IN POLICY. — Having thus obtained some idea of the use of iron in art, as dependent on its ductility, I need not, certainly, say anything of its uses in manufacture and commerce; we all of us know enough — perhaps a little too much — about them. So I pass lastly to consider its uses in policy; dependent chiefly upon its tenacity — that is to say, on its power of bearing a pull, and receiving an edge. These powers, which enable it to pierce, to bind, and to smite, render it fit for the three great instruments by which its political action may be simply typified; namely, the Plough, the Fetter, and the Sword.

35. On our understanding the right use of these three instruments depends, of course, all our power as a nation, and all our happiness as individuals.

36.(1) THE PLOUGH. — I say, first, on our understanding the right use of the plough, with which, in justice to the fairest of our labourers, we must always associate that feminine plough — the needle. The first requirement for the happiness of a nation is that it should understand the function in this world of these two great instruments: a happy nation may be defined as one in which the husband's hand is on the plough, and the housewife's on the needle; so in due time reaping its golden harvest, and shining in golden vesture: and an unhappy nation is one which, acknowledging no use of plough nor needle, will assuredly at last find its storehouse empty in the famine, and its breast naked to the cold.

37. Perhaps you think this is a mere truism, which I am wasting your time in repeating. I wish it were.

38. By far the greater part of the suffering and crime which exist at this moment in civilized Europe, arises simply from people not understanding this truism — not knowing that produce or wealth is eternally connected by the laws of heaven and earth with resolute labour; but hoping in some way to cheat or abrogate this everlasting law of life, and to feed where they have not furrowed, and be warm where they have not woven.

39. I repeat, nearly all our misery and crime result from this one misapprehension. The law of nature is, that a certain quantity of work is necessary to produce a certain quantity of good, of any kind whatever. If you want knowledge, you must toil for it: if food, you must toil for it: and if pleasure, you must toil for it. But men do not acknowledge this law; or strive to evade it, hoping to get their knowledge, and food, and pleasure for nothing: and in this effort they either fail of getting them, and remain ignorant and miserable, or they obtain them by making other men work for their benefit; and then they are tyrants and robbers. Yes, and worse than robbers. I am not one who in the least doubts or disputes the progress of this century in many things useful to mankind; but it seems to me a very dark sign respecting us that we look with so much indifference upon dishonesty and cruelty in the pursuit of wealth. In the dream of Nebuchadnezzar, it was only the feet that were part of iron and part of clay, but many of us are now getting so cruel in our avarice that it seems as if, in us, the heart were part of iron, part of clay.

40. From what I have heard of the inhabitants of this town, I do not doubt but that I may be permitted to do here what I have found it usually thought elsewhere highly improper and absurd to do, namely, trace a few Bible sentences to their practical result.

41. You cannot but have noticed how often in those parts of the Bible which are likely to be oftenest opened when people look for guidance, comfort, or help in the affairs of daily life, — namely, the Psalms and Proverbs, — mention is made of the guilt attaching to the Oppression of the poor. Observe: not the neglect of them, but the Oppression of them: the word is as frequent as it is strange. You can hardly open either of those books, but somewhere in their pages you will find a description of the wicked man's attempts against the poor: such as, — 'He doth ravish the poor when he getteth him into his net.'

'He sitteth in the lurking places of the villages; his eyes are privily set against the poor.'

'In his pride he doth persecute the poor, and blesseth the covetous, whom God abhorreth.'

'His mouth is full of deceit and fraud; in the secret places doth he murder the innocent. Have the workers of iniquity no knowledge, who eat up my people as they eat bread? They have drawn out the sword, and bent the bow, to cast down the poor and needy.'

'They are corrupt, and speak wickedly concerning oppression.'

'Pride compasseth them about as a chain, and violence as a garment.'

'Their poison is like the poison of a serpent. Ye weigh the violence of your hands in the earth.'

42. Yes: 'Ye weigh the violence of your hands:' — weigh these words as well. The last things we ever usually think of weighing are Bible words. We like to dream and dispute over them; but to weigh them, and see what their true contents are — anything but that. Yet, weigh these; for I have purposely taken all these verses, perhaps more striking to you read in this connection than separately in their places, out of the Psalms, because, for all people belonging to the Established Church of this country, these Psalms are appointed lessons, portioned out to them by their clergy to be read once through every month. Presumably, therefore, whatever portions of Scripture we may pass by or forget, these, at all events, must be brought continually to our observance as useful for direction of daily life. Now, do we ever ask ourselves what the real meaning of these passages may be, and who these wicked people are, who are 'murdering the innocent'? You know it is rather singular language, this! — rather strong language, we might, perhaps, call it — hearing it for the first time. Murder! and murder of innocent people! — nay, even a sort of cannibalism. Eating people, — yes, and God's people, too — eating My people as if they were bread! swords drawn, bows bent, poison of serpents mixed! violence of hands weighed, measured, and trafficked with as so much coin! — where is all this going on? Do you suppose it was only going on in the time of David, and that nobody but Jews ever murder the poor? If so, it would surely be wiser not to mutter and mumble for our daily lessons what does not concern us; but if there be any chance that it may concern us, and if this description, in the Psalms, of human guilt is at all generally applicable, as the descriptions in the Psalms of human sorrow are, may it not be advisable to know wherein this guilt is being committed round about us, or by ourselves? and when we take the words of the Bible into our mouths in a congregational way, to be sure whether we mean merely to chant a piece of melodious poetry relating to other people — (we know not exactly to whom) — or to assert our belief in facts bearing somewhat stringently on ourselves and our daily business. And if you make up your minds to do this no longer, and take pains to examine into the matter, you will find that these strange words, occurring as they do, not in a few places only, but almost in every alternate psalm and every alternate chapter of proverb or prophecy, with tremendous reiteration, were not written for one nation or one time only, but for all nations and languages, for all places and all centuries; and it is as true of the wicked man now as ever it was of Nabal or Dives, that 'his eyes are set against the poor.'

43. Set against the poor, mind you. Not merely set away from the poor, so as to neglect or lose sight of them, but set against, so as to afflict and destroy them. This is the main point I want to fix your attention upon. You will often hear sermons about neglect or carelessness of the poor. But neglect and carelessness are not at all the points. The Bible hardly ever talks about neglect of the poor. It always talks of oppression of the poor — a very different matter. It does not merely speak of passing by on the other side, and binding up no wounds, but of drawing the sword and ourselves smiting the men down. It does not charge us with being idle in the pest-house, and giving no medicine, but with being busy in the pest-house, and giving much poison.

44. May we not advisedly look into this matter a little, even to-night, and ask first, Who are these poor?

45. No country is, or ever will be, without them: that is to say, without the class which cannot, on the average, do more by its labour than provide for its subsistence, and which has no accumulations of property laid by on any considerable scale. Now there are a certain number of this class whom we cannot oppress with much severity. An able-bodied and intelligent workman — sober, honest, and industrious, — will almost always command a fair price for his work, and lay by enough in a few years to enable him to hold his own in the labour market. But all men are not able-bodied, nor intelligent, nor industrious; and you cannot expect them to be. Nothing appears to me at once more ludicrous and more melancholy than the way the people of the present age usually talk about the morals of labourers. You hardly ever address a labouring man upon his prospects in life, without quietly assuming that he is to possess, at starting, as a small moral capital to begin with, the virtue of Socrates, the philosophy of Plato, and the heroism of Epaminondas. 'Be assured, my good man,' — you say to him, — 'that if you work steadily for ten hours a day all your life long, and if you drink nothing but water, or the very mildest beer, and live on very plain food, and never lose your temper, and go to church every Sunday, and always remain content in the position in which Providence has placed you, and never grumble, nor swear; and always keep your clothes decent, and rise early, and use every opportunity of improving yourself, you will get on very well, and never come to the parish.'

46. All this is exceedingly true; but before giving the advice so confidently, it would be well if we sometimes tried it practically ourselves, and spent a year or so at some hard manual labour, not of an entertaining kind — ploughing or digging, for instance, with a very moderate allowance of beer; nothing but bread and cheese for dinner; no papers nor muffins in the morning; no sofas nor magazines at night; one small room for parlour and kitchen; and a large family of children always in the middle of the floor. If we think we could, under these circumstances, enact Socrates, or Epaminondas, entirely to our own satisfaction, we shall be somewhat justified in requiring the same behaviour from our poorer neighbours; but if not, we should surely consider a little whether among the various forms of the oppression of the poor, we may not rank as one of the first and likeliest — the oppression of expecting too much from them.

47. But let this pass; and let it be admitted that we never can be guilty of oppression towards the sober, industrious, intelligent, exemplary labourer. There will always be in the world some who are not altogether intelligent and exemplary; we shall, I believe, to the end of time find the majority somewhat unintelligent, a little inclined to be idle, and occasionally, on Saturday night, drunk; we must even be prepared to hear of reprobates who like skittles on Sunday morning better than prayers; and of unnatural parents who send their children out to beg instead of to go to school.

48. Now these are the kind of people whom you can oppress, and whom you do oppress, and that to purpose, — and with all the more cruelty and the greater sting, because it is just their own fault that puts them into your power. You know the words about wicked people are, 'He doth ravish the poor when he getteth him into his net.' This getting into the net is constantly the fault or folly of the sufferer — his own heedlessness or his own indolence; but after he is once in the net, the oppression of him, and making the most of his distress, are ours. The nets which we use against the poor are just those worldly embarrassments which either their ignorance or their improvidence are almost certain at some time or other to bring them into: then, just at the time when we ought to hasten to help them, and disentangle them, and teach them how to manage better in future, we rush forward to pillage them, and force all we can out of them in their adversity. For, to take one instance only, remember this is literally and simply what we do, whenever we buy, or try to buy, cheap goods — goods offered at a price which we know cannot be remunerative for the labour involved in them. Whenever we buy such goods, remember we are stealing somebody's labour. Don't let us mince the matter. I say, in plain Saxon, STEALING — taking from him the proper reward of his work, and putting it into our own pocket. You know well enough that the thing could not have been offered you at that price, unless distress of some kind had forced the producer to part with it. You take advantage of this distress, and you force as much out of him as you can under the circumstances. The old barons of the Middle Ages used, in general, the thumbscrew to extort property; we moderns use, in preference, hunger, or domestic affliction: but the fact of extortion remains precisely the same. Whether we force the man's property from him by pinching his stomach, or pinching his fingers, makes some difference anatomically; — morally, none whatsoever: we use a form of torture of some sort in order to make him give up his property; we use, indeed, the man's own anxieties, instead of the rack; and his immediate peril of starvation, instead of the pistol at the head; but otherwise we differ from Front de Bœuf, or Dick Turpin, merely in being less dexterous, more cowardly, and more cruel. More cruel, I say, because the fierce baron and the redoubted highwayman are reported to have robbed, at least by preference, only the rich; we steal habitually from the poor. We buy our liveries, and gild our prayer-books, with pilfered pence out of children's and sick men's wages, and thus ingeniously dispose a given quantity of Theft, so that it may produce the largest possible measure of delicately-distributed suffering.

49. But this is only one form of common oppression of the poor — only one way of taking our hands off the Plough-handle, and binding another's upon it. The first way of doing it is the economical way — the way preferred by prudent and virtuous people. The bolder way is the acquisitive way: — the way of speculation. You know we are considering at present the various modes in which a nation corrupts itself, by not acknowledging the eternal connection between its plough and its pleasure; — by striving to get pleasure, without working for it. Well, I say the first and commonest way of doing so is to try to get the product of other people's work, and enjoy it ourselves, by cheapening their labour in times of distress; then the second way is that grand one of watching the chances of the market; — the way of speculation. Of course there are some speculations that are fair and honest — speculations made with our own money, and which do not involve in their success the loss, by others, of what we gain. But generally modern speculation involves much risk to others, with chance of profit only to ourselves; even in its best conditions it is merely one of the forms of gambling or treasure-hunting: it is either leaving the steady plough and the steady pilgrimage of life, to look for silver mines beside the way; or else it is the full stop beside the dice-tables in Vanity Fair — investing all the thoughts and passions of the soul in the fall of the cards, and choosing rather the wild accidents of idle fortune than the calm and accumulative rewards of toil. And this is destructive enough, at least to our peace and virtue. But it is usually destructive of far more than our peace, or our virtue. Have you ever deliberately set yourselves to imagine and measure the suffering, the guilt, and the mortality caused necessarily by the failure of any large-dealing merchant, or largely-branched bank? Take it at the lowest possible supposition — count, at the fewest you choose, the families whose means of support have been involved in the catastrophe. Then, on the morning after the intelligence of ruin, let us go forth amongst them in earnest thought; let us use that imagination which we waste so often on fictitious sorrow, to measure the stem facts of that multitudinous distress; strike open the private doors of their chambers, and enter silently into the midst of the domestic misery; look upon the old men, who had reserved for their failing strength some remainder of rest in the evening-tide of life, cast helplessly back into its trouble and tumult; look upon the active strength of middle age suddenly blasted into incapacity — its hopes crushed, and its hardly-earned rewards snatched away in the same instant — at once the heart withered, and the right arm snapped; look upon the piteous children, delicately nurtured, whose soft eyes, now large with wonder at their parents' grief, must soon be set in the dimness of famine; and, far more than all this, look forward to the length of sorrow beyond — to the hardest labour of life, now to be undergone either in all the severity of unexpected and inexperienced trial, or else, more bitter still, to be begun again, and endured for the second time, amidst the ruins of cherished hopes and the feebleness of advancing years, embittered by the continual sting and taunt of the inner feeling that it has all been brought about, not by the fair course of appointed circumstance, but by miserable chance and wanton treachery; and, last of all, look beyond this — to the shattered destinies of those who have faltered under the trial, and sunk past recovery to despair. And then consider whether the hand which has poured this poison into all the springs of life be one whit less guiltily red with human blood than that which literally pours the hemlock into the cup, or guides the dagger to the heart? We read with horror of the crimes of a Borgia or a Tophana; but there never lived Borgias such as live now in the midst of us. The cruel lady of Ferrara slew only in the strength of passion — she slew only a few, those who thwarted her purposes or who vexed her soul; she slew sharply and suddenly, embittering the fate of her victims with no foretastes of destruction, no prolongations of pain; and, finally and chiefly, she slew not without remorse nor without pity. But we, in no storm of passion, — in no blindness of wrath, — we, in calm and clear and untempted selfishness, pour our poison — not for a few only, but for multitudes; — not for those who have wronged us, or resisted, — but for those who have trusted us and aided; — we, not with sudden gift of merciful and unconscious death, but with slow waste of hunger and weary rack of disappointment and despair! — we, lastly and chiefly, do our murdering, not with any pauses of pity or scorching of conscience, but in facile and forgetful calm of mind — and so, forsooth, read day by day, complacently, as if they meant any one else than ourselves, the words that for ever describe the wicked: 'The poison of asps is under their lips, and their feet are swift to shed blood.'

50. You may indeed, perhaps, think there is some excuse for many in this matter, just because the sin is so unconscious; that the guilt is not so great when it is unapprehended, and that it is much more pardonable to slay heedlessly than purposefully. I believe no feeling can be more mistaken; and that in reality, and in the sight of heaven, the callous indifference which pursues its own interests at any cost of life, though it does not definitely adopt the purpose of sin, is a state of mind at once more heinous and more hopeless than the wildest aberrations of ungoverned passion. There may be, in the last case, some elements of good and of redemption still mingled in the character; but, in the other, few or none. There may be hope for the man who has slain his enemy in anger; — hope even for the man who has betrayed his friend in fear; but what hope for him who trades in unregarded blood, and builds his fortune on unrepented treason?

51. But, however this may be, and wherever you may think yourselves bound in justice to impute the greater sin, be assured that the question is one of responsibilities only, not of facts. The definite result of all our modern haste to be rich is assuredly, and constantly, the murder of a certain number of persons by our hands every year. I have not time to go into the details of another — on the whole, the broadest and terriblest way in which we cause the destruction of the poor — namely, the way of luxury and waste, destroying, in improvidence, what might have been the support of thousands; but if you follow out the subject for yourselves at home — and what I have endeavoured to lay before you to-night will only be useful to you if you do — you will find that wherever and whenever men are endeavouring to make money hastily, and to avoid the labour which Providence has appointed to be the only source of honourable profit; — and also wherever and whenever they permit themselves to spend it luxuriously, without reflecting how far they are misguiding the labour of others; — there and then, in either case, they are literally and infallibly causing, for their own benefit or their own pleasure, a certain annual number of human deaths; that, therefore, the choice given to every man born into this world is, simply, whether he will be a labourer or an assassin; and that whosoever has not his hand on the Stilt of the plough, has it on the Hilt of the dagger.

52. It would also be quite vain for me to endeavour to follow out this evening the lines of thought which would be suggested by the other two great political uses of iron in the Fetter and the Sword: a few words only I must permit myself respecting both.

53.(2) THE FETTER. — As the plough is the typical instrument of industry, so the fetter is the typical instrument of the restraint or subjection necessary in a nation — either literally, for its evildoers, or figuratively, in accepted laws, for its wise and good men. You have to choose between this figurative and literal use; for depend upon it, the more laws you accept, the fewer penalties you will have to endure, and the fewer punishments to enforce. For wise laws and just restraints are to a noble nation not chains, but chain mail — strength and defence, though something also of an incumbrance. And this necessity of restraint, remember, is just as honourable to man as the necessity of labour. You hear every day greater numbers of foolish people speaking about liberty, as if it were such an honourable thing: so far from being that, it is on the whole, and in the broadest sense, dishonourable, and an attribute of the lower creatures. No human being, however great, or powerful, was ever so free as a fish. There is always something that he must, or must not do; while the fish may do whatever he likes. All the kingdoms of the world put together are not half so large as the sea, and all the railroads and wheels that ever were, or will be, invented are not so easy as fins. You will find on fairly thinking of it, that it is his Restraint which is honourable to man, not his Liberty; and, what is more, it is restraint which is honourable even in the lower animals. A butterfly is much more free than a bee; but you honour the bee more, just because it is subject to certain laws which fit it for orderly function in bee society. And throughout the world, of the two abstract things, liberty and restraint, restraint is always the more honourable. It is true, indeed, that in these and all other matters you never can reason finally from the abstraction, for both liberty and restraint are good when they are nobly chosen, and both are bad when they are basely chosen; but of the two, I repeat, it is restraint which characterizes the higher creature, and betters the lower creature: and, from the ministering of the archangel to the labour of the insect, — from the poising of the planets to the gravitation of a grain of dust, — the power and glory of all creatures, and all matter, consist in their obedience, not in their freedom. The Sun has no liberty — a dead leaf has much. The dust of which you are formed has no liberty. Its liberty will come — with its corruption.

54. And, therefore, I say boldly, though it seems a strange thing to say in England, that as the first power of a nation consists in knowing how to guide the Plough, its second power consists in knowing how to wear the Fetter: —

55.(3) THE SWORD. — And its third power, which perfects it as a nation, consists in knowing how to wield the sword, so that the three talismans of national existence are expressed in these three short words — Labour, Law, and Courage.

56. This last virtue we at least possess; and all that is to be alleged against us is that we do not honour it enough. I do not mean honour by acknowledgment of service, though sometimes we are slow in doing even that. But we do not honour it enough in consistent regard to the lives and souls of our soldiers. How wantonly we have wasted their lives you have seen lately in the reports of their mortality by disease, which a little care and science might have prevented; but we regard their souls less than their lives, by keeping them in ignorance and idleness, and regarding them merely as instruments of battle. The argument brought forward for the maintenance of a standing army usually refers only to expediency in the case of unexpected war, whereas, one of the chief reasons for the maintenance of an army is the advantage of the military system as a method of education. The most fiery and headstrong, who are often also the most gifted and generous of your youths, have always a tendency both in the lower and upper classes to offer themselves for your soldiers: others, weak and unserviceable in the civil capacity, are tempted or entrapped into the army in a fortunate hour for them: out of this fiery or uncouth material, it is only soldier's discipline which can bring the full value and power. Even at present, by mere force of order and authority, the army is the salvation of myriads; and men who, under other circumstances, would have sunk into lethargy or dissipation, are redeemed into noble life by a service which at once summons and directs their energies. How much more than this, military education is capable of doing, you will find only when you make it education indeed. We have no excuse for leaving our private soldiers at their present level of ignorance and want of refinement, for we shall invariably find that, both among officers and men, the gentlest and best informed are the bravest; still less have we excuse for diminishing our army, either in the present state of political events, or, as I believe, in any other conjunction of them that for many a year will be possible in this world.

57. You may, perhaps, be surprised at my saying this; perhaps surprised at my implying that war itself can be right, or necessary, or noble at all. Nor do I speak of all war as necessary, nor of all war as noble. Both peace and war are noble or ignoble according to their kind and occasion. No man has a profounder sense of the horror and guilt of ignoble war than I have: I have personally seen its effects, upon nations, of unmitigated evil, on soul and body, with perhaps as much pity, and as much bitterness of indignation, as any of those whom you will hear continually declaiming in the cause of peace. But peace may be sought in two ways. One way is as Gideon sought it, when he built his altar in Ophrah, naming it, 'God send peace,' yet sought this peace that he loved, as he was ordered to seek it, and the peace was sent, in God's way: — 'the country was in quietness forty years in the days of Gideon.' And the other way of seeking peace is as Menahem sought it, when he gave the King of Assyria a thousand talents of silver, that 'his hand might be with him.' That is, you may either win your peace, or buy it: — win it, by resistance to evil; — buy it, by compromise with evil. You may buy your peace, with silenced consciences; — you may buy it, with broken vows, — buy it, with lying words, — buy it, with base connivances, — buy it, with the blood of the slain, and the cry of the captive, and the silence of lost souls — over hemispheres of the earth, while you sit smiling at your serene hearths, lisping comfortable prayers evening and morning, and counting your pretty Protestant beads (which are flat, and of gold, instead of round, and of ebony, as the monks' ones were), and so mutter continually to yourselves, 'Peace, peace,' when there is No peace; but only captivity and death, for you, as well as for those you leave unsaved; — and yours darker than theirs.

58. I cannot utter to you what I would in this matter; we all see too dimly, as yet, what our great world-duties are, to allow any of us to try to outline their enlarging shadows. But think over what I have said; and as you return to your quiet homes to-night, reflect that their peace was not won for you by your own hands, but by theirs who long ago jeoparded their lives for you, their children; and remember that neither this inherited peace, nor any other, can be kept, but through the same jeopardy. No peace was ever won from Fate by subterfuge or agreement; no peace is ever in store for any of us, but that which we shall win by victory over shame or sin; — victory over the sin that oppresses, as well as over that which corrupts. For many a year to come, the sword of every righteous nation must be whetted to save or to subdue; nor will it be by patience of others' suffering, but by the offering of your own, that you will ever draw nearer to the time when the great change shall pass upon the iron of the earth; — when men shall beat their swords into ploughshares, and their spears into pruning-hooks; neither shall they learn war any more.

注释

【1】　Gold

【2】　I do not mean to attach any degree of blame to the effort to represent leafage in marble for certain expressive purposes. The later works of Mr Munro have depended for some of their most tender thoughts on a delicate and skilful use of such accessories. And in general, leaf sculpture is good and admirable, if it renders, as in Gothic work, the grace and lightness of the leaf by the arrangement of light and shadow — supporting the masses well by strength of stone below; but all carving is base which proposes to itself slightness as an aim, and tries to imitate the absolute thinness of thin or slight things, as much modern wood-carving does. I saw in Italy, a year or two ago, a marble sculpture of birds' nests.